<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 06:27:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Shock compression of FeOOH and implications for iron-water interactions in super-earth magma oceans</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67845-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67845-8</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 09:45:08 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yanyao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Komal Bali</dc:creator><dc:creator>Caroline Dorn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alessandra Ravasio</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Silvia Pandolfi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Amanda J. Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuehui Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lélia Libon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qijun Che</dc:creator><dc:creator>Donghao Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eglantine Boulard</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alessandra Benuzzi-Mounaix</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hae Ja Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eric Galtier</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicholas A. Czapla</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dimosthenis Sokaras</dc:creator><dc:creator>Roberto Alonso-Mori</dc:creator><dc:creator>Arianna E. Gleason</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sang Heon Shim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guillaume Morard</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wendy L. Mao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67845-8</prism:doi><description>Iron(Fe)-water reactions in a magma ocean can influence water storage and density of planets. These reactions can form Fe-O-H phases, whose density, melting, and electronic properties at planetary interior conditions are important for informing planetary models. Here, we study natural goethite (α-FeOOH) that is shock-compressed along its principal Hugoniot. Analysis of our velocity interferometer system for any reflector (VISAR) results extends the equation of state to over 800 GPa. X-ray diffraction and VISAR reflectivity results indicate the onset of melting occurs at ~95 GPa with complete melting by 166 GPa, which may be relevant to low seismic velocity anomalies observed above the core-mantle boundary. Analysis of X-ray emission spectroscopy results up to 285 GPa shows the spin crossover of Fe, with dominantly low spin Fe above ~265 GPa in the melt, supporting formation of dense basal magma oceans in terrestrial planets. Using our measured FeOOH densities, we model planetary interiors up to 10 Earth masses. Assuming FeOOH forms via iron-water reactions, the radius decreases by up to 28%, while the density increases by up to 165% compared to the unreacted case, providing an avenue to investigate water storage and evolution in super-Earths and sub-Neptunes. Laser shock experiments on an iron-water phase reveal its density, melting, and electronic changes under extreme pressures. The results suggest dense deep magma oceans and show that iron-water reactions can greatly shrink and densify super-Earths.
Published: 2025-12-27T09:45:08+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.568 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yanyao Zhang; Komal Bali; Caroline Dorn; Alessandra Ravasio; Hong Yang; Silvia Pandolfi; Amanda J. Chen; Xuehui Wei; Lélia Libon; Qijun Che; Donghao Zheng; Eglantine Boulard; Alessandra Benuzzi-Mounaix; Hae Ja Lee; Eric Galtier; Nicholas A. Czapla; Dimosthenis Sokaras; Roberto Alonso-Mori; Arianna E. Gleason; Sang Heon Shim; Guillaume Morard; Wendy L. Mao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67845-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67845-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.568 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iron(Fe)-water reactions in a magma ocean can influence water storage and density of planets. These reactions can form Fe-O-H phases, whose density, melting, and electronic properties at planetary interior conditions are important for informing planetary models. Here, we study natural goethite (α-FeOOH) that is shock-compressed along its principal Hugoniot. Analysis of our velocity interferometer system for any reflector (VISAR) results extends the equation of state to over 800 GPa. X-ray diffraction and VISAR reflectivity results indicate the onset of melting occurs at ~95 GPa with complete melting by 166 GPa, which may be relevant to low seismic velocity anomalies observed above the core-mantle boundary. Analysis of X-ray emission spectroscopy results up to 285 GPa shows the spin crossover of Fe, with dominantly low spin Fe above ~265 GPa in the melt, supporting formation of dense basal magma oceans in terrestrial planets. Using our measured FeOOH densities, we model planetary interiors up to 10 Earth masses. Assuming FeOOH forms via iron-water reactions, the radius decreases by up to 28%, while the density increases by up to 165% compared to the unreacted case, providing an avenue to investigate water storage and evolution in super-Earths and sub-Neptunes. Laser shock experiments on an iron-water phase reveal its density, melting, and electronic changes under extreme pressures. The results suggest dense deep magma oceans and show that iron-water reactions can greatly shrink and densify super-Earths.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Water Incorporation Mechanisms and Effects in MgSiO
                    &lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;
                    ‐Majorite Under High Temperature and Pressure Conditions</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032448</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032448</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 06:23:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yancheng Lou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhigang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrew M. Walker</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephen Stackhouse</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meng Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongping He</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032448</prism:doi><description>Abstract The incorporation of water in high‐pressure minerals is essential for the water cycle within the interiors of terrestrial planets. Majoritic garnet, a major component in the mantles of Earth and Mars, plays a significant role in this context. In this study, we use first‐principles simulations to explore water incorporation mechanisms in MgSiO 3 ‐majorite, which is a key end‐member of majoritic garnet, at conditions up to 2,000 K and 20 GPa. By dealing with the relationship between chemical potential and the Gibbs free energy changes for the reactions at equilibrium conditions, we determine the ratios of the seven potential hydrous defects. Our results reveal that the Si2 and Si3 defects, which are of the hydrogarnet‐type, dominate water incorporation in MgSiO 3 ‐majorite. In addition, we evaluate the effects of these hydrous defects on seismic wave velocities. The presence of Si2 and Si3 defects, with an expected water concentration of ∼700 ppm, has a small effect on both P‐wave and S‐wave velocities. Nevertheless, the influence of water on lateral variations in the seismic wave velocities of MgSiO 3 ‐majorite, which is opposite to that found for ringwoodite, offers a potential tool for investigating compositional heterogeneities in hydrated regions of planetary mantles.
Published: 2025-12-27T06:23:21+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.552 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yancheng Lou; Zhigang Zhang; Andrew M. Walker; Stephen Stackhouse; Meng Chen; Hongping He&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032448"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032448&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.552 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The incorporation of water in high‐pressure minerals is essential for the water cycle within the interiors of terrestrial planets. Majoritic garnet, a major component in the mantles of Earth and Mars, plays a significant role in this context. In this study, we use first‐principles simulations to explore water incorporation mechanisms in MgSiO 3 ‐majorite, which is a key end‐member of majoritic garnet, at conditions up to 2,000 K and 20 GPa. By dealing with the relationship between chemical potential and the Gibbs free energy changes for the reactions at equilibrium conditions, we determine the ratios of the seven potential hydrous defects. Our results reveal that the Si2 and Si3 defects, which are of the hydrogarnet‐type, dominate water incorporation in MgSiO 3 ‐majorite. In addition, we evaluate the effects of these hydrous defects on seismic wave velocities. The presence of Si2 and Si3 defects, with an expected water concentration of ∼700 ppm, has a small effect on both P‐wave and S‐wave velocities. Nevertheless, the influence of water on lateral variations in the seismic wave velocities of MgSiO 3 ‐majorite, which is opposite to that found for ringwoodite, offers a potential tool for investigating compositional heterogeneities in hydrated regions of planetary mantles.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Near-surface liquid water on Mars inferred from seasonal marsquakes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67784-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67784-4</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 14:33:30 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jing Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaqi Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Caoanla Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haoran Meng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cong Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Qi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Siteng Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenliang Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lian Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xie Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ling Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67784-4</prism:doi><description>Exploring the presence and behavior of water on Mars is critical for understanding the planet’s geological evolution, hydrological processes, and potential habitability, which has been a central objective of past and ongoing Martian exploration missions. Martian geomorphology provides evidence of ancient groundwater activity, but confirmation of present-day liquid water remains limited. Here, we infer near-surface brines confined to meter-scale depths in regions north of about 30 °N in the northern hemisphere, based on the analysis of seasonal variations in marsquake seismicity and thermal modeling. The absence of seasonal marsquakes during colder periods and their abrupt resurgence in warmer seasons can be explained by ice-to-brine phase transitions. Our findings reveal a mechanism whereby seasonal melting of subsurface ice elevates pore pressure and lubricates faults, leading to a reduction in frictional strength, and ultimately inducing marsquakes. This mechanism accounts for the seasonal variation, clustering, high seismic b-values, and shallow focal depths of seasonal marsquakes. Additionally, we estimate that the melting point of briny ice on Mars is below approximately 250 ± 13 K, advancing our understanding of Mars’ present-day brine cycle and near-surface hydrological processes. The study finds that seasonal marsquake patterns may indicate active near-surface brines on Mars today. By connecting seismicity changes to ice-to-brine melting, it infers that shallow liquid water continues to operate beneath the surface and influence Martian fault activity.
Published: 2025-12-26T14:33:30+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.544 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jing Shi; Jiaqi Li; Caoanla Li; Haoran Meng; Cong Sun; Chao Qi; Lu Pan; Siteng Fan; Zhenliang Tian; Tao Wang; Lian Xue; Xie Hu; Ling Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67784-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67784-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.544 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exploring the presence and behavior of water on Mars is critical for understanding the planet’s geological evolution, hydrological processes, and potential habitability, which has been a central objective of past and ongoing Martian exploration missions. Martian geomorphology provides evidence of ancient groundwater activity, but confirmation of present-day liquid water remains limited. Here, we infer near-surface brines confined to meter-scale depths in regions north of about 30 °N in the northern hemisphere, based on the analysis of seasonal variations in marsquake seismicity and thermal modeling. The absence of seasonal marsquakes during colder periods and their abrupt resurgence in warmer seasons can be explained by ice-to-brine phase transitions. Our findings reveal a mechanism whereby seasonal melting of subsurface ice elevates pore pressure and lubricates faults, leading to a reduction in frictional strength, and ultimately inducing marsquakes. This mechanism accounts for the seasonal variation, clustering, high seismic b-values, and shallow focal depths of seasonal marsquakes. Additionally, we estimate that the melting point of briny ice on Mars is below approximately 250 ± 13 K, advancing our understanding of Mars’ present-day brine cycle and near-surface hydrological processes. The study finds that seasonal marsquake patterns may indicate active near-surface brines on Mars today. By connecting seismicity changes to ice-to-brine melting, it infers that shallow liquid water continues to operate beneath the surface and influence Martian fault activity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Thermal Conductivity of Basalt‐Olivine Aggregates: Implications for Heat Transfer in Partially Molten Rocks</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032070</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032070</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:08:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chengcheng Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Geeth Manthilake</dc:creator><dc:creator>Antoine Mathieu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mohamed Ali Bouhifd</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032070</prism:doi><description>Abstract We measured the thermal conductivity of composites consisting of mid‐ocean ridge basalt (MORB) and polycrystalline olivine, as an analog for partially molten systems, to investigate the influence of low degree melting on heat transport. Experiments were conducted at 1 GPa and temperatures up to 1,600 K, with MORB fractions ranging from 0.1 to 10 vol.%. Adding MORB to the olivine matrix significantly altered the composite's thermal conductivity. Prior to melting, composites containing 0.1 and 10 vol.% MORB showed the most pronounced increase in conductivity relative to pure olivine, while intermediate fractions (∼1–5 vol.%) exhibited a decrease, followed by a rise at higher MORB contents. We attribute this non‐monotonic behavior to impurity–lattice interactions within the MORB‐bearing olivine, which reduce lattice disorder and enhance heat transport. Upon melting MORB, the thermal conductivity of the composites decreased, with the largest reductions (∼35%) observed in the 0.1 and 10 vol.% MORB samples, indicating that the melt acts as a thermal insulator. Applied to planetary interiors, these results suggest that lateral variations in melt fraction within thermal boundary layers could generate heterogeneities in heat flow, potentially affecting mantle convection patterns and the formation or evolution of thermal plumes.
Published: 2025-12-27T18:08:14+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.538 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chengcheng Zhao; Geeth Manthilake; Antoine Mathieu; Mohamed Ali Bouhifd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032070"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032070&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.538 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract We measured the thermal conductivity of composites consisting of mid‐ocean ridge basalt (MORB) and polycrystalline olivine, as an analog for partially molten systems, to investigate the influence of low degree melting on heat transport. Experiments were conducted at 1 GPa and temperatures up to 1,600 K, with MORB fractions ranging from 0.1 to 10 vol.%. Adding MORB to the olivine matrix significantly altered the composite&amp;#x27;s thermal conductivity. Prior to melting, composites containing 0.1 and 10 vol.% MORB showed the most pronounced increase in conductivity relative to pure olivine, while intermediate fractions (∼1–5 vol.%) exhibited a decrease, followed by a rise at higher MORB contents. We attribute this non‐monotonic behavior to impurity–lattice interactions within the MORB‐bearing olivine, which reduce lattice disorder and enhance heat transport. Upon melting MORB, the thermal conductivity of the composites decreased, with the largest reductions (∼35%) observed in the 0.1 and 10 vol.% MORB samples, indicating that the melt acts as a thermal insulator. Applied to planetary interiors, these results suggest that lateral variations in melt fraction within thermal boundary layers could generate heterogeneities in heat flow, potentially affecting mantle convection patterns and the formation or evolution of thermal plumes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Northward rupture and early afterslip of two graben-bounding normal faults during the 2025 Dingri earthquake of Tibet</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03132-0</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03132-0</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 14:54:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Wenbin Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengyuan Bai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuanchao Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Roland Bürgmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Baojun Shan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinjian Shan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhidan Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Shi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03132-0</prism:doi><description>The Mw 7.0 Dingri earthquake, the largest documented normal-faulting event in southern Tibet, struck within the NS-trending Dinggye-Xainza Rift system. Here we combine field observations, high resolution optical and synthetic aperture radar imagery and seismic waveforms to determine the three-dimensional coseismic deformation field, coseismic rupture processes and early postseismic deformation mechanisms of the event. We find that the rupture propagated unilaterally northward from the earthquake hypocenter, concurrently activating two graben-bounding faults. The main rupture was concentrated on the Dengmo Co fault causing a maximum subsidence of 3 m and a 25-km-long rupture trace at the surface. The first four-months postseismic deformation is dominated by shallow afterslip, which exhibits spatial overlap with the coseismic slip zone. Our observations provide important insights into the rupture kinematics and strain partitioning within the Dinggye-Xainza Rift, offering a valuable framework for understanding continental extensional tectonics and seismic cycle processes in similar southern Tibet grabens. A wedge-shaped graben extension mechanism for the 2025 Dingri earthquake involved two graben-bounding faults, highlighting that early postseismic deformation is mainly driven by shallow afterslip and viscoelastic relaxation, with the afterslip spatially complementing coseismic slip, according to integration of field observations, geodetic and seismic data.
Published: 2025-12-26T14:54:21+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.535 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Wenbin Xu; Chengyuan Bai; Chuanchao Huang; Roland Bürgmann; Baojun Shan; Xinjian Shan; Zhidan Chen; Lei Xie; Feng Shi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03132-0"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03132-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.535 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mw 7.0 Dingri earthquake, the largest documented normal-faulting event in southern Tibet, struck within the NS-trending Dinggye-Xainza Rift system. Here we combine field observations, high resolution optical and synthetic aperture radar imagery and seismic waveforms to determine the three-dimensional coseismic deformation field, coseismic rupture processes and early postseismic deformation mechanisms of the event. We find that the rupture propagated unilaterally northward from the earthquake hypocenter, concurrently activating two graben-bounding faults. The main rupture was concentrated on the Dengmo Co fault causing a maximum subsidence of 3 m and a 25-km-long rupture trace at the surface. The first four-months postseismic deformation is dominated by shallow afterslip, which exhibits spatial overlap with the coseismic slip zone. Our observations provide important insights into the rupture kinematics and strain partitioning within the Dinggye-Xainza Rift, offering a valuable framework for understanding continental extensional tectonics and seismic cycle processes in similar southern Tibet grabens. A wedge-shaped graben extension mechanism for the 2025 Dingri earthquake involved two graben-bounding faults, highlighting that early postseismic deformation is mainly driven by shallow afterslip and viscoelastic relaxation, with the afterslip spatially complementing coseismic slip, according to integration of field observations, geodetic and seismic data.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magnetotelluric Imaging of a Magma Plumbing System From the Asthenosphere to Crust Beneath the Newer Volcanic Province, Australia</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118189</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl118189</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 12:12:10 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xinpeng Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunhe Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Changchun Yin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haibin Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhihao Rong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingru Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lutz Gross</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yabin Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl118189</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Newer Volcanic Province (NVP) in southeastern Australia is a classic example of continental intraplate volcanism located far from a plate boundary, yet the configuration of its magma plumbing system remains unclear. Using three‐dimensional (3D) magnetotelluric (MT) inversion, we imaged a vertically continuous, trans‐lithospheric conductive structure beneath the NVP. This structure consists of a sub‐horizontal zone in the asthenospheric mantle, interpreted as 0.1–1.0 vol.% carbonate‐rich melt, vertically linked to hydrous basaltic melt zones (2–5 vol.%) in the lithospheric mantle and shallow crust. These upper crust conductive zones likely represent remnant melt or metasomatic minerals. These features define a vertically integrated magma plumbing system from the asthenosphere to the surface. The geometry and depth of the anomalies are consistent with scenarios in which the carbonate‐rich melt may form in response to shear‐driven upwelling and edge‐driven convection. These observations provide new constraints on possible mantle processes that drive intraplate volcanism.
Published: 2025-12-26T12:12:10+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.530 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xinpeng Ma; Yunhe Liu; Changchun Yin; Haibin Yang; Zhihao Rong; Jingru Li; Lutz Gross; Yabin Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118189"&gt;10.1029/2025gl118189&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.530 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Newer Volcanic Province (NVP) in southeastern Australia is a classic example of continental intraplate volcanism located far from a plate boundary, yet the configuration of its magma plumbing system remains unclear. Using three‐dimensional (3D) magnetotelluric (MT) inversion, we imaged a vertically continuous, trans‐lithospheric conductive structure beneath the NVP. This structure consists of a sub‐horizontal zone in the asthenospheric mantle, interpreted as 0.1–1.0 vol.% carbonate‐rich melt, vertically linked to hydrous basaltic melt zones (2–5 vol.%) in the lithospheric mantle and shallow crust. These upper crust conductive zones likely represent remnant melt or metasomatic minerals. These features define a vertically integrated magma plumbing system from the asthenosphere to the surface. The geometry and depth of the anomalies are consistent with scenarios in which the carbonate‐rich melt may form in response to shear‐driven upwelling and edge‐driven convection. These observations provide new constraints on possible mantle processes that drive intraplate volcanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Nano-confinement engineering boosts C–N coupling for urea electrosynthesis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67741-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67741-1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 11:44:11 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jiaxin Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunshuo Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Siyu Fang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daliang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Heng Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhongbiao Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gaoqing Max Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuanhao Wu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67741-1</prism:doi><description>The electrochemical co-reduction of CO2 and nitrate provides a sustainable route for urea synthesis via C–N coupling, yet kinetic limitations and poor intermediate interactions hinder urea yields. Here, we engineer a nano-confined CuRu bimetallic catalyst within mesoporous carbon hollow spheres (MCHS) to overcome these barriers. By spatially confining reactants and intermediates, the catalyst achieves a urea yield of 12.51 g h–1 gcat–1 at 250 mA cm–2, with 125-hour stability. In situ spectroscopy and computational analyses reveal that nano-confinement switches the C–N coupling pathway from the thermodynamically favored *COOH–*NH2 to kinetically driven *OCO–*NO intermediates, bypassing energy barriers. Precise pore-size engineering (4–11 nm) demonstrates that optimal confinement simultaneously enhances reactant transport and intermediate retention, boosting selectivity. This work establishes nano-confinement as a versatile approach for controlling multi-step electrocatalytic processes, enabling sustainable chemical synthesis. This study introduces a nano-confined CuRu catalyst that leverages confinement effects to enhance CO2–nitrate C–N coupling by improving reactant transport and strengthening the stabilization of key reaction intermediates, thereby achieving high urea yield and long-term operational stability.
Published: 2025-12-26T11:44:11+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.525 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jiaxin Du; Yunshuo Wu; Siyu Fang; Daliang Xu; Min Liu; Heng Liang; Zhongbiao Wu; Gaoqing Max Lu; Xuanhao Wu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67741-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67741-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.525 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electrochemical co-reduction of CO2 and nitrate provides a sustainable route for urea synthesis via C–N coupling, yet kinetic limitations and poor intermediate interactions hinder urea yields. Here, we engineer a nano-confined CuRu bimetallic catalyst within mesoporous carbon hollow spheres (MCHS) to overcome these barriers. By spatially confining reactants and intermediates, the catalyst achieves a urea yield of 12.51 g h–1 gcat–1 at 250 mA cm–2, with 125-hour stability. In situ spectroscopy and computational analyses reveal that nano-confinement switches the C–N coupling pathway from the thermodynamically favored *COOH–*NH2 to kinetically driven *OCO–*NO intermediates, bypassing energy barriers. Precise pore-size engineering (4–11 nm) demonstrates that optimal confinement simultaneously enhances reactant transport and intermediate retention, boosting selectivity. This work establishes nano-confinement as a versatile approach for controlling multi-step electrocatalytic processes, enabling sustainable chemical synthesis. This study introduces a nano-confined CuRu catalyst that leverages confinement effects to enhance CO2–nitrate C–N coupling by improving reactant transport and strengthening the stabilization of key reaction intermediates, thereby achieving high urea yield and long-term operational stability.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Elevated atmospheric CO2 decreases methylmercury production in freshwater lakes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67788-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67788-0</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 06:22:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pei Lei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jin Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ri-Qing Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maciej Bartosiewicz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengjun Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>R. Iestyn Woolway</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin Tsz-Ki Tsui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Meng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Raymond W. M. Kwong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuming Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huan He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinghui Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongqiang Ren</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huan Zhong</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67788-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract Elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) level reshapes microbial communities in nature, yet its consequences for neurotoxic methylmercury (MeHg) production in waters remain unclear. Here, we show that elevated CO 2 levels (650 and 1000 ppm) consistently reduced net MeHg production across 45 freshwater lakes spanning 1200 longitudinal kilometers, particularly in eutrophic conditions (54–96%). Elevated CO 2 -driven shifts in carbon substrates favored hydrogenotrophic methanogens (e.g., Methanobacterium ) lacking the hgcA methylation gene over hgcA -harboring acetoclastic strains (e.g., Methanosarcina ), decreasing methanogen abundance (18–98% in hgcA copies) and activity (13–53% in net CH 4 production) and suppressing Hg methylation. Model simulations predict a 33%–74% global decline in lake MeHg production under future CO 2 scenarios, partially counteract MeHg increases associated with intensified algal blooms under warming. This overlooked pathway highlights the need to integrate interacting climate drivers to improve predictions of MeHg risks in a climate-changing future.
Published: 2025-12-26T06:22:14+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.524 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pei Lei; Jin Zhang; Ri-Qing Yu; Maciej Bartosiewicz; Chengjun Li; R. Iestyn Woolway; Martin Tsz-Ki Tsui; Tao Jiang; Bo Meng; Raymond W. M. Kwong; Yuming Guo; Huan He; Xinghui Xia; Hongqiang Ren; Huan Zhong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67788-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67788-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.524 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) level reshapes microbial communities in nature, yet its consequences for neurotoxic methylmercury (MeHg) production in waters remain unclear. Here, we show that elevated CO 2 levels (650 and 1000 ppm) consistently reduced net MeHg production across 45 freshwater lakes spanning 1200 longitudinal kilometers, particularly in eutrophic conditions (54–96%). Elevated CO 2 -driven shifts in carbon substrates favored hydrogenotrophic methanogens (e.g., Methanobacterium ) lacking the hgcA methylation gene over hgcA -harboring acetoclastic strains (e.g., Methanosarcina ), decreasing methanogen abundance (18–98% in hgcA copies) and activity (13–53% in net CH 4 production) and suppressing Hg methylation. Model simulations predict a 33%–74% global decline in lake MeHg production under future CO 2 scenarios, partially counteract MeHg increases associated with intensified algal blooms under warming. This overlooked pathway highlights the need to integrate interacting climate drivers to improve predictions of MeHg risks in a climate-changing future.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Small PdCx interstitial compound for efficient acidic CO2 electroreduction to formic acid</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67949-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67949-1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 10:45:37 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yaodong Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zuochao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weizhou Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiani Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tian Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guangzhe Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongdong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qingliang Lv</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexander V. Kutchin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianping Lai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67949-1</prism:doi><description>The development of efficient acidic CO2 reduction reaction (CO2RR) to high value-added chemical HCOOH at high current density (&amp;gt;1 A cm-2) is crucial. However, addressing high potential, low Faradaic efficiency (FE), and poor stability simultaneously under acidic conditions remains challenging. Here, we construct small PdCx interstitial compounds and engineer the interstitial atoms to modulate the catalyst’s soft acid strength, thereby overcoming the triple challenge of “low overpotential-high current density-high stability” in acidic CO₂RR to HCOOH. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations and experimental characterization reveal that interstitial carbon infusion modulates Pd’s soft acid strength and weakens the Pd-O bond energy to form and desorb HCOOH, circumventing CO poisoning of the catalyst. Meanwhile, interstitial carbon infusion optimizes electronic structures, enhancing OCHO intermediate coverage as well as the effective retention and utilization of *H. This effect suppresses hydrogen evolution reaction (HER) while enhancing HCOOH selectivity. The optimized PdC0.13/CNT achieves &amp;gt;95% FEHCOOH and demonstrates stability in a proton exchange membrane (PEM) electrolyzer, maintaining 1000 mA cm-2 operation for 500 hours at 1.8 V cell voltage. Efficient acidic CO2 reduction to HCOOH at high current density faces challenges of high overpotential, low Faraday efficiency, and poor stability. This study optimizes these three key metrics by modulating soft acid strength through interstitial atoms.
Published: 2025-12-26T10:45:37+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.521 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yaodong Yu; Zuochao Wang; Weizhou Wang; Jiani Han; Tian Dong; Guangzhe Jin; Hongdong Li; Qingliang Lv; Alexander V. Kutchin; Jianping Lai; Lei Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67949-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67949-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.521 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development of efficient acidic CO2 reduction reaction (CO2RR) to high value-added chemical HCOOH at high current density (&amp;amp;gt;1 A cm-2) is crucial. However, addressing high potential, low Faradaic efficiency (FE), and poor stability simultaneously under acidic conditions remains challenging. Here, we construct small PdCx interstitial compounds and engineer the interstitial atoms to modulate the catalyst’s soft acid strength, thereby overcoming the triple challenge of “low overpotential-high current density-high stability” in acidic CO₂RR to HCOOH. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations and experimental characterization reveal that interstitial carbon infusion modulates Pd’s soft acid strength and weakens the Pd-O bond energy to form and desorb HCOOH, circumventing CO poisoning of the catalyst. Meanwhile, interstitial carbon infusion optimizes electronic structures, enhancing OCHO intermediate coverage as well as the effective retention and utilization of *H. This effect suppresses hydrogen evolution reaction (HER) while enhancing HCOOH selectivity. The optimized PdC0.13/CNT achieves &amp;amp;gt;95% FEHCOOH and demonstrates stability in a proton exchange membrane (PEM) electrolyzer, maintaining 1000 mA cm-2 operation for 500 hours at 1.8 V cell voltage. Efficient acidic CO2 reduction to HCOOH at high current density faces challenges of high overpotential, low Faraday efficiency, and poor stability. This study optimizes these three key metrics by modulating soft acid strength through interstitial atoms.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Brittle and Crystal‐Plastic Defect Dynamics of Calcite Single Crystals</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032846</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032846</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 12:51:51 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>H. O’ Ghaffari</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. Peč</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. J. Cross</dc:creator><dc:creator>T. Mittal</dc:creator><dc:creator>U. Mok</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032846</prism:doi><description>Abstract The response of Earth materials to stress has a first‐order control on solid‐Earth dynamics ranging from earthquakes to volcanic eruptions to landslides. Thus, understanding the rheological behavior of minerals, preferentially at a micro‐scale to allow process‐based upscaling, has broad applications across the Earth sciences. Cracks, dislocations, and point defects are microscale agents of deformation that govern the macro‐scale response of rocks under stress. Complexity in deformation behavior arises from the interplay among these defect types. Here, we deformed calcite single crystals under uniaxial loading to study defect dynamics using an array of piezo‐sensors synchronized with fast‐camera recordings. We demonstrate that brittle cracking co‐occurs with crystal‐plastic twinning deformation. Furthermore, each mechanism produces distinct impulsive ultrasonic signals. Cracking produces energetic signals often with high‐frequency patterns. Meanwhile, mechanical twinning produces less energetic, shorter duration, low‐frequency signals correlated with propagating twin fronts. These signals can be fit with a second derivative of a Gaussian function for the first few cycles after their onset. Our results illustrate key microscale processes that drive permanent deformation in calcite, and thus contribute to building an experimentally based, process‐driven understanding of rheological behavior. We highlight the utility of using ultrasonic signals, with detailed time‐series analysis, to help infer in situ microscale deformation at a range of spatiotemporal scales.
Published: 2025-12-26T12:51:51+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.518 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; H. O’ Ghaffari; M. Peč; A. J. Cross; T. Mittal; U. Mok&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032846"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032846&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.518 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The response of Earth materials to stress has a first‐order control on solid‐Earth dynamics ranging from earthquakes to volcanic eruptions to landslides. Thus, understanding the rheological behavior of minerals, preferentially at a micro‐scale to allow process‐based upscaling, has broad applications across the Earth sciences. Cracks, dislocations, and point defects are microscale agents of deformation that govern the macro‐scale response of rocks under stress. Complexity in deformation behavior arises from the interplay among these defect types. Here, we deformed calcite single crystals under uniaxial loading to study defect dynamics using an array of piezo‐sensors synchronized with fast‐camera recordings. We demonstrate that brittle cracking co‐occurs with crystal‐plastic twinning deformation. Furthermore, each mechanism produces distinct impulsive ultrasonic signals. Cracking produces energetic signals often with high‐frequency patterns. Meanwhile, mechanical twinning produces less energetic, shorter duration, low‐frequency signals correlated with propagating twin fronts. These signals can be fit with a second derivative of a Gaussian function for the first few cycles after their onset. Our results illustrate key microscale processes that drive permanent deformation in calcite, and thus contribute to building an experimentally based, process‐driven understanding of rheological behavior. We highlight the utility of using ultrasonic signals, with detailed time‐series analysis, to help infer in situ microscale deformation at a range of spatiotemporal scales.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Oxygen-modulated engineering of Cu0–Cu+ interfaces for CO2-to-C2H4 photoreduction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67844-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67844-9</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 08:45:30 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yuqi Ren</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miao Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongbin He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Changjun You</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lunbo Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenkun Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruoxuan Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuan-Hao Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongyang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiancheng Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Guan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Naixu Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67844-9</prism:doi><description>CO2-to-hydrocarbon fuel conversion via artificial photosynthesis is limited by catalyst poisoning under high O2 partial pressures and sluggish C2-product formation. Herein, Ru0.6Cu1(Cu0–Cu1+)/CeO2 catalysts with adaptive O2 tolerance are prepared by O2-mediated dynamic interfacial reconstruction. Single-atom Ru doping at Ce lattice sites creates a trigonal prismatic coordination configuration, enabling proton-coupled electron transfer and accelerating H2O dissociation. Photothermal effect promotes O2-driven self-assembly of Cu0–Cu1+ charge-gradient interfaces within Ru/Cu alloy clusters, thereby optimizing the adsorption behavior of *CHOCO intermediates and restructuring the C–C coupling pathway. Interfacial charge cascade transfer and geometric site synergy thermodynamically shift the product selectivity from C1 to C2, as determined by operando spectroscopy and electronic structure analysis. Under concentrated solar irradiation, the catalyst produces 549 ± 20 μmol·g−1 C2H4 with 74.3% selectivity and 0.5% solar-to-chemical energy conversion efficiency—25-fold higher than that in non-concentrated systems. Dynamic interfacial regulation facilitates precise carbon chain synthesis in complex reaction networks. Ru0.6Cu1(Cu0–Cu1+)/CeO2 catalyst converts CO2-to-fuels via artificial photosynthesis, overcoming O2 poisoning and sluggish C2 yield through photothermal interface reconstruction. It achieves 74.3% selectivity for C2H4 with 0.5% solar efficiency.
Published: 2025-12-26T08:45:30+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.517 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yuqi Ren; Miao Cheng; Hongbin He; Changjun You; Lunbo Duan; Zhenkun Sun; Ruoxuan Peng; Yuan-Hao Zhu; Hongyang Zhang; Jiancheng Zhou; Kai Huang; Jie Guan; Naixu Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67844-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67844-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.517 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CO2-to-hydrocarbon fuel conversion via artificial photosynthesis is limited by catalyst poisoning under high O2 partial pressures and sluggish C2-product formation. Herein, Ru0.6Cu1(Cu0–Cu1+)/CeO2 catalysts with adaptive O2 tolerance are prepared by O2-mediated dynamic interfacial reconstruction. Single-atom Ru doping at Ce lattice sites creates a trigonal prismatic coordination configuration, enabling proton-coupled electron transfer and accelerating H2O dissociation. Photothermal effect promotes O2-driven self-assembly of Cu0–Cu1+ charge-gradient interfaces within Ru/Cu alloy clusters, thereby optimizing the adsorption behavior of *CHOCO intermediates and restructuring the C–C coupling pathway. Interfacial charge cascade transfer and geometric site synergy thermodynamically shift the product selectivity from C1 to C2, as determined by operando spectroscopy and electronic structure analysis. Under concentrated solar irradiation, the catalyst produces 549 ± 20 μmol·g−1 C2H4 with 74.3% selectivity and 0.5% solar-to-chemical energy conversion efficiency—25-fold higher than that in non-concentrated systems. Dynamic interfacial regulation facilitates precise carbon chain synthesis in complex reaction networks. Ru0.6Cu1(Cu0–Cu1+)/CeO2 catalyst converts CO2-to-fuels via artificial photosynthesis, overcoming O2 poisoning and sluggish C2 yield through photothermal interface reconstruction. It achieves 74.3% selectivity for C2H4 with 0.5% solar efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Tuning valley polarization of moiré trapped biexcitons by fine structure occupation in WS2/WSe2 heterostructures</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67846-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67846-7</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 09:46:04 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yufei Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongzhi She</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinke Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qinghai Tan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinlong Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yilong Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peiwu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaotian Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zengkai Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongbing Cai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nan Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoping Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67846-7</prism:doi><description>Abstract Two-dimensional transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) heterostructures formed moiré superlattices have emerged as a new platform for exploring correlated excitonic states and valleytronic phenomena. Despite the significant progress in moiré-trapped single excitons, the valley polarization and fine structure of moiré-trapped biexcitons remain poorly understood, with the existing studies reporting only limited or zero polarization and lacking insight into the underlying mechanisms. Here, we study the moiré-trapped interlayer biexcitons in WS 2 /WSe 2 heterostructures through power- and temperature-dependent photoluminescence (PL) spectroscopy. We find that the valley polarization of these biexcitons can be effectively tuned, reaching ~ $$55\%$$ 55 % at 120 K. This behavior is attributed to the different occupation of intravalley and intervalley biexcitons within the fine structure, with the intravalley biexcitons playing a dominant role. The power-dependent energy splitting and temperature-dependent polarization trends further confirm the existence of biexciton fine structure and its influence on valley polarization. Furthermore, the experiment revealed a fine structure splitting of 2.77 meV, consistent with theoretical calculations. Our study provides new insight into the rational control of excitonic states in moiré superlattices and establishes a basis for developing advanced valleytronic devices, such as polarization-sensitive photodetectors and quantum light sources.
Published: 2025-12-26T09:46:04+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.515 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yufei Jiang; Yongzhi She; Xinke Cheng; Qinghai Tan; Jinlong Yang; Yilong Zhao; Peiwu Liu; Min Wu; Xiaotian Dai; Zengkai Wang; Hongbing Cai; Nan Pan; Xiaoping Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67846-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67846-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.515 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Two-dimensional transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) heterostructures formed moiré superlattices have emerged as a new platform for exploring correlated excitonic states and valleytronic phenomena. Despite the significant progress in moiré-trapped single excitons, the valley polarization and fine structure of moiré-trapped biexcitons remain poorly understood, with the existing studies reporting only limited or zero polarization and lacking insight into the underlying mechanisms. Here, we study the moiré-trapped interlayer biexcitons in WS 2 /WSe 2 heterostructures through power- and temperature-dependent photoluminescence (PL) spectroscopy. We find that the valley polarization of these biexcitons can be effectively tuned, reaching ~ $$55\%$$ 55 % at 120 K. This behavior is attributed to the different occupation of intravalley and intervalley biexcitons within the fine structure, with the intravalley biexcitons playing a dominant role. The power-dependent energy splitting and temperature-dependent polarization trends further confirm the existence of biexciton fine structure and its influence on valley polarization. Furthermore, the experiment revealed a fine structure splitting of 2.77 meV, consistent with theoretical calculations. Our study provides new insight into the rational control of excitonic states in moiré superlattices and establishes a basis for developing advanced valleytronic devices, such as polarization-sensitive photodetectors and quantum light sources.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Continental outflow shapes the circum-Antarctic pattern of summertime atmospheric mercury depletion zones</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67864-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67864-5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 18:04:54 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhouqing Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fange Yue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hélène Angot</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haicong Zhan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongwei Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Biao Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aurélien Dommergue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Olivier Magand</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67864-5</prism:doi><description>Atmospheric mercury depletion events (AMDEs) are a unique phenomenon in polar mercury cycling, involving intense atmospheric mercury oxidation and deposition that amplify marine mercury sinks. The Southern Ocean, a critical hotspot for environmental mercury exposure, exhibits AMDEs whose characteristics and distribution patterns remain unclear. This study presents the observational dataset of atmospheric gaseous elemental mercury (GEM) across the circum-Antarctic Southern Ocean. We observed pronounced summertime AMDEs that drove high spatial heterogeneity in circumpolar GEM distribution. By combining Generalized Additive Models (GAM) simulations with multi-platform observational evidence, we demonstrate that the Antarctic continental outflow largely shapes the circumpolar distribution of summertime AMDEs, concentrating these events within the convergence zones of katabatic winds. This work highlights the critical role of land-sea coupling effects in Antarctic atmospheric chemistry, and underscores the need to systematically assess the implications of these processes for mercury bioavailability across Southern Ocean ecosystems. Air flowing out from the Antarctic continent largely determines where summer atmospheric mercury depletion events (AMDEs) occur around Antarctica, making them most common in areas where Antarctic cold, downslope winds meet.
Published: 2025-12-26T18:04:54+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.509 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhouqing Xie; Fange Yue; Hélène Angot; Haicong Zhan; Hongwei Liu; Biao Tian; Aurélien Dommergue; Olivier Magand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67864-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67864-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.509 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atmospheric mercury depletion events (AMDEs) are a unique phenomenon in polar mercury cycling, involving intense atmospheric mercury oxidation and deposition that amplify marine mercury sinks. The Southern Ocean, a critical hotspot for environmental mercury exposure, exhibits AMDEs whose characteristics and distribution patterns remain unclear. This study presents the observational dataset of atmospheric gaseous elemental mercury (GEM) across the circum-Antarctic Southern Ocean. We observed pronounced summertime AMDEs that drove high spatial heterogeneity in circumpolar GEM distribution. By combining Generalized Additive Models (GAM) simulations with multi-platform observational evidence, we demonstrate that the Antarctic continental outflow largely shapes the circumpolar distribution of summertime AMDEs, concentrating these events within the convergence zones of katabatic winds. This work highlights the critical role of land-sea coupling effects in Antarctic atmospheric chemistry, and underscores the need to systematically assess the implications of these processes for mercury bioavailability across Southern Ocean ecosystems. Air flowing out from the Antarctic continent largely determines where summer atmospheric mercury depletion events (AMDEs) occur around Antarctica, making them most common in areas where Antarctic cold, downslope winds meet.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Surface halogenation engineering for reversible silicon-based solid-state batteries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67985-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67985-x</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 15:14:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Haosheng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yaru Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guantai Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Caijin Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liang Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huiqin Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haochang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ning Lin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67985-x</prism:doi><description>Silicon-based solid-state batteries are promising next-generation high-energy-density technologies. However, poor (electro)chemical compatibility between silicon negative electrodes and solid electrolytes (e.g., Li6PS5Cl) plus sluggish interfacial kinetics severely limits their reversibility and Coulombic efficiency. Here, we propose a surface halogenation strategy that transforms the native amorphous SiO2 passivation layer on silicon particles into a functional Al(Si)OCl composite surface via controlled reaction with AlCl3. This artificial interphase reconciles interfacial incompatibility and enables fast ionic/electronic transport, suppressing irreversible lithium loss. The optimized negative electrode achieves a high initial Coulombic efficiency of 94.3% in half-cells and 85.6% initial Coulombic efficiency (86.6% with pre-lithiation) in full cells paired with LiNi0.88Co0.09Mn0.03O2. Enhanced reversibility further delivers long-term cyclability. The optimized negative electrode delivers 86% capacity retention and 99.998% average Coulombic efficiency over 200 cycles. Even at high-loading ( &amp;gt; 10 mAh cm-2, and no adhesives/conductive carbon/electrolyte), it retains 72% capacity after 500 cycles. The full cells maintain 80% capacity after 200 cycles at 1 C, with an average Coulombic efficiency exceeding 99.95%. The versatility of this halogenation strategy underscores halide chemistry’s broad potential in advancing high-performance, reversible silicon-based solid-state batteries. Silicon negative electrodes in solid-state batteries exhibit poor reversibility. Here, the authors demonstrate surface halogenation engineering that suppresses irreversible lithium loss, achieving 94.3% initial Coulombic efficiency and 72% capacity retention over 500 cycles at 25°C.
Published: 2025-12-27T15:14:17+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.505 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Haosheng Li; Yaru Li; Guantai Hu; Ying Li; Caijin Xiao; Liang Zhao; Huiqin Huang; Haochang Zhang; Wei Xia; Ning Lin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67985-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67985-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.505 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silicon-based solid-state batteries are promising next-generation high-energy-density technologies. However, poor (electro)chemical compatibility between silicon negative electrodes and solid electrolytes (e.g., Li6PS5Cl) plus sluggish interfacial kinetics severely limits their reversibility and Coulombic efficiency. Here, we propose a surface halogenation strategy that transforms the native amorphous SiO2 passivation layer on silicon particles into a functional Al(Si)OCl composite surface via controlled reaction with AlCl3. This artificial interphase reconciles interfacial incompatibility and enables fast ionic/electronic transport, suppressing irreversible lithium loss. The optimized negative electrode achieves a high initial Coulombic efficiency of 94.3% in half-cells and 85.6% initial Coulombic efficiency (86.6% with pre-lithiation) in full cells paired with LiNi0.88Co0.09Mn0.03O2. Enhanced reversibility further delivers long-term cyclability. The optimized negative electrode delivers 86% capacity retention and 99.998% average Coulombic efficiency over 200 cycles. Even at high-loading ( &amp;amp;gt; 10 mAh cm-2, and no adhesives/conductive carbon/electrolyte), it retains 72% capacity after 500 cycles. The full cells maintain 80% capacity after 200 cycles at 1 C, with an average Coulombic efficiency exceeding 99.95%. The versatility of this halogenation strategy underscores halide chemistry’s broad potential in advancing high-performance, reversible silicon-based solid-state batteries. Silicon negative electrodes in solid-state batteries exhibit poor reversibility. Here, the authors demonstrate surface halogenation engineering that suppresses irreversible lithium loss, achieving 94.3% initial Coulombic efficiency and 72% capacity retention over 500 cycles at 25°C.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seismic Anisotropy and Mantle Deformation Beneath Northeast China: Insight From Shear Wave Splitting Analysis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031814</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb031814</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:03:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhengyang Qiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qingju Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yonghua Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb031814</prism:doi><description>Abstract This study investigates upper mantle deformation beneath northeast (NE) China by reanalyzing shear wave splitting measurements from the WAVESArray network. We identify potential overestimations of anisotropy strength in previous studies, likely caused by sensor misorientation and misclassification of null measurements. Our analysis yields 110 well‐constrained splitting measurements from 66 stations and 43 high‐quality null measurements from 28 stations. The mean delay time is 0.82 ± 0.28 s, consistent with the global continental average (∼1.0 s) but significantly smaller than prior estimates. Based on the spatial coherence analysis of shear wave splitting parameters and previous P ‐wave anisotropy results, we conclude that the anisotropy mainly originates in the lithosphere or the upper mantle transition zone (MTZ), rather than the mantle wedge. Combining our measurements with previous shear wave splitting results, we infer that the predominant NNW‐SSE trending anisotropy reflects fossilized Mesozoic extensional deformation in the lithosphere or the influence of the Paleo‐Pacific Plate subduction within the MTZ. Additionally, in the easternmost Xing'an Block, localized ENE‐WSW fast directions may reflect preserved Proterozoic microcontinental fragments. The solely null measurements and weak anisotropy observed around the intraplate volcanoes suggest the possible presence of localized upwelling of hot material or oriented melt pockets. These findings highlight a complex interplay of multi‐scale mantle and lithospheric processes shaping seismic anisotropy in NE China, providing important insights into the geodynamic processes of the Central Asian Orogenic Belt.
Published: 2025-12-27T18:03:52+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.503 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhengyang Qiang; Qingju Wu; Yonghua Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031814"&gt;10.1029/2025jb031814&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.503 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract This study investigates upper mantle deformation beneath northeast (NE) China by reanalyzing shear wave splitting measurements from the WAVESArray network. We identify potential overestimations of anisotropy strength in previous studies, likely caused by sensor misorientation and misclassification of null measurements. Our analysis yields 110 well‐constrained splitting measurements from 66 stations and 43 high‐quality null measurements from 28 stations. The mean delay time is 0.82 ± 0.28 s, consistent with the global continental average (∼1.0 s) but significantly smaller than prior estimates. Based on the spatial coherence analysis of shear wave splitting parameters and previous P ‐wave anisotropy results, we conclude that the anisotropy mainly originates in the lithosphere or the upper mantle transition zone (MTZ), rather than the mantle wedge. Combining our measurements with previous shear wave splitting results, we infer that the predominant NNW‐SSE trending anisotropy reflects fossilized Mesozoic extensional deformation in the lithosphere or the influence of the Paleo‐Pacific Plate subduction within the MTZ. Additionally, in the easternmost Xing&amp;#x27;an Block, localized ENE‐WSW fast directions may reflect preserved Proterozoic microcontinental fragments. The solely null measurements and weak anisotropy observed around the intraplate volcanoes suggest the possible presence of localized upwelling of hot material or oriented melt pockets. These findings highlight a complex interplay of multi‐scale mantle and lithospheric processes shaping seismic anisotropy in NE China, providing important insights into the geodynamic processes of the Central Asian Orogenic Belt.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Highly efficient heterogeneous thermal catalysis for noble-metal-free hydrogen production from formic acid</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67895-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67895-y</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 02:54:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Liang Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lin Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ping Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiwei Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinglin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yixin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaosong Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Muhammad Salman Nasir</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ding Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinqiang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Baowen Zhou</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67895-y</prism:doi><description>Hydrogen extraction from liquid hydrogen carriers is a promising strategy to address hydrogen storage and transportation challenges for a hydrogen economy. We report a novel heterogeneous catalytic architecture, Ni(Mn)-O-P/GaN nanowires, for efficient, selective, and ultra-stable hydrogen evolution from formic acid (FA). The catalyst achieves a high activity of 29.92 mol H2·gcat−1·h−1 with nearly 100% selectivity and a high turnover frequency (TOF) of 31,019.2 h−1 at 150 °C. It exhibits exceptional stability over 4000 hours under fluctuated temperatures (55-75 °C) with a turnover numbers (TONs) of 5,023,060, integrable with low-grade industrial waste heat. In-situ characterizations, isotope experiments, and density functional theory calculations collectively reveal that the synergy between Ni(Mn)-O-P and GaN are favorable for the O-H dissociation of FA with an interesting H-exchange mechanism with H2O while inhibiting the undesired FA dehydration and coking formation. An industrial prototype test validates practical on-demand hydrogen production using waste heat. Finding efficient ways to release hydrogen from liquid carriers is key to advancing clean energy systems. This study introduces a resilient catalyst that drives highly selective hydrogen production from formic acid using low-grade heat.
Published: 2025-12-27T02:54:16+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.501 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Liang Qiu; Lin Yao; Ping Wang; Zhiwei Jiang; Jinglin Li; Ying Li; Yixin Li; Zhaosong Wu; Muhammad Salman Nasir; Ding Wang; Xinqiang Wang; Zhen Huang; Baowen Zhou&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67895-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67895-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.501 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hydrogen extraction from liquid hydrogen carriers is a promising strategy to address hydrogen storage and transportation challenges for a hydrogen economy. We report a novel heterogeneous catalytic architecture, Ni(Mn)-O-P/GaN nanowires, for efficient, selective, and ultra-stable hydrogen evolution from formic acid (FA). The catalyst achieves a high activity of 29.92 mol H2·gcat−1·h−1 with nearly 100% selectivity and a high turnover frequency (TOF) of 31,019.2 h−1 at 150 °C. It exhibits exceptional stability over 4000 hours under fluctuated temperatures (55-75 °C) with a turnover numbers (TONs) of 5,023,060, integrable with low-grade industrial waste heat. In-situ characterizations, isotope experiments, and density functional theory calculations collectively reveal that the synergy between Ni(Mn)-O-P and GaN are favorable for the O-H dissociation of FA with an interesting H-exchange mechanism with H2O while inhibiting the undesired FA dehydration and coking formation. An industrial prototype test validates practical on-demand hydrogen production using waste heat. Finding efficient ways to release hydrogen from liquid carriers is key to advancing clean energy systems. This study introduces a resilient catalyst that drives highly selective hydrogen production from formic acid using low-grade heat.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Spectrally encoded parallel LiDAR driven by super-bunching light</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67926-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67926-8</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 09:46:04 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xuedong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinghui Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiangdong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuanyuan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunrui Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aoni Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kaige Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenxue Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhichun Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianyong Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruiyun Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guofeng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liantuan Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suotang Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengbing Qin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67926-8</prism:doi><description>Parallel light detection and ranging (LiDAR) is widely adopted for its low computational burden and rapid three-dimensional (3D) reconstruction. Yet, it remains constrained by inter-channel crosstalk and limited long-distance performance. Here, we introduce a spectrally encoded parallel LiDAR based on super-bunching light, exhibiting negligible cross-correlation between wavelengths, enabling quasi-orthogonal channel division without crosstalk. This approach supports robust parallel ranging, rapid and accurate 3D reconstruction, and effective target classification. Our scheme achieves high-precision ranging with errors as low as 4 mm and can detect targets moving at velocities as low as 5 mm/s. It further enables reliable ranging and 3D imaging beyond 40 m, with exceptional anti-interference performance, even when noise exceeds the echo signal by three orders of magnitude. Combining high precision, sensitivity, long-range detection, dynamic target acquisition, precise 3D reconstruction, and robust anti-interference, our LiDAR offers significant potential for enhancing environmental perception technologies. The authors leverage a super-bunching light to develop a spectrally encoded parallel LiDAR that achieves crosstalk-free optical channel division and supports effective long-range detection beyond conventional pulse-period limitations without requiring additional encoding or decoding.
Published: 2025-12-26T09:46:04+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.495 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xuedong Zhang; Xinghui Liu; Xiangdong Li; Yuanyuan Li; Yunrui Song; Aoni Wei; Kaige Hu; Wenxue Zhang; Zhichun Yang; Jianyong Hu; Ruiyun Chen; Guofeng Zhang; Jie Ma; Liantuan Xiao; Suotang Jia; Chengbing Qin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67926-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67926-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.495 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parallel light detection and ranging (LiDAR) is widely adopted for its low computational burden and rapid three-dimensional (3D) reconstruction. Yet, it remains constrained by inter-channel crosstalk and limited long-distance performance. Here, we introduce a spectrally encoded parallel LiDAR based on super-bunching light, exhibiting negligible cross-correlation between wavelengths, enabling quasi-orthogonal channel division without crosstalk. This approach supports robust parallel ranging, rapid and accurate 3D reconstruction, and effective target classification. Our scheme achieves high-precision ranging with errors as low as 4 mm and can detect targets moving at velocities as low as 5 mm/s. It further enables reliable ranging and 3D imaging beyond 40 m, with exceptional anti-interference performance, even when noise exceeds the echo signal by three orders of magnitude. Combining high precision, sensitivity, long-range detection, dynamic target acquisition, precise 3D reconstruction, and robust anti-interference, our LiDAR offers significant potential for enhancing environmental perception technologies. The authors leverage a super-bunching light to develop a spectrally encoded parallel LiDAR that achieves crosstalk-free optical channel division and supports effective long-range detection beyond conventional pulse-period limitations without requiring additional encoding or decoding.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Variability of Particulate Organic Carbon Stock in the South China Sea With Reference to Profile Structures</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119155</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119155</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 16:06:34 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Teng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Bai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xianqiang He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bangyi Tao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fang Gong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yifan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuchen Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunfang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhihong Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119155</prism:doi><description>Abstract Accurate characterization of particulate organic carbon (POC) stock is essential for understanding regional biological pump processes, yet the roles of vertical structure and integration depth in regulating POC stock variability remain unclear in marginal seas. Using a performance‐evaluated 3D POC data set, we assessed POC stock changes in the South China Sea. Column‐mean POC covaries tightly with surface POC ( R &gt; 0.9) in both the euphotic zone and the upper 100 m. From 2003 to 2023, POC in the upper 100 m showed a basin‐wide decline (−0.1 mg·m −3 ·y −1 ). For euphotic‐zone POC stock, vertical structure accounts for only ∼30% of its variability, whereas euphotic depth exerts dominant control, driving a summertime maximum and a positive changing rate (3.68 mg·m −2 ·y −1 ) in 2003–2023. These non‐steady‐state stock changes highlight the need to jointly evaluate POC production, storage, and export when assessing local biological carbon pump dynamics.
Published: 2025-12-26T16:06:34+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.493 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Teng Li; Yan Bai; Xianqiang He; Bangyi Tao; Xuan Zhang; Fang Gong; Yifan Zhang; Xuchen Jin; Chunfang Zhang; Zhihong Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119155"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119155&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.493 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Accurate characterization of particulate organic carbon (POC) stock is essential for understanding regional biological pump processes, yet the roles of vertical structure and integration depth in regulating POC stock variability remain unclear in marginal seas. Using a performance‐evaluated 3D POC data set, we assessed POC stock changes in the South China Sea. Column‐mean POC covaries tightly with surface POC ( R &amp;gt; 0.9) in both the euphotic zone and the upper 100 m. From 2003 to 2023, POC in the upper 100 m showed a basin‐wide decline (−0.1 mg·m −3 ·y −1 ). For euphotic‐zone POC stock, vertical structure accounts for only ∼30% of its variability, whereas euphotic depth exerts dominant control, driving a summertime maximum and a positive changing rate (3.68 mg·m −2 ·y −1 ) in 2003–2023. These non‐steady‐state stock changes highlight the need to jointly evaluate POC production, storage, and export when assessing local biological carbon pump dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Printable polymer nanocomposites for scalable and architected radiative cooling</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67831-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67831-0</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 17:05:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kai Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Songtao Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pranto Karua</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fukang Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sungmin Hong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Diya Patel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gwendolyn M. Reeser</dc:creator><dc:creator>Donald M. Cropek</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul V. Braun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lili Cai</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67831-0</prism:doi><description>Space cooling and lighting together consume 25% of global electricity, yet existing daytime radiative coolers are mostly limited to porous planar coatings that block visible light and lack durability. Here, we introduce rheology-optics coupling as a design principle that links polymer viscoelasticity to particle dispersion and optical scattering. Guided by this principle, we develop printable polydimethylsiloxane-zirconium oxide composites that achieve solar reflectance ( ~ 97.3%) and mid-infrared emissivity ( ~ 96.9%) comparable to the best reported values, despite a low filler loading of only ~4.5 vol.%. These scalable coatings provide up to 7.4 oC sub-ambient cooling and cut electricity use by 37% versus commercial paint in pilot-scale testing, while withstanding mechanical, thermal, and environmental stresses. Beyond planar coatings, the rheology-tunable polydimethylsiloxane-zirconium oxide ink enables direct ink writing of daylight-regulating architectures that deliver sub-ambient radiative cooling while admitting diffuse daylight for illumination, reducing both cooling and lighting demand. This work provides a practical and versatile platform for radiative cooling. Daytime radiative cooling materials typically require high filler loading or porosity. Here, authors introduce rheology–optics coupling to control particle dispersion, enabling printable low-filler PDMS–ZrO₂ composites for scalable and durable radiative coolers with versatile architectures.
Published: 2025-12-27T17:05:19+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.492 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kai Zhou; Songtao Tang; Pranto Karua; Fukang Wu; Sungmin Hong; Diya Patel; Gwendolyn M. Reeser; Donald M. Cropek; Paul V. Braun; Lili Cai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67831-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67831-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.492 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Space cooling and lighting together consume 25% of global electricity, yet existing daytime radiative coolers are mostly limited to porous planar coatings that block visible light and lack durability. Here, we introduce rheology-optics coupling as a design principle that links polymer viscoelasticity to particle dispersion and optical scattering. Guided by this principle, we develop printable polydimethylsiloxane-zirconium oxide composites that achieve solar reflectance ( ~ 97.3%) and mid-infrared emissivity ( ~ 96.9%) comparable to the best reported values, despite a low filler loading of only ~4.5 vol.%. These scalable coatings provide up to 7.4 oC sub-ambient cooling and cut electricity use by 37% versus commercial paint in pilot-scale testing, while withstanding mechanical, thermal, and environmental stresses. Beyond planar coatings, the rheology-tunable polydimethylsiloxane-zirconium oxide ink enables direct ink writing of daylight-regulating architectures that deliver sub-ambient radiative cooling while admitting diffuse daylight for illumination, reducing both cooling and lighting demand. This work provides a practical and versatile platform for radiative cooling. Daytime radiative cooling materials typically require high filler loading or porosity. Here, authors introduce rheology–optics coupling to control particle dispersion, enabling printable low-filler PDMS–ZrO₂ composites for scalable and durable radiative coolers with versatile architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Crustal Sources of Geothermal and Magmatic Activity in the Area of Mutnovsky‐Gorely Volcanic Complex (Kamchatka) Inferred From Ambient Noise Tomography</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032025</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032025</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:07:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>N. Belovezhets</dc:creator><dc:creator>Y. Berezhnev</dc:creator><dc:creator>S. Abramenkov</dc:creator><dc:creator>I. Abkadyrov</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. Dergach</dc:creator><dc:creator>E. Khmarin</dc:creator><dc:creator>D. Chebrov</dc:creator><dc:creator>I. Koulakov</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032025</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Mutnovsky and Gorely volcanoes in Kamchatka, located 70–80 km southwest of Petropavlovsk‐Kamchatsky, pose significant hazard due to their potential for explosive eruptions. Mutnovsky also hosts the Mutnovsky Geothermal Power Plant (MGPP). This study presents the first crustal‐scale three‐dimensional seismic velocity model derived from ambient noise tomography, utilizing data from a temporary 2023–2024 seismic network of 65 mixed broadband and short‐period stations, in addition to four permanent stations. The model reveals multiple low‐velocity zones: a low‐velocity anomaly at 2–5 km depth below sea level is interpreted as a Mutnovsky magma chamber, while the other one at 2.5–5 km depth beneath the MGPP likely reflects an active magmatic intrusion sustaining the geothermal system. A shallow anomaly at 0.5–1 km depth beneath the MGPP is attributed to production intervals associated with geothermal boreholes. Furthermore, the model indicates hydrothermal connectivity between the Mutnovsky field and the Zhirovskoy Valley, with no apparent connection to the Vilyuchinsky Valley springs. Beneath the Gorely caldera, a wide low‐velocity zone suggests the presence of unconsolidated sediments and an underlying magmatic intrusion at 2–4 km depth.
Published: 2025-12-27T18:07:36+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.487 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; N. Belovezhets; Y. Berezhnev; S. Abramenkov; I. Abkadyrov; P. Dergach; E. Khmarin; D. Chebrov; I. Koulakov&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032025"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032025&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.487 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Mutnovsky and Gorely volcanoes in Kamchatka, located 70–80 km southwest of Petropavlovsk‐Kamchatsky, pose significant hazard due to their potential for explosive eruptions. Mutnovsky also hosts the Mutnovsky Geothermal Power Plant (MGPP). This study presents the first crustal‐scale three‐dimensional seismic velocity model derived from ambient noise tomography, utilizing data from a temporary 2023–2024 seismic network of 65 mixed broadband and short‐period stations, in addition to four permanent stations. The model reveals multiple low‐velocity zones: a low‐velocity anomaly at 2–5 km depth below sea level is interpreted as a Mutnovsky magma chamber, while the other one at 2.5–5 km depth beneath the MGPP likely reflects an active magmatic intrusion sustaining the geothermal system. A shallow anomaly at 0.5–1 km depth beneath the MGPP is attributed to production intervals associated with geothermal boreholes. Furthermore, the model indicates hydrothermal connectivity between the Mutnovsky field and the Zhirovskoy Valley, with no apparent connection to the Vilyuchinsky Valley springs. Beneath the Gorely caldera, a wide low‐velocity zone suggests the presence of unconsolidated sediments and an underlying magmatic intrusion at 2–4 km depth.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Interactions with bacteria shape diatom adaptation to carbon concentration changes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68050-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68050-3</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 18:03:18 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chenjie Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenxiu Yin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yufang Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanhua Hu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68050-3</prism:doi><description>Abstract Diatoms are key contributors to global primary production, and have developed intricate partnerships with bacteria through long-term co-evolution. Here, we uncover a syntrophic relationship between the model obligate photoautotroph diatom Phaeodactylum tricornutum and the rod-shaped bacterium Loktanella vestfoldensis , which enables the diatom to indirectly utilize glucose. To be specific, growth of the diatom depends on the support of L. vestfoldensis for the supply of necessary carbon source when glucose serves as the sole carbon source, while L. vestfoldensis shows dependence on P. tricornutum when CO 2 is the sole carbon source. Reanalysis of Tara Oceans metagenomic data shows frequent co-occurrence of Loktanella with diatoms including Chaetoceros and Thalassiosira , indicating the ecological relevance of this partnership. Co-culture with L. vestfoldensis supports robust growth of Chaetoceros muelleri and Thalassiosira pseudonana in the presence of glucose as the sole carbon source. Transcriptomic and metabolomic analyses reveal that P. tricornutum maintains a photoautotrophic metabolism in co-culture, as indicated by the up-regulation of genes involved in inorganic carbon concentration and photosynthesis, while the co-cultured bacterium likely supplies CO 2 and growth-stimulating metabolites such as indole-3-acetic acid. Our findings demonstrate that bacterial-algal interactions may shape diatom adaptation to carbon changes and contribute to marine carbon cycling.
Published: 2025-12-27T18:03:18+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.484 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chenjie Li; Wenxiu Yin; Yufang Pan; Hanhua Hu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68050-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68050-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.484 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Diatoms are key contributors to global primary production, and have developed intricate partnerships with bacteria through long-term co-evolution. Here, we uncover a syntrophic relationship between the model obligate photoautotroph diatom Phaeodactylum tricornutum and the rod-shaped bacterium Loktanella vestfoldensis , which enables the diatom to indirectly utilize glucose. To be specific, growth of the diatom depends on the support of L. vestfoldensis for the supply of necessary carbon source when glucose serves as the sole carbon source, while L. vestfoldensis shows dependence on P. tricornutum when CO 2 is the sole carbon source. Reanalysis of Tara Oceans metagenomic data shows frequent co-occurrence of Loktanella with diatoms including Chaetoceros and Thalassiosira , indicating the ecological relevance of this partnership. Co-culture with L. vestfoldensis supports robust growth of Chaetoceros muelleri and Thalassiosira pseudonana in the presence of glucose as the sole carbon source. Transcriptomic and metabolomic analyses reveal that P. tricornutum maintains a photoautotrophic metabolism in co-culture, as indicated by the up-regulation of genes involved in inorganic carbon concentration and photosynthesis, while the co-cultured bacterium likely supplies CO 2 and growth-stimulating metabolites such as indole-3-acetic acid. Our findings demonstrate that bacterial-algal interactions may shape diatom adaptation to carbon changes and contribute to marine carbon cycling.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Permafrost Thaw Dynamics Drive the Regime Shifts of Iron‐Bound Organic Carbon Sequestration in the East Siberian Arctic Shelf</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118350</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl118350</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 18:16:25 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jiazong Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaoyong She</dc:creator><dc:creator>Limin Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fudong Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zenghui Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kirill Aksentov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuriy Vasilenko</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexander Bosin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anatolii Astakhov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuefa Shi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl118350</prism:doi><description>Abstract In the changing Arctic, permafrost thaw is shifting from gradual to abrupt. Although iron‐bound organic carbon (OC‐Fe R ) critically modulates permafrost carbon‐climate feedbacks, its decadal‐scale variability and response to this regime shift remain poorly constrained. Focusing on the East Siberian Arctic, a hotspot of land‐to‐ocean permafrost carbon transfer, we established critical linkages between marine sedimentary OC‐Fe R burial records and terrestrial permafrost‐climate dynamics. Results revealed that coastal OC‐Fe R reservoirs exhibited temporally‐distinct responses to permafrost thawing dynamics. During the pre‐2000s, the progressive decline in OC‐Fe R coincided with watershed‐scale soil moisture redistribution driven by gradual active‐layer deepening, which preferentially retained OC‐Fe R in permafrost, attenuating its land‐to‐ocean fluxes. Since 2000s, although abrupt thaw has rapidly mobilized OC, ∼19% of sedimentary OC remained stabilized as OC‐Fe R , thus partially decoupling abrupt thaw from immediate permafrost carbon‐climate feedbacks. Therefore, this mineralogical buffering mechanism can attenuate the net climate impact of accelerating abrupt thaw across the Northern Hemisphere cryosphere.
Published: 2025-12-26T18:16:25+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.484 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jiazong Du; Zhaoyong She; Limin Hu; Fudong Lin; Zenghui Yu; Kirill Aksentov; Yuriy Vasilenko; Alexander Bosin; Anatolii Astakhov; Xuefa Shi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118350"&gt;10.1029/2025gl118350&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.484 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract In the changing Arctic, permafrost thaw is shifting from gradual to abrupt. Although iron‐bound organic carbon (OC‐Fe R ) critically modulates permafrost carbon‐climate feedbacks, its decadal‐scale variability and response to this regime shift remain poorly constrained. Focusing on the East Siberian Arctic, a hotspot of land‐to‐ocean permafrost carbon transfer, we established critical linkages between marine sedimentary OC‐Fe R burial records and terrestrial permafrost‐climate dynamics. Results revealed that coastal OC‐Fe R reservoirs exhibited temporally‐distinct responses to permafrost thawing dynamics. During the pre‐2000s, the progressive decline in OC‐Fe R coincided with watershed‐scale soil moisture redistribution driven by gradual active‐layer deepening, which preferentially retained OC‐Fe R in permafrost, attenuating its land‐to‐ocean fluxes. Since 2000s, although abrupt thaw has rapidly mobilized OC, ∼19% of sedimentary OC remained stabilized as OC‐Fe R , thus partially decoupling abrupt thaw from immediate permafrost carbon‐climate feedbacks. Therefore, this mineralogical buffering mechanism can attenuate the net climate impact of accelerating abrupt thaw across the Northern Hemisphere cryosphere.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Designer RNA nanostructures co-transcribed and self-assembled inside human cell nuclei</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67817-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67817-y</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 22:46:51 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xu Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maciej Jeziorek</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Edward M. Bonder</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jean-Pierre Etchegaray</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fei Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67817-y</prism:doi><description>The use of nucleic acid-based nanostructures as synthetic biological tools to interface with and regulate cell processes remains challenging. A major obstacle lies in nuclear delivery and retention within live eukaryotic cells. Here, we present a platform of single-stranded RNAs that can co-transcriptionally fold into defined nanostructures and assemble into rings, ribbons, and nanonet-like architectures. We validate the formation of these structures in vitro using atomic force microscopy. Then, we demonstrate the functional integration of fluorescent aptamers and RNA sensing capability within the single chain by co-folding with these structures. Notably, we show that the RNA nanonets can be co-transcriptionally produced and assembled directly inside the nucleus of live human cells. We use confocal live-cell imaging and transmission electron microscopy to reveal well-defined nanostructure patterns retained in the nucleus. Together, these results establish a genetically encoded, self-assembling RNA nanostructure system with programmable geometry and localization, providing a foundation for the development of RNA-based nanodevices to examine biological properties in live cells and tissues. The use of nucleic acid-based nanostructures as synthetic biological tools remains challenging. Here they present synthetic RNA structures that fold and self-assemble inside human cell nuclei, offering a platform for imaging, sensing, and future therapeutic applications.
Published: 2025-12-26T22:46:51+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.481 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xu Chang; Maciej Jeziorek; Qi Yang; Edward M. Bonder; Hao Yan; Jean-Pierre Etchegaray; Fei Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67817-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67817-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.481 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of nucleic acid-based nanostructures as synthetic biological tools to interface with and regulate cell processes remains challenging. A major obstacle lies in nuclear delivery and retention within live eukaryotic cells. Here, we present a platform of single-stranded RNAs that can co-transcriptionally fold into defined nanostructures and assemble into rings, ribbons, and nanonet-like architectures. We validate the formation of these structures in vitro using atomic force microscopy. Then, we demonstrate the functional integration of fluorescent aptamers and RNA sensing capability within the single chain by co-folding with these structures. Notably, we show that the RNA nanonets can be co-transcriptionally produced and assembled directly inside the nucleus of live human cells. We use confocal live-cell imaging and transmission electron microscopy to reveal well-defined nanostructure patterns retained in the nucleus. Together, these results establish a genetically encoded, self-assembling RNA nanostructure system with programmable geometry and localization, providing a foundation for the development of RNA-based nanodevices to examine biological properties in live cells and tissues. The use of nucleic acid-based nanostructures as synthetic biological tools remains challenging. Here they present synthetic RNA structures that fold and self-assemble inside human cell nuclei, offering a platform for imaging, sensing, and future therapeutic applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Late Aqueous Activity on Vesta</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009178</link><guid>10.1029/2025je009178</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 11:26:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tianjing Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weibiao Hsu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025je009178</prism:doi><description>Abstract Fluid‐assisted metasomatism was prevalent on Vesta, but the timing and source(s) of aqueous activities remain elusive. Here, we report an absolute 207 Pb/ 206 Pb isochron age (4,169 ± 85 Ma) of apatites from a plagioclase‐rich eucrite clast within the Jikharra 001 eucrite. Petrographic, mineralogical, and geochemical characteristics demonstrate that apatite veins in the clast formed during fluid‐assisted metasomatism on Vesta. The elevated 87 Sr/ 86 Sr ratios observed in the bulk clast and plagioclase grains suggest the incorporation of fluid from primitive sources, probably carbonaceous chondrites. The slightly negative oxygen isotopic composition (Δ 17 O = −0.275 ± 0.013‰) of the clast further indicates a largely carbonaceous chondrite source. Impacts from carbonaceous chondrites are the probable origin of Veneneia. Evidence from apatite veins in the Jikharra 001 is consistent with a carbonaceous fluid source and may constrain the age of Veneneia to the late heavy bombardment, approximately 4.1–4.2 Ga.
Published: 2025-12-27T11:26:36+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets
Score: 0.477 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tianjing Gao; Weibiao Hsu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009178"&gt;10.1029/2025je009178&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.477 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Fluid‐assisted metasomatism was prevalent on Vesta, but the timing and source(s) of aqueous activities remain elusive. Here, we report an absolute 207 Pb/ 206 Pb isochron age (4,169 ± 85 Ma) of apatites from a plagioclase‐rich eucrite clast within the Jikharra 001 eucrite. Petrographic, mineralogical, and geochemical characteristics demonstrate that apatite veins in the clast formed during fluid‐assisted metasomatism on Vesta. The elevated 87 Sr/ 86 Sr ratios observed in the bulk clast and plagioclase grains suggest the incorporation of fluid from primitive sources, probably carbonaceous chondrites. The slightly negative oxygen isotopic composition (Δ 17 O = −0.275 ± 0.013‰) of the clast further indicates a largely carbonaceous chondrite source. Impacts from carbonaceous chondrites are the probable origin of Veneneia. Evidence from apatite veins in the Jikharra 001 is consistent with a carbonaceous fluid source and may constrain the age of Veneneia to the late heavy bombardment, approximately 4.1–4.2 Ga.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>In-sensor analog optoelectronic processing of concurrent event and memory signals for dynamic vision sensing</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68013-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68013-8</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 16:32:38 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yelim Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hyeonsu Park</dc:creator><dc:creator>Minjoo Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suhee Jang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dae Yeop Jeong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lia Saptini Handriani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hyuncheol Yun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Namyoung Gwak</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nuri Oh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sung Ik Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Soyeong Kwon</dc:creator><dc:creator>SungWoo Nam</dc:creator><dc:creator>Won Il Park</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68013-8</prism:doi><description>Efficient dynamic vision requires capturing instantaneous changes and temporal context, yet existing image and event sensors rely on power-hungry digital processing. Here, we introduce an in-sensor dual-response architecture that concurrently generates analog event spikes and persistent memory tails. A prototype sensor integrates phosphor pairs with silicon photodiodes and transimpedance amplifiers to achieve microsecond- and millisecond-scale dual kinetics. Measurements during light-emitting diode replay reconstruct event frames that match software frame differences, while the slow channel behaves as a linear reservoir of motion history. A single memory frame fed to a convolutional neural network enables accurate classification of human actions (93.1%) and vehicle trajectories (98.0%), as well as speed estimation with errors of 2.15 km/h. Integration with a compressive optical neural network front end mapping 4900 inputs to 16 per frame yields 93.3% action classification accuracy. By eliminating analog-to-digital conversion and digital accumulation, this approach enables ultralow-latency, ultralow-power neuromorphic vision. High-efficient dynamic vision requires capturing instantaneous motion and its temporal evolution to infer trajectories, velocities, and even predict future motion. Kim et al. introduce an analog event-memory sensor that is capable of event detection and temporal integration. The proposed architecture can reduce latency, power consumption, and circuit complexity compared to conventional dynamic vision sensors.
Published: 2025-12-26T16:32:38+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.476 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yelim Kim; Hyeonsu Park; Minjoo Kim; Suhee Jang; Dae Yeop Jeong; Lia Saptini Handriani; Hyuncheol Yun; Namyoung Gwak; Nuri Oh; Sung Ik Yang; Soyeong Kwon; SungWoo Nam; Won Il Park&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68013-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68013-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.476 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efficient dynamic vision requires capturing instantaneous changes and temporal context, yet existing image and event sensors rely on power-hungry digital processing. Here, we introduce an in-sensor dual-response architecture that concurrently generates analog event spikes and persistent memory tails. A prototype sensor integrates phosphor pairs with silicon photodiodes and transimpedance amplifiers to achieve microsecond- and millisecond-scale dual kinetics. Measurements during light-emitting diode replay reconstruct event frames that match software frame differences, while the slow channel behaves as a linear reservoir of motion history. A single memory frame fed to a convolutional neural network enables accurate classification of human actions (93.1%) and vehicle trajectories (98.0%), as well as speed estimation with errors of 2.15 km/h. Integration with a compressive optical neural network front end mapping 4900 inputs to 16 per frame yields 93.3% action classification accuracy. By eliminating analog-to-digital conversion and digital accumulation, this approach enables ultralow-latency, ultralow-power neuromorphic vision. High-efficient dynamic vision requires capturing instantaneous motion and its temporal evolution to infer trajectories, velocities, and even predict future motion. Kim et al. introduce an analog event-memory sensor that is capable of event detection and temporal integration. The proposed architecture can reduce latency, power consumption, and circuit complexity compared to conventional dynamic vision sensors.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magnetically actuated momentum-driven millirobots</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67936-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67936-6</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 14:22:12 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Min Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenlong Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zeju Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tianyi Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rui Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuxuan Xiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Steven Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiachen Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zuankai Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67936-6</prism:doi><description>Designing millirobots capable of navigating high-friction environments remains a significant challenge due to limitations in force output and the absence of efficient transmission mechanisms at small scales. In this study, we introduce a magnetically inner actuated millirobot capable of generating a thrust force exceeding 15 N with a body weight of 5.82 g for moving across diverse frictional terrains. The inner-actuated millirobot features a dual-coil array positioned at each end of a plastic skeleton and a permanent magnet accommodated in the center channel of the body. When powered by a 0.5 A current, the internal magnetic interaction propels the magnet to a velocity of 2.10 m/s within 17 ms, striking the end wall to produce a powerful instantaneous thrust that overcomes friction forces. Experimental results demonstrate the millirobot’s ability to operate in viscous oil, traverse sand and granular media, and transport cargo exceeding 300 times its body weight. Furthermore, the magnetically inner actuated millirobot shows promising potential for accessing confined tubular environments. This magnetically inner-actuated design, leveraging momentum conservation for propulsion, enables millirobots with high force capacity for high-friction and confined-space applications. The authors developed a 5.82 g magnetically inner-actuated millirobot capable of carrying over 300 times its own weight. The high thrust and payload capability enable it to navigate tough terrains, such as sand, viscous oil, and confined spaces.
Published: 2025-12-27T14:22:12+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.475 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Min Wang; Wenlong Wu; Zeju Zheng; Wei Dai; Tianyi Wu; Rui Liu; Yuxuan Xiang; Steven Wang; Jiachen Zhang; Zuankai Wang; Jun Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67936-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67936-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.475 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designing millirobots capable of navigating high-friction environments remains a significant challenge due to limitations in force output and the absence of efficient transmission mechanisms at small scales. In this study, we introduce a magnetically inner actuated millirobot capable of generating a thrust force exceeding 15 N with a body weight of 5.82 g for moving across diverse frictional terrains. The inner-actuated millirobot features a dual-coil array positioned at each end of a plastic skeleton and a permanent magnet accommodated in the center channel of the body. When powered by a 0.5 A current, the internal magnetic interaction propels the magnet to a velocity of 2.10 m/s within 17 ms, striking the end wall to produce a powerful instantaneous thrust that overcomes friction forces. Experimental results demonstrate the millirobot’s ability to operate in viscous oil, traverse sand and granular media, and transport cargo exceeding 300 times its body weight. Furthermore, the magnetically inner actuated millirobot shows promising potential for accessing confined tubular environments. This magnetically inner-actuated design, leveraging momentum conservation for propulsion, enables millirobots with high force capacity for high-friction and confined-space applications. The authors developed a 5.82 g magnetically inner-actuated millirobot capable of carrying over 300 times its own weight. The high thrust and payload capability enable it to navigate tough terrains, such as sand, viscous oil, and confined spaces.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Buprestidae metamorphosis-inspired stiffening photonic elastomers for shape-color integrated memory and information encryption</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67905-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67905-z</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 17:46:02 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tianqi Ren</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuanzhe Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhibo Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cheng Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qingyan Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chen Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyuan Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuzhen Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinbao Guo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67905-z</prism:doi><description>Integrating shape memory polymers into the device provides multifunctionality and recyclability. However, complex programming steps and the immutability of material properties hinder their applications. Here, inspired by the Buprestidae sclerotization process, linear long side chains are introduced into chiral liquid crystal elastomers (CLCEs), a class of polymeric photonic crystals, enhancing the phase transition tendency of the system. Through microphase separation between the more ordered structure (smectic and crystalline phases) and the primary chiral nematic (N*) phase, self-enhancement of the material is achieved at room temperature while retaining the selective reflection of the N* phase. Within 48 hours, the Young’s modulus increases by 1854%, and the strain energy density in the 0–100% strain range increases by 1533%. This induces a shape-color integrated memory effect which can be fully restored upon heating. Cyclic utilization of a single CLCE film is demonstrated through programming, achieving the memory of colorful shapes and high-fidelity textures. Furthermore, local regulation of microphase separation enables encrypted information writing and recycling. Programmable shape memory polymers are of interest for smart materials, meanwhile the integration of shape and color enriches the applications. Here the authors use chiral liquid crystal elastomers affording a shape and color changing material, with dynamic mechanical properties.
Published: 2025-12-26T17:46:02+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.475 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tianqi Ren; Xuanzhe Shen; Zhibo Huang; Cheng Xue; Qingyan Fan; Chen Yang; Xinyuan Ma; Yuzhen Zhao; Jinbao Guo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67905-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67905-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.475 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrating shape memory polymers into the device provides multifunctionality and recyclability. However, complex programming steps and the immutability of material properties hinder their applications. Here, inspired by the Buprestidae sclerotization process, linear long side chains are introduced into chiral liquid crystal elastomers (CLCEs), a class of polymeric photonic crystals, enhancing the phase transition tendency of the system. Through microphase separation between the more ordered structure (smectic and crystalline phases) and the primary chiral nematic (N*) phase, self-enhancement of the material is achieved at room temperature while retaining the selective reflection of the N* phase. Within 48 hours, the Young’s modulus increases by 1854%, and the strain energy density in the 0–100% strain range increases by 1533%. This induces a shape-color integrated memory effect which can be fully restored upon heating. Cyclic utilization of a single CLCE film is demonstrated through programming, achieving the memory of colorful shapes and high-fidelity textures. Furthermore, local regulation of microphase separation enables encrypted information writing and recycling. Programmable shape memory polymers are of interest for smart materials, meanwhile the integration of shape and color enriches the applications. Here the authors use chiral liquid crystal elastomers affording a shape and color changing material, with dynamic mechanical properties.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Photochromism of pyridine-substituted merocyanine through reversible C-N bond formation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67626-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67626-3</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 21:34:51 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>He Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ya Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feifan Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shiquan Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zixu He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sijia Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Quan Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaohua Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huimin Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen Shi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67626-3</prism:doi><description>The reversible interconversion between spiropyran and merocyanine constitutes one of the most intensively investigated photochromic systems, enabling diverse applications in stimuli-responsive materials and optical imaging. Here, we report pyridine-substituted merocyanines (PMCs) as a class of photochromic molecules. Upon visible light irradiation, these compounds undergo an uncommon photoinduced C-N bond formation to yield spiroindolizine (SIZ) structures, accompanied by the color fading. The SIZs can thermally revert to the colored PMC form. This photochromism is marked by rapid response, high photo-switching ratio, robust water compatibility, and fatigue resistance. Furthermore, we have synthesized quinoline-substituted merocyanines and found that they can be bidirectionally switched by 660 nm and 500 nm light to form SIZ and PMC structures. Finally, we showed the photochromism of these molecules in solid matrices and demonstrated a light-controlled sequential switching function, highlighting their potential for advanced photonic applications. Spiropyran and merocyanine systems are useful due to the photoswitching properties, but do have some limitations. Here, the authors report pyridine-substituted merocyanines as photochromic compounds, with a photoinitiated C-N bond formation.
Published: 2025-12-26T21:34:51+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.474 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; He Li; Ya Liu; Feifan Sun; Shiquan Lin; Zixu He; Sijia Lu; Quan Tang; Xiaohua Li; Huimin Ma; Wen Shi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67626-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67626-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.474 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reversible interconversion between spiropyran and merocyanine constitutes one of the most intensively investigated photochromic systems, enabling diverse applications in stimuli-responsive materials and optical imaging. Here, we report pyridine-substituted merocyanines (PMCs) as a class of photochromic molecules. Upon visible light irradiation, these compounds undergo an uncommon photoinduced C-N bond formation to yield spiroindolizine (SIZ) structures, accompanied by the color fading. The SIZs can thermally revert to the colored PMC form. This photochromism is marked by rapid response, high photo-switching ratio, robust water compatibility, and fatigue resistance. Furthermore, we have synthesized quinoline-substituted merocyanines and found that they can be bidirectionally switched by 660 nm and 500 nm light to form SIZ and PMC structures. Finally, we showed the photochromism of these molecules in solid matrices and demonstrated a light-controlled sequential switching function, highlighting their potential for advanced photonic applications. Spiropyran and merocyanine systems are useful due to the photoswitching properties, but do have some limitations. Here, the authors report pyridine-substituted merocyanines as photochromic compounds, with a photoinitiated C-N bond formation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A topological superconductor tuned by electronic correlations</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67957-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67957-1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 02:44:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Haoran Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher L. Jacobs</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenhui Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gillian M. Nolan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gabriele Berruto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Patrick Singleton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Khanh Duy Nguyen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunhe Bai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiang Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xianxin Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao-Xing Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gangbin Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suin Choi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nathan P. Guisinger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pinshane Y. Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Subhasish Mandal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuolong Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67957-1</prism:doi><description>A topological superconductor, characterized by either a chiral order parameter or a topological surface state in proximity to bulk superconductivity, is foundational to topological quantum computing. A key open challenge is whether electron-electron interactions can tune such topological superconducting phases. Here, we provide experimental signatures of a unique topological superconducting phase in competition with electronic correlations in 10-unit-cell thick FeTexSe1-x films grown on SrTiO3 substrates. When the Te content x exceeds 0.7, we observe a topological transition marked by the emergence of a superconducting surface state. Near the FeTe limit, the system undergoes another transition where the surface state disappears, and superconductivity is suppressed. Theory suggests that electron-electron interactions in the odd-parity xy− band drives this second topological transition. The flattening and eventual decoherence of dxy-derived bands track the superconducting dome, linking correlation effects directly to superconducting coherent transport. Our work establishes many-body electronic correlations as a sensitive knob for tuning topology and superconductivity, offering a pathway to engineer new topological phases in correlated materials. The authors report superconducting topological surface states (TSS) on MBE-grown Fe(Te,Se) films by high-resolution laser-ARPES. Near the FeTe limit, the surface state disappears due to an electron-correlation-driven topological transition associated with decoherence of the dxy-orbital-derived bands.
Published: 2025-12-26T02:44:49+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.472 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Haoran Lin; Christopher L. Jacobs; Chenhui Yan; Gillian M. Nolan; Gabriele Berruto; Patrick Singleton; Khanh Duy Nguyen; Yunhe Bai; Qiang Gao; Xianxin Wu; Chao-Xing Liu; Gangbin Yan; Suin Choi; Chong Liu; Nathan P. Guisinger; Pinshane Y. Huang; Subhasish Mandal; Shuolong Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67957-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67957-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.472 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A topological superconductor, characterized by either a chiral order parameter or a topological surface state in proximity to bulk superconductivity, is foundational to topological quantum computing. A key open challenge is whether electron-electron interactions can tune such topological superconducting phases. Here, we provide experimental signatures of a unique topological superconducting phase in competition with electronic correlations in 10-unit-cell thick FeTexSe1-x films grown on SrTiO3 substrates. When the Te content x exceeds 0.7, we observe a topological transition marked by the emergence of a superconducting surface state. Near the FeTe limit, the system undergoes another transition where the surface state disappears, and superconductivity is suppressed. Theory suggests that electron-electron interactions in the odd-parity xy− band drives this second topological transition. The flattening and eventual decoherence of dxy-derived bands track the superconducting dome, linking correlation effects directly to superconducting coherent transport. Our work establishes many-body electronic correlations as a sensitive knob for tuning topology and superconductivity, offering a pathway to engineer new topological phases in correlated materials. The authors report superconducting topological surface states (TSS) on MBE-grown Fe(Te,Se) films by high-resolution laser-ARPES. Near the FeTe limit, the surface state disappears due to an electron-correlation-driven topological transition associated with decoherence of the dxy-orbital-derived bands.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Subsurface Frontal Dynamics Induce Nitrate Regeneration and Phytoplankton Accumulation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022974</link><guid>10.1029/2025jc022974</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 08:21:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xin Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunqing Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingjun Rao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sihai Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fajin Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuwen Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jc022974</prism:doi><description>Abstract Oceanic fronts significantly affect primary production. While surface fronts are well‐studied, subsurface fronts have received relatively little attention. The impacts and underlying mechanisms of subsurface fronts on phytoplankton distribution and nitrogen cycle remain unclear, limiting our understanding of primary production. Based on data from in situ sampling, satellite, and reanalysis, pronounced thermal fronts occurred in the subsurface layers but weakened and disappeared toward the surface and deeper layers of the northern South China Sea. Despite differing formation mechanisms (i.e., dipole eddies and warm offshore water intrusion), both frontal zones exhibited substantially higher chlorophyll a (Chl a ) levels than non‐frontal zones (on average, Chl a concentrations increased by 77.78% and inventories rose by 88.56%). Positive correlations between frontal intensities and Chl a concentrations, along with enhanced convergence‐divergence and vertical processes, suggested that Chl a aggregate relates to physical accumulation. Additionally, evident nitrate (NO 3 − ) loss and isotope enrichment factors ( 15 = 3.4‰ and 18 = 4.5‰) supported that Chl a increase were also associated with NO 3 − assimilation. However, 22.7% of the total NO 3 − pool in frontal zones was from nitrification, representing an increase of 15.2% compared to non‐frontal zones. Elevated regeneration was attributed to enhanced oxygen exchange related to frontal dynamics, as suggested by comparable dissolved oxygen and ammonium levels in both zones, yet with elevated apparent oxygen utilization and NO 3 − in frontal zones. This study highlights that subsurface fronts not only facilitate phytoplankton aggregation but also drive active NO 3 − regeneration, thereby leading to an overestimation of new production in oligotrophic oceans.
Published: 2025-12-27T08:21:07+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans
Score: 0.466 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xin Zhou; Chunqing Chen; Jingjun Rao; Sihai Liu; Fajin Chen; Shuwen Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022974"&gt;10.1029/2025jc022974&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.466 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Oceanic fronts significantly affect primary production. While surface fronts are well‐studied, subsurface fronts have received relatively little attention. The impacts and underlying mechanisms of subsurface fronts on phytoplankton distribution and nitrogen cycle remain unclear, limiting our understanding of primary production. Based on data from in situ sampling, satellite, and reanalysis, pronounced thermal fronts occurred in the subsurface layers but weakened and disappeared toward the surface and deeper layers of the northern South China Sea. Despite differing formation mechanisms (i.e., dipole eddies and warm offshore water intrusion), both frontal zones exhibited substantially higher chlorophyll a (Chl a ) levels than non‐frontal zones (on average, Chl a concentrations increased by 77.78% and inventories rose by 88.56%). Positive correlations between frontal intensities and Chl a concentrations, along with enhanced convergence‐divergence and vertical processes, suggested that Chl a aggregate relates to physical accumulation. Additionally, evident nitrate (NO 3 − ) loss and isotope enrichment factors ( 15 = 3.4‰ and 18 = 4.5‰) supported that Chl a increase were also associated with NO 3 − assimilation. However, 22.7% of the total NO 3 − pool in frontal zones was from nitrification, representing an increase of 15.2% compared to non‐frontal zones. Elevated regeneration was attributed to enhanced oxygen exchange related to frontal dynamics, as suggested by comparable dissolved oxygen and ammonium levels in both zones, yet with elevated apparent oxygen utilization and NO 3 − in frontal zones. This study highlights that subsurface fronts not only facilitate phytoplankton aggregation but also drive active NO 3 − regeneration, thereby leading to an overestimation of new production in oligotrophic oceans.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>