<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 23:55:29 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Coesite Discovery in Eclogites Confirms UHP Metamorphism in the Orlica‐Śnieżnik Dome (SW Poland)</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1111/jmg.70029</link><guid>10.1111/jmg.70029</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 11:45:24 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Małgorzata Nowak</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lucie Tajčmanová</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marcin Dąbrowski</dc:creator><dc:creator>Iris Buisman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jacek Szczepański</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Metamorphic Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1111/jmg.70029</prism:doi><description>ABSTRACT Eclogite lenses are exposed within the orthogneiss‐dominated core of the Orlica‐Śnieżnik Dome in the Sudetes, which forms the northeastern margin of the Bohemian Massif (Variscan Belt of Central Europe). The presence of coesite inclusions in garnet and omphacite confirms that these eclogites underwent ultrahigh‐pressure metamorphism. This interpretation is further supported by phase equilibria modelling, which indicates peak‐pressure metamorphic conditions of 2.9–3.2 GPa and 750°C–830°C. The results are consistent with estimates derived from conventional geothermobarometry and Zr‐in‐rutile thermometry applied to rutile inclusions in garnet. Based on quartz‐in‐garnet elastic barometry, a maximum entrapment pressure of approximately 2.0 GPa is obtained. We interpret this discrepancy as a result of viscous relaxation of garnet at high temperature. The first stage of re‐equilibration during decompression occurred at a pressure of 2.0–2.2 GPa and a temperature of 680°C–770°C. The observed rock associations exhibit similarities to other UHP occurrences within the Saxo‐Thuringian Zone, suggesting a comparable exhumation mechanism. This likely involved initial buoyancy‐driven exhumation within a subduction channel, followed by crustal‐scale folding. Furthermore, the maximum pressure recorded in the eclogites may partly reflect nonlithostatic components, such as transient pressure variations arising from rheological heterogeneity between the eclogites and their host rocks.
Published: 2026-01-02T11:45:24+00:00
Venue: Journal of Metamorphic Geology
Score: 0.637 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Małgorzata Nowak; Lucie Tajčmanová; Marcin Dąbrowski; Iris Buisman; Jacek Szczepański&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Metamorphic Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/jmg.70029"&gt;10.1111/jmg.70029&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.637 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT Eclogite lenses are exposed within the orthogneiss‐dominated core of the Orlica‐Śnieżnik Dome in the Sudetes, which forms the northeastern margin of the Bohemian Massif (Variscan Belt of Central Europe). The presence of coesite inclusions in garnet and omphacite confirms that these eclogites underwent ultrahigh‐pressure metamorphism. This interpretation is further supported by phase equilibria modelling, which indicates peak‐pressure metamorphic conditions of 2.9–3.2 GPa and 750°C–830°C. The results are consistent with estimates derived from conventional geothermobarometry and Zr‐in‐rutile thermometry applied to rutile inclusions in garnet. Based on quartz‐in‐garnet elastic barometry, a maximum entrapment pressure of approximately 2.0 GPa is obtained. We interpret this discrepancy as a result of viscous relaxation of garnet at high temperature. The first stage of re‐equilibration during decompression occurred at a pressure of 2.0–2.2 GPa and a temperature of 680°C–770°C. The observed rock associations exhibit similarities to other UHP occurrences within the Saxo‐Thuringian Zone, suggesting a comparable exhumation mechanism. This likely involved initial buoyancy‐driven exhumation within a subduction channel, followed by crustal‐scale folding. Furthermore, the maximum pressure recorded in the eclogites may partly reflect nonlithostatic components, such as transient pressure variations arising from rheological heterogeneity between the eclogites and their host rocks.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>New constraints on oxygen fugacity of basalts in large igneous provinces using Cr isotopes: Implications for Fe-Ni-PGE mineralization</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38590.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38590.1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 17:57:13 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yuxi Mo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingjing Ou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Juan Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sheng-Ao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hengci Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guochun Zhao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38590.1</prism:doi><description>The genetic linkage between large igneous provinces (LIPs) basalts and large-scale mineralization has been extensively documented. Oxygen fugacity is a critical metallogenic factor controlling magmatic systems. This study presents the first Cr isotope analysis of Permian high-Ti and low-Ti basalts from the Emeishan large igneous province (ELIP), revealing distinct isotopic signatures between the two basalt groups. The δ53Cr values in low-Ti basalts are slightly lighter than that in high-Ti basalts on average. Both basalt types demonstrate significant enrichment in heavy Cr isotopes compared to mid-ocean-ridge basalts (MORB) and ocean-island basalts (OIB). Trace element patterns and Sr-Nd isotopic compositions of ELIP basalts indicate that low-Ti basalts are geochemically similar to an enriched mantle type II mantle source, whereas high-Ti basalts exhibit affinities to OIB-like compositions, providing crucial insights into mantle source characteristics. Comparative analysis of Cr isotopes in MORB and Emeishan basalts reveals that the oxygen fugacity of low-Ti basalts (ΔlogfO2 = FMQ −1.5 ± 1) is slightly lower than that of MORB, whereas high-Ti basalts show higher oxygen fugacity (ΔlogfO2 = FMQ +0.5 ± 1) is higher, indicating a more oxidized state compared to MORB. This elevated oxygen fugacity in Emeishan basalts creates favorable conditions for mineralization, offering new constraints on the redox conditions of the ELIP mantle sources and their implications for magmatic processes and associated mineralization events.
Published: 2026-01-02T17:57:13+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.615 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yuxi Mo; Mingjing Ou; Li-Juan Xu; Sheng-Ao Liu; Ming Xiao; Hengci Tian; Guochun Zhao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38590.1"&gt;10.1130/b38590.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.615 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The genetic linkage between large igneous provinces (LIPs) basalts and large-scale mineralization has been extensively documented. Oxygen fugacity is a critical metallogenic factor controlling magmatic systems. This study presents the first Cr isotope analysis of Permian high-Ti and low-Ti basalts from the Emeishan large igneous province (ELIP), revealing distinct isotopic signatures between the two basalt groups. The δ53Cr values in low-Ti basalts are slightly lighter than that in high-Ti basalts on average. Both basalt types demonstrate significant enrichment in heavy Cr isotopes compared to mid-ocean-ridge basalts (MORB) and ocean-island basalts (OIB). Trace element patterns and Sr-Nd isotopic compositions of ELIP basalts indicate that low-Ti basalts are geochemically similar to an enriched mantle type II mantle source, whereas high-Ti basalts exhibit affinities to OIB-like compositions, providing crucial insights into mantle source characteristics. Comparative analysis of Cr isotopes in MORB and Emeishan basalts reveals that the oxygen fugacity of low-Ti basalts (ΔlogfO2 = FMQ −1.5 ± 1) is slightly lower than that of MORB, whereas high-Ti basalts show higher oxygen fugacity (ΔlogfO2 = FMQ +0.5 ± 1) is higher, indicating a more oxidized state compared to MORB. This elevated oxygen fugacity in Emeishan basalts creates favorable conditions for mineralization, offering new constraints on the redox conditions of the ELIP mantle sources and their implications for magmatic processes and associated mineralization events.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Channelization Versus Retardation During Trace Element Segregation in Compaction‐Driven Fluid Flow</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119610</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119610</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:25:39 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Stefan M. Schmalholz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Samuel Cingari</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lyudmila Khakimova</dc:creator><dc:creator>Evangelos Moulas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yury Y. Podladchikov</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119610</prism:doi><description>Abstract The migration of fluids, such as aqueous fluids and melts, is often channelized and crucial for trace element transport. However, trace elements typically migrate slower than the fluid due to partitioning between solid and fluid phases, known as retardation. The influence of channelization intensity on trace element retardation remains poorly quantified. Here, we use two‐dimensional numerical simulations to investigate trace element transport during compaction‐driven flow involving porosity waves and channelization caused by decompaction weakening. We employ a small‐amplitude porosity perturbation to study fluid segregation. A data collapse of systematic numerical results quantifies how the increase in channelization intensity cancels out the decrease in trace element transport caused by retardation, showing that channelized porosity waves enable segregated trace element mass transport. We illustrate changes of trace element distributions during fluid migration using multi‐element (spider) and ternary diagrams as well as trace element profiles across channels.
Published: 2026-01-02T08:25:39+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.541 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Stefan M. Schmalholz; Samuel Cingari; Lyudmila Khakimova; Evangelos Moulas; Yury Y. Podladchikov&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119610"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119610&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.541 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The migration of fluids, such as aqueous fluids and melts, is often channelized and crucial for trace element transport. However, trace elements typically migrate slower than the fluid due to partitioning between solid and fluid phases, known as retardation. The influence of channelization intensity on trace element retardation remains poorly quantified. Here, we use two‐dimensional numerical simulations to investigate trace element transport during compaction‐driven flow involving porosity waves and channelization caused by decompaction weakening. We employ a small‐amplitude porosity perturbation to study fluid segregation. A data collapse of systematic numerical results quantifies how the increase in channelization intensity cancels out the decrease in trace element transport caused by retardation, showing that channelized porosity waves enable segregated trace element mass transport. We illustrate changes of trace element distributions during fluid migration using multi‐element (spider) and ternary diagrams as well as trace element profiles across channels.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Experimental Deformation of Textured Amphibolites in the Semi‐Brittle Regime: Microstructural Signatures of Dislocation‐Mediated Deformation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031852</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb031852</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 06:53:47 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bhupesh Meher</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sarah Incel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jörg Renner</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuval Boneh</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb031852</prism:doi><description>Abstract Hornblende amphibole is difficult to deform plastically in experiments due to its anisotropic nature and breakdown at relatively low temperatures (∼850°C). The lack of experimental analysis of hornblende plasticity hampers interpreting the deformation mechanisms of natural samples, which remain unresolved and debated. Here, we used strongly textured amphibolite, oriented for the activation of hornblende's cleavage and/or easy slip system, to investigate the interplay of brittle and plastic deformation mechanisms. Samples with the lineation oriented at 30° to the loading direction were deformed at a confining pressure of 1 GPa, strain rates of 10 −5 to 10 −4 s −1 , and temperatures of 400, 600, and 800°C. Deformed samples exhibit marked tilting of significant subvolumes manifested as kink bands. On the grain scale, deformation is accommodated by fracturing and dislocation mechanisms. A significant decrease in sample strength with temperature is accompanied by an increase in intragrain misorientations due to an increase in dislocation activity. The dominant orientation of the intragrain misorientation axis shifts from [001] at 400°C to [010] at 800°C. Nano‐scale analysis revealed that at 800°C, intragrain misorientation occurs through a sequence in which dislocation structures develop first and then act as sites for fracture nucleation. The observed intragrain misorientation is corroborated by an example from the Javanahalli schist belt (India). We conclude that the experimentally observed transition in the dominant intragrain misorientation axis accompanying the transition from fracture to dislocation‐mediated deformation can be used to interpret conditions experienced by naturally deformed samples.
Published: 2026-01-02T06:53:47+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.529 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bhupesh Meher; Sarah Incel; Jörg Renner; Yuval Boneh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031852"&gt;10.1029/2025jb031852&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.529 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Hornblende amphibole is difficult to deform plastically in experiments due to its anisotropic nature and breakdown at relatively low temperatures (∼850°C). The lack of experimental analysis of hornblende plasticity hampers interpreting the deformation mechanisms of natural samples, which remain unresolved and debated. Here, we used strongly textured amphibolite, oriented for the activation of hornblende&amp;#x27;s cleavage and/or easy slip system, to investigate the interplay of brittle and plastic deformation mechanisms. Samples with the lineation oriented at 30° to the loading direction were deformed at a confining pressure of 1 GPa, strain rates of 10 −5 to 10 −4 s −1 , and temperatures of 400, 600, and 800°C. Deformed samples exhibit marked tilting of significant subvolumes manifested as kink bands. On the grain scale, deformation is accommodated by fracturing and dislocation mechanisms. A significant decrease in sample strength with temperature is accompanied by an increase in intragrain misorientations due to an increase in dislocation activity. The dominant orientation of the intragrain misorientation axis shifts from [001] at 400°C to [010] at 800°C. Nano‐scale analysis revealed that at 800°C, intragrain misorientation occurs through a sequence in which dislocation structures develop first and then act as sites for fracture nucleation. The observed intragrain misorientation is corroborated by an example from the Javanahalli schist belt (India). We conclude that the experimentally observed transition in the dominant intragrain misorientation axis accompanying the transition from fracture to dislocation‐mediated deformation can be used to interpret conditions experienced by naturally deformed samples.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Tunneling field emission from nano-optics under electron irradiation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5421</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.ady5421</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kenan Elibol</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vesna Srot</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sayooj Satheesh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Serkan Arslan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marko Burghard</dc:creator><dc:creator>Harald Giessen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter A. van Aken</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.ady5421</prism:doi><description>While field emission, which is crucial for sub–angstrom resolution imaging and nanofabrication, has been extensively investigated in high-voltage and laser-driven systems, its realization through plasmonics under electron irradiation remains unexplored. Here, we demonstrate a proof of concept for electron beam–driven field emission from plasmonic emitter arrays with nanoscale hotspots acting as highly efficient emission sites, which also exhibit strong surface-enhanced Raman scattering activity. The electron beam–induced field distributions and electrical polarization switching are visualized by four-dimensional scanning transmission electron microscopy. Classical and quantum-corrected electromagnetic simulations combined with experimental field maps identify the highest field intensities at the apex of emitter tips. Optical excitation experiments confirm the giant field enhancement at these locations. In situ electrical measurements in a transmission electron microscope reveal a distinct tunneling field emission signature that surpasses secondary electron emission. The demonstrated field emission mechanism opens unexplored possibilities for realizing spatially confined electron sources with ultrafast temporal switching capabilities.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.528 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kenan Elibol; Vesna Srot; Chao Yang; Sayooj Satheesh; Serkan Arslan; Marko Burghard; Harald Giessen; Peter A. van Aken&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5421"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.ady5421&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.528 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While field emission, which is crucial for sub–angstrom resolution imaging and nanofabrication, has been extensively investigated in high-voltage and laser-driven systems, its realization through plasmonics under electron irradiation remains unexplored. Here, we demonstrate a proof of concept for electron beam–driven field emission from plasmonic emitter arrays with nanoscale hotspots acting as highly efficient emission sites, which also exhibit strong surface-enhanced Raman scattering activity. The electron beam–induced field distributions and electrical polarization switching are visualized by four-dimensional scanning transmission electron microscopy. Classical and quantum-corrected electromagnetic simulations combined with experimental field maps identify the highest field intensities at the apex of emitter tips. Optical excitation experiments confirm the giant field enhancement at these locations. In situ electrical measurements in a transmission electron microscope reveal a distinct tunneling field emission signature that surpasses secondary electron emission. The demonstrated field emission mechanism opens unexplored possibilities for realizing spatially confined electron sources with ultrafast temporal switching capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Organic lateral heterostructures with interfacial fluctuation for polarization-resolved photonics</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea6228</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aea6228</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yan-Peng Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiang Lv</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao-Fei Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhao-Ji Lv</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xue-Dong Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aea6228</prism:doi><description>Organic lateral heterostructures (OLHs) based on two-dimensional (2D) molecular crystals are formed through the coplanar assembly of multiple components, and they hold great promise for optoelectronic applications. However, the precise construction of 2D OLHs with noncoplanar epitaxial layers remains challenging, limiting further exploration of lateral heterojunctions. Here, we present a stepwise vapor-phase growth strategy for synthesizing 2D OLHs with interfacial fluctuation, forming convex, flat, and concave architectures. During the lateral epitaxial growth processes, higher growth temperatures enhance molecular deposition, driving the transition of the secondary component from in-plane to out-of-plane growth. Consequently, the epitaxial layer thickness is precisely tuned from 20 to 800 nm by increasing the growth temperature. The resulting OLHs exhibit orthogonally polarized exciton conversion, with dual photoluminescence emission bands at 450 and 670 nm, functioning as multimode photonic converters. These findings provide a strategy to regulate the epitaxial growth route of 2D OLHs, paving the way for integrated photonic circuits.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.526 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yan-Peng Ye; Qiang Lv; Chao-Fei Xu; Zhao-Ji Lv; Lei Wang; Xue-Dong Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea6228"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aea6228&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.526 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organic lateral heterostructures (OLHs) based on two-dimensional (2D) molecular crystals are formed through the coplanar assembly of multiple components, and they hold great promise for optoelectronic applications. However, the precise construction of 2D OLHs with noncoplanar epitaxial layers remains challenging, limiting further exploration of lateral heterojunctions. Here, we present a stepwise vapor-phase growth strategy for synthesizing 2D OLHs with interfacial fluctuation, forming convex, flat, and concave architectures. During the lateral epitaxial growth processes, higher growth temperatures enhance molecular deposition, driving the transition of the secondary component from in-plane to out-of-plane growth. Consequently, the epitaxial layer thickness is precisely tuned from 20 to 800 nm by increasing the growth temperature. The resulting OLHs exhibit orthogonally polarized exciton conversion, with dual photoluminescence emission bands at 450 and 670 nm, functioning as multimode photonic converters. These findings provide a strategy to regulate the epitaxial growth route of 2D OLHs, paving the way for integrated photonic circuits.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Dynamic changes in phycosphere carbonate chemistry reveal rapid modulation of carbon uptake in single diatom cells</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady8646</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.ady8646</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Matthew Keys</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrea Highfield</dc:creator><dc:creator>Abdul Chrachri</dc:creator><dc:creator>Clare Ostle</dc:creator><dc:creator>Colin Brownlee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Glen L. Wheeler</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.ady8646</prism:doi><description>Diatoms use multiple mechanisms of dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) uptake to maintain CO 2 supply to RuBisCO (ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase), but how these different pathways are coordinated in response to rapid changes in their environment remains unclear. By measuring the dynamic changes in phycosphere carbonate chemistry around single diatom cells, we show that DIC uptake is rapidly modulated. We find that external carbonic anhydrase (eCA) plays a major role in DIC uptake in large centric diatoms at ambient seawater CO 2 , but there is a strong switch to direct HCO 3 − uptake under low CO 2 . Inhibition of eCA leads to rapid activation of HCO 3 − uptake, which can compensate for the loss of eCA activity under lower irradiances. These different modes of DIC uptake have distinct influences on phycosphere carbonate chemistry that may directly affect nutrient acquisition and biotic interactions. Our findings reveal that dynamic modulation of DIC uptake allows diatoms to rapidly respond to changes in CO 2 supply and demand.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.526 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Matthew Keys; Andrea Highfield; Abdul Chrachri; Clare Ostle; Colin Brownlee; Glen L. Wheeler&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady8646"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.ady8646&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.526 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Diatoms use multiple mechanisms of dissolved inorganic carbon (DIC) uptake to maintain CO 2 supply to RuBisCO (ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase), but how these different pathways are coordinated in response to rapid changes in their environment remains unclear. By measuring the dynamic changes in phycosphere carbonate chemistry around single diatom cells, we show that DIC uptake is rapidly modulated. We find that external carbonic anhydrase (eCA) plays a major role in DIC uptake in large centric diatoms at ambient seawater CO 2 , but there is a strong switch to direct HCO 3 − uptake under low CO 2 . Inhibition of eCA leads to rapid activation of HCO 3 − uptake, which can compensate for the loss of eCA activity under lower irradiances. These different modes of DIC uptake have distinct influences on phycosphere carbonate chemistry that may directly affect nutrient acquisition and biotic interactions. Our findings reveal that dynamic modulation of DIC uptake allows diatoms to rapidly respond to changes in CO 2 supply and demand.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Frozen Soil Hydrological Processes and Their Effects: A Review and Synthesis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2024rg000839</link><guid>10.1029/2024rg000839</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 06:30:43 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ying Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ce Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexander Gelfan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kunio Watanabe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haojie Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephanie Wright</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaolong Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>William Quinton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuhua Yi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongyong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yujie Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wentao Jiao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Reviews of Geophysics</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2024rg000839</prism:doi><description>Abstract Frozen soils, including seasonally frozen ground and permafrost, are rapidly changing under a warming climate, with cascading effects on water, energy, and carbon cycles. We synthesize recent advances in the physics, observation, and modeling of frozen‐soil hydrology, emphasizing freeze–thaw dynamics, infiltration regimes and preferential flow, groundwater–permafrost interactions (including talik development and advective heat), and resulting shifts in streamflow seasonality. Progress in in situ sensing, geophysics, and remote sensing now resolves unfrozen water, freezing fronts, and active‐layer dynamics across scales, while land‐surface and tracer‐aided hydrological models increasingly represent phase change, macropore bypass, and vapor transport. Thaw‐induced activation of subsurface pathways alters recharge and baseflow, influences vegetation and biogeochemistry, and modulates greenhouse‐gas emissions. Key uncertainties persist in scaling micro‐scale processes, parameterizing ice‐impeded hydraulics, and representing abrupt thaw and wetland dynamics. We outline a tiered modeling framework, priority observations, and integration of vegetation–hydrology–carbon processes to improve projections of cold‐region water resources and climate feedbacks.
Published: 2026-01-03T06:30:43+00:00
Venue: Reviews of Geophysics
Score: 0.526 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ying Zhao; Ce Zheng; Alexander Gelfan; Kunio Watanabe; Haojie Liu; Stephanie Wright; Xiaolong Wu; William Quinton; Yi Wang; Shuhua Yi; Yongyong Zhang; Yujie Shi; Wentao Jiao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Reviews of Geophysics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2024rg000839"&gt;10.1029/2024rg000839&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.526 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Frozen soils, including seasonally frozen ground and permafrost, are rapidly changing under a warming climate, with cascading effects on water, energy, and carbon cycles. We synthesize recent advances in the physics, observation, and modeling of frozen‐soil hydrology, emphasizing freeze–thaw dynamics, infiltration regimes and preferential flow, groundwater–permafrost interactions (including talik development and advective heat), and resulting shifts in streamflow seasonality. Progress in in situ sensing, geophysics, and remote sensing now resolves unfrozen water, freezing fronts, and active‐layer dynamics across scales, while land‐surface and tracer‐aided hydrological models increasingly represent phase change, macropore bypass, and vapor transport. Thaw‐induced activation of subsurface pathways alters recharge and baseflow, influences vegetation and biogeochemistry, and modulates greenhouse‐gas emissions. Key uncertainties persist in scaling micro‐scale processes, parameterizing ice‐impeded hydraulics, and representing abrupt thaw and wetland dynamics. We outline a tiered modeling framework, priority observations, and integration of vegetation–hydrology–carbon processes to improve projections of cold‐region water resources and climate feedbacks.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Subcritical Cracking Associated With Subgrain Rotation Recrystallisation in Quartz Inferred From Cathodoluminescence Study</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1111/ter.70024</link><guid>10.1111/ter.70024</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 11:15:34 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Takuro Yoshioka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takamoto Okudaira</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hideo Takagi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Terra Nova</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1111/ter.70024</prism:doi><description>ABSTRACT We employed cathodoluminescence (CL) to study deformed quartz phenocrysts from the Cretaceous granite porphyry in SW Japan and observed fracture‐like planar structures appearing as CL‐dark bands. These CL‐dark bands were aligned with low‐angle grain boundaries formed by subgrain rotation recrystallisation. The low brightness of the CL‐dark bands can be attributed to the precipitation of new quartz with lower dislocation density from fluids that infiltrate into cracks along subgrain boundaries. The cracking along subgrain boundaries may be related to stress corrosion. We propose that stress corrosion occurs along subgrain boundaries, followed by the precipitation of new quartz from crack‐filling fluids. The results of this study indicate that stress corrosion cracking significantly contributes to brittle fracturing and grain‐size reduction in quartz.
Published: 2026-01-02T11:15:34+00:00
Venue: Terra Nova
Score: 0.512 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Takuro Yoshioka; Takamoto Okudaira; Hideo Takagi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Terra Nova&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/ter.70024"&gt;10.1111/ter.70024&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.512 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT We employed cathodoluminescence (CL) to study deformed quartz phenocrysts from the Cretaceous granite porphyry in SW Japan and observed fracture‐like planar structures appearing as CL‐dark bands. These CL‐dark bands were aligned with low‐angle grain boundaries formed by subgrain rotation recrystallisation. The low brightness of the CL‐dark bands can be attributed to the precipitation of new quartz with lower dislocation density from fluids that infiltrate into cracks along subgrain boundaries. The cracking along subgrain boundaries may be related to stress corrosion. We propose that stress corrosion occurs along subgrain boundaries, followed by the precipitation of new quartz from crack‐filling fluids. The results of this study indicate that stress corrosion cracking significantly contributes to brittle fracturing and grain‐size reduction in quartz.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hysteretic self-oscillatory acoustic radiation with tunable orbital angular momentum</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5416</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.ady5416</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Li Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong-yu Zou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yong Ge</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenwen Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong-xiang Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fujia Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiaolu Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuang Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingyu Tong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuze Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ning Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bei Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junyao Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qingdong Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shou-qi Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongsheng Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yihao Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuang Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.ady5416</prism:doi><description>Vortex beams carrying orbital angular momentum (OAM) have attracted growing attention across fields, including optics and acoustics, for potential applications in particle manipulation and high-speed communication. Intracavity generation of OAM beams, such as OAM lasers, efficiently produces high-power, high–beam-quality vortices. This scheme, however, remains rarely explored in acoustics. Here, we propose and demonstrate an acoustic intracavity OAM generation mechanism with tunable topological charges via a single nonreciprocal nonlinear boundary in a compact resonator ring. In the linear regime, the boundary creates non-Hermitian complex effective magnetic fields piercing the ring, leading to a non-Hermitian Zeeman-like effect that splits clockwise and counterclockwise eigenmodes. Upon incorporation of nonlinearity to the boundary, all resonators are mutually locked, producing a single-mode self-oscillatory OAM radiation exhibiting hysteresis and bistability. Moreover, the topological charge is tunable by manipulating the boundary. Our work reveals intriguing physics related to nonlinear, non-Hermitian boundaries and offers potentials in the next generation of acoustic self-oscillatory OAM sources, switchers, and memory devices.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.511 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Li Zhang; Hong-yu Zou; Yong Ge; Wenwen Liu; Hong-xiang Sun; Fujia Chen; Qiaolu Chen; Yuang Pan; Mingyu Tong; Yuze Hu; Ning Han; Bei Wu; Junyao Wu; Qingdong Yang; Shou-qi Yuan; Hongsheng Chen; Yihao Yang; Shuang Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5416"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.ady5416&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.511 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vortex beams carrying orbital angular momentum (OAM) have attracted growing attention across fields, including optics and acoustics, for potential applications in particle manipulation and high-speed communication. Intracavity generation of OAM beams, such as OAM lasers, efficiently produces high-power, high–beam-quality vortices. This scheme, however, remains rarely explored in acoustics. Here, we propose and demonstrate an acoustic intracavity OAM generation mechanism with tunable topological charges via a single nonreciprocal nonlinear boundary in a compact resonator ring. In the linear regime, the boundary creates non-Hermitian complex effective magnetic fields piercing the ring, leading to a non-Hermitian Zeeman-like effect that splits clockwise and counterclockwise eigenmodes. Upon incorporation of nonlinearity to the boundary, all resonators are mutually locked, producing a single-mode self-oscillatory OAM radiation exhibiting hysteresis and bistability. Moreover, the topological charge is tunable by manipulating the boundary. Our work reveals intriguing physics related to nonlinear, non-Hermitian boundaries and offers potentials in the next generation of acoustic self-oscillatory OAM sources, switchers, and memory devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Gradient interfacial water dynamics for stable aqueous metal anodes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2525975123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2525975123</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 17:39:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tianrui Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengyu Ju</dc:creator><dc:creator>Amy C. Marschilok</dc:creator><dc:creator>Esther S. Takeuchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kenneth J. Takeuchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guihua Yu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2525975123</prism:doi><description>The deployment of renewable energy necessitates reliable grid-scale storage technologies. Aqueous metal battery systems are one of the promising candidates due to high safety, low cost, and high theoretical capacity of metal anodes, yet their long-term stability is hindered by dendritic growth and parasitic water-induced side reactions. In particular, in the case of aqueous zinc (Zn) batteries, high water reactivity at the metal anode results in hydrogen evolution and corrosion in conventional ZnSO 4 aqueous electrolytes. However, restrained water activity often leads to slow charge transport kinetics of solvated cations, limiting the high-rate operation capability of aqueous batteries. Here, we report a gradient composite hydrogel interlayer incorporating vermiculite (VMT) nanosheets within a polyacrylamide polymer matrix to synergistically regulate interfacial water dynamics and stabilize Zn anodes. Abundant hydroxyl groups and negatively charged silicate layers in VMT nanosheets strongly interact with adjacent water molecules, converting free water into bound water to suppress its activity. Charge transport behaviors of Zn ions in the hydrogel interlayer are further improved by rationally tuning the water activity along the depth of the interlayer, resulting in high ion diffusion kinetics close to the bulk electrolyte. Therefore, such a design enables Zn||Zn symmetric cells to stably cycle for over 2,000 h at 5 mA cm −2 and 5 mAh cm −2 , and sustain high current densities up to 40 mA cm −2 . This work brings critical scientific understanding on interfacial water dynamics and highlights its importance for durable metal anode during operation, advancing aqueous batteries toward practical grid-scale energy storage.
Published: 2026-01-02T17:39:09+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.510 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tianrui Zheng; Zhengyu Ju; Amy C. Marschilok; Esther S. Takeuchi; Kenneth J. Takeuchi; Guihua Yu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2525975123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2525975123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.510 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deployment of renewable energy necessitates reliable grid-scale storage technologies. Aqueous metal battery systems are one of the promising candidates due to high safety, low cost, and high theoretical capacity of metal anodes, yet their long-term stability is hindered by dendritic growth and parasitic water-induced side reactions. In particular, in the case of aqueous zinc (Zn) batteries, high water reactivity at the metal anode results in hydrogen evolution and corrosion in conventional ZnSO 4 aqueous electrolytes. However, restrained water activity often leads to slow charge transport kinetics of solvated cations, limiting the high-rate operation capability of aqueous batteries. Here, we report a gradient composite hydrogel interlayer incorporating vermiculite (VMT) nanosheets within a polyacrylamide polymer matrix to synergistically regulate interfacial water dynamics and stabilize Zn anodes. Abundant hydroxyl groups and negatively charged silicate layers in VMT nanosheets strongly interact with adjacent water molecules, converting free water into bound water to suppress its activity. Charge transport behaviors of Zn ions in the hydrogel interlayer are further improved by rationally tuning the water activity along the depth of the interlayer, resulting in high ion diffusion kinetics close to the bulk electrolyte. Therefore, such a design enables Zn||Zn symmetric cells to stably cycle for over 2,000 h at 5 mA cm −2 and 5 mAh cm −2 , and sustain high current densities up to 40 mA cm −2 . This work brings critical scientific understanding on interfacial water dynamics and highlights its importance for durable metal anode during operation, advancing aqueous batteries toward practical grid-scale energy storage.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Blue carbon sequestration dominated by dissolved organic carbon pathways for kelp forests and eelgrass meadows in Nova Scotia, Canada</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03122-2</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03122-2</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 06:23:40 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kira A. Krumhansl</dc:creator><dc:creator>Melisa C. Wong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manon M. M. Picard</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meredith Fraser</dc:creator><dc:creator>Carrie-Ellen Gabriel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongsheng Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kumiko Azetsu-Scott</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03122-2</prism:doi><description>Abstract Existing estimates of carbon sequestration by coastal vegetated ecosystems (e.g., kelp forests, seagrass meadows) remain highly uncertain because they utilize few measurements with high uncertainty or focus on individual stocks or fluxes. Here, we combine empirical data with modeling to generate detailed carbon budgets for kelp forests and eelgrass meadows in Nova Scotia, Canada. Our budgeting showed that the release and export of dissolved organic carbon accounts for substantially more carbon sequestered by these habitats than has been estimated globally (98.5 ± 64.6% for kelp and 84 ± 36.0% for eelgrass), suggesting this carbon pathway has been undervalued. Further, kelp forests are estimated to sequester more carbon than eelgrass by ~1.3 orders of magnitude (27 ± 19% and 12.1 ± 6.3% of annual net primary production for kelp and eelgrass) mainly due to their large habitat area, highlighting their significant but largely overlooked role in ocean carbon sequestration relative to other blue carbon ecosystems.
Published: 2026-01-03T06:23:40+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.508 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kira A. Krumhansl; Melisa C. Wong; Manon M. M. Picard; Meredith Fraser; Carrie-Ellen Gabriel; Yongsheng Wu; Kumiko Azetsu-Scott&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03122-2"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03122-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.508 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Existing estimates of carbon sequestration by coastal vegetated ecosystems (e.g., kelp forests, seagrass meadows) remain highly uncertain because they utilize few measurements with high uncertainty or focus on individual stocks or fluxes. Here, we combine empirical data with modeling to generate detailed carbon budgets for kelp forests and eelgrass meadows in Nova Scotia, Canada. Our budgeting showed that the release and export of dissolved organic carbon accounts for substantially more carbon sequestered by these habitats than has been estimated globally (98.5 ± 64.6% for kelp and 84 ± 36.0% for eelgrass), suggesting this carbon pathway has been undervalued. Further, kelp forests are estimated to sequester more carbon than eelgrass by ~1.3 orders of magnitude (27 ± 19% and 12.1 ± 6.3% of annual net primary production for kelp and eelgrass) mainly due to their large habitat area, highlighting their significant but largely overlooked role in ocean carbon sequestration relative to other blue carbon ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Janus Mn single atoms for triggering efficient photothermal catalytic CO
                    &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
                    methanation through spin polarization effect</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz7504</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adz7504</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yong Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shujuan Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lulu Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weili Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianbo Fang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenggao Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenping Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianping Zou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xubiao Luo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adz7504</prism:doi><description>Photothermal catalysis, using sunlight as single energy source, is an ideal pattern for CO 2 reduction. Herein, Mn single atoms (SAs) are constructed on the surface of NNSO, which induces spin polarization effect, thus promoting directional transfer of photothermal electrons, and improving electron density of Mn sites and adsorption ability of CO 2 . Meanwhile, Mn SAs act as new active sites enhancing the adsorption of intermediate * CO, thus suppressing CO production, lowering energy barriers of hydrogenation, and changing the reaction path. In addition, the hydrogen overflow energy barriers decrease under the effect of spin polarization, promoting the rapid transfer of active H from Ni atoms to Mn SAs. As a result, the rate of CO 2 methanation is 195.7 millimoles per gram per hour with near-unity selectivity, and the catalytic activity of 1.0%Mn/NNSO increases by approximately 140 times compared with NNSO. To our knowledge, this is the first study that uses the spin polarization effect to achieve efficient photothermal CO 2 methanation.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.507 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yong Xu; Shujuan Chen; Lulu Yao; Weili Dai; Jianbo Fang; Chenggao Sun; Wenping Feng; Jianping Zou; Xubiao Luo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz7504"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adz7504&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.507 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photothermal catalysis, using sunlight as single energy source, is an ideal pattern for CO 2 reduction. Herein, Mn single atoms (SAs) are constructed on the surface of NNSO, which induces spin polarization effect, thus promoting directional transfer of photothermal electrons, and improving electron density of Mn sites and adsorption ability of CO 2 . Meanwhile, Mn SAs act as new active sites enhancing the adsorption of intermediate * CO, thus suppressing CO production, lowering energy barriers of hydrogenation, and changing the reaction path. In addition, the hydrogen overflow energy barriers decrease under the effect of spin polarization, promoting the rapid transfer of active H from Ni atoms to Mn SAs. As a result, the rate of CO 2 methanation is 195.7 millimoles per gram per hour with near-unity selectivity, and the catalytic activity of 1.0%Mn/NNSO increases by approximately 140 times compared with NNSO. To our knowledge, this is the first study that uses the spin polarization effect to achieve efficient photothermal CO 2 methanation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Stable Cuδ+ sites derived from analogous rectifying interface in AgCu biphasic aerogels for efficient urea electrosynthesis at low potential</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-65857-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-65857-y</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 07:04:43 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pingyi Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zechuan Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanxu Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bocheng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingyu Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Buqi Ke</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Genqiang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fuqiang Huang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-65857-y</prism:doi><description>Urea electrosynthesis through CO2 and NO3- coupling presents a promising alternative to energy-intensive industrial processes. However, intricate catalytic mechanisms and competitive reactions impede achieving high-efficiency C-N coupling. Herein, we constructed analogous rectifying interfaces in AgCu biphasic aerogels, by leveraging electronegativity difference to derive stable Cuδ+ active sites, which simultaneously promoted *NOH adsorption and *CO coverage, thereby improving C-N coupling dynamics, confirmed by both operando technique and theoretical calculations. Specifically, notable urea yield (54.8 mmol h-1 gcat.−1) with Faradaic efficiency (FE, 36.6%) at a low potential (−0.52 V vs. RHE) was achieved using Ag67Cu33 in a flow-cell. As a proof-of-concept demonstration for practicability, Ag67Cu33 exhibited bifunctional electrosynthesis for urea (FE: 56.07%, yield: 104.6 mmol h-1 gcat.−1) and HCOOH (FE: over 90%) at 40 mA cm-2 in two-electrode system, with durability over 60 h. This work provides an indicative rationale to construct active sites for C-N coupling, facilitating the development of urea electrosynthesis. Electrocatalytic co-reduction of CO2 and NO3 - for urea synthesis is constrained by low efficiency. Here, the stable Cuδ+ active sites, regulated by an analogous rectifying interface effect, not only enhanced the critical C-N coupling dynamics but also enabled high-performance urea synthesis.
Published: 2026-01-03T07:04:43+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.507 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pingyi Feng; Shao Wang; Zechuan Dai; Yanxu Chen; Bocheng Zhang; Mingyu Cheng; Buqi Ke; Jing Xia; Genqiang Zhang; Fuqiang Huang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-65857-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-65857-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.507 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urea electrosynthesis through CO2 and NO3- coupling presents a promising alternative to energy-intensive industrial processes. However, intricate catalytic mechanisms and competitive reactions impede achieving high-efficiency C-N coupling. Herein, we constructed analogous rectifying interfaces in AgCu biphasic aerogels, by leveraging electronegativity difference to derive stable Cuδ+ active sites, which simultaneously promoted *NOH adsorption and *CO coverage, thereby improving C-N coupling dynamics, confirmed by both operando technique and theoretical calculations. Specifically, notable urea yield (54.8 mmol h-1 gcat.−1) with Faradaic efficiency (FE, 36.6%) at a low potential (−0.52 V vs. RHE) was achieved using Ag67Cu33 in a flow-cell. As a proof-of-concept demonstration for practicability, Ag67Cu33 exhibited bifunctional electrosynthesis for urea (FE: 56.07%, yield: 104.6 mmol h-1 gcat.−1) and HCOOH (FE: over 90%) at 40 mA cm-2 in two-electrode system, with durability over 60 h. This work provides an indicative rationale to construct active sites for C-N coupling, facilitating the development of urea electrosynthesis. Electrocatalytic co-reduction of CO2 and NO3 - for urea synthesis is constrained by low efficiency. Here, the stable Cuδ+ active sites, regulated by an analogous rectifying interface effect, not only enhanced the critical C-N coupling dynamics but also enabled high-performance urea synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Metaoptics merging computational optics and optical computing toward intelligent visual perception</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea8941</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aea8941</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yueqiang Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanbin Chi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huigao Duan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aea8941</prism:doi><description>Visual perception systems are evolving toward multifunctionality, miniaturization, and real-time intelligence, necessitating coadvancements in optical hardware and computational software. Computational optics enhances optical encoding through algorithms but faces computational limits, while optical computing offers photonic parallelism yet struggles with hardware complexity. Metaoptics, using subwavelength nanostructures for multidimensional light-field control, resolves this tension by serving dual roles: as an efficient computational optics encoder offloading algorithmic burdens and as a nanoscale optical computing processor enabling ultrahigh-density parallelism. This synergy drives computational optical integration for next-generation optoelectronics. This review outlines computational optics and optical computing fundamentals, analyzes metaoptics’ advantages in multidimensional optical information encoding and processing, and details recent metaoptics-based advances and challenges in computational optics, optical computing, and their convergence. The conclusion provides a future roadmap, highlighting metaoptics-driven integration’s potential for chip-scale intelligent visual perception by bridging the hardware-software divide to enable miniaturized devices with real-time adaptability, massive parallelism, and energy efficiency.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.507 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yueqiang Hu; Hanbin Chi; Huigao Duan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea8941"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aea8941&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.507 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visual perception systems are evolving toward multifunctionality, miniaturization, and real-time intelligence, necessitating coadvancements in optical hardware and computational software. Computational optics enhances optical encoding through algorithms but faces computational limits, while optical computing offers photonic parallelism yet struggles with hardware complexity. Metaoptics, using subwavelength nanostructures for multidimensional light-field control, resolves this tension by serving dual roles: as an efficient computational optics encoder offloading algorithmic burdens and as a nanoscale optical computing processor enabling ultrahigh-density parallelism. This synergy drives computational optical integration for next-generation optoelectronics. This review outlines computational optics and optical computing fundamentals, analyzes metaoptics’ advantages in multidimensional optical information encoding and processing, and details recent metaoptics-based advances and challenges in computational optics, optical computing, and their convergence. The conclusion provides a future roadmap, highlighting metaoptics-driven integration’s potential for chip-scale intelligent visual perception by bridging the hardware-software divide to enable miniaturized devices with real-time adaptability, massive parallelism, and energy efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Data-driven superresolution imaging in disordered media</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2530449123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2530449123</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 17:39:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Alexander Christie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Matan Leibovich</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miguel Moscoso</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexei Novikov</dc:creator><dc:creator>George Papanicolaou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chrysoula Tsogka</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2530449123</prism:doi><description>We propose a methodology that exploits large and diverse datasets to accurately estimate the ambient medium’s Green’s functions in strongly scattering media. Given these estimates, excellent imaging results are achieved, with a resolution that is better than that of a homogeneous medium. This phenomenon, known as superresolution, arises because the ambient scattering medium effectively enlarges the physical imaging aperture. While superresolution has been demonstrated and analyzed extensively in the context of physical time reversal, time reversal itself is not imaging. Our proposed methodology, based on either conventional optimization methods or neural networks, makes it possible to achieve superresolution imaging in complex media.
Published: 2026-01-02T17:39:09+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.502 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Alexander Christie; Matan Leibovich; Miguel Moscoso; Alexei Novikov; George Papanicolaou; Chrysoula Tsogka&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2530449123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2530449123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.502 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose a methodology that exploits large and diverse datasets to accurately estimate the ambient medium’s Green’s functions in strongly scattering media. Given these estimates, excellent imaging results are achieved, with a resolution that is better than that of a homogeneous medium. This phenomenon, known as superresolution, arises because the ambient scattering medium effectively enlarges the physical imaging aperture. While superresolution has been demonstrated and analyzed extensively in the context of physical time reversal, time reversal itself is not imaging. Our proposed methodology, based on either conventional optimization methods or neural networks, makes it possible to achieve superresolution imaging in complex media.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Detection and identification of vacancy defects in antimony selenide</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68153-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68153-x</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 06:36:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>David J. Keeble</dc:creator><dc:creator>Theodore D. C. Hobson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Julia Wiktor</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ethan Berger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marcel Dickmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mohamed R. M. Elsharkawy</dc:creator><dc:creator>Werner Egger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan D. Major</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ken Durose</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68153-x</prism:doi><description>Abstract Antimony selenide (Sb 2 Se 3 ) has an optimal bandgap and absorption coefficient for thin film solar cell applications and comprises earth abundant elements. The rate of increase in reported power conversion efficiencies has slowed due to a persistently large open circuit voltage deficit attributed to detrimental concentrations of point defects. Here we use depth-profiling positron annihilation lifetime spectroscopy to study Sb 2 Se 3 crystals and thin films. The method is specific to neutral and negative charge states of vacancy-related defects. Both monovacancy and divacancy defects are identified in intrinsic and n-type samples but no monovacancy defects are detected in the p-type sample. Comparison of the experimental positron lifetimes with density functional theory calculated values provide evidence for the observation of Sb monovacancies in the –3 state and of Se monovacancies in the –2 state. The results are consistent with recent density function theory predictions that the Sb and the Se monovacancy defects both have accessible negative charge states.
Published: 2026-01-03T06:36:14+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.500 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; David J. Keeble; Theodore D. C. Hobson; Julia Wiktor; Ethan Berger; Marcel Dickmann; Mohamed R. M. Elsharkawy; Werner Egger; Jonathan D. Major; Ken Durose&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68153-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68153-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.500 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Antimony selenide (Sb 2 Se 3 ) has an optimal bandgap and absorption coefficient for thin film solar cell applications and comprises earth abundant elements. The rate of increase in reported power conversion efficiencies has slowed due to a persistently large open circuit voltage deficit attributed to detrimental concentrations of point defects. Here we use depth-profiling positron annihilation lifetime spectroscopy to study Sb 2 Se 3 crystals and thin films. The method is specific to neutral and negative charge states of vacancy-related defects. Both monovacancy and divacancy defects are identified in intrinsic and n-type samples but no monovacancy defects are detected in the p-type sample. Comparison of the experimental positron lifetimes with density functional theory calculated values provide evidence for the observation of Sb monovacancies in the –3 state and of Se monovacancies in the –2 state. The results are consistent with recent density function theory predictions that the Sb and the Se monovacancy defects both have accessible negative charge states.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Issue Information</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/rog.70006</link><guid>10.1029/rog.70006</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 06:35:12 +0000</pubDate><prism:publicationName>Reviews of Geophysics</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/rog.70006</prism:doi><description>No abstract is available for this article.
Published: 2026-01-03T06:35:12+00:00
Venue: Reviews of Geophysics
Score: 0.498 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Reviews of Geophysics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/rog.70006"&gt;10.1029/rog.70006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.498 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No abstract is available for this article.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Equation of state of Fe-bearing epidote-group minerals determined by X-ray diffraction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2024-9699</link><guid>10.2138/am-2024-9699</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 22:08:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xinyue Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ningyu Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhu Mao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>American Mineralogist</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.2138/am-2024-9699</prism:doi><description>Abstract Minerals in the epidote group, such as zoisite, clinozoisite, and epidote, are important water carriers to the Earth’s deep interior through subducting slabs. In this study, we have performed synchrotron X-ray diffraction (XRD) measurements on four epidote-group minerals up to 60 GPa at 300 K in diamond-anvil cells (DACs) to investigate the influence of structure and Fe content on the equation of state and density of these minerals. The obtained volume-pressure data were fitted using a third-order Birch-Murnaghan equation of state, giving V0 = 902.6(1) Å3, KT0 = 112(2) GPa, and KT0′=7.1(3) for zoisite with XFe = 0 [XFe = Fe3+/(Fe3++Al-2)], V0 = 455.0(2) Å3, KT0 = 160(6) GPa, and KT0′=3.4(6) for clinozoisite with XFe = 0.24, V0 = 457.53(5) Å3, KT0 = 142(4) GPa, and KT0′=4.5(3) for clinozoisite with XFe = 0.47, and V0 = 458.5(7) Å3, KT0 = 157(5) GPa, and KT0′=2.9(2) for epidote with XFe = 0.84. Together with literature results, we found that elevating the Fe content will increase the density of epidote-group minerals but decrease the bulk modulus. Compared to monoclinic clinozoisite with the same iron content, the orthorhombic zoisite has a higher density but a lower bulk modulus. The axial-compression behavior of epidote-group minerals is also discussed. Combining the elastic properties and density of other minerals in the CaO-Al2O3-SiO2-H2O (CASH) system, we discuss the effect of water and Fe on this system and further elucidate the role of epidote minerals in water circulation inside the Earth.
Published: 2026-01-03T22:08:26+00:00
Venue: American Mineralogist
Score: 0.496 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xinyue Zhang; Ningyu Sun; Zhu Mao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; American Mineralogist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2024-9699"&gt;10.2138/am-2024-9699&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.496 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Minerals in the epidote group, such as zoisite, clinozoisite, and epidote, are important water carriers to the Earth’s deep interior through subducting slabs. In this study, we have performed synchrotron X-ray diffraction (XRD) measurements on four epidote-group minerals up to 60 GPa at 300 K in diamond-anvil cells (DACs) to investigate the influence of structure and Fe content on the equation of state and density of these minerals. The obtained volume-pressure data were fitted using a third-order Birch-Murnaghan equation of state, giving V0 = 902.6(1) Å3, KT0 = 112(2) GPa, and KT0′=7.1(3) for zoisite with XFe = 0 [XFe = Fe3+/(Fe3++Al-2)], V0 = 455.0(2) Å3, KT0 = 160(6) GPa, and KT0′=3.4(6) for clinozoisite with XFe = 0.24, V0 = 457.53(5) Å3, KT0 = 142(4) GPa, and KT0′=4.5(3) for clinozoisite with XFe = 0.47, and V0 = 458.5(7) Å3, KT0 = 157(5) GPa, and KT0′=2.9(2) for epidote with XFe = 0.84. Together with literature results, we found that elevating the Fe content will increase the density of epidote-group minerals but decrease the bulk modulus. Compared to monoclinic clinozoisite with the same iron content, the orthorhombic zoisite has a higher density but a lower bulk modulus. The axial-compression behavior of epidote-group minerals is also discussed. Combining the elastic properties and density of other minerals in the CaO-Al2O3-SiO2-H2O (CASH) system, we discuss the effect of water and Fe on this system and further elucidate the role of epidote minerals in water circulation inside the Earth.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Observation of Kerr soliton microcomb locked with a phonon laser</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aeb3400</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aeb3400</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xinxin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yifeng Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shulin Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Menghua Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yaya He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bing He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoshun Jiang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aeb3400</prism:doi><description>Cavity optomechanics and dissipative Kerr soliton microcomb are two research fields that followed the parallel lines of development, and the interplay of their respective elements was unseen in the past. Here, we present an observation of mutually synchronized Kerr soliton microcomb and optomechanical oscillation in the same microresonator. We generated a previously unknown type of breathing soliton to drive the mechanical mode of the microresonator into a forced oscillation at the breathing frequency. Once the breathing frequency is tuned close to the mechanical frequency of the system, the breathing soliton and the excited mechanical oscillation suddenly lock together into a synchronization. This state locks to an almost unchanged breathing frequency, and exists over a considerable frequency range of the pump laser. The locked breathing Kerr soliton can substantially lower its phase noise and improve its long-term stability, providing potential applications in various areas.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.495 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xinxin Li; Yifeng Xie; Shulin Ding; Menghua Zhang; Yaya He; Bing He; Min Xiao; Xiaoshun Jiang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aeb3400"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aeb3400&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.495 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cavity optomechanics and dissipative Kerr soliton microcomb are two research fields that followed the parallel lines of development, and the interplay of their respective elements was unseen in the past. Here, we present an observation of mutually synchronized Kerr soliton microcomb and optomechanical oscillation in the same microresonator. We generated a previously unknown type of breathing soliton to drive the mechanical mode of the microresonator into a forced oscillation at the breathing frequency. Once the breathing frequency is tuned close to the mechanical frequency of the system, the breathing soliton and the excited mechanical oscillation suddenly lock together into a synchronization. This state locks to an almost unchanged breathing frequency, and exists over a considerable frequency range of the pump laser. The locked breathing Kerr soliton can substantially lower its phase noise and improve its long-term stability, providing potential applications in various areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Imaging of Magma Intrusion Below La Palma During a Strong Effusive Eruption in 2021 Inferred From Repeated Seismic Tomography</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031599</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb031599</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 06:30:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ivan Koulakov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luca D’Auria</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jesús M. Ibáñez</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb031599</prism:doi><description>Abstract The 2021 eruption of Cumbre Vieja on La Palma, Canary Islands, provided a unique opportunity to investigate the dynamics of magma migration and storage during a large effusive eruption. In this study, we employ repeated seismic tomography to image temporal changes in the subsurface structure beneath La Palma, using body‐wave travel times from local earthquakes recorded before and during the eruption. By carefully selecting paired data sets with identical numbers of events and similar ray path distributions, we minimize biases introduced by variations in seismicity patterns and ensure robust detection of velocity changes. Our results reveal a complex magma plumbing system characterized by a deep magma storage zone below 8 km depth and a shallow, fluid‐saturated region extending to ∼3 km depth. During the eruption, a high Vp/Vs anomaly, interpreted as a magma conduit, formed and ascended through a rigid barrier at 5–8 km depth, facilitating the transport of significant volumes of magma to the surface. The conduit evolved from a diapir‐like structure with a stable head at 6–7 km depth in the early stages of the eruption to an ascending plume reaching 3 km depth in later stages. This study highlights the utility of repeated seismic tomography in unraveling the dynamic processes driving effusive eruptions and provides new insights into the evolution of magma systems during volcanic unrest.
Published: 2026-01-02T06:30:17+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.493 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ivan Koulakov; Luca D’Auria; Jesús M. Ibáñez&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031599"&gt;10.1029/2025jb031599&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.493 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The 2021 eruption of Cumbre Vieja on La Palma, Canary Islands, provided a unique opportunity to investigate the dynamics of magma migration and storage during a large effusive eruption. In this study, we employ repeated seismic tomography to image temporal changes in the subsurface structure beneath La Palma, using body‐wave travel times from local earthquakes recorded before and during the eruption. By carefully selecting paired data sets with identical numbers of events and similar ray path distributions, we minimize biases introduced by variations in seismicity patterns and ensure robust detection of velocity changes. Our results reveal a complex magma plumbing system characterized by a deep magma storage zone below 8 km depth and a shallow, fluid‐saturated region extending to ∼3 km depth. During the eruption, a high Vp/Vs anomaly, interpreted as a magma conduit, formed and ascended through a rigid barrier at 5–8 km depth, facilitating the transport of significant volumes of magma to the surface. The conduit evolved from a diapir‐like structure with a stable head at 6–7 km depth in the early stages of the eruption to an ascending plume reaching 3 km depth in later stages. This study highlights the utility of repeated seismic tomography in unraveling the dynamic processes driving effusive eruptions and provides new insights into the evolution of magma systems during volcanic unrest.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Barents Sea atlantification driven by a shift in atmospheric synoptic timescale</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02535-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41558-025-02535-3</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 10:01:57 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Robinson Hordoir</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vahidreza Jahanmard</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pål Erik Isachsen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ulrike Löptien</dc:creator><dc:creator>Heiner Dietze</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anne Britt Sandø</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vidar S. Lien</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Climate Change</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41558-025-02535-3</prism:doi><description>Abstract Climate change impinges on the Arctic Ocean, leading to sea-ice loss and potentially drastic cascading ecosystem changes. A recent process is atlantification, the growing influence of warm and salty waters from the Atlantic on the Arctic with increasing ocean volume transport from the Nordic Seas to the Barents Sea playing a key role. Despite its importance and a multitude of hypotheses that have been tested, this trend remains mainly unexplained. Here we explore nonlinear effects and successfully link the flow trend through the Barents Sea Opening to a frequency shift of atmospheric synoptic. We show that a part of the flow through Barents Sea Opening is driven by topographic Rossby waves, and that they have a very sensitive response to atmospheric frequency over the Nordic Seas. These findings highlight how anthropogenic changes to the atmosphere are altering ocean processes, with implications for sea-ice extent and ecosystems in the Arctic.
Published: 2026-01-02T10:01:57+00:00
Venue: Nature Climate Change
Score: 0.491 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Robinson Hordoir; Vahidreza Jahanmard; Pål Erik Isachsen; Ulrike Löptien; Heiner Dietze; Anne Britt Sandø; Vidar S. Lien&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Climate Change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02535-3"&gt;10.1038/s41558-025-02535-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.491 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Climate change impinges on the Arctic Ocean, leading to sea-ice loss and potentially drastic cascading ecosystem changes. A recent process is atlantification, the growing influence of warm and salty waters from the Atlantic on the Arctic with increasing ocean volume transport from the Nordic Seas to the Barents Sea playing a key role. Despite its importance and a multitude of hypotheses that have been tested, this trend remains mainly unexplained. Here we explore nonlinear effects and successfully link the flow trend through the Barents Sea Opening to a frequency shift of atmospheric synoptic. We show that a part of the flow through Barents Sea Opening is driven by topographic Rossby waves, and that they have a very sensitive response to atmospheric frequency over the Nordic Seas. These findings highlight how anthropogenic changes to the atmosphere are altering ocean processes, with implications for sea-ice extent and ecosystems in the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Monolayer nanocrystalline graphene synthesized from pyrolyzing a Langmuir monolayer of a polyaromatic hydrocarbon</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adv1856</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adv1856</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xue Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dario Calvani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher Leist</dc:creator><dc:creator>Max Makurat</dc:creator><dc:creator>Adéla Melcrová</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meng He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Douwe Scholma</dc:creator><dc:creator>G. J. Agur Sevink</dc:creator><dc:creator>Francesco Buda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yannick Hermans</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jan P. Hofmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haoyuan Qi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinliang Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wouter H. Roos</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ute Kaiser</dc:creator><dc:creator>Grégory F. Schneider</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adv1856</prism:doi><description>Bulk carbon materials can be synthesized through the modulation of precursor structures, stacking mode, and the optimization of pyrolysis conditions. The structure of two-dimensional (2D) carbon materials, however, is mainly driven by the pyrolysis temperature, pressure, and organic gas flow rates. Here, we report the synthesis of a centimeter-sized nanocrystalline graphene monolayer from pyrolyzing a Langmuir monolayer of a hexa(terpyridine)hexaphenylbenzene polyaromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) yielding a 2D carbon material with a thickness of 0.36 ± 0.07 nm. By designing the amphiphilic PAHs and reducing intermolecular π-π stacking interactions, a monolayer of horizontally aligned PAH was obtained at the water-air interface. During the pyrolysis, the monolayer served as a molecularly thin solid carbon source, leading to the controlled preparation of an electrically insulating nanocrystalline graphene monolayer. Our work proposes a 2D carbon material formed from the initial assembly of PAH monolayer at the water-air interface and subsequent pyrolysis and offers a modular strategy for designing nanocrystalline 2D films.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.489 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xue Liu; Dario Calvani; Christopher Leist; Max Makurat; Adéla Melcrová; Meng He; Douwe Scholma; G. J. Agur Sevink; Francesco Buda; Yannick Hermans; Jan P. Hofmann; Haoyuan Qi; Xinliang Feng; Wouter H. Roos; Ute Kaiser; Grégory F. Schneider&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adv1856"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adv1856&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.489 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bulk carbon materials can be synthesized through the modulation of precursor structures, stacking mode, and the optimization of pyrolysis conditions. The structure of two-dimensional (2D) carbon materials, however, is mainly driven by the pyrolysis temperature, pressure, and organic gas flow rates. Here, we report the synthesis of a centimeter-sized nanocrystalline graphene monolayer from pyrolyzing a Langmuir monolayer of a hexa(terpyridine)hexaphenylbenzene polyaromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) yielding a 2D carbon material with a thickness of 0.36 ± 0.07 nm. By designing the amphiphilic PAHs and reducing intermolecular π-π stacking interactions, a monolayer of horizontally aligned PAH was obtained at the water-air interface. During the pyrolysis, the monolayer served as a molecularly thin solid carbon source, leading to the controlled preparation of an electrically insulating nanocrystalline graphene monolayer. Our work proposes a 2D carbon material formed from the initial assembly of PAH monolayer at the water-air interface and subsequent pyrolysis and offers a modular strategy for designing nanocrystalline 2D films.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Building material stock drives embodied carbon emissions and risks future climate goals in China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02527-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41558-025-02527-3</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 10:01:54 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chaoqun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lin Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dominik Wiedenhofer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianping Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ziyue Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shaoying Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mei-po Kwan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuyu Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liqiang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manchun Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiqi Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bailang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bin Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xing Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoqi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bingbo Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianqiang Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuheng Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiancheng Lv</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanzhao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qianqian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiao Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Climate Change</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41558-025-02527-3</prism:doi><description>Long-term effects of massive building material use in China, which experienced intense urbanization in the past two decades, remain insufficiently explored. Here, to fill these gaps, we developed a high-resolution time-series database of building material stocks from 2000 to 2019 and found that China held 15% of the global stock, which accounted for 19% of the country’s total carbon emissions. Although rapid urbanization generally increased per capita building material stock, the extent of this increase varied across cities and building types. We show that the growth rate has slowed since 2016; however, it remains challenging to simultaneously achieve both carbon-neutrality and urbanization goals. Future urbanization in China is projected to consume 12.5% of the nation’s total 1.5 °C carbon budget and 37.4% of its average annual budget allocation. Addressing these challenges requires targeted urban interventions, such as aligning low-carbon material production with projected regional demand and strategically planning materials recycling from future building demolitions. Reducing the embodied carbon emissions of building material stock is essential for mitigation. Using a high-resolution multiyear dataset in China, researchers show the historically massive contributions of these emissions during past decades of rapid urbanization and the potential risks for future climate goals.
Published: 2026-01-02T10:01:54+00:00
Venue: Nature Climate Change
Score: 0.487 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chaoqun Zhang; Lin Yang; Dominik Wiedenhofer; Jianping Guo; Ziyue Chen; Shaoying Li; Zhen Wang; Mei-po Kwan; Yuyu Zhou; Lu Lin; Liqiang Zhang; Manchun Li; Qiqi Zhu; Bailang Yu; Bin Chen; Xing Yan; Xiaoqi Wang; Bingbo Gao; Ying Liang; Jianqiang Hu; Yuheng Fu; Qiancheng Lv; Jing Yang; Yanzhao Wang; Qianqian Wang; Qiao Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Climate Change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02527-3"&gt;10.1038/s41558-025-02527-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.487 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long-term effects of massive building material use in China, which experienced intense urbanization in the past two decades, remain insufficiently explored. Here, to fill these gaps, we developed a high-resolution time-series database of building material stocks from 2000 to 2019 and found that China held 15% of the global stock, which accounted for 19% of the country’s total carbon emissions. Although rapid urbanization generally increased per capita building material stock, the extent of this increase varied across cities and building types. We show that the growth rate has slowed since 2016; however, it remains challenging to simultaneously achieve both carbon-neutrality and urbanization goals. Future urbanization in China is projected to consume 12.5% of the nation’s total 1.5 °C carbon budget and 37.4% of its average annual budget allocation. Addressing these challenges requires targeted urban interventions, such as aligning low-carbon material production with projected regional demand and strategically planning materials recycling from future building demolitions. Reducing the embodied carbon emissions of building material stock is essential for mitigation. Using a high-resolution multiyear dataset in China, researchers show the historically massive contributions of these emissions during past decades of rapid urbanization and the potential risks for future climate goals.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Fungal parasites infecting N2-fixing cyanobacteria reshape carbon and N2 fixation and trophic transfer</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67818-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67818-x</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 06:24:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Anna Feuring</dc:creator><dc:creator>Connor D. Lawrence</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jessica Salcedo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin J. Whitehouse</dc:creator><dc:creator>Angela Vogts</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luca Zoccarato</dc:creator><dc:creator>Isabell Klawonn</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67818-x</prism:doi><description>Abstract Fungal parasites are associated with bloom-forming algae, yet their impact on N 2 fixation and the fate of newly fixed nitrogen during cyanobacterial blooms is poorly understood. We report infections on the ecologically important N 2 -fixing cyanobacterium Dolichospermum (formerly Anabaena ) in the Baltic Sea. Using single-cell isotope probing, microscopy, and biogeochemical analyses, we examine how infections affect carbon and N 2 fixation and elemental transfer within a natural community. Fungal sporangia infect up to 80% of filaments, mostly targeting storage cells (akinetes, 82% prevalence) and N 2 -fixing cells (heterocytes, 44%), but rarely vegetative cells (5%). Infections at akinete–heterocyte junctions extract 4- and 10-fold more carbon and nitrogen than those on vegetative cells, reducing host storage by 28% and 56%. Overall, 22% of newly fixed nitrogen is transferred to fungi, comparable to heterotrophic bacteria. Infections also occur in Nodularia and Aphanizomenon , suggesting fungi-like parasitism broadly affects bloom dynamics and the fate of new nitrogen.
Published: 2026-01-03T06:24:41+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.486 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Anna Feuring; Connor D. Lawrence; Jessica Salcedo; Martin J. Whitehouse; Angela Vogts; Luca Zoccarato; Isabell Klawonn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67818-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67818-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.486 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Fungal parasites are associated with bloom-forming algae, yet their impact on N 2 fixation and the fate of newly fixed nitrogen during cyanobacterial blooms is poorly understood. We report infections on the ecologically important N 2 -fixing cyanobacterium Dolichospermum (formerly Anabaena ) in the Baltic Sea. Using single-cell isotope probing, microscopy, and biogeochemical analyses, we examine how infections affect carbon and N 2 fixation and elemental transfer within a natural community. Fungal sporangia infect up to 80% of filaments, mostly targeting storage cells (akinetes, 82% prevalence) and N 2 -fixing cells (heterocytes, 44%), but rarely vegetative cells (5%). Infections at akinete–heterocyte junctions extract 4- and 10-fold more carbon and nitrogen than those on vegetative cells, reducing host storage by 28% and 56%. Overall, 22% of newly fixed nitrogen is transferred to fungi, comparable to heterotrophic bacteria. Infections also occur in Nodularia and Aphanizomenon , suggesting fungi-like parasitism broadly affects bloom dynamics and the fate of new nitrogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Self-supervised AI for decoding and designing disordered metamaterials</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx7389</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adx7389</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Min Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sheng Mao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chiara Daraio</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adx7389</prism:doi><description>Disordered microstructures are key to the distinct multifunctional properties of many natural materials. However, understanding the relationship between their microstructures and physical functions remains formidable, hindering engineering applications. Here, we introduce a physics-guided, self-supervised artificial intelligence (AI) framework called generative networks for disordered metamaterials (GNDM), trained on a progressively expanding dataset starting from a few initial samples. We integrate a formula writing module in the training process of neural networks to enforce the identification of the most selective set of hidden geometric invariants that dictate bulk properties. By inversely solving the formulae, GNDM manipulate disordered geometric features to extrapolate property space and design previously unknown structures via its generator module, validated by experiments. GNDM offers an all-in-one AI framework that closes the loop of feature extraction, property prediction, formula writing, and inverse design, unraveling the regulative role of disorder, a critical challenge in the study of metamaterials with complex microstructures.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.485 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Min Shen; Ke Liu; Sheng Mao; Chiara Daraio&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx7389"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adx7389&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.485 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disordered microstructures are key to the distinct multifunctional properties of many natural materials. However, understanding the relationship between their microstructures and physical functions remains formidable, hindering engineering applications. Here, we introduce a physics-guided, self-supervised artificial intelligence (AI) framework called generative networks for disordered metamaterials (GNDM), trained on a progressively expanding dataset starting from a few initial samples. We integrate a formula writing module in the training process of neural networks to enforce the identification of the most selective set of hidden geometric invariants that dictate bulk properties. By inversely solving the formulae, GNDM manipulate disordered geometric features to extrapolate property space and design previously unknown structures via its generator module, validated by experiments. GNDM offers an all-in-one AI framework that closes the loop of feature extraction, property prediction, formula writing, and inverse design, unraveling the regulative role of disorder, a critical challenge in the study of metamaterials with complex microstructures.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Alteration evolution of lightning fossils: Insights from natural fulgurite scars and hydrothermal experiments</title><link>https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2025-9815</link><guid>10.2138/am-2025-9815</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 22:08:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tze Yuan Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Wei Kuo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Matthew A. Pasek</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>American Mineralogist</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.2138/am-2025-9815</prism:doi><description>Abstract Rock fulgurite is a high-temperature, high-pressure metamorphic rock that contains glass and is attributed to transient extreme deformation events caused by lightning strikes. Their glassy nature and susceptibility to weathering on Earth’s surface present significant challenges to their preservation and recognition in the field, and the associated alteration processes are poorly constrained. Based on a well-exposed outcrop containing both ancient and fresh rock fulgurite, this study aims to investigate the evolution of rock fulgurite through alteration, integrating both natural observations and alteration experiments. The latter were conducted on fresh fulgurite with simulated rainwater and deionized water at temperatures ranging from room temperature to 300 °C and durations from 10 min to 117 days. The altered rock was investigated by microanalytical methods, with results showing matrix dissolution, element depletion, and the formation of hydrated minerals within the glassy layers. Chemical analysis of the alteration solutions suggests that the glassy layers will completely dissolve on a thousand-year scale. By integrating experimental results with field observations, this study establishes the evolution of rock fulgurite under geological and temporal constraints and provides insights into the alteration processes of rock fulgurite exposed at the surface. Our findings also offer applications for recognizing rock fulgurite and the relevant remnants and, by extension, other rock-exposed regions with incomplete lightning catalogs.
Published: 2026-01-03T22:08:31+00:00
Venue: American Mineralogist
Score: 0.485 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tze Yuan Chen; Li-Wei Kuo; Matthew A. Pasek&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; American Mineralogist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2025-9815"&gt;10.2138/am-2025-9815&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.485 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Rock fulgurite is a high-temperature, high-pressure metamorphic rock that contains glass and is attributed to transient extreme deformation events caused by lightning strikes. Their glassy nature and susceptibility to weathering on Earth’s surface present significant challenges to their preservation and recognition in the field, and the associated alteration processes are poorly constrained. Based on a well-exposed outcrop containing both ancient and fresh rock fulgurite, this study aims to investigate the evolution of rock fulgurite through alteration, integrating both natural observations and alteration experiments. The latter were conducted on fresh fulgurite with simulated rainwater and deionized water at temperatures ranging from room temperature to 300 °C and durations from 10 min to 117 days. The altered rock was investigated by microanalytical methods, with results showing matrix dissolution, element depletion, and the formation of hydrated minerals within the glassy layers. Chemical analysis of the alteration solutions suggests that the glassy layers will completely dissolve on a thousand-year scale. By integrating experimental results with field observations, this study establishes the evolution of rock fulgurite under geological and temporal constraints and provides insights into the alteration processes of rock fulgurite exposed at the surface. Our findings also offer applications for recognizing rock fulgurite and the relevant remnants and, by extension, other rock-exposed regions with incomplete lightning catalogs.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>In situ mechanostimulation of biohybrid millirobots for enhanced cell functionality and delivery</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx9616</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adx9616</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jianhua Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xianqiang Bao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhou Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rongjing Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunxiang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingtong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kaichen Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yong He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dietmar W. Hutmacher</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ziyu Ren</dc:creator><dc:creator>Metin Sitti</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adx9616</prism:doi><description>This study proposes a perforated, soft millirobot with dual functions: in situ mechanostimulation to enhance cell functionality and local cell delivery. Following protein modification and silica coating, the soft millirobots exhibit excellent biocompatibility, promoting cell adhesion and tissue ingrowth within their perforated architectures under both in vitro and in vivo conditions. They can apply in situ mechanostimulation to various cellular morphologies, including two-dimensional (2D) cell sheets, 3D cell–laden hydrogels, and ex vivo tissue models. The mechanical stimulation improves the functionality of muscle cells by enhancing cellular orientation, myotube contraction, and myocyte differentiation. In parallel, we develop an integrated robotic platform combining magnetic actuation with ultrasound imaging. It demonstrates the proof of principle that delivers 2D cell-sheet and 3D cell–laden biohybrid millirobots to narrow regions in an ex vivo pig liver model. This work expands the potential applications of soft millirobots in mechanobiology studies and future cell-based therapies.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.483 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jianhua Zhang; Xianqiang Bao; Zhou Zhu; Rongjing Zhang; Chunxiang Wang; Mingtong Li; Kaichen Xu; Yong He; Dietmar W. Hutmacher; Ziyu Ren; Metin Sitti&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx9616"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adx9616&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.483 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study proposes a perforated, soft millirobot with dual functions: in situ mechanostimulation to enhance cell functionality and local cell delivery. Following protein modification and silica coating, the soft millirobots exhibit excellent biocompatibility, promoting cell adhesion and tissue ingrowth within their perforated architectures under both in vitro and in vivo conditions. They can apply in situ mechanostimulation to various cellular morphologies, including two-dimensional (2D) cell sheets, 3D cell–laden hydrogels, and ex vivo tissue models. The mechanical stimulation improves the functionality of muscle cells by enhancing cellular orientation, myotube contraction, and myocyte differentiation. In parallel, we develop an integrated robotic platform combining magnetic actuation with ultrasound imaging. It demonstrates the proof of principle that delivers 2D cell-sheet and 3D cell–laden biohybrid millirobots to narrow regions in an ex vivo pig liver model. This work expands the potential applications of soft millirobots in mechanobiology studies and future cell-based therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Decoding anomalous thermal transport in magnetic semiconductors</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adw7332</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adw7332</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 18:59:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bidesh Biswas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sourav Rudra</dc:creator><dc:creator>Taishun Manjo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ashalatha Indiradevi Kamalasanan Pillai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manisha Bansal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marian Brännvall</dc:creator><dc:creator>Davide Gambino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Magnus Garbrecht</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tuhin Subhra Maity</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroshi Fukui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Björn Alling</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bivas Saha</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adw7332</prism:doi><description>Thermal conductivity in semiconductors typically decreases at high temperatures due to enhanced phonon-phonon interactions. In contrast, certain magnetic semiconductors, such as chromium nitride (CrN), exhibit an increased thermal conductivity above its Néel temperature, predicted to be caused by strong spin-phonon coupling. However, this hypothesis lacks experimental verification and detailed understanding. Here, we present conclusive experimental evidence showing that the enhanced thermal conductivity in CrN arises from anomalous temperature-dependent acoustic phonon lifetimes, driven by a dynamic coupling between spin fluctuations and acoustic phonons in the system. Temperature-dependent inelastic x-ray scattering measurements reveal that acoustic phonon lifetimes in CrN are strongly suppressed near Néel temperature but anomalously increase at higher temperatures. In contrast, the optical phonon lifetime decreases with rising temperature, akin to a nonmagnetic semiconductor, as it remains unaffected by spin-phonon coupling. This finding unveils the microscopic origin of anomalous heat transport behavior in magnetostructurally coupled materials, offering a pathway for effective thermal management in magnetic material–based devices.
Published: 2026-01-02T18:59:44+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.480 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bidesh Biswas; Sourav Rudra; Taishun Manjo; Ashalatha Indiradevi Kamalasanan Pillai; Manisha Bansal; Marian Brännvall; Davide Gambino; Magnus Garbrecht; Tuhin Subhra Maity; Hiroshi Fukui; Björn Alling; Bivas Saha&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adw7332"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adw7332&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.480 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thermal conductivity in semiconductors typically decreases at high temperatures due to enhanced phonon-phonon interactions. In contrast, certain magnetic semiconductors, such as chromium nitride (CrN), exhibit an increased thermal conductivity above its Néel temperature, predicted to be caused by strong spin-phonon coupling. However, this hypothesis lacks experimental verification and detailed understanding. Here, we present conclusive experimental evidence showing that the enhanced thermal conductivity in CrN arises from anomalous temperature-dependent acoustic phonon lifetimes, driven by a dynamic coupling between spin fluctuations and acoustic phonons in the system. Temperature-dependent inelastic x-ray scattering measurements reveal that acoustic phonon lifetimes in CrN are strongly suppressed near Néel temperature but anomalously increase at higher temperatures. In contrast, the optical phonon lifetime decreases with rising temperature, akin to a nonmagnetic semiconductor, as it remains unaffected by spin-phonon coupling. This finding unveils the microscopic origin of anomalous heat transport behavior in magnetostructurally coupled materials, offering a pathway for effective thermal management in magnetic material–based devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Possible liquid-nitrogen-temperature superconductivity driven by perpendicular electric field in the single-bilayer film of La3Ni2O7 at ambient pressure</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67880-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67880-5</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 06:20:28 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhi-Yan Shao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia-Heng Ji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Congjun Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dao-Xin Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fan Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67880-5</prism:doi><description>Recently, high-temperature superconductivity (HTSC) is found in the La3Ni2O7/SrLaAlO4 ultrathin film with critical temperature Tc above the McMillan limit at ambient pressure (AP). It is eager to enhance Tc of La3Ni2O7 at AP. We propose that a perpendicular electric field strongly enhances Tc in the single-bilayer film of La3Ni2O7 at AP. Under electric field, the layer with lower potential energy will accept electrons flowing from the other layer to fill in the Ni-$$3{d}_{{x}^{2}-{y}^{2}}$$ orbitals, as the nearly half-filled Ni-$$3{d}_{{z}^{2}}$$ orbital cannot accommodate more electrons. With the enhancement of the filling fraction in the $$3{d}_{{x}^{2}-{y}^{2}}$$ orbitals in this layer, the interlayer s-wave pairing is suppressed, but the intralayer d-wave pairing in this layer is strongly enhanced. We numerically verify this idea and yield that an imposed voltage of about 0.1&amp;nbsp;~&amp;nbsp;0.2 volt between layers is enough to realize liquid-nitrogen-temperature HTSC in this single bilayer at AP. Our results appeal for experimental verification. Recently superconductivity was observed in La3Ni2O7 ultrathin film grown on the SrLaAlO4 substrate with Tc&amp;nbsp;≈&amp;nbsp;40 K at ambient pressure. Here, the authors propose that an imposed strong perpendicular electric field can strongly enhance the Tc in the single-bilayer film of La3Ni2O7 at ambient pressure.
Published: 2026-01-03T06:20:28+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.477 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhi-Yan Shao; Jia-Heng Ji; Congjun Wu; Dao-Xin Yao; Fan Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67880-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67880-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.477 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, high-temperature superconductivity (HTSC) is found in the La3Ni2O7/SrLaAlO4 ultrathin film with critical temperature Tc above the McMillan limit at ambient pressure (AP). It is eager to enhance Tc of La3Ni2O7 at AP. We propose that a perpendicular electric field strongly enhances Tc in the single-bilayer film of La3Ni2O7 at AP. Under electric field, the layer with lower potential energy will accept electrons flowing from the other layer to fill in the Ni-$$3{d}_{{x}^{2}-{y}^{2}}$$ orbitals, as the nearly half-filled Ni-$$3{d}_{{z}^{2}}$$ orbital cannot accommodate more electrons. With the enhancement of the filling fraction in the $$3{d}_{{x}^{2}-{y}^{2}}$$ orbitals in this layer, the interlayer s-wave pairing is suppressed, but the intralayer d-wave pairing in this layer is strongly enhanced. We numerically verify this idea and yield that an imposed voltage of about 0.1&amp;amp;nbsp;~&amp;amp;nbsp;0.2 volt between layers is enough to realize liquid-nitrogen-temperature HTSC in this single bilayer at AP. Our results appeal for experimental verification. Recently superconductivity was observed in La3Ni2O7 ultrathin film grown on the SrLaAlO4 substrate with Tc&amp;amp;nbsp;≈&amp;amp;nbsp;40 K at ambient pressure. Here, the authors propose that an imposed strong perpendicular electric field can strongly enhance the Tc in the single-bilayer film of La3Ni2O7 at ambient pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>