<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:25:40 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Dislocation creep may control bridgmanite deformation in the Earth’s lower mantle</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03212-9</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03212-9</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 08:05:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Longli Guan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daisuke Yamazaki</dc:creator><dc:creator>Noriyoshi Tsujino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuji Higo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sho Kakizawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiang Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junfeng Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03212-9</prism:doi><description>Abstract Seismic anisotropy in the Earth’s lower mantle, particularly around subduction zones, is commonly attributed to deformation by dislocation creep, yet much of the lower mantle appears nearly isotropic. This contrast complicates interpretations of mantle rheology. Here we report the temperature dependence of lattice preferred orientation in bridgmanite, the most abundant lower mantle mineral, through high-pressure deformation experiments at 25 gigapascals and 1700–2100 kelvin. Both iron-free and iron-bearing bridgmanite develop lattice preferred orientations across this temperature range, with distinct slip systems occurring below and above 1800 kelvin. Low-temperature fabric produces strong seismic anisotropy, whereas high-temperature fabric yields weak, near-isotropic signatures under horizontal shearing. These results provide a unified explanation for strong seismic anisotropy near subduction zones and globally near-isotropic behavior of the lower mantle. They suggest that dislocation creep could dominate lower mantle deformation while generating diverse seismic signatures, providing important understanding for lower mantle rheology and dynamics.
Published: 2026-01-26T08:05:45+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.603 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Longli Guan; Daisuke Yamazaki; Noriyoshi Tsujino; Yuji Higo; Sho Kakizawa; Xiang Wu; Junfeng Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03212-9"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03212-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.603 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Seismic anisotropy in the Earth’s lower mantle, particularly around subduction zones, is commonly attributed to deformation by dislocation creep, yet much of the lower mantle appears nearly isotropic. This contrast complicates interpretations of mantle rheology. Here we report the temperature dependence of lattice preferred orientation in bridgmanite, the most abundant lower mantle mineral, through high-pressure deformation experiments at 25 gigapascals and 1700–2100 kelvin. Both iron-free and iron-bearing bridgmanite develop lattice preferred orientations across this temperature range, with distinct slip systems occurring below and above 1800 kelvin. Low-temperature fabric produces strong seismic anisotropy, whereas high-temperature fabric yields weak, near-isotropic signatures under horizontal shearing. These results provide a unified explanation for strong seismic anisotropy near subduction zones and globally near-isotropic behavior of the lower mantle. They suggest that dislocation creep could dominate lower mantle deformation while generating diverse seismic signatures, providing important understanding for lower mantle rheology and dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mo Isotopic Records Imply Persistent Ocean Oxygenation in the Deep Southwest Pacific During the Early Cenozoic Warming Period</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119743</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119743</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:18:47 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiaowen Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaole Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weidong Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuchen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yufei Hao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sifan Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Le Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Huang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119743</prism:doi><description>Abstract During the early Cenozoic greenhouse period, counterintuitive contractions in tropical Pacific oxygen‐deficient zones have been linked to enhanced deep‐ocean ventilation, yet direct geological evidence remains limited. Here we present molybdenum (Mo) isotopic records from International Ocean Discovery Program Site U1509. Raman spectroscopy shows that Mn and Fe occur mainly as MnO 2 and Fe–Mn oxides. The δ 98 / 95 Mo values show a sustained negative shift from ∼1‰ to −2‰ between ∼59.5 and 50.5 Ma, and this trend is best explained by strengthened Mo adsorption onto Mn and Fe bearing oxides at the sediment–water interface. This mechanism provides a direct basis for interpreting the Mo isotope depletion, indicating prolonged bottom‐water oxygenation within early Cenozoic greenhouse conditions. At ∼50.5 Ma, a sharp decline in silicate εNd values and coeval rises in Ti, Zr, and Sc enrichment factors indicate intensified continental weathering that supplied isotopically light Mo. These results provide new constraints on early Cenozoic redox evolution.
Published: 2026-01-25T03:18:47+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.575 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiaowen Liu; Xiaole Sun; Yi Huang; Weidong Sun; Yuchen Li; Yufei Hao; Sifan Wu; Le Li; Jing Huang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119743"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119743&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.575 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract During the early Cenozoic greenhouse period, counterintuitive contractions in tropical Pacific oxygen‐deficient zones have been linked to enhanced deep‐ocean ventilation, yet direct geological evidence remains limited. Here we present molybdenum (Mo) isotopic records from International Ocean Discovery Program Site U1509. Raman spectroscopy shows that Mn and Fe occur mainly as MnO 2 and Fe–Mn oxides. The δ 98 / 95 Mo values show a sustained negative shift from ∼1‰ to −2‰ between ∼59.5 and 50.5 Ma, and this trend is best explained by strengthened Mo adsorption onto Mn and Fe bearing oxides at the sediment–water interface. This mechanism provides a direct basis for interpreting the Mo isotope depletion, indicating prolonged bottom‐water oxygenation within early Cenozoic greenhouse conditions. At ∼50.5 Ma, a sharp decline in silicate εNd values and coeval rises in Ti, Zr, and Sc enrichment factors indicate intensified continental weathering that supplied isotopically light Mo. These results provide new constraints on early Cenozoic redox evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hydrogen generation potential of peridotites and pyroxenites in ophiolitic settings</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123266</link><guid>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123266</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 15:29:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Vivian Azor de Freitas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tiziano Boschetti</dc:creator><dc:creator>Isabelle Moretti</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alessandra Montanini</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Chemical Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123266</prism:doi><description>The partially serpentinized mantle bodies exposed in the western sector of the Northern Apennines, Italy, represent a favorable environment for natural hydrogen (H 2 ) studies, particularly Mt. Prinzera, which hosts a hyperalkaline spring containing dissolved H 2 . A geochemical characterization of peridotite, pyroxenite, and serpentinite samples was carried out to reconstruct the past and present stages of serpentinization and to assess their H 2 generation potential. This study combined mineralogical, whole-rock compositional, and redox-state analyses, along with thermodynamic modeling of spring waters. The major serpentinization event associated with mantle exhumation in the Middle to Late Jurassic was marked by extensive replacement of olivine, clinopyroxene, orthopyroxene by serpentine and subordinate magnetite. Alteration was more intense in olivine than in pyroxenes, resulting in higher serpentinization degrees in peridotites (~ 50 vol%), compared to pyroxenites (~ 10 vol%). Mineralogical evidence suggests temperatures of approximately 220 °C and 300 °C for this stage. Currently, serpentinization and H 2 generation are likely active at Mt. Prinzera, with fluid-rock interactions involving particularly the oxidation of a small fraction of Fe 2+ -serpentine and/or magnetite, rather than the primary mineral assemblage. Thermodynamic equilibria, based on the activities obtained from the aqueous speciation, and the isotope composition of the hyperalkaline water were used to estimate the temperature at depth, which appears to be markedly low. In addition, trapped H₂ accumulations originating from earlier serpentinization stages can also be considered. Thus, serpentinization may occur either at the base of Mt. Prinzera or within a deeper, hidden ultramafic body.
Published: 2026-01-25T15:29:15+00:00
Venue: Chemical Geology
Score: 0.561 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Vivian Azor de Freitas; Tiziano Boschetti; Isabelle Moretti; Alessandra Montanini&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Chemical Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123266"&gt;10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123266&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.561 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The partially serpentinized mantle bodies exposed in the western sector of the Northern Apennines, Italy, represent a favorable environment for natural hydrogen (H 2 ) studies, particularly Mt. Prinzera, which hosts a hyperalkaline spring containing dissolved H 2 . A geochemical characterization of peridotite, pyroxenite, and serpentinite samples was carried out to reconstruct the past and present stages of serpentinization and to assess their H 2 generation potential. This study combined mineralogical, whole-rock compositional, and redox-state analyses, along with thermodynamic modeling of spring waters. The major serpentinization event associated with mantle exhumation in the Middle to Late Jurassic was marked by extensive replacement of olivine, clinopyroxene, orthopyroxene by serpentine and subordinate magnetite. Alteration was more intense in olivine than in pyroxenes, resulting in higher serpentinization degrees in peridotites (~ 50 vol%), compared to pyroxenites (~ 10 vol%). Mineralogical evidence suggests temperatures of approximately 220 °C and 300 °C for this stage. Currently, serpentinization and H 2 generation are likely active at Mt. Prinzera, with fluid-rock interactions involving particularly the oxidation of a small fraction of Fe 2+ -serpentine and/or magnetite, rather than the primary mineral assemblage. Thermodynamic equilibria, based on the activities obtained from the aqueous speciation, and the isotope composition of the hyperalkaline water were used to estimate the temperature at depth, which appears to be markedly low. In addition, trapped H₂ accumulations originating from earlier serpentinization stages can also be considered. Thus, serpentinization may occur either at the base of Mt. Prinzera or within a deeper, hidden ultramafic body.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>3-D velocity model of the crust and uppermost mantle beneath Xinjiang region, constructed by joint tomography of body and surface wave data</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1742-4</link><guid>10.1007/s11430-025-1742-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:01:53 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhiqi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huajian Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jikun Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingshuai Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weitao Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science China Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s11430-025-1742-4</prism:doi><description>The Xinjiang region is situated between the Tethyan and Central Asian orogenic belts. It has undergone multiple episodes of accretionary orogenesis and was tectonically reactivated during the Cenozoic by the far-field compressional effects of the India-Eurasia continental collision. These processes have generated pronounced seismicity and recurrent earthquake-related hazards in this region. A high-resolution three-dimensional velocity model is essential for multi-scale velocity model construction, source-parameter inversion, simulation of strong ground motion, and seismic hazard assessment. In this study, we collected first-arrival body-wave travel-time data recorded by permanent stations in and around Xinjiang and processed both ambient-noise and regional-earthquake surface-wave records. The resulting dataset comprises ∼8.1 million body-wave travel-time picks—including absolute arrival times and event-pair differential times—and ∼5,000 surface-wave dispersion curves (5–50 s period). By joint inversion of these complementary body and surface wave datasets, we determined a high-resolution three-dimensional Vp and Vs model for the crust and uppermost mantle beneath Xinjiang (XJVM-1.0) with a lateral resolution of 50–100 km and a vertical resolution of ∼10 km. XJVM-1.0 reveals that the Tianshan orogen exhibits a relatively rigid upper crust that hosts abundant seismicity under far-field compression, whereas its middle-lower crust accommodates the majority of compressional stress through plastic deformation and/or partial melting. In contrast, the interiors of the Junggar and Tarim basins have experienced negligible internal deformation and are inferred to underthrust beneath the Tianshan orogen in response to the India-Eurasia collision. Relocated seismicity indicates that earthquakes are predominantly concentrated within the Tianshan range, with a notable proportion occurring in the middle-lower crust, implying whole-crust tectonic activity and highlighting the potential for great earthquakes in this region.
Published: 2026-01-26T05:01:53+00:00
Venue: Science China Earth Sciences
Score: 0.546 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhiqi Zhang; Ying Liu; Huajian Yao; Jikun Feng; Mingshuai Tang; Weitao Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science China Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1742-4"&gt;10.1007/s11430-025-1742-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.546 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Xinjiang region is situated between the Tethyan and Central Asian orogenic belts. It has undergone multiple episodes of accretionary orogenesis and was tectonically reactivated during the Cenozoic by the far-field compressional effects of the India-Eurasia continental collision. These processes have generated pronounced seismicity and recurrent earthquake-related hazards in this region. A high-resolution three-dimensional velocity model is essential for multi-scale velocity model construction, source-parameter inversion, simulation of strong ground motion, and seismic hazard assessment. In this study, we collected first-arrival body-wave travel-time data recorded by permanent stations in and around Xinjiang and processed both ambient-noise and regional-earthquake surface-wave records. The resulting dataset comprises ∼8.1 million body-wave travel-time picks—including absolute arrival times and event-pair differential times—and ∼5,000 surface-wave dispersion curves (5–50 s period). By joint inversion of these complementary body and surface wave datasets, we determined a high-resolution three-dimensional Vp and Vs model for the crust and uppermost mantle beneath Xinjiang (XJVM-1.0) with a lateral resolution of 50–100 km and a vertical resolution of ∼10 km. XJVM-1.0 reveals that the Tianshan orogen exhibits a relatively rigid upper crust that hosts abundant seismicity under far-field compression, whereas its middle-lower crust accommodates the majority of compressional stress through plastic deformation and/or partial melting. In contrast, the interiors of the Junggar and Tarim basins have experienced negligible internal deformation and are inferred to underthrust beneath the Tianshan orogen in response to the India-Eurasia collision. Relocated seismicity indicates that earthquakes are predominantly concentrated within the Tianshan range, with a notable proportion occurring in the middle-lower crust, implying whole-crust tectonic activity and highlighting the potential for great earthquakes in this region.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Carbon sequestration for geological negative emissions of the shale gas value chain in China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68829-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68829-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:03:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pu Hong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meiyu Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sai Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenrui Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yumeng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xi Lu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68829-y</prism:doi><description>Carbon sequestration in shale gas operations represents a crucial pathway to achieve Geological Negative Emissions, which is essential for global 1.5 °C targets. However, the emissions reduction potential and economic viability of this approach in China’s shale gas value chain remain unclear. This study quantifies the potential for transforming China’s shale gas value chain from an emission source to a carbon sink, while revealing spatial heterogeneity in economic feasibility. Results demonstrate that synergistic deployment of CO2-based technologies can achieve Geological Negative Emissions across the value chain, with national carbon sink potential reaching 66 billion tonnes of CO2-equivalents and shale gas production increasing by 4,518 billion cubic meters. Multi-scenario economic assessments reveal that marine shale in the Sichuan Basin exhibits inherent profitability, whereas continental reservoirs require carbon credit integration or optimized production. Current Chinese carbon market prices provide insufficient incentives, implementing region-specific subsidies and enhancing carbon pricing frameworks could unlock this potential, thereby contributing to national carbon neutrality goals and multiple Sustainable Development Goals. China’s shale gas value chain can achieve net-negative carbon emissions through geological sequestration, offering a viable pathway for large-scale decarbonization in the energy sector.
Published: 2026-01-26T06:03:16+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.535 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pu Hong; Meiyu Guo; Sai Liang; Wenrui Shi; Yumeng Li; Xi Lu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68829-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68829-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.535 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbon sequestration in shale gas operations represents a crucial pathway to achieve Geological Negative Emissions, which is essential for global 1.5 °C targets. However, the emissions reduction potential and economic viability of this approach in China’s shale gas value chain remain unclear. This study quantifies the potential for transforming China’s shale gas value chain from an emission source to a carbon sink, while revealing spatial heterogeneity in economic feasibility. Results demonstrate that synergistic deployment of CO2-based technologies can achieve Geological Negative Emissions across the value chain, with national carbon sink potential reaching 66 billion tonnes of CO2-equivalents and shale gas production increasing by 4,518 billion cubic meters. Multi-scenario economic assessments reveal that marine shale in the Sichuan Basin exhibits inherent profitability, whereas continental reservoirs require carbon credit integration or optimized production. Current Chinese carbon market prices provide insufficient incentives, implementing region-specific subsidies and enhancing carbon pricing frameworks could unlock this potential, thereby contributing to national carbon neutrality goals and multiple Sustainable Development Goals. China’s shale gas value chain can achieve net-negative carbon emissions through geological sequestration, offering a viable pathway for large-scale decarbonization in the energy sector.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>From subduction initiation to oceanic core complex formation: a tale of two ophiolites in the Kurdistan, NW Iran</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1080/00206814.2025.2612208</link><guid>10.1080/00206814.2025.2612208</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 02:15:22 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bahman Rahimzadeh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fatemeh Sepidbar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Harald Furnes</dc:creator><dc:creator>Richard M. Palin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>International Geology Review</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1080/00206814.2025.2612208</prism:doi><description>The processes of subduction initiation and oceanic core complex (OCC) formation are essential to understanding plate tectonic evolution. The Kermanshah–Walash Ophiolitic Complex (KWOC) in Kurdistan, NW Iran, preserves a unique record of both mechanisms in spatially parallel but temporally distinct Late Cretaceous (Razab) and Eocene (Sarv-Abad) ophiolites. These ophiolites comprise peridotite, gabbroic bodies, a dike complex, and pillowed and massive basaltic lavas. Whole-rock geochemistry, U–Pb zircon geochronology, and field structures reveal distinct ages and tectonic settings for the two ophiolites. While radiolarian cherts constrain the Razab ophiolite to the Cretaceous, new U–Pb zircon (42–38 Ma) geochronology firmly places the formation of the Sarv-Abad oceanic core complex in the Eocene. The Cretaceous Razab unit contains high-Cr# spinel chromitite (0.77–0.82), forearc, and island arc tholeiitic (IAT) lavas, supporting formation during subduction initiation. In contrast, the Eocene Sarv-Abad unit features mylonitized gabbros, syn-extensional dikes, and contemporaneous D-MORB/E-MORB magmatism derived from heterogeneous mantle melting, diagnostic of an Oceanic Core Complex (OCC) in an extensional back-arc. Our results demonstrate that the KWOC was shaped by two distinct geodynamic mechanisms: subduction initiation in the Cretaceous and oceanic core complex formation in the Eocene. Despite ∼50 Myr separation, both units were emplaced during the Miocene closure, suggesting how contrasting mechanisms may have shaped the KWOC. The OCC model also offers a potential resolution to prior ambiguities in the geodynamic evolution of Peri-Arabic ophiolites.
Published: 2026-01-26T02:15:22+00:00
Venue: International Geology Review
Score: 0.523 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bahman Rahimzadeh; Fatemeh Sepidbar; Harald Furnes; Richard M. Palin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; International Geology Review&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00206814.2025.2612208"&gt;10.1080/00206814.2025.2612208&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.523 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processes of subduction initiation and oceanic core complex (OCC) formation are essential to understanding plate tectonic evolution. The Kermanshah–Walash Ophiolitic Complex (KWOC) in Kurdistan, NW Iran, preserves a unique record of both mechanisms in spatially parallel but temporally distinct Late Cretaceous (Razab) and Eocene (Sarv-Abad) ophiolites. These ophiolites comprise peridotite, gabbroic bodies, a dike complex, and pillowed and massive basaltic lavas. Whole-rock geochemistry, U–Pb zircon geochronology, and field structures reveal distinct ages and tectonic settings for the two ophiolites. While radiolarian cherts constrain the Razab ophiolite to the Cretaceous, new U–Pb zircon (42–38 Ma) geochronology firmly places the formation of the Sarv-Abad oceanic core complex in the Eocene. The Cretaceous Razab unit contains high-Cr# spinel chromitite (0.77–0.82), forearc, and island arc tholeiitic (IAT) lavas, supporting formation during subduction initiation. In contrast, the Eocene Sarv-Abad unit features mylonitized gabbros, syn-extensional dikes, and contemporaneous D-MORB/E-MORB magmatism derived from heterogeneous mantle melting, diagnostic of an Oceanic Core Complex (OCC) in an extensional back-arc. Our results demonstrate that the KWOC was shaped by two distinct geodynamic mechanisms: subduction initiation in the Cretaceous and oceanic core complex formation in the Eocene. Despite ∼50 Myr separation, both units were emplaced during the Miocene closure, suggesting how contrasting mechanisms may have shaped the KWOC. The OCC model also offers a potential resolution to prior ambiguities in the geodynamic evolution of Peri-Arabic ophiolites.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magmatic degassing as the primary source of salt in Archean oceans</title><link>https://eartharxiv.org/repository/object/11513/download/20829/</link><guid>oai:EA:id:11513</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:43:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ranta, Eemu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fusswinkel, Tobias</dc:creator><dc:creator>Beier, Christoph</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bali, Eniko</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>EarthArXiv</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.31223/X52472</prism:doi><description>The salinification of Earth’s early oceans impacted both the climate and the evolution of life. However, available halogen data of Archean seawater samples are at apparent odds with a conventionally assumed mantle origin of sea salt, highlighting a critical lack of mechanistic understanding of how the Archean oceans became salty. Here, we present new triple halogen (Cl-Br-I) data from high temperature (~750–840 °C) fluid inclusions from a gabbroic intrusion in Iceland. Our data show that the magmatic degassing fractionates the halogens and generates fluids with high Br/Cl and I/Cl that match with Archean seawater. These observations suggest that seawater salinity in the Archean oceans was primarily regulated via fluids exsolved from cooling intrusions during genesis of early crust, and that the mantle had a modern-like halogen composition by 3.5 Ga. Our findings highlight the strong connection between the chemistry of the mantle, magmatic fluids and the oceans, with implications for understanding the chemical environments that guided the evolution of early marine organisms.
Published: 2026-01-21T16:43:00+00:00
Venue: EarthArXiv
Score: 0.502 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ranta, Eemu; Fusswinkel, Tobias; Beier, Christoph; Bali, Eniko&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; EarthArXiv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.31223/X52472"&gt;10.31223/X52472&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.502 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The salinification of Earth’s early oceans impacted both the climate and the evolution of life. However, available halogen data of Archean seawater samples are at apparent odds with a conventionally assumed mantle origin of sea salt, highlighting a critical lack of mechanistic understanding of how the Archean oceans became salty. Here, we present new triple halogen (Cl-Br-I) data from high temperature (~750–840 °C) fluid inclusions from a gabbroic intrusion in Iceland. Our data show that the magmatic degassing fractionates the halogens and generates fluids with high Br/Cl and I/Cl that match with Archean seawater. These observations suggest that seawater salinity in the Archean oceans was primarily regulated via fluids exsolved from cooling intrusions during genesis of early crust, and that the mantle had a modern-like halogen composition by 3.5 Ga. Our findings highlight the strong connection between the chemistry of the mantle, magmatic fluids and the oceans, with implications for understanding the chemical environments that guided the evolution of early marine organisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Soil carbon debt from land use change in Brazil</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68340-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68340-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 06:03:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>João M. Villela</dc:creator><dc:creator>Júnior M. Damian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel R. P. Gonçalves</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luis G. Barioni</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maurício R. Cherubin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Carlos E. P. Cerri</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68340-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract Carbon farming is a fundamental strategy for mitigating climate change. Brazil, with 276 million hectares of agricultural land, has strong potential to lead this agenda, but uncertainty about soil carbon (C) debt hinders understanding of its true mitigation capacity. Here, we estimate the soil carbon gap, the difference between soil organic carbon (SOC) stocks under native vegetation and agricultural land across Brazil’s six biomes, which represents the theoretical potential for soil recarbonization. A meta-analysis using a comprehensive national SOC database (4,290 records, 0–30 cm) is used to estimate an overall carbon debt of 1.40 ± 0.1 Pg C. The results show that sustainable practices such as crop rotation, intercropping, no-tillage, and integrated agricultural systems enhance SOC recovery. These findings highlight Brazil’s capacity to drive global emissions mitigation, guide low-carbon policies, and position the country as a key actor in the emerging global carbon market.
Published: 2026-01-26T06:03:07+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.484 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; João M. Villela; Júnior M. Damian; Daniel R. P. Gonçalves; Luis G. Barioni; Maurício R. Cherubin; Carlos E. P. Cerri&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68340-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68340-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.484 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Carbon farming is a fundamental strategy for mitigating climate change. Brazil, with 276 million hectares of agricultural land, has strong potential to lead this agenda, but uncertainty about soil carbon (C) debt hinders understanding of its true mitigation capacity. Here, we estimate the soil carbon gap, the difference between soil organic carbon (SOC) stocks under native vegetation and agricultural land across Brazil’s six biomes, which represents the theoretical potential for soil recarbonization. A meta-analysis using a comprehensive national SOC database (4,290 records, 0–30 cm) is used to estimate an overall carbon debt of 1.40 ± 0.1 Pg C. The results show that sustainable practices such as crop rotation, intercropping, no-tillage, and integrated agricultural systems enhance SOC recovery. These findings highlight Brazil’s capacity to drive global emissions mitigation, guide low-carbon policies, and position the country as a key actor in the emerging global carbon market.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Low- and high-temperature evolution of löweite, Na
                    &lt;sub&gt;12&lt;/sub&gt;
                    Mg
                    &lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;
                    (SO
                    &lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;
                    )
                    &lt;sub&gt;13&lt;/sub&gt;
                    ⸱15H
                    &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
                    O</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1180/mgm.2026.10192</link><guid>10.1180/mgm.2026.10192</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:29:56 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>E.V. Nazarchuk</dc:creator><dc:creator>O.I. Siidra</dc:creator><dc:creator>A.S. Baikina</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Mineralogical Magazine</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1180/mgm.2026.10192</prism:doi><description>//static.cambridge.org/content/id/urn%3Acambridge.org%3Aid%3Aarticle%3AS0026461X26101923/resource/name/firstPage-pdf-S0026461X26101923a.jpg
Published: 2026-01-26T07:29:56+00:00
Venue: Mineralogical Magazine
Score: 0.481 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; E.V. Nazarchuk; O.I. Siidra; A.S. Baikina&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Mineralogical Magazine&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1180/mgm.2026.10192"&gt;10.1180/mgm.2026.10192&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.481 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;//static.cambridge.org/content/id/urn%3Acambridge.org%3Aid%3Aarticle%3AS0026461X26101923/resource/name/firstPage-pdf-S0026461X26101923a.jpg&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Connecting the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation to the Southern Ocean Following the Closure of Equatorial Seaways During the Cenozoic</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119115</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119115</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 06:26:20 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Erwan Pineau</dc:creator><dc:creator>Camille Lique</dc:creator><dc:creator>David Ferreira</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thierry Huck</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jean‐Baptiste Ladant</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emma Fabre</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeanne Millot‐Weil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yannick Donnadieu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119115</prism:doi><description>Abstract Global ocean circulation regulates climate and has undergone significant changes over the Cenozoic. Today, the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) is driven by North Atlantic Deep Water (NADW) formation and Southern Ocean upwelling. By contrast, during the middle Eocene to early Oligocene (48–28 Ma), a restricted Drake Passage was limiting the northern Ekman transport, while a circum‐equatorial current sustained by trade winds promoted low‐latitude upwelling. Our set of simulations with the IPSL‐CM5A2 model reveals that this paleogeographic setting favored proto‐NADW upwelling at low latitudes, confining the AMOC to the Northern Hemisphere. Consequently, the role of southern westerly winds was limited, and the northward heat transport was weaker than in the modern ocean.
Published: 2026-01-25T06:26:20+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.478 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Erwan Pineau; Camille Lique; David Ferreira; Thierry Huck; Jean‐Baptiste Ladant; Emma Fabre; Jeanne Millot‐Weil; Yannick Donnadieu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119115"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119115&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.478 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Global ocean circulation regulates climate and has undergone significant changes over the Cenozoic. Today, the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) is driven by North Atlantic Deep Water (NADW) formation and Southern Ocean upwelling. By contrast, during the middle Eocene to early Oligocene (48–28 Ma), a restricted Drake Passage was limiting the northern Ekman transport, while a circum‐equatorial current sustained by trade winds promoted low‐latitude upwelling. Our set of simulations with the IPSL‐CM5A2 model reveals that this paleogeographic setting favored proto‐NADW upwelling at low latitudes, confining the AMOC to the Northern Hemisphere. Consequently, the role of southern westerly winds was limited, and the northward heat transport was weaker than in the modern ocean.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Petrological insights into magma storage and evolution at Rabaul Caldera, Papua New Guinea</title><link>https://eartharxiv.org/repository/object/11516/download/20831/</link><guid>oai:EA:id:11516</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:42:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Höhn, Melina</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hartley. Margaret E.</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dikaung, John</dc:creator><dc:creator>Itikarai, Ima</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mulina, Kila</dc:creator><dc:creator>Saunders, Steve</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sindang, Mikhail</dc:creator><dc:creator>McCormick Kilbride. Brendan T.</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>EarthArXiv</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.31223/X55T9N</prism:doi><description>Rabaul is a caldera volcano in Papua New Guinea. Its most recent caldera-forming eruption occurred ~1400 years ago, with numerous intra-caldera eruptions since. Erupted whole rock compositions are commonly attributed to fractional crystallisation along a single liquid line of descent, but mafic mineral clots indicate mafic recharge and magma mixing also influence whole rock compositions. Geophysical studies identified two low-velocity zones at ~0.5–4 km and 9–15 km beneath the caldera, suggesting a shallow reservoir for evolved magmas and a deeper mafic storage zone. However, uncertainties remain regarding depths, connectivity and temporal evolution of Rabaul’s magma storage zones. We present petrological and thermobarometric analyses of products from the 1937, 1994 and 2014 eruptions at Rabaul. Samples contain two distinct mineral clot types. Mafic mineral clots comprise olivine, high-anorthite plagioclase and high-Mg# clinopyroxene that are out of equilibrium with surrounding matrix glass. Textures include rapid growth rims, olivine replacement by orthopyroxene and reversely zoned clinopyroxene. We interpret these mafic mineral clots as cumulate fragments mobilised from a deep mafic mush by mafic recharge. Intermediate mineral clots contain low-anorthite plagioclase, low-Mg# clinopyroxene, orthopyroxene and Ti-magnetite, and occur as macrocrysts in equilibrium with matrix glasses (Mg# 30–40). We interpret these intermediate mineral clots as fragments from a shallower, more evolved mush stored. Binary mixing models demonstrate that eruption products can be reproduced by mixing a mafic magma similar to 1937 basaltic enclaves with a dacitic magma resembling the last caldera-forming deposit. Clinopyroxene-only and clinopyroxene–liquid thermobarometry yield crystallisation pressures of 0.5–5 kbar (~2–20 km) and temperatures of 960–1125 °C, but the models lack the vertical resolution to resolve storage zones separated by ~5 km. Combining geophysical, geochemical and thermobarometric data we propose a refined model of magma storage beneath Rabaul, in which magmas are stored in a complex, vertically extensive magma plumbing system with a heterogeneous but interconnected mush reservoir.
Published: 2026-01-21T16:42:00+00:00
Venue: EarthArXiv
Score: 0.472 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Höhn, Melina; Hartley. Margaret E.; Dikaung, John; Itikarai, Ima; Mulina, Kila; Saunders, Steve; Sindang, Mikhail; McCormick Kilbride. Brendan T.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; EarthArXiv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.31223/X55T9N"&gt;10.31223/X55T9N&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.472 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rabaul is a caldera volcano in Papua New Guinea. Its most recent caldera-forming eruption occurred ~1400 years ago, with numerous intra-caldera eruptions since. Erupted whole rock compositions are commonly attributed to fractional crystallisation along a single liquid line of descent, but mafic mineral clots indicate mafic recharge and magma mixing also influence whole rock compositions. Geophysical studies identified two low-velocity zones at ~0.5–4 km and 9–15 km beneath the caldera, suggesting a shallow reservoir for evolved magmas and a deeper mafic storage zone. However, uncertainties remain regarding depths, connectivity and temporal evolution of Rabaul’s magma storage zones. We present petrological and thermobarometric analyses of products from the 1937, 1994 and 2014 eruptions at Rabaul. Samples contain two distinct mineral clot types. Mafic mineral clots comprise olivine, high-anorthite plagioclase and high-Mg# clinopyroxene that are out of equilibrium with surrounding matrix glass. Textures include rapid growth rims, olivine replacement by orthopyroxene and reversely zoned clinopyroxene. We interpret these mafic mineral clots as cumulate fragments mobilised from a deep mafic mush by mafic recharge. Intermediate mineral clots contain low-anorthite plagioclase, low-Mg# clinopyroxene, orthopyroxene and Ti-magnetite, and occur as macrocrysts in equilibrium with matrix glasses (Mg# 30–40). We interpret these intermediate mineral clots as fragments from a shallower, more evolved mush stored. Binary mixing models demonstrate that eruption products can be reproduced by mixing a mafic magma similar to 1937 basaltic enclaves with a dacitic magma resembling the last caldera-forming deposit. Clinopyroxene-only and clinopyroxene–liquid thermobarometry yield crystallisation pressures of 0.5–5 kbar (~2–20 km) and temperatures of 960–1125 °C, but the models lack the vertical resolution to resolve storage zones separated by ~5 km. Combining geophysical, geochemical and thermobarometric data we propose a refined model of magma storage beneath Rabaul, in which magmas are stored in a complex, vertically extensive magma plumbing system with a heterogeneous but interconnected mush reservoir.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A highly dynamic mononuclear non-heme iron enzyme for the two-step isonitrile biosynthesis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68588-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68588-w</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 07:55:37 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Naike Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Antonio Del Rio Flores</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenjun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Catherine L. Drennan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68588-w</prism:doi><description>Abstract The recent discovery of the isonitrile biosynthetic enzyme ScoE expanded the catalytic repertoire of the Fe(II)/αKG-dependent dioxygenase enzyme family. ScoE synthesizes an isonitrile functional group from a glycyl-fatty acid adduct, with both the isonitrile nitrogen and carbon atoms coming from the glycyl moiety. This challenging chemistry cannot be performed in a single step. Instead, the mechanism appears to require two half reactions, each involving αKG cleavage to generate a highly reactive iron-oxygen species. Here, we report sixteen crystal structures that provide snapshots along the reaction trajectory of Rv0097, a ScoE homolog from Mycobacterium tuberculosis . These structures, which are both of wild-type and Rv0097 variants, include a substrate 3-((carboxymethyl)amino)decanoic acid (CADA)-bound structure, an αKG-bound structure, and a structure with both CADA and αKG bound. These structural data reveal how Rv0097 employs conformational rearrangements to protect the unstable CADA-reaction intermediate that is formed in the first half reaction while swapping out αKG cleavage products for a second molecule of αKG. Additionally, these structures, together with data from site-directed mutagenesis, provide insight into Rv0097’s preference for substrates with long alkyl chains, potentially facilitating efforts to re-engineer ScoE/Rv0097 to synthesize isonitrile functional groups on a wider range of small molecules.
Published: 2026-01-26T07:55:37+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.458 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Naike Ye; Antonio Del Rio Flores; Wenjun Zhang; Catherine L. Drennan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68588-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68588-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.458 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The recent discovery of the isonitrile biosynthetic enzyme ScoE expanded the catalytic repertoire of the Fe(II)/αKG-dependent dioxygenase enzyme family. ScoE synthesizes an isonitrile functional group from a glycyl-fatty acid adduct, with both the isonitrile nitrogen and carbon atoms coming from the glycyl moiety. This challenging chemistry cannot be performed in a single step. Instead, the mechanism appears to require two half reactions, each involving αKG cleavage to generate a highly reactive iron-oxygen species. Here, we report sixteen crystal structures that provide snapshots along the reaction trajectory of Rv0097, a ScoE homolog from Mycobacterium tuberculosis . These structures, which are both of wild-type and Rv0097 variants, include a substrate 3-((carboxymethyl)amino)decanoic acid (CADA)-bound structure, an αKG-bound structure, and a structure with both CADA and αKG bound. These structural data reveal how Rv0097 employs conformational rearrangements to protect the unstable CADA-reaction intermediate that is formed in the first half reaction while swapping out αKG cleavage products for a second molecule of αKG. Additionally, these structures, together with data from site-directed mutagenesis, provide insight into Rv0097’s preference for substrates with long alkyl chains, potentially facilitating efforts to re-engineer ScoE/Rv0097 to synthesize isonitrile functional groups on a wider range of small molecules.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Audio long read: ‘I rarely get outside’ — scientists ditch fieldwork in the age of AI</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00255-y</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-026-00255-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:42:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Aisling Irwin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Benjamin Thompson</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-026-00255-y</prism:doi><description>In the wake of new computer-based methods, some ecologists fear their field is losing touch with nature. Listen to an audio version of a recent Nature Feature.
Published: 2026-01-26T16:42:50+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.455 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Aisling Irwin; Benjamin Thompson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00255-y"&gt;10.1038/d41586-026-00255-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.455 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the wake of new computer-based methods, some ecologists fear their field is losing touch with nature. Listen to an audio version of a recent Nature Feature.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Frozen Ground Induces Seawater Retreat in Coastal Unconfined Aquifers</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117947</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl117947</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 05:41:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiayang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yue Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Pu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junjie Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pei Xin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl117947</prism:doi><description>Abstract While seawater intrusion (SWI) in coastal aquifers has been extensively investigated, most studies focused on unfrozen conditions. In many cold regions, frozen ground is common, yet its impact on SWI remains poorly understood. Here, we demonstrate that the formation of frozen ground alters salinity distribution in coastal unconfined aquifers, based on laboratory experiments and numerical simulations. Under steady‐state conditions with subzero ground temperature, frozen ground creates a confined flow path between itself and the saltwater wedge. This configuration accelerates terrestrial groundwater flow and induces a pronounced seaward retreat of the saltwater wedge. Moreover, lower ground surface and groundwater temperatures enhance this effect by promoting frozen ground formation. These findings have important implications for understanding salinity dynamics in coastal cold‐region aquifers with varying frozen ground.
Published: 2026-01-25T05:41:14+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.451 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiayang Yu; Yue Li; Li Pu; Junjie Wu; Pei Xin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117947"&gt;10.1029/2025gl117947&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.451 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract While seawater intrusion (SWI) in coastal aquifers has been extensively investigated, most studies focused on unfrozen conditions. In many cold regions, frozen ground is common, yet its impact on SWI remains poorly understood. Here, we demonstrate that the formation of frozen ground alters salinity distribution in coastal unconfined aquifers, based on laboratory experiments and numerical simulations. Under steady‐state conditions with subzero ground temperature, frozen ground creates a confined flow path between itself and the saltwater wedge. This configuration accelerates terrestrial groundwater flow and induces a pronounced seaward retreat of the saltwater wedge. Moreover, lower ground surface and groundwater temperatures enhance this effect by promoting frozen ground formation. These findings have important implications for understanding salinity dynamics in coastal cold‐region aquifers with varying frozen ground.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Flow‐Dependent Inertial Permeability Defines Crossover Between Darcy and Forchheimer Flow Regimes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120616</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl120616</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 02:54:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kuldeep Singh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Negin Sharifabad</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl120616</prism:doi><description>Abstract We present mechanistic evidence that the Forchheimer inertial permeability coefficient () is flow‐dependent in the weak‐to‐intermediate inertia crossover regime, governed by pore‐scale eddy growth‐to‐confinement dynamics. In contrast to classical theory, attains steady‐state () asymptotically in the dominant inertial regime, marking the validity of Forchheimer law. This highlights a hydrodynamic gap between Darcy and Forchheimer regimes, which is addressed using a physics‐based Eddy‐Growth Dynamics–Inertial Permeability (EG‐DIP) model. The EG‐DIP model contributes to ongoing discussions on inertial permeability by providing a framework to determine , integrate it into Forchheimer law, and suggest a physical basis for estimating . This supports predictive modeling of flow across regimes and identifies as the characteristic medium‐specific property for reliable correlation with porosity, permeability, and grain size. By unifying inertial flow theory through eddy growth dynamics, the EG‐DIP model has direct implications for injection‐induced seismicity, CO 2 storage security, and geothermal energy recovery.
Published: 2026-01-25T02:54:45+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.445 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kuldeep Singh; Negin Sharifabad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120616"&gt;10.1029/2025gl120616&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.445 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract We present mechanistic evidence that the Forchheimer inertial permeability coefficient () is flow‐dependent in the weak‐to‐intermediate inertia crossover regime, governed by pore‐scale eddy growth‐to‐confinement dynamics. In contrast to classical theory, attains steady‐state () asymptotically in the dominant inertial regime, marking the validity of Forchheimer law. This highlights a hydrodynamic gap between Darcy and Forchheimer regimes, which is addressed using a physics‐based Eddy‐Growth Dynamics–Inertial Permeability (EG‐DIP) model. The EG‐DIP model contributes to ongoing discussions on inertial permeability by providing a framework to determine , integrate it into Forchheimer law, and suggest a physical basis for estimating . This supports predictive modeling of flow across regimes and identifies as the characteristic medium‐specific property for reliable correlation with porosity, permeability, and grain size. By unifying inertial flow theory through eddy growth dynamics, the EG‐DIP model has direct implications for injection‐induced seismicity, CO 2 storage security, and geothermal energy recovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Microanalysis of Hornblende for Fluorine and Chlorine: Impact of Analytical Parameters on Accuracy and Detection Limits</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1111/ggr.70036</link><guid>10.1111/ggr.70036</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 05:48:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Juan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yonghong Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunlei Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoxin Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zihan Yi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geostandards and Geoanalytical Research</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1111/ggr.70036</prism:doi><description>The F and Cl contents in hornblende are critical for geological studies, but their accurate determination by electron probe microanalysis (EPMA) faces technical challenges. Existing “dual current” methods for major and trace elements are limited by instrumentation and data volume, and cannot meet large‐scale analytical needs. This study systematically evaluates EPMA parameters to establish general conditions for “single current” in situ determination of major elements, F and Cl in hornblende. Results show optimal F counting stability on TAP/LDE1 crystals at 0–5 μm beam sizes. Long dwell times with high currents reduce DLs to 11 μg g ‐1 (F) and 2 μg g ‐1 (Cl), with BG ± 10 mm yielding lower DLs than ±5 mm. However, currents beyond 100 nA cause loss of major components (notably SiO 2 ), so moderate currents are safer. For hornblende F determination, accuracy prioritises PHA setting &gt; BG correction &gt; probe current &gt; counting time &gt; reference material selection &gt; beam size, whereas Cl is less parameter‐sensitive. A general parameter set for simultaneous in situ major element, F and Cl determination in hornblende is established, with results consistent with literature values for the Kakanui and Arenal hornblende reference materials. This method can be applied to research on magmatic‐hydrothermal evolution, metamorphism and subduction‐zone cycling.
Published: 2026-01-26T05:48:49+00:00
Venue: Geostandards and Geoanalytical Research
Score: 0.442 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Juan Wang; Yonghong Shi; Chunlei Peng; Guoxin Tang; Zihan Yi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geostandards and Geoanalytical Research&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/ggr.70036"&gt;10.1111/ggr.70036&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.442 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The F and Cl contents in hornblende are critical for geological studies, but their accurate determination by electron probe microanalysis (EPMA) faces technical challenges. Existing “dual current” methods for major and trace elements are limited by instrumentation and data volume, and cannot meet large‐scale analytical needs. This study systematically evaluates EPMA parameters to establish general conditions for “single current” in situ determination of major elements, F and Cl in hornblende. Results show optimal F counting stability on TAP/LDE1 crystals at 0–5 μm beam sizes. Long dwell times with high currents reduce DLs to 11 μg g ‐1 (F) and 2 μg g ‐1 (Cl), with BG ± 10 mm yielding lower DLs than ±5 mm. However, currents beyond 100 nA cause loss of major components (notably SiO 2 ), so moderate currents are safer. For hornblende F determination, accuracy prioritises PHA setting &amp;gt; BG correction &amp;gt; probe current &amp;gt; counting time &amp;gt; reference material selection &amp;gt; beam size, whereas Cl is less parameter‐sensitive. A general parameter set for simultaneous in situ major element, F and Cl determination in hornblende is established, with results consistent with literature values for the Kakanui and Arenal hornblende reference materials. This method can be applied to research on magmatic‐hydrothermal evolution, metamorphism and subduction‐zone cycling.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Subsurface mass monitoring at Theistareykir geothermal field, Iceland, using hybrid gravimetry</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvolgeores.2026.108539</link><guid>10.1016/j.jvolgeores.2026.108539</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 15:31:54 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>B. Giuliante</dc:creator><dc:creator>U. Riccardi</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. Hinderer</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. Jousset</dc:creator><dc:creator>T. Pivetta</dc:creator><dc:creator>A.K. Mortensen</dc:creator><dc:creator>J.D. Bernard</dc:creator><dc:creator>S. Schröder</dc:creator><dc:creator>C.M. Krawczyk</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.jvolgeores.2026.108539</prism:doi><description>Understanding underground mass redistribution in geothermal fields is fundamental to assess the harnessing in geothermal reservoir. Here we apply the hybrid gravimetry method at Theistareykir geothermal field (Northern Iceland). We collected absolute and discrete microgravity measurements yearly within the geothermal field at fixed locations jointly with continuously recorded gravity time series with two superconducting gravimeters (SGs). Data acquisition started in 2017 at the onset of the anthropogenic perturbation. We present and interpret the discrete and continuous gravity datasets from 2017 until 2024 in an attempt to characterize fluid redistribution within the subsurface. The hybrid gravimetry dataset reveal a gravity decrease nearby the extraction area with rates of about −20 μGal per year for the 2017–2022 period, that reduces to few μGal per year in the last two years (2023–2024). An increase in gravity is observed towards the injection area (around 5 to 10 μGal per year). Time-lapse gravity maps reveal a localized gravity decrease (with a maximum of −60 μGal), not collocated with the zone of largest extraction and furthermore an additional trendline of gravity increase (+15 μGal) is observed towards the North. The first suggests a possible lower permeability subsurface zone within the geothermal field, the latter, is in accordance with the direction of the fault system that crosses Theistareykir field, suggesting potential underground fluid pathways. From 2023, although extraction and injection rates did not change, we evidence a change in the gravity trends outside the western part of the geothermal field possibly associated with the 2023 magmatic intrusion.
Published: 2026-01-25T15:31:54+00:00
Venue: Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research
Score: 0.423 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; B. Giuliante; U. Riccardi; J. Hinderer; P. Jousset; T. Pivetta; A.K. Mortensen; J.D. Bernard; S. Schröder; C.M. Krawczyk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jvolgeores.2026.108539"&gt;10.1016/j.jvolgeores.2026.108539&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.423 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding underground mass redistribution in geothermal fields is fundamental to assess the harnessing in geothermal reservoir. Here we apply the hybrid gravimetry method at Theistareykir geothermal field (Northern Iceland). We collected absolute and discrete microgravity measurements yearly within the geothermal field at fixed locations jointly with continuously recorded gravity time series with two superconducting gravimeters (SGs). Data acquisition started in 2017 at the onset of the anthropogenic perturbation. We present and interpret the discrete and continuous gravity datasets from 2017 until 2024 in an attempt to characterize fluid redistribution within the subsurface. The hybrid gravimetry dataset reveal a gravity decrease nearby the extraction area with rates of about −20 μGal per year for the 2017–2022 period, that reduces to few μGal per year in the last two years (2023–2024). An increase in gravity is observed towards the injection area (around 5 to 10 μGal per year). Time-lapse gravity maps reveal a localized gravity decrease (with a maximum of −60 μGal), not collocated with the zone of largest extraction and furthermore an additional trendline of gravity increase (+15 μGal) is observed towards the North. The first suggests a possible lower permeability subsurface zone within the geothermal field, the latter, is in accordance with the direction of the fault system that crosses Theistareykir field, suggesting potential underground fluid pathways. From 2023, although extraction and injection rates did not change, we evidence a change in the gravity trends outside the western part of the geothermal field possibly associated with the 2023 magmatic intrusion.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Zonal Wave‐3 Mode Impacts Antarctic Dense Water Formation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119079</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119079</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:11:11 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>M. Auger</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. Spence</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. K. Morrison</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119079</prism:doi><description>Abstract At the Antarctic margins, dense water masses form as sea ice develops, driving the Antarctic branch of the global meridional overturning circulation. Previous studies found that large‐scale climate modes such as the Southern Annular Mode and El Niño Southern do not fully account for the interannual variability of dense water formation. Here, we investigate the influence of the overlooked Zonal Wave‐3 (ZW3) mode, characterized by three alternating cyclone–anticyclone pairs in the Southern Hemisphere mid‐latitudes. Simulations with ZW3 perturbations of different phases show multi‐year impacts on dense water formation and export. The PC1 phase exerts the strongest influence in the Ross Sea, while the PC2 phase can nearly shut down or double dense water formation in the Weddell Sea. A simulation with interannually varying atmospheric forcing confirms ZW3 correlates with dense water formation in both regions. Our results highlight that ZW3 is a key driver of Antarctic dense water dynamics.
Published: 2026-01-25T07:11:11+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.422 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; M. Auger; P. Spence; A. K. Morrison&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119079"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119079&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.422 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract At the Antarctic margins, dense water masses form as sea ice develops, driving the Antarctic branch of the global meridional overturning circulation. Previous studies found that large‐scale climate modes such as the Southern Annular Mode and El Niño Southern do not fully account for the interannual variability of dense water formation. Here, we investigate the influence of the overlooked Zonal Wave‐3 (ZW3) mode, characterized by three alternating cyclone–anticyclone pairs in the Southern Hemisphere mid‐latitudes. Simulations with ZW3 perturbations of different phases show multi‐year impacts on dense water formation and export. The PC1 phase exerts the strongest influence in the Ross Sea, while the PC2 phase can nearly shut down or double dense water formation in the Weddell Sea. A simulation with interannually varying atmospheric forcing confirms ZW3 correlates with dense water formation in both regions. Our results highlight that ZW3 is a key driver of Antarctic dense water dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Origin of small chromosome A08 and genome evolution of Arachis species</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68884-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68884-5</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 04:45:53 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pei Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liuyang Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoquan Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suoyi Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaobo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ziqi Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiyuan Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuemin Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hua Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenyu Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lijuan Miao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Qin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhongxin Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenzhao Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zengjun Qi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyou Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68884-5</prism:doi><description>Wild Arachis species exhibit abundant genetic diversity for peanut improvement. However, the evolutionary history of their genomes is unclear. Here, through comparative oligopainting, we establish a one-to-one correspondence between microscopically observed chromosomes and sequenced pseudomolecules of Arachis duranensis, A. ipaensis, and cultivated peanut, and determine the 10 homoeologous groups (Hgs) of the A, B, F, K, and H genomes. Analysis of the telomere-to-telomere (T2T) genome assembly of A. hoehnei reveals that its genome is a diverging form of the A genome and is designated as genome A’. In addition, the unique small chromosome A08 is originated from two inversions and a substantial contraction of A
Published: 2026-01-26T04:45:53+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.422 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pei Du; Liuyang Fu; Guoquan Chen; Qian Wang; Suoyi Han; Xiaobo Wang; Ziqi Sun; Zhiyuan Zhou; Xuemin Xu; Hua Liu; Chenyu Li; Lijuan Miao; Li Qin; Jing Xu; Zhongxin Zhang; Zheng Zheng; Wenzhao Dong; Zengjun Qi; Xinyou Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68884-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68884-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.422 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wild Arachis species exhibit abundant genetic diversity for peanut improvement. However, the evolutionary history of their genomes is unclear. Here, through comparative oligopainting, we establish a one-to-one correspondence between microscopically observed chromosomes and sequenced pseudomolecules of Arachis duranensis, A. ipaensis, and cultivated peanut, and determine the 10 homoeologous groups (Hgs) of the A, B, F, K, and H genomes. Analysis of the telomere-to-telomere (T2T) genome assembly of A. hoehnei reveals that its genome is a diverging form of the A genome and is designated as genome A’. In addition, the unique small chromosome A08 is originated from two inversions and a substantial contraction of A&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Recent giant detachment of a glacier on the Tibetan plateau provoked by its frozen tongue</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03125-z</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03125-z</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 16:39:51 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Andreas Kääb</dc:creator><dc:creator>Juditha Aga</dc:creator><dc:creator>Désirée Treichler</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luc Girod</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei-An Chao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03125-z</prism:doi><description>Abstract Sudden detachments of entire glacier tongues are rare but potentially devastating events that remain poorly understood. Here, we report on an event that occurred in Tibet on November 1, 2022, with an ice volume of ~40 million cubic meters, ranking it among the largest recorded ice avalanches. Utilizing a broad array of satellite data and seismic signals, we reconstruct the motion of the source glacier leading to its failure and the large landscape changes caused by the avalanche. The lack of glacier advance during its acceleration phase suggests that a frozen terminus has played a key role in the evolution of the glacier failure by acting as a dam to the ice mass pushing from above and its potential water content. The dense coverage by satellite data reveals details of an exponential increase in glacier speeds, up to 46 m per day in the weeks and days prior to failure.
Published: 2026-01-26T16:39:51+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.420 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Andreas Kääb; Juditha Aga; Désirée Treichler; Luc Girod; Wei-An Chao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03125-z"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03125-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.420 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Sudden detachments of entire glacier tongues are rare but potentially devastating events that remain poorly understood. Here, we report on an event that occurred in Tibet on November 1, 2022, with an ice volume of ~40 million cubic meters, ranking it among the largest recorded ice avalanches. Utilizing a broad array of satellite data and seismic signals, we reconstruct the motion of the source glacier leading to its failure and the large landscape changes caused by the avalanche. The lack of glacier advance during its acceleration phase suggests that a frozen terminus has played a key role in the evolution of the glacier failure by acting as a dam to the ice mass pushing from above and its potential water content. The dense coverage by satellite data reveals details of an exponential increase in glacier speeds, up to 46 m per day in the weeks and days prior to failure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Estimation of Near-Surface Density using Vertical Gravity Gradients in Central and Western Japan</title><link>https://eartharxiv.org/repository/object/11530/download/20853/</link><guid>oai:EA:id:11530</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 21:25:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Nishiyama, Ryuichi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>EarthArXiv</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.31223/X5DF2C</prism:doi><description>The Vertical Gravity Gradient (VGG), derived from the difference between terrestrial and airborne gravity data, highlights shallow density contrasts. We estimated the near-surface density structure of Central and Western Japan using VGGs derived from terrestrial data within 3 km of airborne flight lines. We constructed an inversion model on a 1/7-degree grid to estimate surface density and a regional VGG trend, imposing spatial continuity con-straints on the trend. Hyperparameters were determined by minimizing the Akaike Bayesian Information Criterion (ABIC). The resulting model clearly identifies low-density zones in major plains, such as Kanto and Echigo, and distinct low-VGG anomalies along the Itoigawa-Shizuoka Tectonic Line (western margin of the Fossa Magna) and the Osaka-Lake Biwa region. The estimated surface density showed a weak correlation with seismic S-wave velocity models.
Published: 2026-01-22T21:25:00+00:00
Venue: EarthArXiv
Score: 0.419 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Nishiyama, Ryuichi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; EarthArXiv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.31223/X5DF2C"&gt;10.31223/X5DF2C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.419 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Vertical Gravity Gradient (VGG), derived from the difference between terrestrial and airborne gravity data, highlights shallow density contrasts. We estimated the near-surface density structure of Central and Western Japan using VGGs derived from terrestrial data within 3 km of airborne flight lines. We constructed an inversion model on a 1/7-degree grid to estimate surface density and a regional VGG trend, imposing spatial continuity con-straints on the trend. Hyperparameters were determined by minimizing the Akaike Bayesian Information Criterion (ABIC). The resulting model clearly identifies low-density zones in major plains, such as Kanto and Echigo, and distinct low-VGG anomalies along the Itoigawa-Shizuoka Tectonic Line (western margin of the Fossa Magna) and the Osaka-Lake Biwa region. The estimated surface density showed a weak correlation with seismic S-wave velocity models.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Intensified Western Boundary Currents in South China Sea Under Global Warming</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022920</link><guid>10.1029/2025jc022920</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:04:22 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>RunChen Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinzhuo Cai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haiyuan Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bolan Gan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingjie Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xingzhi Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jc022920</prism:doi><description>Abstract The upper‐layer western boundary currents (WBCs) in the South China Sea (SCS) play a crucial role in regulating ocean dynamics, marine ecosystems, and regional climate. However, due to limited observations and coarse model resolution, changes in these currents on centennial timescales remain unclear. This study investigates trends in upper‐layer circulation in the SCS from 1951 to 2050 using outputs from an ensemble of 16 high‐resolution climate model members. Under global warming, the WBCs exhibit strengthening in both winter and summer, with a 7.7% increase (0.60 ± 0.47 Sv) in the winter Vietnam Coastal Current (VCC) and an 8.5% increase (1.10 ± 0.55 Sv) in the summer Vietnam Offshore Current (VOC) over the study period. Further analysis using a 1.5‐layer reduced‐gravity model suggests that enhanced stratification drives the intensification of the VCC in winter while the strengthening of the VOC in summer is primarily modulated by increased stratification and partially influenced by the intensified local wind stress curl. The results of this study may serve as a foundation for further research on the ecological effects caused by enhanced WBCs of the SCS.
Published: 2026-01-25T07:04:22+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans
Score: 0.406 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; RunChen Zeng; Jinzhuo Cai; Haiyuan Yang; Bolan Gan; Jingjie Yu; Xingzhi Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022920"&gt;10.1029/2025jc022920&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.406 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The upper‐layer western boundary currents (WBCs) in the South China Sea (SCS) play a crucial role in regulating ocean dynamics, marine ecosystems, and regional climate. However, due to limited observations and coarse model resolution, changes in these currents on centennial timescales remain unclear. This study investigates trends in upper‐layer circulation in the SCS from 1951 to 2050 using outputs from an ensemble of 16 high‐resolution climate model members. Under global warming, the WBCs exhibit strengthening in both winter and summer, with a 7.7% increase (0.60 ± 0.47 Sv) in the winter Vietnam Coastal Current (VCC) and an 8.5% increase (1.10 ± 0.55 Sv) in the summer Vietnam Offshore Current (VOC) over the study period. Further analysis using a 1.5‐layer reduced‐gravity model suggests that enhanced stratification drives the intensification of the VCC in winter while the strengthening of the VOC in summer is primarily modulated by increased stratification and partially influenced by the intensified local wind stress curl. The results of this study may serve as a foundation for further research on the ecological effects caused by enhanced WBCs of the SCS.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Direct Observational Evidence of the Mesoscale Gravity Wave Modulations on Low‐Latitude Sporadic E Layer</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl121033</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl121033</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:50:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Junyi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinan Yue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xu Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yihui Cai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jorge L. Chau</dc:creator><dc:creator>David C. Fritts</dc:creator><dc:creator>Juha Vierinen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alan Z. Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Baiqi Ning</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl121033</prism:doi><description>Abstract Sporadic E (Es) layer plays essential role in ionosphere‐atmosphere coupling. Theoretical simulations show that the atmospheric gravity waves (GWs) in the lower thermosphere are the main modulatory source on Es dynamics at small spatial scales and short periods. Based on Sanya Incoherent Scatter Radar, direct observational evidence for the mesoscale GW modulations on low‐latitude Es layer is firstly obtained by four‐dimensional electron density with extreme fine resolutions of 37.5 m in range and 50 s in time. The wave‐like horizontal structures, with ∼10 min period and ∼55 km wavelength, indicate the typical features of mesoscale GWs. Our results confirm that, interacting with the background tidal winds, the upward propagating GWs modulate the horizontal structures and drift velocity of Es layers at different altitudes with increasing amplitude to cause the rapid oscillations in range.
Published: 2026-01-25T03:50:52+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.403 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Junyi Wang; Xinan Yue; Xu Zhou; Yihui Cai; Feng Ding; Jorge L. Chau; David C. Fritts; Juha Vierinen; Alan Z. Liu; Baiqi Ning&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl121033"&gt;10.1029/2025gl121033&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.403 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Sporadic E (Es) layer plays essential role in ionosphere‐atmosphere coupling. Theoretical simulations show that the atmospheric gravity waves (GWs) in the lower thermosphere are the main modulatory source on Es dynamics at small spatial scales and short periods. Based on Sanya Incoherent Scatter Radar, direct observational evidence for the mesoscale GW modulations on low‐latitude Es layer is firstly obtained by four‐dimensional electron density with extreme fine resolutions of 37.5 m in range and 50 s in time. The wave‐like horizontal structures, with ∼10 min period and ∼55 km wavelength, indicate the typical features of mesoscale GWs. Our results confirm that, interacting with the background tidal winds, the upward propagating GWs modulate the horizontal structures and drift velocity of Es layers at different altitudes with increasing amplitude to cause the rapid oscillations in range.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Origin of Intense Plasma Depletions After Midnight Over the Korean Peninsula During the Geomagnetic Storm on 11 May 2024</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119954</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119954</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:20:28 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hyosub Kil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Se‐Heon Jeong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Woo Kyoung Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junseok Hong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Septi Perwitasari</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michi Nishioka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Prayitno Abadi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119954</prism:doi><description>Abstract A band of total electron content (TEC) depletions of about 5–15 TEC unit passed over the Korean Peninsula after midnight during the geomagnetic storm on 11 May 2024. This magnitude of TEC depletions has not been previously reported in the region. We track the origin and evolution of these depletions using the TEC data from global navigation satellite system network in Korea and Japan. A distinctive TEC depletion band aligned in the northwest‐southeast direction emerges in the northern east of Japan. The TEC depletions observed over the Korean Peninsula exhibit a similar band structure, and their appearance coincides with the arrival of the TEC depletion band from Japan. This band appears to be part of a pre‐existing midlatitude TEC perturbation layer. We suggest that deep TEC depletions can develop locally from tilted TEC structures when westward winds are present.
Published: 2026-01-25T03:20:28+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.394 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hyosub Kil; Se‐Heon Jeong; Woo Kyoung Lee; Junseok Hong; Septi Perwitasari; Michi Nishioka; Prayitno Abadi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119954"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119954&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.394 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract A band of total electron content (TEC) depletions of about 5–15 TEC unit passed over the Korean Peninsula after midnight during the geomagnetic storm on 11 May 2024. This magnitude of TEC depletions has not been previously reported in the region. We track the origin and evolution of these depletions using the TEC data from global navigation satellite system network in Korea and Japan. A distinctive TEC depletion band aligned in the northwest‐southeast direction emerges in the northern east of Japan. The TEC depletions observed over the Korean Peninsula exhibit a similar band structure, and their appearance coincides with the arrival of the TEC depletion band from Japan. This band appears to be part of a pre‐existing midlatitude TEC perturbation layer. We suggest that deep TEC depletions can develop locally from tilted TEC structures when westward winds are present.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>On the Seeding of Equatorial Plasma Bubbles by Longitudinal Variations in the Meridional Wind</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120025</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl120025</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:31:08 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>J. D. Huba</dc:creator><dc:creator>N. Pedatella</dc:creator><dc:creator>H.‐L. Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl120025</prism:doi><description>Abstract We report results from SAMI3/WACCM‐X simulations that small‐scale (few 100 km) longitudinal variations in the meridional wind provide seeds to initiate equatorial plasma bubbles (EPBs). The meridional wind variations generate variations in the ion density along the magnetic field via ion‐neutral collisions. This in turn leads to longitudinal variations in the Pedersen conductivity and conductance producing localized E B drifts that can initiate EPBs. The spatial dependence of the meridional wind variations can also determine the longitudinal spacing of EPBs.
Published: 2026-01-25T03:31:08+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.389 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; J. D. Huba; N. Pedatella; H.‐L. Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120025"&gt;10.1029/2025gl120025&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.389 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract We report results from SAMI3/WACCM‐X simulations that small‐scale (few 100 km) longitudinal variations in the meridional wind provide seeds to initiate equatorial plasma bubbles (EPBs). The meridional wind variations generate variations in the ion density along the magnetic field via ion‐neutral collisions. This in turn leads to longitudinal variations in the Pedersen conductivity and conductance producing localized E B drifts that can initiate EPBs. The spatial dependence of the meridional wind variations can also determine the longitudinal spacing of EPBs.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Persisting Day and Night High Surface Ozone Pollution Driven by Compound Heatwaves</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl121138</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl121138</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 05:50:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jiayi Xing</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guicai Ning</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoling Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bin Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Minjie Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tianliang Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junfeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuanjian Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl121138</prism:doi><description>Abstract While daytime heatwaves are well‐known to exacerbate surface ozone (O 3 ) pollution, the role of compound heatwaves with persistent day‐night hot in O 3 pollution remains unclear. Taking China's Sichuan Basin (SCB) as an example, we find compound heatwaves persistently intensify surface O 3 concentration day and night, with significant positive anomalies of 29.3 μg/m 3 and 12.1 μg/m 3 during daytime and nighttime, respectively. In details, daytime hot triggers high daytime O 3 concentration by enhancing O 3 ‐forming photochemistry, thereby providing a nocturnal residual layer (RL) with O 3 ‐rich air and substantial heat storage. Nighttime, the persistent day‐night hot combined with easterly flow jointly drive a plateau‐basin secondary circulation across RL and stable boundary layer over the SCB, facilitating RL's O 3 ‐rich air mixing to the surface and increasing nighttime O 3 concentration. These findings advance understanding of how extreme heat and large‐scale topographic forcing jointly modulate atmospheric environmental changes in plateau‐basin regions.
Published: 2026-01-25T05:50:55+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.387 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jiayi Xing; Guicai Ning; Xiaoling Zhang; Bin Zhu; Minjie Cheng; Tianliang Zhao; Junfeng Wang; Yuanjian Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl121138"&gt;10.1029/2025gl121138&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.387 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract While daytime heatwaves are well‐known to exacerbate surface ozone (O 3 ) pollution, the role of compound heatwaves with persistent day‐night hot in O 3 pollution remains unclear. Taking China&amp;#x27;s Sichuan Basin (SCB) as an example, we find compound heatwaves persistently intensify surface O 3 concentration day and night, with significant positive anomalies of 29.3 μg/m 3 and 12.1 μg/m 3 during daytime and nighttime, respectively. In details, daytime hot triggers high daytime O 3 concentration by enhancing O 3 ‐forming photochemistry, thereby providing a nocturnal residual layer (RL) with O 3 ‐rich air and substantial heat storage. Nighttime, the persistent day‐night hot combined with easterly flow jointly drive a plateau‐basin secondary circulation across RL and stable boundary layer over the SCB, facilitating RL&amp;#x27;s O 3 ‐rich air mixing to the surface and increasing nighttime O 3 concentration. These findings advance understanding of how extreme heat and large‐scale topographic forcing jointly modulate atmospheric environmental changes in plateau‐basin regions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Fabric, texture, and bubble characteristics of the million-year old Allan Hills blue ice core ALHIC1901</title><link>https://eartharxiv.org/repository/object/11519/download/20836/</link><guid>oai:EA:id:11519</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 22:15:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Stoll, Nicolas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shaya, Marguerite</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kirkpatrick, Liam</dc:creator><dc:creator>Freitag, Johannes</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hishamunda, Valens</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manos, John-Morgan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jansen, Daniela</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weikusat, Ilka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fegyveresi, John</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lipovsky. Bradley P</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brook, Ed</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shackleton, Sarah</dc:creator><dc:creator>Higgins. John A</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fudge, T. J.</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>EarthArXiv</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.31223/X5NV0X</prism:doi><description>Ice cores from the Allan Hills blue ice area in Antarctica have been dated to several million years of age. However, the stratigraphy of these cores is often disturbed, and age reversals are common, hampering the interpretation of the derived climate records. To better understand the physical processes affecting the ice, we here use a variety of microstructural methods to investigate the fabric, texture and bubble characteristics of four depth regimes in the ALHIC1901 core. We find single maximum CPOs with an occasional second maximum; stripes of differently orientated crystals are common. We further observe small, potentially elongated, grains containing indications of dynamic recrystallisation. 2D and 3D bubble data show strongly elongated bubbles and very low bubble number densities compared to similar depths of deep ice cores. We interpret these findings as indications of simple shear, including kink and z-folds at the centimeter scale and potential alterations to the original air bubbles and, thus, their gas content. Extended studies of Allan Hills ice cores using continuous sections are needed to evaluate the spatial scale of the folding and its impact on the climate record.
Published: 2026-01-21T22:15:00+00:00
Venue: EarthArXiv
Score: 0.384 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Stoll, Nicolas; Shaya, Marguerite; Kirkpatrick, Liam; Freitag, Johannes; Hishamunda, Valens; Manos, John-Morgan; Jansen, Daniela; Weikusat, Ilka; Fegyveresi, John; Lipovsky. Bradley P; Brook, Ed; Shackleton, Sarah; Higgins. John A; Fudge, T. J.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; EarthArXiv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.31223/X5NV0X"&gt;10.31223/X5NV0X&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.384 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice cores from the Allan Hills blue ice area in Antarctica have been dated to several million years of age. However, the stratigraphy of these cores is often disturbed, and age reversals are common, hampering the interpretation of the derived climate records. To better understand the physical processes affecting the ice, we here use a variety of microstructural methods to investigate the fabric, texture and bubble characteristics of four depth regimes in the ALHIC1901 core. We find single maximum CPOs with an occasional second maximum; stripes of differently orientated crystals are common. We further observe small, potentially elongated, grains containing indications of dynamic recrystallisation. 2D and 3D bubble data show strongly elongated bubbles and very low bubble number densities compared to similar depths of deep ice cores. We interpret these findings as indications of simple shear, including kink and z-folds at the centimeter scale and potential alterations to the original air bubbles and, thus, their gas content. Extended studies of Allan Hills ice cores using continuous sections are needed to evaluate the spatial scale of the folding and its impact on the climate record.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Satellite Data Trace Seasonal Freshwater Dispersion in Hudson and James Bays</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl116442</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl116442</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:40:46 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Atreya Basu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Simon Bélanger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zou Zou A. Kuzyk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rakesh K. Singh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Soham Mukherjee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pierre Larouche</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alessia C. Guzzi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emma L. Ausen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Greg McCullough</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jens K. Ehn</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl116442</prism:doi><description>Abstract Freshwater dispersal controls stratification, circulation, and biogeochemical processes in Hudson and James Bay (HJB); however, limited field observations hinder understanding of how different freshwater types drive change. This study uses Aqua‐Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer and Soil Moisture and Ocean Salinity‐Microwave Imaging Radiometer using Aperture Synthesis data to distinguish and map river water (RW) and sea ice melt (SIM), the main freshwater types in HJB. Satellite‐derived RW and SIM agree with in situ tracers, filling field data gaps that support future freshwater research. Higher RW fractions up to 0.40 in southern HJB and a seasonal SIM decline from 0.35 to 0.00 in central HJB match observed patterns. RW spreads offshore in July, contracts in August, and forms a coastal band in September, sustained by cyclonic winds despite reduced discharge. From 2011 to 2019, RW fractions increased (0.0048 yr −1 ) while SIM fractions declined (−0.003 yr −1 ) across HJB.
Published: 2026-01-25T03:40:46+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.382 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Atreya Basu; Simon Bélanger; Zou Zou A. Kuzyk; Rakesh K. Singh; Soham Mukherjee; Pierre Larouche; Alessia C. Guzzi; Emma L. Ausen; Greg McCullough; Jens K. Ehn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl116442"&gt;10.1029/2025gl116442&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.382 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Freshwater dispersal controls stratification, circulation, and biogeochemical processes in Hudson and James Bay (HJB); however, limited field observations hinder understanding of how different freshwater types drive change. This study uses Aqua‐Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer and Soil Moisture and Ocean Salinity‐Microwave Imaging Radiometer using Aperture Synthesis data to distinguish and map river water (RW) and sea ice melt (SIM), the main freshwater types in HJB. Satellite‐derived RW and SIM agree with in situ tracers, filling field data gaps that support future freshwater research. Higher RW fractions up to 0.40 in southern HJB and a seasonal SIM decline from 0.35 to 0.00 in central HJB match observed patterns. RW spreads offshore in July, contracts in August, and forms a coastal band in September, sustained by cyclonic winds despite reduced discharge. From 2011 to 2019, RW fractions increased (0.0048 yr −1 ) while SIM fractions declined (−0.003 yr −1 ) across HJB.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A New Climatology of Continentality Based on Lagrangian Air Mass Travel Times From the Ocean</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120627</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl120627</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 05:29:06 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Georg Brack</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marina Dütsch</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andreas Stohl</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl120627</prism:doi><description>Abstract Climate classifications such as the Köppen classification have a long tradition and wide fields of application. An important classification aspect is continentality, for which we present a new metric based on Lagrangian dispersion model calculations. It measures the time it takes for air to travel from the marine boundary layer to the continental boundary layer, mapped onto the continental arrival locations. We find the highest annual mean values of the Lagrangian continentality over arid regions, with an absolute maximum of about 50 days over the Taklamakan desert. We also find strong seasonal variations, with summer values often being higher by about a factor 2 than winter values. Exceptions are summer minima over areas affected by monsoon systems. Generally, we find that the Lagrangian continentality metric demarcates different known climate zones well and also produces meaningful seasonal variations, which previous classifications could not capture.
Published: 2026-01-25T05:29:06+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.382 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Georg Brack; Marina Dütsch; Andreas Stohl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120627"&gt;10.1029/2025gl120627&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.382 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Climate classifications such as the Köppen classification have a long tradition and wide fields of application. An important classification aspect is continentality, for which we present a new metric based on Lagrangian dispersion model calculations. It measures the time it takes for air to travel from the marine boundary layer to the continental boundary layer, mapped onto the continental arrival locations. We find the highest annual mean values of the Lagrangian continentality over arid regions, with an absolute maximum of about 50 days over the Taklamakan desert. We also find strong seasonal variations, with summer values often being higher by about a factor 2 than winter values. Exceptions are summer minima over areas affected by monsoon systems. Generally, we find that the Lagrangian continentality metric demarcates different known climate zones well and also produces meaningful seasonal variations, which previous classifications could not capture.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Storm signals in coastal sediments: A review of palaeostorm archives and analytical approaches in north-west Europe</title><link>https://eartharxiv.org/repository/object/11518/download/20839/</link><guid>oai:EA:id:11518</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 22:24:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hess, Katharina</dc:creator><dc:creator>Engel, Max</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>EarthArXiv</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.31223/X58N0F</prism:doi><description>Coastal sedimentary archives offer key insights into past severe storms and related flooding, contributing to a better understanding of long-term coastal hazard histories. Although interest in palaeostorm reconstructions has increased in recent decades, a comprehensive overview and information for north-west Europe is missing. This synoptic literature review compiles all known sedimentary storm archives between 45°N and 75°N, outlining their geographical distribution, ages, and methodological approaches. We identified 77 sites described in 69 publications since 1985. The most frequently investigated archive types are peat bogs, followed by coastal dunes, salt marshes, coastal lakes and lagoons, and cliff-top storm deposits. Most records are concentrated in the British Isles, particularly Scotland, while data from southern Norway and the German coasts are largely absent, indicating a strong spatial bias. The ages of these records range from the Late Pleistocene (~14 ka BP) to the present, with a median sedimentary age range of 2.3 ka BP. Storm deposits are commonly identified as minerogenic sand layers embedded within organic-rich fine-grained sediments. Grain size and composition, often combined with loss-on-ignition analyses to estimate organic content, are the primary proxies used to infer depositional processes, which can generally be classified as marginal marine, overwash, or aeolian. The use of microfossils and stable isotopes remains limited across European studies. Recent studies show a growing trend toward more comprehensive laboratory analyses. Overall, this review highlights the need for standardised protocols in sampling, analysis, and interpretation to enable broader comparisons and to reconstruct long-term storm patterns across Europe more reliably.
Published: 2026-01-22T22:24:00+00:00
Venue: EarthArXiv
Score: 0.381 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hess, Katharina; Engel, Max&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; EarthArXiv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.31223/X58N0F"&gt;10.31223/X58N0F&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.381 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coastal sedimentary archives offer key insights into past severe storms and related flooding, contributing to a better understanding of long-term coastal hazard histories. Although interest in palaeostorm reconstructions has increased in recent decades, a comprehensive overview and information for north-west Europe is missing. This synoptic literature review compiles all known sedimentary storm archives between 45°N and 75°N, outlining their geographical distribution, ages, and methodological approaches. We identified 77 sites described in 69 publications since 1985. The most frequently investigated archive types are peat bogs, followed by coastal dunes, salt marshes, coastal lakes and lagoons, and cliff-top storm deposits. Most records are concentrated in the British Isles, particularly Scotland, while data from southern Norway and the German coasts are largely absent, indicating a strong spatial bias. The ages of these records range from the Late Pleistocene (~14 ka BP) to the present, with a median sedimentary age range of 2.3 ka BP. Storm deposits are commonly identified as minerogenic sand layers embedded within organic-rich fine-grained sediments. Grain size and composition, often combined with loss-on-ignition analyses to estimate organic content, are the primary proxies used to infer depositional processes, which can generally be classified as marginal marine, overwash, or aeolian. The use of microfossils and stable isotopes remains limited across European studies. Recent studies show a growing trend toward more comprehensive laboratory analyses. Overall, this review highlights the need for standardised protocols in sampling, analysis, and interpretation to enable broader comparisons and to reconstruct long-term storm patterns across Europe more reliably.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>