<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Dec 2025 00:57:54 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Has the Southern Tan-Lu Fault Zone in eastern China been thickened?</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38589.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38589.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 20:29:35 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manlan Niu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhe Heng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuai Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guang Zhu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38589.1</prism:doi><description>Early Cretaceous adakitic rocks are widespread along the Tan-Lu Fault and the Dabie Orogen in eastern China. Conventional models attribute their origin to partial melting of thickened lower crust, associated with lithospheric thinning in the North China Craton. Our study presents comprehensive geochemistry for low-Mg adakitic rocks (LMAs) from the Southern Tan-Lu Fault Zone (STLFZ), and compares them with those from the Dabie Orogen. The STLFZ LMAs share similar Sr-Nd-Hf isotopic signatures with the Dabie LMAs, suggesting a shared source derived from the Paleoproterozoic basement of the northern Yangtze Block. However, the STLFZ LMAs are geochemically distinct, with lower La/Yb, Sr/CaO, and Nb/Ta ratios, but higher Nb/La ratios, reflecting differences in residual mineral assemblages and melting conditions. Phase equilibrium modeling reveals that the STLFZ LMAs likely formed through fluid-fluxed melting under garnet amphibolite facies, contrasting with the eclogite-facies dehydration melting for the Dabie LMAs. This implies that the STLFZ was not significantly thickened at the time of melting. Furthermore, the STLFZ LMAs were emplaced at ca. 130−115 Ma, later than the Dabie LMAs (ca. 143−130 Ma). These spatial, temporal, and genetic differences probably reflect the reactivation of the Tan-Lu Fault (ca. 146−130 Ma), which triggered dehydration melting, crustal foundering, and mantle metasomatism in the Dabie Orogen. Subsequent underplating of hydrous magmas beneath the STLFZ then facilitated fluid-fluxed melting under normal crustal thickness conditions. These findings provide new insights into the heterogeneous mechanisms of adakitic magmatism and the role of major tectonic structures in controlling crustal evolution.
Published: 2025-12-23T20:29:35+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.616 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hang Liu; Manlan Niu; Qi Wu; Zhe Heng; Shuai Zhang; Guang Zhu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38589.1"&gt;10.1130/b38589.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.616 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early Cretaceous adakitic rocks are widespread along the Tan-Lu Fault and the Dabie Orogen in eastern China. Conventional models attribute their origin to partial melting of thickened lower crust, associated with lithospheric thinning in the North China Craton. Our study presents comprehensive geochemistry for low-Mg adakitic rocks (LMAs) from the Southern Tan-Lu Fault Zone (STLFZ), and compares them with those from the Dabie Orogen. The STLFZ LMAs share similar Sr-Nd-Hf isotopic signatures with the Dabie LMAs, suggesting a shared source derived from the Paleoproterozoic basement of the northern Yangtze Block. However, the STLFZ LMAs are geochemically distinct, with lower La/Yb, Sr/CaO, and Nb/Ta ratios, but higher Nb/La ratios, reflecting differences in residual mineral assemblages and melting conditions. Phase equilibrium modeling reveals that the STLFZ LMAs likely formed through fluid-fluxed melting under garnet amphibolite facies, contrasting with the eclogite-facies dehydration melting for the Dabie LMAs. This implies that the STLFZ was not significantly thickened at the time of melting. Furthermore, the STLFZ LMAs were emplaced at ca. 130−115 Ma, later than the Dabie LMAs (ca. 143−130 Ma). These spatial, temporal, and genetic differences probably reflect the reactivation of the Tan-Lu Fault (ca. 146−130 Ma), which triggered dehydration melting, crustal foundering, and mantle metasomatism in the Dabie Orogen. Subsequent underplating of hydrous magmas beneath the STLFZ then facilitated fluid-fluxed melting under normal crustal thickness conditions. These findings provide new insights into the heterogeneous mechanisms of adakitic magmatism and the role of major tectonic structures in controlling crustal evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ni redispersion from SiO2 to molybdenum carbide creates dual interfaces to boost tandem CO2 hydrogenation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-64030-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-64030-9</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 02:33:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Haiyan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuetao Qin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zirui Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanan Diao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shenghua Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mi Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shida Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuandi Hou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinwen Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ding Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuan Shi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-64030-9</prism:doi><description>Interface engineering is crucial in the design of supported metal catalysts, as it significantly influences the catalytic process, particularly in terms of selectivity. Herein, we discover the redispersion of Ni nanoparticles from SiO2 to molybdenum carbide (Mo2C) being induced by the strong interaction between metal and Mo2C. Parameters affect such migration are thoroughly investigated from carbon source, proximity between Ni and Mo2C to activation atmosphere and temperature. The established dual interface on Mo2C-Ni/SiO2 catalyst exhibits excellent catalytic performance for CO2 hydrogenation, readily shifting the selectivity from 91% CO on Ni/Mo2C to near 100% CH4 on Mo2C-Ni/SiO2. Density functional theory calculations further verify the interfacial synergy between Ni/Mo2C and Ni/SiO2 sites with low barrier for CO2 activation and a subsequent successive hydrogenation of CO. These findings highlight the important role of strong metal-support interaction (SMSI) induced metal redispersion for the rational fabrication of dual interfaces, leading to a highly active catalyst for target products. Engineering catalyst interfaces plays a key role in designing supported metal systems. Here, the authors report that Ni nanoparticles redisperse from SiO₂ to molybdenum carbide, forming dual interfaces that enhance tandem CO₂ hydrogenation.
Published: 2025-12-23T02:33:33+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.591 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Haiyan Wang; Xuetao Qin; Zirui Gao; Yanan Diao; Shenghua Liu; Mi Peng; Shida Liu; Shuandi Hou; Xin Liu; Xinwen Guo; Ding Ma; Chuan Shi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-64030-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-64030-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.591 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interface engineering is crucial in the design of supported metal catalysts, as it significantly influences the catalytic process, particularly in terms of selectivity. Herein, we discover the redispersion of Ni nanoparticles from SiO2 to molybdenum carbide (Mo2C) being induced by the strong interaction between metal and Mo2C. Parameters affect such migration are thoroughly investigated from carbon source, proximity between Ni and Mo2C to activation atmosphere and temperature. The established dual interface on Mo2C-Ni/SiO2 catalyst exhibits excellent catalytic performance for CO2 hydrogenation, readily shifting the selectivity from 91% CO on Ni/Mo2C to near 100% CH4 on Mo2C-Ni/SiO2. Density functional theory calculations further verify the interfacial synergy between Ni/Mo2C and Ni/SiO2 sites with low barrier for CO2 activation and a subsequent successive hydrogenation of CO. These findings highlight the important role of strong metal-support interaction (SMSI) induced metal redispersion for the rational fabrication of dual interfaces, leading to a highly active catalyst for target products. Engineering catalyst interfaces plays a key role in designing supported metal systems. Here, the authors report that Ni nanoparticles redisperse from SiO₂ to molybdenum carbide, forming dual interfaces that enhance tandem CO₂ hydrogenation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Melting the myth: Prograde garnet dissolves during early crustal melting</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/g54000.1</link><guid>10.1130/g54000.1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 21:38:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lucas R. Tesser</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pierre Lanari</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jacob B. Forshaw</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thorsten A. Markmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mathias Hueck</dc:creator><dc:creator>Benita Putlitz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Noralinde de Leijer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cauê R. Cioffi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miguel A.S. Basei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Carlos E. Ganade</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/g54000.1</prism:doi><description>Garnet is widely thought to increase in stability and volume during prograde metamorphism and partial melting. Yet, whether early-formed subsolidus garnet persists or breaks down when melting begins remains an open question. Here, we integrate 3-D X-ray tomography with high-resolution major- and trace-element mapping of centrally sectioned garnets across a metapelitic metamorphic sequence to track their response from the subsolidus-suprasolidus transition to melting temperatures up to ∼770 °C. Contrary to experimental and phase equilibrium predictions, garnet undergoes extensive dissolution at the onset of partial melting, losing &amp;gt;40% of its volume. Melt percolation creates internal cavity networks within garnet, connecting crystal interiors to the reactive matrix, markedly shortening intracrystalline diffusion pathways at the melt-crystal interface. This process leads to the consumption of garnet and results in major- and trace-element redistribution at temperatures too low for intracrystalline diffusion in larger grains. Our findings reconcile the long-standing discrepancy between predicted progressive garnet growth above the solidus and the scarcity of melt inclusions in garnet rims in migmatites and granulites. As partial melting begins, subsolidus garnet reacts and becomes a permeable heavy rare earth elements and yttrium (HREE-Y) reservoir in the residual crust.
Published: 2025-12-24T21:38:49+00:00
Venue: Geology
Score: 0.583 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lucas R. Tesser; Pierre Lanari; Jacob B. Forshaw; Thorsten A. Markmann; Mathias Hueck; Benita Putlitz; Noralinde de Leijer; Cauê R. Cioffi; Miguel A.S. Basei; Carlos E. Ganade&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/g54000.1"&gt;10.1130/g54000.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.583 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Garnet is widely thought to increase in stability and volume during prograde metamorphism and partial melting. Yet, whether early-formed subsolidus garnet persists or breaks down when melting begins remains an open question. Here, we integrate 3-D X-ray tomography with high-resolution major- and trace-element mapping of centrally sectioned garnets across a metapelitic metamorphic sequence to track their response from the subsolidus-suprasolidus transition to melting temperatures up to ∼770 °C. Contrary to experimental and phase equilibrium predictions, garnet undergoes extensive dissolution at the onset of partial melting, losing &amp;amp;gt;40% of its volume. Melt percolation creates internal cavity networks within garnet, connecting crystal interiors to the reactive matrix, markedly shortening intracrystalline diffusion pathways at the melt-crystal interface. This process leads to the consumption of garnet and results in major- and trace-element redistribution at temperatures too low for intracrystalline diffusion in larger grains. Our findings reconcile the long-standing discrepancy between predicted progressive garnet growth above the solidus and the scarcity of melt inclusions in garnet rims in migmatites and granulites. As partial melting begins, subsolidus garnet reacts and becomes a permeable heavy rare earth elements and yttrium (HREE-Y) reservoir in the residual crust.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Winding coupling phase for pseudo-spin-derived topological photonics</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67627-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67627-2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 09:45:22 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tianyuan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Yan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67627-2</prism:doi><description>Topological phases derived from spin or pseudo-spin typically leverage specific effects like spin-orbit interaction or antiferromagnetism. Here, we propose a flexible theoretical framework capable of designing pseudo-spin-derived topological phases. We reveal that the evanescent coupling between nearby resonators exhibits a $${\pi }_{1}({S}^{1})$$ topology characterized by a quantized coupling winding number. By tailoring the coupling winding number in photonic crystals, we propose silicon-on-insulator designs for the spin-valley Hall phase (SVHP), its anomalous variant, the anomalous Hall phase, and anti-helical edge states. Notably, the SVHP is obtained in a non-antiferromagnetic system without the need of time-reversal symmetry breaking, and the anti-helical edge states are designed independently of next-nearest coupling tuning. The results are compatible with conventional fabrication processes, demonstrating the simplicity and versatility of this framework and its potential for applications in spin-valley protected light transport and slow light guiding. Topological phases derived from spin and pseudo-spin dynamics are generally described by case-specific models. Here, authors propose a general theoretical framework that enables a flexible design of a variety of pseudo-spin-induced topological phases including spin-valley Hall phase, anomalous Hall phase and anti-helical edge states.
Published: 2025-12-24T09:45:22+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.578 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tianyuan Liu; Min Qiu; Wei Yan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67627-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67627-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.578 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topological phases derived from spin or pseudo-spin typically leverage specific effects like spin-orbit interaction or antiferromagnetism. Here, we propose a flexible theoretical framework capable of designing pseudo-spin-derived topological phases. We reveal that the evanescent coupling between nearby resonators exhibits a $${\pi }_{1}({S}^{1})$$ topology characterized by a quantized coupling winding number. By tailoring the coupling winding number in photonic crystals, we propose silicon-on-insulator designs for the spin-valley Hall phase (SVHP), its anomalous variant, the anomalous Hall phase, and anti-helical edge states. Notably, the SVHP is obtained in a non-antiferromagnetic system without the need of time-reversal symmetry breaking, and the anti-helical edge states are designed independently of next-nearest coupling tuning. The results are compatible with conventional fabrication processes, demonstrating the simplicity and versatility of this framework and its potential for applications in spin-valley protected light transport and slow light guiding. Topological phases derived from spin and pseudo-spin dynamics are generally described by case-specific models. Here, authors propose a general theoretical framework that enables a flexible design of a variety of pseudo-spin-induced topological phases including spin-valley Hall phase, anomalous Hall phase and anti-helical edge states.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Intrinsic light reflection of conjugated films towards high-performance organic solar cells</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67379-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67379-z</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 16:24:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zichao Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guanyu Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xian Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuanyuan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Songqiao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jin Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinde Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fan Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laju Bu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuanwei Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongge Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lingxian Meng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guanghao Lu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67379-z</prism:doi><description>In organic solar cells (OSCs), which represent a quintessential application system for organic conjugated films, the intrinsic light reflection of these films significantly influences the optical performance of the devices through the Fabry–Pérot micro-cavity effect. However, this phenomenon has not been comprehensively investigated. This study demonstrates that the film’s intrinsic reflection arises from the light-matter interaction, which is mainly governed by the polarizability of delocalized electron cloud and the orientation of the conjugated backbone. Furthermore, the multi-level interference within the OSC micro-cavity leads to a dependence of both the reflection properties and the short-circuit current density (JSC) on the active layer thickness. Based on these insights, a strategy for synergistic optimization of device performance through precise tailoring of optical constants and the micro-cavity structure is proposed. By systematically analyzing the intrinsic reflection behavior of organic conjugated films, this study enhances the understanding of the role reflection plays in the performance of photovoltaic devices and provides theoretical support for further optical optimization of organic photovoltaics. The intrinsic light reflection of organic conjugated films significantly influences the optical performance of devices through Fabry–Pérot micro-cavity effect. Here, authors modulate cell micro cavity via tuning materials’ refractive index to improve photovoltaic performance of organic solar cells.
Published: 2025-12-23T16:24:52+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.573 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zichao Shen; Guanyu Lu; Xian Tang; Yuanyuan Zhang; Songqiao Li; Jin Wang; Jinde Yu; Fan Gao; Laju Bu; Xin Chen; Yuanwei Zhu; Hongge Pan; Lingxian Meng; Guanghao Lu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67379-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67379-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.573 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In organic solar cells (OSCs), which represent a quintessential application system for organic conjugated films, the intrinsic light reflection of these films significantly influences the optical performance of the devices through the Fabry–Pérot micro-cavity effect. However, this phenomenon has not been comprehensively investigated. This study demonstrates that the film’s intrinsic reflection arises from the light-matter interaction, which is mainly governed by the polarizability of delocalized electron cloud and the orientation of the conjugated backbone. Furthermore, the multi-level interference within the OSC micro-cavity leads to a dependence of both the reflection properties and the short-circuit current density (JSC) on the active layer thickness. Based on these insights, a strategy for synergistic optimization of device performance through precise tailoring of optical constants and the micro-cavity structure is proposed. By systematically analyzing the intrinsic reflection behavior of organic conjugated films, this study enhances the understanding of the role reflection plays in the performance of photovoltaic devices and provides theoretical support for further optical optimization of organic photovoltaics. The intrinsic light reflection of organic conjugated films significantly influences the optical performance of devices through Fabry–Pérot micro-cavity effect. Here, authors modulate cell micro cavity via tuning materials’ refractive index to improve photovoltaic performance of organic solar cells.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Carbon dynamics control contemporary mercury burial in Arctic Ocean sediments</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03058-7</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03058-7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 16:15:43 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Charles Gobeil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sophia C. Johannessen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miguel A. Goñi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zou Zou A. Kuzyk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel Cossa</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03058-7</prism:doi><description>Understanding the high mercury concentrations observed in Arctic ecosystems requires in-depth knowledge of mercury cycling. Here, we show that variations in mercury concentration in the sediments of the North American Arctic Margin and the Arctic Ocean basins can be explained by carbon sources and cycling. Sedimentary mercury concentrations are predicted (p &amp;lt; 0.001) considering three carbon sources and, in some areas, the recapture of soluble mercury released during burial. Terrigenous organic carbon dominates mercury delivery (50-90%) in the western North American Arctic Margin, whereas inorganic carbon predominates at many eastern sites (40-70%). Marine organic carbon contributes &amp;lt;15% of the total mercury concentration. Mercury–organic carbon endmember ratios of terrigenous and marine organic carbon are higher in deep Arctic Ocean basins than in the continental margin, likely due to greater organic matter remineralization during transit. The observed enrichment in mercury toward the sediment surface results from remineralization of organic carbon, not from an increase in mercury flux. Mercury concentrations in sediments of the North American Arctic Margin and the Arctic Ocean basins can be entirely explained by carbon sources and cycling, according to analysis of sediment cores from the polar ocean.
Published: 2025-12-24T16:15:43+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.572 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Charles Gobeil; Sophia C. Johannessen; Miguel A. Goñi; Zou Zou A. Kuzyk; Daniel Cossa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03058-7"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03058-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.572 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the high mercury concentrations observed in Arctic ecosystems requires in-depth knowledge of mercury cycling. Here, we show that variations in mercury concentration in the sediments of the North American Arctic Margin and the Arctic Ocean basins can be explained by carbon sources and cycling. Sedimentary mercury concentrations are predicted (p &amp;amp;lt; 0.001) considering three carbon sources and, in some areas, the recapture of soluble mercury released during burial. Terrigenous organic carbon dominates mercury delivery (50-90%) in the western North American Arctic Margin, whereas inorganic carbon predominates at many eastern sites (40-70%). Marine organic carbon contributes &amp;amp;lt;15% of the total mercury concentration. Mercury–organic carbon endmember ratios of terrigenous and marine organic carbon are higher in deep Arctic Ocean basins than in the continental margin, likely due to greater organic matter remineralization during transit. The observed enrichment in mercury toward the sediment surface results from remineralization of organic carbon, not from an increase in mercury flux. Mercury concentrations in sediments of the North American Arctic Margin and the Arctic Ocean basins can be entirely explained by carbon sources and cycling, according to analysis of sediment cores from the polar ocean.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Feldspar reduces fault frictional healing rate under hydrothermal conditions</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67521-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67521-x</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 10:25:39 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Wei Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenzhou Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rodrigo Gomila</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shengli Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qunyang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Giulio Di Toro</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67521-x</prism:doi><description>Fault restrengthening after earthquakes enables country rocks to restore elastic strain energy for subsequent seismic cycles. It originates from the contribution of several processes resulting in fault sealing and fault frictional healing, the latter arising from contact area growth and formation of new chemical bonds between grains. Laboratory studies demonstrate that fault frictional healing typically increases logarithmically with time during quasi-stationary contact (i.e., positive healing rate). Here we show that this logarithmic healing does not hold under certain (hydrothermal) conditions for feldspar, the most abundant mineral in the Earth’s crust, and for common feldspar-rich rocks. The healing rate switches from positive to negative with increasing quasi-stationary contact time at temperatures ≥ 200 °C in the presence of pressurized water. This unusual healing behavior suggests that thermally-activated friction weakening processes may exist at feldspar interfaces. This hypothesis is further validated through nano-scale friction experiments by sliding single-feldspar crystals on a feldspar substrate. Given the abundance of feldspars in the Earth’s crust, their peculiar healing behavior under hydrothermal conditions can lead to unexpected variations in fault strength, changing our understanding of fault mechanics and the seismic cycle, and challenging the direct extrapolation of laboratory-derived healing parameters to natural earthquake recurrence intervals. By integrating macro-scale and nano-scale experiments that reproduce the seismic cycle, this study reveals that feldspars, very common minerals, reduce the rate at which faults heal after a seismic rupture under certain hydrothermal conditions.
Published: 2025-12-23T10:25:39+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.560 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Wei Feng; Wenzhou Wang; Lu Yao; Rodrigo Gomila; Shengli Ma; Qunyang Li; Giulio Di Toro&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67521-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67521-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.560 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fault restrengthening after earthquakes enables country rocks to restore elastic strain energy for subsequent seismic cycles. It originates from the contribution of several processes resulting in fault sealing and fault frictional healing, the latter arising from contact area growth and formation of new chemical bonds between grains. Laboratory studies demonstrate that fault frictional healing typically increases logarithmically with time during quasi-stationary contact (i.e., positive healing rate). Here we show that this logarithmic healing does not hold under certain (hydrothermal) conditions for feldspar, the most abundant mineral in the Earth’s crust, and for common feldspar-rich rocks. The healing rate switches from positive to negative with increasing quasi-stationary contact time at temperatures ≥ 200 °C in the presence of pressurized water. This unusual healing behavior suggests that thermally-activated friction weakening processes may exist at feldspar interfaces. This hypothesis is further validated through nano-scale friction experiments by sliding single-feldspar crystals on a feldspar substrate. Given the abundance of feldspars in the Earth’s crust, their peculiar healing behavior under hydrothermal conditions can lead to unexpected variations in fault strength, changing our understanding of fault mechanics and the seismic cycle, and challenging the direct extrapolation of laboratory-derived healing parameters to natural earthquake recurrence intervals. By integrating macro-scale and nano-scale experiments that reproduce the seismic cycle, this study reveals that feldspars, very common minerals, reduce the rate at which faults heal after a seismic rupture under certain hydrothermal conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Two-Dimensional Metastable-Phase Nickel Hexagonal Nanosheets for Highly-Performance Electrochemical Acetone Hydrogenation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67839-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67839-6</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 15:35:57 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Long Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zonghao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Penghao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanzhuo Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenchen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sihui Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei-Hsiang Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chih-Wen Pao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiwei Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi Shao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67839-6</prism:doi><description>Electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation into high-value alcohols offers a sustainable alternative to thermal methods. However, developing non-noble metal catalysts with superior performance for electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation remains challenging. Two-dimensional non-noble metal structure with metastable-phase active sites is promising due to its high-energy structure and unique electronic environment. However, its precise synthesis remains a great challenge. In this work, we report a two-dimensional metastable hexagonal close-packed phase nickel nanosheets (hcp Ni NSs) with a space group of P63/mmc. In the electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation, it achieves 95.0 % acetone conversion with 100 % isopropanol selectivity. Notably, in the scale-up experiment, the hcp Ni NSs also exhibit 11.51 g gcat-1 h-1 isopropanol production rate at a current density of −250 mA cm-2. Furthermore, this catalyst is widely applicable to various carbonyl compounds. Mechanism study shows that hcp Ni NSs enable strong acetone adsorption and rapid isopropanol desorption. Morphology control of two-dimensional metastable phase nanomaterials is a core issue for catalyst design. Here, two-dimensional metastable-phase Ni hexagonal nanosheets are synthesized via a one-pot method, exhibiting competitive catalytic performance in the electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation.
Published: 2025-12-24T15:35:57+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.556 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Long Chen; Zonghao Zhang; Penghao Li; Hanzhuo Luo; Chenchen Li; Sihui Pan; Wei-Hsiang Huang; Chih-Wen Pao; Hao Yang; Zhiwei Hu; Qi Shao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67839-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67839-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.556 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation into high-value alcohols offers a sustainable alternative to thermal methods. However, developing non-noble metal catalysts with superior performance for electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation remains challenging. Two-dimensional non-noble metal structure with metastable-phase active sites is promising due to its high-energy structure and unique electronic environment. However, its precise synthesis remains a great challenge. In this work, we report a two-dimensional metastable hexagonal close-packed phase nickel nanosheets (hcp Ni NSs) with a space group of P63/mmc. In the electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation, it achieves 95.0 % acetone conversion with 100 % isopropanol selectivity. Notably, in the scale-up experiment, the hcp Ni NSs also exhibit 11.51 g gcat-1 h-1 isopropanol production rate at a current density of −250 mA cm-2. Furthermore, this catalyst is widely applicable to various carbonyl compounds. Mechanism study shows that hcp Ni NSs enable strong acetone adsorption and rapid isopropanol desorption. Morphology control of two-dimensional metastable phase nanomaterials is a core issue for catalyst design. Here, two-dimensional metastable-phase Ni hexagonal nanosheets are synthesized via a one-pot method, exhibiting competitive catalytic performance in the electrocatalytic acetone hydrogenation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Rapid viscous flow of crustal rocks controls dyke emplacement in the ductile crust</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67464-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67464-3</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 05:43:03 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hans Jørgen Kjøll</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Scheiber</dc:creator><dc:creator>Olivier Galland</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67464-3</prism:doi><description>Abstract Magmatic dykes are the main pathways for magma through Earth’s crust. They are often assumed to be magma-filled fractures that propagate as thin, tapered sheet intrusions through mode I tensile opening at the fracture tip and elastic bending of the host rock along the dyke walls. Here, we present field evidence from northern Sweden, showing that deep-crustal dyke emplacement was, despite high strain rates, associated with significant ductile deformation of the host rocks. On average, 25% of the dyke thickness was accommodated by ductile flow of the immediate host rock. Modelling magma cooling times suggests average ductile strain rates of 10 −3 s −1 to 10 −6 s −1 , i.e. 6 to 10 orders of magnitude faster than typical tectonic ductile strain rates in the middle crust. These results have major implications for understanding ductile crustal strength and the interpretation of geophysical signals used to mitigate geohazards in volcanically active areas.
Published: 2025-12-23T05:43:03+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.553 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hans Jørgen Kjøll; Thomas Scheiber; Olivier Galland&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67464-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67464-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.553 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Magmatic dykes are the main pathways for magma through Earth’s crust. They are often assumed to be magma-filled fractures that propagate as thin, tapered sheet intrusions through mode I tensile opening at the fracture tip and elastic bending of the host rock along the dyke walls. Here, we present field evidence from northern Sweden, showing that deep-crustal dyke emplacement was, despite high strain rates, associated with significant ductile deformation of the host rocks. On average, 25% of the dyke thickness was accommodated by ductile flow of the immediate host rock. Modelling magma cooling times suggests average ductile strain rates of 10 −3 s −1 to 10 −6 s −1 , i.e. 6 to 10 orders of magnitude faster than typical tectonic ductile strain rates in the middle crust. These results have major implications for understanding ductile crustal strength and the interpretation of geophysical signals used to mitigate geohazards in volcanically active areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Origin of the Late Permian tuffs in South China and a Pompeii-style death assemblage</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38672.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38672.1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 19:57:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hai-Feng Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Zou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul B. Wignall</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lin-Hao Fang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hua-Wen Cao</dc:creator><dc:creator>He Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bin Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chang-Cheng Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hui-Dong Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zi-Han Ma</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38672.1</prism:doi><description>Volcanic ash or tuff layers are widely developed in the sedimentary sequences of the Middle Permian to the Middle Triassic within the Yangtze Block, South China. The tuff layers in the Longtan Formation (Late Permian) at the Baoding section in the eastern Sichuan Basin contain some remarkable fossils preserved in a Pompeii-style. The depositional processes, provenance, and tectonic setting of these tuffs are evaluated based on petrography, whole-rock geochemistry, zircon U-Pb geochronology, and zircon Hf-O isotopic analyses. The petrographic characteristics include angular quartz, with clean surfaces and melt embayed margins, along with a homogeneous grain size distribution, without sorting or sedimentary structures within the tuff layers, which indicate ash fallout deposition, a process that could smother seafloor benthos. Zircon U-Pb dating yields an age range of 255.2−254.1 Ma (late Wuchiapingian), which corresponds to the waning stage of the Emeishan large igneous province (Emeishan LIP). Geochemical characteristics of whole-rock samples, including SiO2 (30.19−59.71 wt%, average 48.38 wt%), Al2O3/TiO2 (mostly &amp;lt;8), Th/Sc (mostly &amp;lt;0.6), along with positive zircon εHf(t) values (1.3−6.0) and low zircon Th/Nb (mostly &amp;lt;10), collectively point to a mantle source. Additionally, low δ18O zircon values (mean 4.04‰) suggest that the mafic magma, after separating from the mantle during its ascent, assimilated ancient crustal materials that had previously undergone hydrothermal alteration. Geochemical characteristics and tectonic setting discrimination diagrams further support an intraplate rift-related origin linked to the Emeishan LIP.
Published: 2025-12-24T19:57:55+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.551 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hai-Feng Chen; Hao Zou; Paul B. Wignall; Xin Jin; Lin-Hao Fang; Hua-Wen Cao; He Zhu; Bin Xiao; Chang-Cheng Huang; Hui-Dong Yu; Zi-Han Ma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38672.1"&gt;10.1130/b38672.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.551 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volcanic ash or tuff layers are widely developed in the sedimentary sequences of the Middle Permian to the Middle Triassic within the Yangtze Block, South China. The tuff layers in the Longtan Formation (Late Permian) at the Baoding section in the eastern Sichuan Basin contain some remarkable fossils preserved in a Pompeii-style. The depositional processes, provenance, and tectonic setting of these tuffs are evaluated based on petrography, whole-rock geochemistry, zircon U-Pb geochronology, and zircon Hf-O isotopic analyses. The petrographic characteristics include angular quartz, with clean surfaces and melt embayed margins, along with a homogeneous grain size distribution, without sorting or sedimentary structures within the tuff layers, which indicate ash fallout deposition, a process that could smother seafloor benthos. Zircon U-Pb dating yields an age range of 255.2−254.1 Ma (late Wuchiapingian), which corresponds to the waning stage of the Emeishan large igneous province (Emeishan LIP). Geochemical characteristics of whole-rock samples, including SiO2 (30.19−59.71 wt%, average 48.38 wt%), Al2O3/TiO2 (mostly &amp;amp;lt;8), Th/Sc (mostly &amp;amp;lt;0.6), along with positive zircon εHf(t) values (1.3−6.0) and low zircon Th/Nb (mostly &amp;amp;lt;10), collectively point to a mantle source. Additionally, low δ18O zircon values (mean 4.04‰) suggest that the mafic magma, after separating from the mantle during its ascent, assimilated ancient crustal materials that had previously undergone hydrothermal alteration. Geochemical characteristics and tectonic setting discrimination diagrams further support an intraplate rift-related origin linked to the Emeishan LIP.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Steric and hydrophilic/hydrophobic effects of organic cations on electrochemical CO reduction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67761-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67761-x</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 15:21:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Liwei Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fengyuan Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jieyu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuelin Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huijuan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guangzhe Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gongwei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lin Zhuang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67761-x</prism:doi><description>The identity of cations plays a critical role in electrochemical CO2 and CO reduction reactions. While most research has focused on elucidating the effects of alkali metal cations, the influence of organic cations, which are widely employed in practical anion exchange membrane (AEM) electrolyzers, remains underexplored. Here, we systematically investigate the effects of a series of organic cations with varying sizes and hydrophilic/hydrophobic properties on the CO reduction reaction (CORR). By combining electrochemical online mass spectrometry for kinetic analysis, in-situ Raman spectroscopy for interfacial species characterization, and ab initio molecular dynamics (AIMD) simulations to probe interfacial structures, we uncover that the structure of organic cations significantly influences the accessibility of interfacial water to the electrode surface, and thus the potential-dependent behavior of surface *H coverage, ultimately modulating the CORR selectivity. These findings provide new insights into the mechanisms governing CORR and can guide the development of efficient AEM electrolyzers for CO conversion. Understanding the organic cation effect on CO electroreduction is crucial for developing efficient alkaline polyelectrolytes. Here, the authors elucidate how organic cations of varying sizes and hydrophilicity influence the electrocatalytic interface and product selectivity during CO reduction.
Published: 2025-12-23T15:21:09+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.544 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Liwei Xue; Fengyuan Wei; Jieyu Wang; Xuelin Huang; Huijuan Wang; Guangzhe Wang; Li Xiao; Gongwei Wang; Lin Zhuang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67761-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67761-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.544 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The identity of cations plays a critical role in electrochemical CO2 and CO reduction reactions. While most research has focused on elucidating the effects of alkali metal cations, the influence of organic cations, which are widely employed in practical anion exchange membrane (AEM) electrolyzers, remains underexplored. Here, we systematically investigate the effects of a series of organic cations with varying sizes and hydrophilic/hydrophobic properties on the CO reduction reaction (CORR). By combining electrochemical online mass spectrometry for kinetic analysis, in-situ Raman spectroscopy for interfacial species characterization, and ab initio molecular dynamics (AIMD) simulations to probe interfacial structures, we uncover that the structure of organic cations significantly influences the accessibility of interfacial water to the electrode surface, and thus the potential-dependent behavior of surface *H coverage, ultimately modulating the CORR selectivity. These findings provide new insights into the mechanisms governing CORR and can guide the development of efficient AEM electrolyzers for CO conversion. Understanding the organic cation effect on CO electroreduction is crucial for developing efficient alkaline polyelectrolytes. Here, the authors elucidate how organic cations of varying sizes and hydrophilicity influence the electrocatalytic interface and product selectivity during CO reduction.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ultrahigh-pressure elasticity of dense hydrous SiO2</title><link>https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2025-9927</link><guid>10.2138/am-2025-9927</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 17:20:38 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yuichiro Mori</dc:creator><dc:creator>Motohiko Murakami</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takashi Yoshino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroyuki Kagi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>American Mineralogist</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.2138/am-2025-9927</prism:doi><description>Abstract Dense SiO2 phases such as stishovite and CaCl2-type SiO2 are the most elastically stiff minerals among major silicate and oxide minerals in the Earth’s mantle. Those phases have a significantly high water solubility compared to other nominally anhydrous minerals in the lower mantle. To date, there have been no direct measurements of sound velocity on dense hydrous SiO2. In this study, shear wave velocity of hydrous SiO2 was measured at room temperature up to 100 GPa using Brillouin light scattering spectroscopy in a diamond anvil cell. Compared to anhydrous SiO2, the shear wave velocity of hydrous SiO2 is significantly lower, but the difference of them gradually diminishes with increasing pressure. Water incorporation drastically softens SiO2 at lower pressure, whereas progressively make it stiffer with increasing pressure. These results suggest that water incorporation into SiO2 could produce the elastically distinct region with negative shear wave velocity anomalies in the lower mantle. This observation indicates that SiO2 can be a likely cause of water-induced stiffening of silicate minerals with increasing pressure.
Published: 2025-12-23T17:20:38+00:00
Venue: American Mineralogist
Score: 0.541 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yuichiro Mori; Motohiko Murakami; Takashi Yoshino; Hiroyuki Kagi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; American Mineralogist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2025-9927"&gt;10.2138/am-2025-9927&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.541 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Dense SiO2 phases such as stishovite and CaCl2-type SiO2 are the most elastically stiff minerals among major silicate and oxide minerals in the Earth’s mantle. Those phases have a significantly high water solubility compared to other nominally anhydrous minerals in the lower mantle. To date, there have been no direct measurements of sound velocity on dense hydrous SiO2. In this study, shear wave velocity of hydrous SiO2 was measured at room temperature up to 100 GPa using Brillouin light scattering spectroscopy in a diamond anvil cell. Compared to anhydrous SiO2, the shear wave velocity of hydrous SiO2 is significantly lower, but the difference of them gradually diminishes with increasing pressure. Water incorporation drastically softens SiO2 at lower pressure, whereas progressively make it stiffer with increasing pressure. These results suggest that water incorporation into SiO2 could produce the elastically distinct region with negative shear wave velocity anomalies in the lower mantle. This observation indicates that SiO2 can be a likely cause of water-induced stiffening of silicate minerals with increasing pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Cavity-QED-controlled two-dimensional Moiré excitons without twisting</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67570-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67570-2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 08:23:35 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Francesco Troisi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hannes Hübener</dc:creator><dc:creator>Angel Rubio</dc:creator><dc:creator>Simone Latini</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67570-2</prism:doi><description>Abstract We propose an all-optical Moiré-like exciton confinement by means of spatially periodic optical cavities. Such periodic photonic structures can control the material properties by coupling the matter excitations to the confined photons and their quantum fluctuations. We develop a low energy non-perturbative quantum electro-dynamical description of strongly coupled excitons and photons at finite momentum transfer. We find that in the classical limit of a laser driven cavity the induced optical confinement directly emulates Moiré physics. In a dark cavity instead, the sole presence of quantum fluctuations of light generates a sizable renormalization of the excitonic bands and effective mass. We attribute these effects to long-range cavity-mediated exciton-exciton interactions which can only be captured in a non-perturbative treatment. With these findings we propose spatially structured cavities as a promising avenue for cavity material engineering.
Published: 2025-12-24T08:23:35+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.541 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Francesco Troisi; Hannes Hübener; Angel Rubio; Simone Latini&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67570-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67570-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.541 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract We propose an all-optical Moiré-like exciton confinement by means of spatially periodic optical cavities. Such periodic photonic structures can control the material properties by coupling the matter excitations to the confined photons and their quantum fluctuations. We develop a low energy non-perturbative quantum electro-dynamical description of strongly coupled excitons and photons at finite momentum transfer. We find that in the classical limit of a laser driven cavity the induced optical confinement directly emulates Moiré physics. In a dark cavity instead, the sole presence of quantum fluctuations of light generates a sizable renormalization of the excitonic bands and effective mass. We attribute these effects to long-range cavity-mediated exciton-exciton interactions which can only be captured in a non-perturbative treatment. With these findings we propose spatially structured cavities as a promising avenue for cavity material engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Active bridging hydride species in ZnO nanorods originated from hydroxyl and oxygen vacancy</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67625-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67625-4</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 04:42:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Benteng Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhonghan Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin-Ping Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ye Gu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linghai Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qin Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luming Peng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67625-4</prism:doi><description>The bridging hydride species (Zn-H-Zn) formed via H2 dissociation on ZnO surface play crucial roles in hydrogenation of unsaturated hydrocarbon to industrial production. Here, we find that the migration of surface hydroxyl in ZnO nanorods to nearby oxygen vacancy can also lead to the formation of this Zn-H-Zn species that are reactive to CO2 hydrogenation to methanol using solid-state NMR spectroscopy. Below 100 °C, bridging Zn-H-Zn species show no activity toward CO2 activation, while formate species are formed via the reaction of CO2 with surface hydroxyl groups. At 150-200 °C, Zn-H-Zn species hydrogenate formate to methoxy species. At 250 °C, methanol is produced and desorbs from the ZnO surface. These results confirm the methanol formation mechanism via formate and methoxy intermediates in the presence of active bridging Zn-H-Zn species. This work reveals a new source of active hydrogen species in ZnO nanorods without introducing H2, which is highly significant for heterogeneous hydrogenation reactions. The bridging hydride species (Zn–H–Zn), commonly formed through H₂ dissociation on ZnO surfaces, are essential for hydrogenating unsaturated hydrocarbons. Here, the authors show that surface hydroxyls on ZnO nanorods can migrate to nearby oxygen vacancies and similarly generate reactive Zn–H–Zn species, which they identify by solid-state NMR spectroscopy as active in CO₂ hydrogenation to methanol.
Published: 2025-12-23T04:42:17+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.540 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Benteng Song; Zhonghan Feng; Xin-Ping Wu; Ye Gu; Linghai Xie; Qin Zhu; Luming Peng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67625-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67625-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.540 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bridging hydride species (Zn-H-Zn) formed via H2 dissociation on ZnO surface play crucial roles in hydrogenation of unsaturated hydrocarbon to industrial production. Here, we find that the migration of surface hydroxyl in ZnO nanorods to nearby oxygen vacancy can also lead to the formation of this Zn-H-Zn species that are reactive to CO2 hydrogenation to methanol using solid-state NMR spectroscopy. Below 100 °C, bridging Zn-H-Zn species show no activity toward CO2 activation, while formate species are formed via the reaction of CO2 with surface hydroxyl groups. At 150-200 °C, Zn-H-Zn species hydrogenate formate to methoxy species. At 250 °C, methanol is produced and desorbs from the ZnO surface. These results confirm the methanol formation mechanism via formate and methoxy intermediates in the presence of active bridging Zn-H-Zn species. This work reveals a new source of active hydrogen species in ZnO nanorods without introducing H2, which is highly significant for heterogeneous hydrogenation reactions. The bridging hydride species (Zn–H–Zn), commonly formed through H₂ dissociation on ZnO surfaces, are essential for hydrogenating unsaturated hydrocarbons. Here, the authors show that surface hydroxyls on ZnO nanorods can migrate to nearby oxygen vacancies and similarly generate reactive Zn–H–Zn species, which they identify by solid-state NMR spectroscopy as active in CO₂ hydrogenation to methanol.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Earth’s foundational geological events stored in the fundamental mantle source of hotspots</title><link>https://doi.org/10.7185/geochemlet.2553</link><guid>10.7185/geochemlet.2553</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 08:59:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>B.J. Peters</dc:creator><dc:creator>F. Nauret</dc:creator><dc:creator>B. Moine</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. Castillo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geochemical Perspectives Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.7185/geochemlet.2553</prism:doi><description>The geochemical signatures of nearly all Earth’s volcanic hotspots converge on a common isotopic composition, which is often termed the ‘focal zone’ (FOZO) and has been associated with a shared deep mantle source. Yet, unlike other characteristic geochemical components of hotspots, the origin and nature of FOZO remain unclear. Geochemical evidence has been invoked to support both an ancient and a relatively young age for FOZO, and long lived radiogenic isotopic data support many potential geochemical relationships between geographically disparate hotspots. We examine this issue using the short lived 146Sm-142Nd isotopic system, which can identify diverse geochemical origins in the Hadean Eon, more than four billion years ago. Two hotspots with strong geochemical affinity to FOZO, the Crozet and Juan Fernandez hotspots, have statistically distinct 142Nd compositions, meaning that despite the similarity in their long lived radiogenic isotopic compositions, they must reflect different Hadean-aged geological heritages. Detailed analysis of the isotopic compositions of global hotspots using machine learning further reveals that FOZO is most likely not singular but rather represents a spectrum of discrete domains that each have histories dating back to the first 10 % of Earth’s history.
Published: 2025-12-23T08:59:15+00:00
Venue: Geochemical Perspectives Letters
Score: 0.538 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; B.J. Peters; F. Nauret; B. Moine; P. Castillo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geochemical Perspectives Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.7185/geochemlet.2553"&gt;10.7185/geochemlet.2553&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.538 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geochemical signatures of nearly all Earth’s volcanic hotspots converge on a common isotopic composition, which is often termed the ‘focal zone’ (FOZO) and has been associated with a shared deep mantle source. Yet, unlike other characteristic geochemical components of hotspots, the origin and nature of FOZO remain unclear. Geochemical evidence has been invoked to support both an ancient and a relatively young age for FOZO, and long lived radiogenic isotopic data support many potential geochemical relationships between geographically disparate hotspots. We examine this issue using the short lived 146Sm-142Nd isotopic system, which can identify diverse geochemical origins in the Hadean Eon, more than four billion years ago. Two hotspots with strong geochemical affinity to FOZO, the Crozet and Juan Fernandez hotspots, have statistically distinct 142Nd compositions, meaning that despite the similarity in their long lived radiogenic isotopic compositions, they must reflect different Hadean-aged geological heritages. Detailed analysis of the isotopic compositions of global hotspots using machine learning further reveals that FOZO is most likely not singular but rather represents a spectrum of discrete domains that each have histories dating back to the first 10 % of Earth’s history.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Fabrication of low-tortuosity thick electrodes with low material loss by temporally shaped ultraviolet femtosecond laser</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67702-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67702-8</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 13:16:20 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Junrui Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huixin Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruoxi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lan Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Richen Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengyao Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaofeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ran Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiangbiao Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qian Cheng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67702-8</prism:doi><description>Conventional battery electrodes exhibit high tortuosity, which severely impedes ion transport. This limitation restricts electrode thickness, decreases power density, and shortens battery lifetime. Fabricating through-holes can reduce tortuosity, but existing methods are generally complex with poor space utilization. Here, an array of high-density through-holes are fabricated by temporally shaped ultraviolet femtosecond laser. Using this technique, we achieve a 47:1 aspect ratio (6 μm in diameter), ensuring low material loss (&amp;lt;1%) for 280 μm-thick LiFePO4 (LFP) electrodes. The through-hole array reduces tortuosity of LFP thick electrodes by 19.1% (30 mg cm-2), 19.0% (40 mg cm-2), and 20.2% (60 mg cm-2), improving the specific energy density of batteries by 9.39%, 12.27%, 17.39% at 1 C, 1.5 C, and 2 C, respectively. It also boosts LFP power density by 100%–200% and doubles the cycling lifetime. This work demonstrates an effective approach for fabricating low-tortuosity thick electrodes, enhancing comprehensive performance of batteries. Conventional battery electrodes exhibit high tortuosity, impeding ion transport. Here, authors report the use of a temporally shaped ultraviolet femtosecond laser to create an array of high-density through-holes, reducing tortuosity in thick electrodes with low material loss (&amp;gt; 1%) in up to 280 μm-thick LiFePO4 electrodes, improving gravimetric energy density and power capabilities.
Published: 2025-12-23T13:16:20+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.538 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Junrui Wu; Huixin Guo; Ruoxi Wang; Lan Jiang; Xin Li; Jiang Zhang; Richen Jia; Mengyao Tian; Yu Liu; Xiaofeng Wang; Ran Zhao; Xiangbiao Liao; Qian Cheng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67702-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67702-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.538 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventional battery electrodes exhibit high tortuosity, which severely impedes ion transport. This limitation restricts electrode thickness, decreases power density, and shortens battery lifetime. Fabricating through-holes can reduce tortuosity, but existing methods are generally complex with poor space utilization. Here, an array of high-density through-holes are fabricated by temporally shaped ultraviolet femtosecond laser. Using this technique, we achieve a 47:1 aspect ratio (6 μm in diameter), ensuring low material loss (&amp;amp;lt;1%) for 280 μm-thick LiFePO4 (LFP) electrodes. The through-hole array reduces tortuosity of LFP thick electrodes by 19.1% (30 mg cm-2), 19.0% (40 mg cm-2), and 20.2% (60 mg cm-2), improving the specific energy density of batteries by 9.39%, 12.27%, 17.39% at 1 C, 1.5 C, and 2 C, respectively. It also boosts LFP power density by 100%–200% and doubles the cycling lifetime. This work demonstrates an effective approach for fabricating low-tortuosity thick electrodes, enhancing comprehensive performance of batteries. Conventional battery electrodes exhibit high tortuosity, impeding ion transport. Here, authors report the use of a temporally shaped ultraviolet femtosecond laser to create an array of high-density through-holes, reducing tortuosity in thick electrodes with low material loss (&amp;amp;gt; 1%) in up to 280 μm-thick LiFePO4 electrodes, improving gravimetric energy density and power capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Evolution of the Ballantrae Complex, SW Scotland: From the opening of the Iapetus to the Taconian-Grampian orogeny</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38570.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38570.1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 19:57:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Piero A.B. de Sampaio</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng-Xiang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luc S. Doucet</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hugo K.H. Olierook</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bryant Ware</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Rankenburg</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38570.1</prism:doi><description>The opening and closure of the Iapetus Ocean were key geodynamic events during the transition from Rodinia to Pangaea. Mantle-derived rocks formed during this period provide critical insights into the processes that shaped the mantle composition and structure during this tectonic transition. The Ballantrae Complex in Scotland is a well-preserved remnant of the Iapetus Ocean seafloor obducted during the Grampian Orogeny (ca. 475−465 Ma) and provides a window into the composition of the mantle at this period. The complex structure, and the overlying sedimentary rocks that cover the ophiolite, however, have made it difficult to parse the competing processes involved in the generation of the ophiolite. In this work we provide new whole-rock geochemical, Nd-Hf-Pb isotopic, and geochronological analyses on zircon, calcite, and titanite, guided by fieldwork observations, which help unravel the protracted evolution of the Ballantrae Complex. The oldest rock (571 ± 27 Ma) found in the region is a porphyritic dolerite at Bennane Head that contains zircon xenocrysts with a characteristic late Dalradian signature similar to that of the Southern Highlands Group. This dolerite is possibly an intrusion that occurred proximal to the Laurentian margin during the opening of the Iapetus Ocean. Our results reveal a two-stage evolution history for the development of the main body of the ophiolite. Rocks dated at ca. 500−480 Ma are light rare earth element (LREE)-depleted and have low Zr/Y ratios, reminiscent of depleted island-arc tholeiites and boninites, whereas rocks from ca. 475 Ma to 462 Ma are generally more LREE enriched and follow higher Zr/Y trends, akin to more evolved arc basalts and ocean-island basalt (OIB) compositions, including the Downan Point Lava Formation. We suggest that the late OIB-like basalts of the Ballantrae Complex are correlated with similar basalts in the Tyrone Volcanic Group of Northern Ireland and might be related to an intra-arc rifting event or the subduction of a slab window. The Ballantrae Complex, therefore, records a protracted history from the opening until the early-stage closure of the Iapetus Ocean.
Published: 2025-12-24T19:57:49+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.533 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Piero A.B. de Sampaio; Zheng-Xiang Li; Luc S. Doucet; Hugo K.H. Olierook; Bryant Ware; Kai Rankenburg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38570.1"&gt;10.1130/b38570.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.533 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening and closure of the Iapetus Ocean were key geodynamic events during the transition from Rodinia to Pangaea. Mantle-derived rocks formed during this period provide critical insights into the processes that shaped the mantle composition and structure during this tectonic transition. The Ballantrae Complex in Scotland is a well-preserved remnant of the Iapetus Ocean seafloor obducted during the Grampian Orogeny (ca. 475−465 Ma) and provides a window into the composition of the mantle at this period. The complex structure, and the overlying sedimentary rocks that cover the ophiolite, however, have made it difficult to parse the competing processes involved in the generation of the ophiolite. In this work we provide new whole-rock geochemical, Nd-Hf-Pb isotopic, and geochronological analyses on zircon, calcite, and titanite, guided by fieldwork observations, which help unravel the protracted evolution of the Ballantrae Complex. The oldest rock (571 ± 27 Ma) found in the region is a porphyritic dolerite at Bennane Head that contains zircon xenocrysts with a characteristic late Dalradian signature similar to that of the Southern Highlands Group. This dolerite is possibly an intrusion that occurred proximal to the Laurentian margin during the opening of the Iapetus Ocean. Our results reveal a two-stage evolution history for the development of the main body of the ophiolite. Rocks dated at ca. 500−480 Ma are light rare earth element (LREE)-depleted and have low Zr/Y ratios, reminiscent of depleted island-arc tholeiites and boninites, whereas rocks from ca. 475 Ma to 462 Ma are generally more LREE enriched and follow higher Zr/Y trends, akin to more evolved arc basalts and ocean-island basalt (OIB) compositions, including the Downan Point Lava Formation. We suggest that the late OIB-like basalts of the Ballantrae Complex are correlated with similar basalts in the Tyrone Volcanic Group of Northern Ireland and might be related to an intra-arc rifting event or the subduction of a slab window. The Ballantrae Complex, therefore, records a protracted history from the opening until the early-stage closure of the Iapetus Ocean.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>k-dependent modulation of intrinsic spin-orbit interaction in MoSe2 induced by proximity to amorphous Pb</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67833-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67833-y</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 18:34:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Fatima Alarab</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ján Minár</dc:creator><dc:creator>Procopios Constantinou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dhani Nafday</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aki Pulkkinen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thorsten Schmitt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoqiang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vladimir N. Strocov</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67833-y</prism:doi><description>Abstract Tuning the strength of spin-orbit interaction (SOI) is pivotal for developing next-generation spintronic and quantum devices. Proximity-induced SOI is a promising route toward this goal, but its experimental characterization with resolution in k -space using ARPES remains challenging. We advance previous ARPES investigations of proximity-induced SOI in graphene-based systems to transition-metal dichalcogenides (MoSe 2 ) in proximity to an amorphous overlayer of high- Z metal (Pb) whose disordered nature suppresses k -space mismatch at the interface. The use of soft-X-ray ARPES is instrumental for accessing MoSe 2 beneath the Pb layer. We introduce an approach to interpret the experimental data based on the identification of local SOI-derived band gaps—SOI hotspots—where the intrinsic SOI contribution, arising from the SOI field transfer from the overlayer to the host, is isolated from competing effects such as scalar (non-SOI) hybridization, interlayer interactions and Rashba-type splitting. We find that the proximity to Pb strongly enhances the intrinsic SOI as manifested by k -dependent increase of the band splitting in the SOI hotspots by up to several tens of meV. Tunability of this effect via Pb coverage provides versatile means for tailoring SOI to specific spintronic and quantum applications.
Published: 2025-12-24T18:34:17+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.524 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Fatima Alarab; Ján Minár; Procopios Constantinou; Dhani Nafday; Aki Pulkkinen; Thorsten Schmitt; Xiaoqiang Wang; Vladimir N. Strocov&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67833-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67833-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.524 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Tuning the strength of spin-orbit interaction (SOI) is pivotal for developing next-generation spintronic and quantum devices. Proximity-induced SOI is a promising route toward this goal, but its experimental characterization with resolution in k -space using ARPES remains challenging. We advance previous ARPES investigations of proximity-induced SOI in graphene-based systems to transition-metal dichalcogenides (MoSe 2 ) in proximity to an amorphous overlayer of high- Z metal (Pb) whose disordered nature suppresses k -space mismatch at the interface. The use of soft-X-ray ARPES is instrumental for accessing MoSe 2 beneath the Pb layer. We introduce an approach to interpret the experimental data based on the identification of local SOI-derived band gaps—SOI hotspots—where the intrinsic SOI contribution, arising from the SOI field transfer from the overlayer to the host, is isolated from competing effects such as scalar (non-SOI) hybridization, interlayer interactions and Rashba-type splitting. We find that the proximity to Pb strongly enhances the intrinsic SOI as manifested by k -dependent increase of the band splitting in the SOI hotspots by up to several tens of meV. Tunability of this effect via Pb coverage provides versatile means for tailoring SOI to specific spintronic and quantum applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Multistage germanium-rich sphalerite and wurtzite mineralization from the Qingshan carbonate-hosted Zn-Pb deposit, SW China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38269.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38269.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 20:27:39 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Runsheng Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dianwen Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38269.1</prism:doi><description>As a critical raw material for green technologies, germanium (Ge) is frequently concentrated in sphalerite (cubic ZnS). In nature, ZnS also occurs as its hexagonal polymorph, known as wurtzite; however, the distribution and incorporation of Ge in wurtzite still remains poorly understood. Using laser ablation−inductively coupled plasma−mass spectrometry analysis, this study investigates Ge distribution in sphalerite and wurtzite from three mineralization stages at the Qingshan carbonate-hosted Zn-Pb deposit, Southwest China. Stage I sphalerite (Sp-1) is enriched in Ge (109−672 ppm), whereas Stage II sphalerite (Sp-2) displays Ge-rich (dark Sp-2a; 174−899 ppm) and Ge-poor (light Sp-2b; ≤14.8 ppm) domains. Colloform wurtzite precipitated in Stage III (Wz-3) contains 58.0−722 ppm Ge, followed by euhedral sphalerite (Sp-3) with the highest Ge contents (467−1393 ppm). Combining transmission electron microscopy with trace element content correlations reveals that Ge is a structurally bound element in both sphalerite and wurtzite, incorporated via direct substitution mechanisms such as Ge2+ ↔ Zn2+ and Ge4+ + vacancy ↔ 2Zn2+. Ab initio calculations demonstrate no correlation between ZnS crystal structures (cubic/hexagonal) and Ge incorporation levels. The strongly positive δ34S values in Wz-3 (+17.2‰ to +19.2‰) suggest that the colloform texture is independent of low temperatures (&amp;lt;100 °C) and bacterial sulfate reduction. Increasing sulfur fugacity triggered wurtzite-to-sphalerite phase transition (Wz-3→Sp-3) and may have enhanced the incorporation of Ge in Sp-3. We propose a Ge enrichment process involving coupled dissolution-reprecipitation. This study highlights the importance of coupling micro- to nano-scale textural and chemical observations in ZnS minerals for understanding Ge enrichment.
Published: 2025-12-23T20:27:39+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.523 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lei Wang; Runsheng Han; Yan Zhang; Yi Chen; Dianwen Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38269.1"&gt;10.1130/b38269.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.523 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a critical raw material for green technologies, germanium (Ge) is frequently concentrated in sphalerite (cubic ZnS). In nature, ZnS also occurs as its hexagonal polymorph, known as wurtzite; however, the distribution and incorporation of Ge in wurtzite still remains poorly understood. Using laser ablation−inductively coupled plasma−mass spectrometry analysis, this study investigates Ge distribution in sphalerite and wurtzite from three mineralization stages at the Qingshan carbonate-hosted Zn-Pb deposit, Southwest China. Stage I sphalerite (Sp-1) is enriched in Ge (109−672 ppm), whereas Stage II sphalerite (Sp-2) displays Ge-rich (dark Sp-2a; 174−899 ppm) and Ge-poor (light Sp-2b; ≤14.8 ppm) domains. Colloform wurtzite precipitated in Stage III (Wz-3) contains 58.0−722 ppm Ge, followed by euhedral sphalerite (Sp-3) with the highest Ge contents (467−1393 ppm). Combining transmission electron microscopy with trace element content correlations reveals that Ge is a structurally bound element in both sphalerite and wurtzite, incorporated via direct substitution mechanisms such as Ge2+ ↔ Zn2+ and Ge4+ + vacancy ↔ 2Zn2+. Ab initio calculations demonstrate no correlation between ZnS crystal structures (cubic/hexagonal) and Ge incorporation levels. The strongly positive δ34S values in Wz-3 (+17.2‰ to +19.2‰) suggest that the colloform texture is independent of low temperatures (&amp;amp;lt;100 °C) and bacterial sulfate reduction. Increasing sulfur fugacity triggered wurtzite-to-sphalerite phase transition (Wz-3→Sp-3) and may have enhanced the incorporation of Ge in Sp-3. We propose a Ge enrichment process involving coupled dissolution-reprecipitation. This study highlights the importance of coupling micro- to nano-scale textural and chemical observations in ZnS minerals for understanding Ge enrichment.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Momentum space AC Josephson effect and intervalley coherence in multilayer graphene</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67838-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67838-7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 05:07:48 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Mainak Das</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunli Huang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67838-7</prism:doi><description>Electron transport driven by the phase coherence and interference of quantum many-body wavefunctions is a fascinating phenomenon with potential technological significance. Superconductivity, for example, enables dissipationless transport through macroscopic phase twisting, while charge-density waves show broadband noise and AC-DC interference once their phase is depinned. We identify an analogous phase-coherent dynamics in the intervalley-coherent (IVC) state frequently observed in rhombohedral multilayer graphene. We show that a static magnetic field drives an oscillating intervalley current, which produces an oscillating orbital magnetization and thereby a detectable AC Hall response. This mechanism is similar to the Josephson effect observed in superconductors but now happening in momentum space. In this analogy, the static magnetic field acts as the DC voltage, while the oscillating intervalley current is the AC Josephson current. We provide microscopic calculations of all the phase-number free-energy parameters in rhombohedral trilayer graphene, establishing this effect as an experimental signature of IVC order. The authors propose that when an intervalley coherent (IVC) state is subjected to a static magnetic field, it develops an oscillating orbital magnetization at microwave frequency, an effect analogous to a Josephson oscillation in momentum space. The effect could provide an experimental diagnostic for identifying the IVC state.
Published: 2025-12-24T05:07:48+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.521 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mainak Das; Chunli Huang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67838-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67838-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.521 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electron transport driven by the phase coherence and interference of quantum many-body wavefunctions is a fascinating phenomenon with potential technological significance. Superconductivity, for example, enables dissipationless transport through macroscopic phase twisting, while charge-density waves show broadband noise and AC-DC interference once their phase is depinned. We identify an analogous phase-coherent dynamics in the intervalley-coherent (IVC) state frequently observed in rhombohedral multilayer graphene. We show that a static magnetic field drives an oscillating intervalley current, which produces an oscillating orbital magnetization and thereby a detectable AC Hall response. This mechanism is similar to the Josephson effect observed in superconductors but now happening in momentum space. In this analogy, the static magnetic field acts as the DC voltage, while the oscillating intervalley current is the AC Josephson current. We provide microscopic calculations of all the phase-number free-energy parameters in rhombohedral trilayer graphene, establishing this effect as an experimental signature of IVC order. The authors propose that when an intervalley coherent (IVC) state is subjected to a static magnetic field, it develops an oscillating orbital magnetization at microwave frequency, an effect analogous to a Josephson oscillation in momentum space. The effect could provide an experimental diagnostic for identifying the IVC state.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Increased Continental Exposure as a Driver of Carbon Drawdown and Initiation of the Late Paleozoic Ice Age</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119356</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119356</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 09:41:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yinggang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuai Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Benjamin J. W. Mills</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrew S. Merdith</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongyun Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maoyan Zhu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119356</prism:doi><description>Abstract Earth experienced a long‐term cooling trend during the middle‐late Devonian, culminating in the Late Paleozoic Ice Age (LPIA)—the longest icehouse in Earth's history. The onset of glaciation has been attributed to CO 2 removal through silicate weathering, however previous carbon cycle models have failed to reproduce its timing. Here, we build a high‐resolution climate emulator using the Community Earth System Model and couple it with the SCION Earth Evolution model to better simulate continental weathering. This new framework successfully aligns modeled carbon drawdown and glaciation onset with geological proxy data. We find that additional cooling was driven by increased continental exposure during long‐term marine regression associated with Pangea's assembly, which boosted global weatherability and increased albedo. Our results highlight that changes in continental exposure are critical for long‐term climate evolution, and that high‐resolution climate models are needed to understand these impacts.
Published: 2025-12-23T09:41:36+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.512 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yinggang Zhang; Shuai Yuan; Benjamin J. W. Mills; Andrew S. Merdith; Yongyun Hu; Maoyan Zhu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119356"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119356&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.512 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Earth experienced a long‐term cooling trend during the middle‐late Devonian, culminating in the Late Paleozoic Ice Age (LPIA)—the longest icehouse in Earth&amp;#x27;s history. The onset of glaciation has been attributed to CO 2 removal through silicate weathering, however previous carbon cycle models have failed to reproduce its timing. Here, we build a high‐resolution climate emulator using the Community Earth System Model and couple it with the SCION Earth Evolution model to better simulate continental weathering. This new framework successfully aligns modeled carbon drawdown and glaciation onset with geological proxy data. We find that additional cooling was driven by increased continental exposure during long‐term marine regression associated with Pangea&amp;#x27;s assembly, which boosted global weatherability and increased albedo. Our results highlight that changes in continental exposure are critical for long‐term climate evolution, and that high‐resolution climate models are needed to understand these impacts.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Quantum sensing and metrology with free electrons</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67585-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67585-9</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 15:21:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Cruz I. Velasco</dc:creator><dc:creator>F. Javier García de Abajo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67585-9</prism:doi><description>Abstract The quantum properties of matter and radiation can be leveraged to surpass classical limits of sensing and detection. Quantum optics does so by creating and measuring nonclassical light. However, better performance requires higher photon-number states, which are challenging to generate and detect. Here, we combine photons and free electrons to solve the problem of generating and detecting high-number states well beyond those reachable with light alone and further show that an unprecedented level of sensitivity and resolution is gained based on the measurement of free-electron currents after suitably designed electron–light interactions. Our enabling ingredient is the strong electron–light coupling produced by aloof electron reflection on an optical waveguide, leading to the emission or absorption of a high number of guided photons by every single electron. We establish through rigorous theory that, by combining electron-beam splitters with two electron–waveguide interactions, the sensitivity to detect optical-phase changes can be enhanced dramatically using currently attainable technology. These results inaugurate a disruptive quantum technology relying on free electrons and their strong interaction with waveguided light.
Published: 2025-12-23T15:21:16+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.511 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Cruz I. Velasco; F. Javier García de Abajo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67585-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67585-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.511 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The quantum properties of matter and radiation can be leveraged to surpass classical limits of sensing and detection. Quantum optics does so by creating and measuring nonclassical light. However, better performance requires higher photon-number states, which are challenging to generate and detect. Here, we combine photons and free electrons to solve the problem of generating and detecting high-number states well beyond those reachable with light alone and further show that an unprecedented level of sensitivity and resolution is gained based on the measurement of free-electron currents after suitably designed electron–light interactions. Our enabling ingredient is the strong electron–light coupling produced by aloof electron reflection on an optical waveguide, leading to the emission or absorption of a high number of guided photons by every single electron. We establish through rigorous theory that, by combining electron-beam splitters with two electron–waveguide interactions, the sensitivity to detect optical-phase changes can be enhanced dramatically using currently attainable technology. These results inaugurate a disruptive quantum technology relying on free electrons and their strong interaction with waveguided light.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Tailored charging protocol for densified lithium deposition and stable initially anode-free lithium metal pouch cells</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66271-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66271-0</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 16:05:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yuanming Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoguang Yin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hexin Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuwei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Baohua Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guohua Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66271-0</prism:doi><description>The low mechanical strength and insufficient lithium-ion conductivity of solid-electrolyte interphase will incur inhomogeneous lithium deposition and eventually cause battery failure, hindering practical application of lithium metal batteries. Combining multiple characterization techniques and COMSOL simulation, here we report that the commonly-adopted constant current charge protocol would result in formation of highly porous lithium metal negative electrode, leading to severe parasitic reactions. To ameliorate this problem, we propose a middle peak current charge protocol with a peak current in the middle of charging step, which could guide the nucleation and growth of densified lithium deposition with the derived solid-electrolyte interphase possessing significantly improved mechanical strength and Li+ ion conductivity. Therefore, coin-type initially anode-free lithium metal batteries could be stably cycled for 80 cycles (with 3 hours of charging and state-of-charge of ~70%). A 1.5 Ah initially anode-free Li metal pouch cell which delivers a specific energy of 400 Wh kg-1 at 225 mA and with a capacity retention of 80% for 298 cycles (with 3 hours of charging and state-of-charge of 80%) is also demonstrated. The low mechanical strength and insufficient lithium-ion conductivity of the solid-electrolyte interphase result in inhomogeneous lithium deposition. Here, the authors propose a new middle peak current charging protocol, guiding the nucleation and growth of densified lithium deposition and a solid-electrolyte interphase with improved mechanical strength and Li+ ion conductivity.
Published: 2025-12-23T16:05:00+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.510 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yuanming Liu; Xiaoguang Yin; Hexin Guo; Shuwei Wang; Baohua Li; Guohua Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66271-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66271-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.510 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The low mechanical strength and insufficient lithium-ion conductivity of solid-electrolyte interphase will incur inhomogeneous lithium deposition and eventually cause battery failure, hindering practical application of lithium metal batteries. Combining multiple characterization techniques and COMSOL simulation, here we report that the commonly-adopted constant current charge protocol would result in formation of highly porous lithium metal negative electrode, leading to severe parasitic reactions. To ameliorate this problem, we propose a middle peak current charge protocol with a peak current in the middle of charging step, which could guide the nucleation and growth of densified lithium deposition with the derived solid-electrolyte interphase possessing significantly improved mechanical strength and Li+ ion conductivity. Therefore, coin-type initially anode-free lithium metal batteries could be stably cycled for 80 cycles (with 3 hours of charging and state-of-charge of ~70%). A 1.5 Ah initially anode-free Li metal pouch cell which delivers a specific energy of 400 Wh kg-1 at 225 mA and with a capacity retention of 80% for 298 cycles (with 3 hours of charging and state-of-charge of 80%) is also demonstrated. The low mechanical strength and insufficient lithium-ion conductivity of the solid-electrolyte interphase result in inhomogeneous lithium deposition. Here, the authors propose a new middle peak current charging protocol, guiding the nucleation and growth of densified lithium deposition and a solid-electrolyte interphase with improved mechanical strength and Li+ ion conductivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>All-optical temporal integration mediated by subwavelength heat antennas</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67726-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67726-0</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 09:35:28 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nikolaos Farmakidis</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ioannis Roumpos</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miltiadis Moralis-Pegios</dc:creator><dc:creator>Apostolos Tsakyridis</dc:creator><dc:creator>June Sang Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bowei Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuhan He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Samarth Aggarwal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nikos Pleros</dc:creator><dc:creator>Harish Bhaskaran</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67726-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract Optical computing systems deliver unrivalled processing speeds for scalar operations. Yet, integrated implementations have been constrained to low-dimensional tensor operations that fall short of the vector dimensions required for modern artificial intelligence. We demonstrate an all-optical neuromorphic computing system based on time division multiplexing, capable of processing input vectors exceeding 250,000 elements within a unified framework. The platform harnesses optically driven thermo-optic modulation in standing wave optical fields, with titanium nano-antennas functioning as wavelength-selective absorbers. Counterintuitively, the thermal time dynamics of the system enable simultaneous time integration of ultra-fast (50 GHz) signals and the application of programmable, non-linear activation functions, entirely within the optical domain. This unified framework constitutes a leap towards large-scale photonic computing that satisfies the dimensional requirements of AI workloads.
Published: 2025-12-23T09:35:28+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.506 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yi Zhang; Nikolaos Farmakidis; Ioannis Roumpos; Miltiadis Moralis-Pegios; Apostolos Tsakyridis; June Sang Lee; Bowei Dong; Yuhan He; Samarth Aggarwal; Nikos Pleros; Harish Bhaskaran&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67726-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67726-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.506 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Optical computing systems deliver unrivalled processing speeds for scalar operations. Yet, integrated implementations have been constrained to low-dimensional tensor operations that fall short of the vector dimensions required for modern artificial intelligence. We demonstrate an all-optical neuromorphic computing system based on time division multiplexing, capable of processing input vectors exceeding 250,000 elements within a unified framework. The platform harnesses optically driven thermo-optic modulation in standing wave optical fields, with titanium nano-antennas functioning as wavelength-selective absorbers. Counterintuitively, the thermal time dynamics of the system enable simultaneous time integration of ultra-fast (50 GHz) signals and the application of programmable, non-linear activation functions, entirely within the optical domain. This unified framework constitutes a leap towards large-scale photonic computing that satisfies the dimensional requirements of AI workloads.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Rivers accelerate and slow as temperatures rise</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02508-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41558-025-02508-6</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 10:02:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jordan Fields</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Climate Change</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41558-025-02508-6</prism:doi><description>Whether erosion is accelerating or decelerating along Arctic rivers has been unclear, but each trend has distinct implications for the vast amount of carbon stored in permanently frozen soils. Now, research demonstrates that warming air temperatures are driving divergent outcomes for Arctic rivers, causing some to erode their banks more rapidly while others slow down.
Published: 2025-12-24T10:02:09+00:00
Venue: Nature Climate Change
Score: 0.506 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jordan Fields&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Climate Change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02508-6"&gt;10.1038/s41558-025-02508-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.506 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether erosion is accelerating or decelerating along Arctic rivers has been unclear, but each trend has distinct implications for the vast amount of carbon stored in permanently frozen soils. Now, research demonstrates that warming air temperatures are driving divergent outcomes for Arctic rivers, causing some to erode their banks more rapidly while others slow down.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Deformation rates of the Minle-Damaying fault from folded fluvial terraces: Implications for kinematics of the Qilian Shan frontal thrust, NE Tibet</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38053.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38053.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 20:26:38 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Fuer Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenjun Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongli Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shiqi Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunsheng Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaxin Guo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38053.1</prism:doi><description>Fold-and-thrust belts typically develop in the frontal regions of compressive orogens and are characterized by significant fault offsets and fold deformation. Quantifying their geometry and kinematics is essential for understanding the fault behavior and mechanisms driving mountain uplift and propagation of shortening. This study analyzes a flight of five deformed fluvial terraces along the Tongziba River in the eastern Qilian Shan, northeastern Tibetan Plateau, utilizing high-resolution satellite imagery−derived digital elevation models and optically stimulated luminescence dating to elucidate the kinematics and slip rate of the Minle-Damaying fault. The fault-related folding analysis indicates that the Minle-Damaying fault has a listric geometry, with the fault dip decreasing from ∼40° near the surface to 16°−18° at ∼1 km depth. Vertical uplift rates based on terrace uplift are 1.34 ± 0.21 mm/yr for terrace T5 and 1.29 ± 0.27 mm/yr for T4, while shortening rates derived from balanced cross sections reach 1.94 ± 0.25 mm/yr and 1.87 ± 0.36 mm/yr, respectively. These values exceed those estimated from near-field fault scarp measurements, indicating that localized scarp data may underestimate true deformation. The similarity of shortening rates along different segments of the North Qilian Shan fault supports the interpretation that this fault system plays a key role in accommodating crustal shortening, uplift, and northward propagation of the Qilian Shan.
Published: 2025-12-23T20:26:38+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.504 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Fuer Yang; Wenjun Zheng; Dongli Zhang; Shiqi Wei; Yunsheng Yao; Jiaxin Guo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38053.1"&gt;10.1130/b38053.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.504 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fold-and-thrust belts typically develop in the frontal regions of compressive orogens and are characterized by significant fault offsets and fold deformation. Quantifying their geometry and kinematics is essential for understanding the fault behavior and mechanisms driving mountain uplift and propagation of shortening. This study analyzes a flight of five deformed fluvial terraces along the Tongziba River in the eastern Qilian Shan, northeastern Tibetan Plateau, utilizing high-resolution satellite imagery−derived digital elevation models and optically stimulated luminescence dating to elucidate the kinematics and slip rate of the Minle-Damaying fault. The fault-related folding analysis indicates that the Minle-Damaying fault has a listric geometry, with the fault dip decreasing from ∼40° near the surface to 16°−18° at ∼1 km depth. Vertical uplift rates based on terrace uplift are 1.34 ± 0.21 mm/yr for terrace T5 and 1.29 ± 0.27 mm/yr for T4, while shortening rates derived from balanced cross sections reach 1.94 ± 0.25 mm/yr and 1.87 ± 0.36 mm/yr, respectively. These values exceed those estimated from near-field fault scarp measurements, indicating that localized scarp data may underestimate true deformation. The similarity of shortening rates along different segments of the North Qilian Shan fault supports the interpretation that this fault system plays a key role in accommodating crustal shortening, uplift, and northward propagation of the Qilian Shan.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Impact of 3D Structure on Coseismic Coastal Land‐Level Change and Tsunami Generation in the Cascadia Subduction Zone</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117783</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl117783</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 10:18:30 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Audrey M. Dunham</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeonghyeop Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Erin Wirth</dc:creator><dc:creator>David Schmidt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Randall J. LeVeque</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yong Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Loyce M. Adams</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fred Pollitz</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl117783</prism:doi><description>Abstract Estimates of coseismic vertical displacements from past and potential future subduction zone earthquakes provide critical constraints on regional seismic and tsunami hazard. Many studies use elastic homogeneous half‐space models to calculate vertical displacements from a specified earthquake slip distribution, neglecting complexities of 3D structure in subduction zone settings. Here, we use 3D ground motion simulations of potential Cascadia Subduction Zone earthquakes to investigate the impact of realistic 3D Earth structure on estimated vertical displacements. We show that offshore uplift increases when including 3D structure due to high fault slip in low‐rigidity accretionary wedge sediments and coastal subsidence decreases due to higher rigidity material at depth. These larger offshore uplifts cause increased tsunami maximum wave heights, and coastal subsidence at paleoseismic sites decreases on average by ∼17 cm, or ∼60%, which can have important implications for the amplitude and extent of slip in earthquake scenarios developed based on paleoseismic data constraints.
Published: 2025-12-23T10:18:30+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.504 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Audrey M. Dunham; Jeonghyeop Kim; Erin Wirth; David Schmidt; Randall J. LeVeque; Yong Wei; Loyce M. Adams; Fred Pollitz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117783"&gt;10.1029/2025gl117783&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.504 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Estimates of coseismic vertical displacements from past and potential future subduction zone earthquakes provide critical constraints on regional seismic and tsunami hazard. Many studies use elastic homogeneous half‐space models to calculate vertical displacements from a specified earthquake slip distribution, neglecting complexities of 3D structure in subduction zone settings. Here, we use 3D ground motion simulations of potential Cascadia Subduction Zone earthquakes to investigate the impact of realistic 3D Earth structure on estimated vertical displacements. We show that offshore uplift increases when including 3D structure due to high fault slip in low‐rigidity accretionary wedge sediments and coastal subsidence decreases due to higher rigidity material at depth. These larger offshore uplifts cause increased tsunami maximum wave heights, and coastal subsidence at paleoseismic sites decreases on average by ∼17 cm, or ∼60%, which can have important implications for the amplitude and extent of slip in earthquake scenarios developed based on paleoseismic data constraints.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pomeranchuk instability from electronic correlations in CsTi3Bi5 kagome metal</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67037-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67037-4</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 16:05:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chiara Bigi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Matteo Dürrnagel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lennart Klebl</dc:creator><dc:creator>Armando Consiglio</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ganesh Pokharel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marta Zonno</dc:creator><dc:creator>François Bertran</dc:creator><dc:creator>Patrick Le Fèvre</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Jaouen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hulerich C. Tchouekem</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pascal Turban</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alessandro De Vita</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jill A. Miwa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Justin W. Wells</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongjin Oh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Riccardo Comin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ronny Thomale</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ilija Zeljkovic</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brenden R. Ortiz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephen D. Wilson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Giorgio Sangiovanni</dc:creator><dc:creator>Federico Mazzola</dc:creator><dc:creator>Domenico Di Sante</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67037-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract Electronic nematicity, the spontaneous breaking of rotational symmetry, has emerged as a key instability in correlated quantum systems. CsTi 3 Bi 5 , a kagome metal of the AV 3 Sb 5 (A = K, Rb, Cs) family, hosts rich unconventional electronic phases, yet the origin of its nematicity remains unsettled. Here, we combine polarization-dependent angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy with functional renormalization group calculations on a fully interacting ab initio model. We reveal an orbital-selective nematic deformation in the low-energy band structure and identify a finite angular momentum ( d -wave) Pomeranchuk instability driven by electronic correlations in specific orbital channels and detuning from Van Hove singularities. Our results establish a direct link between orbital selectivity and symmetry-breaking instabilities in CsTi 3 Bi 5 , providing a microscopic framework for nematic order in kagome systems.
Published: 2025-12-23T16:05:00+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.500 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chiara Bigi; Matteo Dürrnagel; Lennart Klebl; Armando Consiglio; Ganesh Pokharel; Marta Zonno; François Bertran; Patrick Le Fèvre; Thomas Jaouen; Hulerich C. Tchouekem; Pascal Turban; Alessandro De Vita; Jill A. Miwa; Justin W. Wells; Dongjin Oh; Riccardo Comin; Ronny Thomale; Ilija Zeljkovic; Brenden R. Ortiz; Stephen D. Wilson; Giorgio Sangiovanni; Federico Mazzola; Domenico Di Sante&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67037-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67037-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.500 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Electronic nematicity, the spontaneous breaking of rotational symmetry, has emerged as a key instability in correlated quantum systems. CsTi 3 Bi 5 , a kagome metal of the AV 3 Sb 5 (A = K, Rb, Cs) family, hosts rich unconventional electronic phases, yet the origin of its nematicity remains unsettled. Here, we combine polarization-dependent angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy with functional renormalization group calculations on a fully interacting ab initio model. We reveal an orbital-selective nematic deformation in the low-energy band structure and identify a finite angular momentum ( d -wave) Pomeranchuk instability driven by electronic correlations in specific orbital channels and detuning from Van Hove singularities. Our results establish a direct link between orbital selectivity and symmetry-breaking instabilities in CsTi 3 Bi 5 , providing a microscopic framework for nematic order in kagome systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Unveiling mechanistic patterns of copper-catalyzed radical bond formation through linear free energy relationship</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67770-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67770-w</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 14:34:53 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Guo-Xiong Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ji-Ren Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zeng Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miao-Jiong Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi-Zhou Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhong-Liang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin-Yuan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuo-Qing Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Hong</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67770-w</prism:doi><description>Copper-catalyzed radical transformations have seen extensive investigations over recent decades. Due to the complexity of controlling factors and the diversity of reaction components, accurately delineating the bond formation mechanisms—namely reductive elimination, outer-sphere radical substitution, and ion pair-type bond formation—poses a formidable challenge. This study reveals the linear free energy relationships (LFER) for the C–C bond formation of Cu-catalyzed radical transformations. Leveraging this discovery, we formulate an accurate LFER model for predicting radical bond formation mechanisms in this catalytic system. By establishing LFER scales for ligands, radicals, and nucleophiles, the bond formation mechanisms across 132,300 potential Cu-catalyzed radical transformations are revealed, offering a detailed mechanistic guide for future C–C bond designs. This research advances the mechanistic understanding of Cu-catalyzed radical transformations, providing systematic and quantitative insights into the mechanistic preference of radical bond formations. Due to the complexity of controlling factors and the diversity of reaction components, accurately delineating the bond formation mechanisms for copper-catalyzed radical transformations poses a challenge. Here, the authors reveal the linear free energy relationships for the C–C bond formation of Cu-catalyzed radical transformations.
Published: 2025-12-23T14:34:53+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.500 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Guo-Xiong Xu; Ji-Ren Liu; Zeng Gao; Miao-Jiong Tang; Yi-Zhou Sun; Zhong-Liang Li; Xin-Yuan Liu; Shuo-Qing Zhang; Xin Hong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67770-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67770-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.500 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copper-catalyzed radical transformations have seen extensive investigations over recent decades. Due to the complexity of controlling factors and the diversity of reaction components, accurately delineating the bond formation mechanisms—namely reductive elimination, outer-sphere radical substitution, and ion pair-type bond formation—poses a formidable challenge. This study reveals the linear free energy relationships (LFER) for the C–C bond formation of Cu-catalyzed radical transformations. Leveraging this discovery, we formulate an accurate LFER model for predicting radical bond formation mechanisms in this catalytic system. By establishing LFER scales for ligands, radicals, and nucleophiles, the bond formation mechanisms across 132,300 potential Cu-catalyzed radical transformations are revealed, offering a detailed mechanistic guide for future C–C bond designs. This research advances the mechanistic understanding of Cu-catalyzed radical transformations, providing systematic and quantitative insights into the mechanistic preference of radical bond formations. Due to the complexity of controlling factors and the diversity of reaction components, accurately delineating the bond formation mechanisms for copper-catalyzed radical transformations poses a challenge. Here, the authors reveal the linear free energy relationships for the C–C bond formation of Cu-catalyzed radical transformations.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Achieving trap-depth-tunable organic persistent luminescence through host energy-level engineering</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67529-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67529-3</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:46:46 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chenhan Zhan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cunjian Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rujun Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yajing Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zishuang Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenting Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jumpei Ueda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yixi Zhuang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rong-Jun Xie</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67529-3</prism:doi><description>Recent studies have indicated that traps play a crucial role in determining characteristics of organic persistent luminescence, yet constructing traps with controllable depth remains highly challenging. Herein, we propose a host energy-level engineering strategy, which enables precise control of trap depth. Using the Randall-Wilkins method, the trap depth can be tuned from 0.38 to 0.72 eV without altering emission wavelength and the result aligns well with density functional theory calculations. Specifically, a host-guest material namely CPND@DPEPO, which has a deep trap of ~ 0.72 eV, exhibits deep-blue persistent luminescence lasting for 27 hours and efficient energy storage over 14 days at room temperature. By utilizing these trap-containing materials as the emission layer in organic light-emitting diodes, we develop a pixel-programmable information storage device. This work establishes a fundamental principle for designing organic materials with controllable trap depth, potentially expanding their applications in night tracing, military communication and biological imaging. Zhan et al. report a host energy level engineering strategy to modulate trap depth in organic host-guest systems, achieving persistent luminescence up to 27 hours and energy storage for 14 days. 4×4 electroluminescent arrays based on the host-guest system demonstrate pixel-programmable information storage capabilities.
Published: 2025-12-23T00:46:46+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.500 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chenhan Zhan; Cunjian Lin; Rujun Yang; Yajing Wang; Zishuang Wu; Yang Li; Wenting Deng; Jumpei Ueda; Yixi Zhuang; Rong-Jun Xie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67529-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67529-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.500 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent studies have indicated that traps play a crucial role in determining characteristics of organic persistent luminescence, yet constructing traps with controllable depth remains highly challenging. Herein, we propose a host energy-level engineering strategy, which enables precise control of trap depth. Using the Randall-Wilkins method, the trap depth can be tuned from 0.38 to 0.72 eV without altering emission wavelength and the result aligns well with density functional theory calculations. Specifically, a host-guest material namely CPND@DPEPO, which has a deep trap of ~ 0.72 eV, exhibits deep-blue persistent luminescence lasting for 27 hours and efficient energy storage over 14 days at room temperature. By utilizing these trap-containing materials as the emission layer in organic light-emitting diodes, we develop a pixel-programmable information storage device. This work establishes a fundamental principle for designing organic materials with controllable trap depth, potentially expanding their applications in night tracing, military communication and biological imaging. Zhan et al. report a host energy level engineering strategy to modulate trap depth in organic host-guest systems, achieving persistent luminescence up to 27 hours and energy storage for 14 days. 4×4 electroluminescent arrays based on the host-guest system demonstrate pixel-programmable information storage capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>