<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 23:54:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Reactions, element transfer, and fracturing at ultramafic rock–sediment contacts: insights from reaction experiments at 500 °C and 1 GPa</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02283-9</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02283-9</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 02:27:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shunya Okino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Atsushi Okamoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ryosuke Oyanagi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yukiko Kita</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sando Sawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Muto</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02283-9</prism:doi><description>Metasomatic reactions affect the mechanical properties of the interface between the mantle wedge and a subducting plate. However, the controls on fluid-mediated reactions that occur at the interface, involving mass transfer, volume change, and deformation, are poorly constrained. In this study, we experimentally investigated metasomatic reactions at the boundary between mantle rocks (serpentinite and harzburgite) and sedimentary rocks (quartzite or pelitic schist) at 500&amp;nbsp;°C and 1 GPa, using an assembly with a core of metasedimentary rock sandwiched between serpentinite and harzburgite. In all experimental runs, talc formed preferentially in the mantle rocks. In experiments using quartzite, talc formed along pre-existing fractures in serpentinite and as a layer within harzburgite, while no obvious alteration occurred in the quartzite. In experiments using pelitic schist, talc formed within tree-like fractures in serpentinite, whereas in harzburgite it formed as a layer or wedge-like filling. In the pelitic schist, albite porphyroblasts were preferentially replaced by Mg-rich saponite. These observations and mass balance calculations indicate that: (1) the solid volume-decreasing reactions in serpentinite accompanying reaction-induced fracturing and solid volume-increasing reaction in harzburgite caused the contrasting textures in the two rock types; and (2) Al-bearing minerals in the sedimentary rocks absorbed Mg, which facilitated the overall progress of the Mg-releasing, talc-forming reactions in the mantle rocks. These results suggest that compositional heterogeneity in subducting sediments can produce variations in the talc distribution and rheological properties at the slab–mantle interface, potentially affecting the location of episodic tremor and slip in a mantle wedge corner.
Published: 2026-01-19T02:27:45+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.618 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shunya Okino; Atsushi Okamoto; Ryosuke Oyanagi; Yukiko Kita; Sando Sawa; Jun Muto&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02283-9"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02283-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.618 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metasomatic reactions affect the mechanical properties of the interface between the mantle wedge and a subducting plate. However, the controls on fluid-mediated reactions that occur at the interface, involving mass transfer, volume change, and deformation, are poorly constrained. In this study, we experimentally investigated metasomatic reactions at the boundary between mantle rocks (serpentinite and harzburgite) and sedimentary rocks (quartzite or pelitic schist) at 500&amp;amp;nbsp;°C and 1 GPa, using an assembly with a core of metasedimentary rock sandwiched between serpentinite and harzburgite. In all experimental runs, talc formed preferentially in the mantle rocks. In experiments using quartzite, talc formed along pre-existing fractures in serpentinite and as a layer within harzburgite, while no obvious alteration occurred in the quartzite. In experiments using pelitic schist, talc formed within tree-like fractures in serpentinite, whereas in harzburgite it formed as a layer or wedge-like filling. In the pelitic schist, albite porphyroblasts were preferentially replaced by Mg-rich saponite. These observations and mass balance calculations indicate that: (1) the solid volume-decreasing reactions in serpentinite accompanying reaction-induced fracturing and solid volume-increasing reaction in harzburgite caused the contrasting textures in the two rock types; and (2) Al-bearing minerals in the sedimentary rocks absorbed Mg, which facilitated the overall progress of the Mg-releasing, talc-forming reactions in the mantle rocks. These results suggest that compositional heterogeneity in subducting sediments can produce variations in the talc distribution and rheological properties at the slab–mantle interface, potentially affecting the location of episodic tremor and slip in a mantle wedge corner.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Carbon emissions along divergent plate boundaries modulate icehouse-greenhouse climates</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03097-0</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03097-0</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:02:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ben R. Mather</dc:creator><dc:creator>R. Dietmar Müller</dc:creator><dc:creator>Adriana Dutkiewicz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sabin Zahirovic</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03097-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract The exchange of carbon between oceanic plates, the deep Earth, and the atmosphere plays a significant role in modulating global climate. Icehouse-greenhouse climate fluctuations have been attributed to changes in palaeogeography and solid Earth degassing, particularly along continental arcs, to arc weathering and to the sequestration of carbon into oceanic carbonate-rich sediments. However, the proportions of these contributions and their effect on modulating global climate are poorly constrained. Here we show that the changing balance between volcanic outgassing and carbon sequestration into oceanic lithosphere is the key driver for major climate shifts. Combined volcanic arc, mid-ocean ridge and continental rift emissions exceed carbon sequestration during greenhouse climates. In contrast, oceanic plate sequestration exceeds emissions during icehouse climates. Our results challenge the long-held view that carbon degassing along volcanic arcs is the main contributor to atmospheric carbon, suggesting instead that mid-ocean ridge and rift degassing surpass arc emissions before 100 Ma.
Published: 2026-01-19T10:02:23+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.607 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ben R. Mather; R. Dietmar Müller; Adriana Dutkiewicz; Sabin Zahirovic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03097-0"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03097-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.607 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The exchange of carbon between oceanic plates, the deep Earth, and the atmosphere plays a significant role in modulating global climate. Icehouse-greenhouse climate fluctuations have been attributed to changes in palaeogeography and solid Earth degassing, particularly along continental arcs, to arc weathering and to the sequestration of carbon into oceanic carbonate-rich sediments. However, the proportions of these contributions and their effect on modulating global climate are poorly constrained. Here we show that the changing balance between volcanic outgassing and carbon sequestration into oceanic lithosphere is the key driver for major climate shifts. Combined volcanic arc, mid-ocean ridge and continental rift emissions exceed carbon sequestration during greenhouse climates. In contrast, oceanic plate sequestration exceeds emissions during icehouse climates. Our results challenge the long-held view that carbon degassing along volcanic arcs is the main contributor to atmospheric carbon, suggesting instead that mid-ocean ridge and rift degassing surpass arc emissions before 100 Ma.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Simultaneous sulfide oxidation and sulfate reduction for intracellular redox homeostasis under highly acidic conditions</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68508-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68508-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 09:06:02 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tipei Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongzhen Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lishan Niu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng Qi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinying Xi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68508-y</prism:doi><description>Sulfide oxidation and sulfate reduction are opposing processes in the microbial sulfur cycle, typically separated to avoid futile cycling. Here, we show that Mycobacterium sp. MAG-M116, identified from a biodesulfurization system under low pH, sulfate-rich, and H2S-overload conditions, simultaneously performs sulfide oxidation and assimilatory sulfate reduction (ASR), challenging this paradigm. Under aerobic conditions, MAG-M116 oxidizes sulfide to elemental sulfur, channeling electrons into the quinone pool to drive forward electron transfer for ATP synthesis and reverse electron transfer (RET) for NADPH generation. ASR, acting as a redox homeostat, captures electrons from leak-prone RET to mitigate electron leakage and reduce reactive oxygen species production by 57.5%. This bidirectional sulfur metabolism enables rapid sulfide detoxification while maintaining intracellular redox homeostasis, allowing Mycobacterium to dominate the community (abundance increasing from 3.5% to 99%). These findings reveal an adaptive strategy wherein coupled opposing redox reactions contribute to maintaining intracellular redox homeostasis under substrate-excess conditions. Microbial sulfur metabolism typically separates sulfide oxidation and sulfate reduction, but this limits adaptation under sulfide-overloaded conditions. Authors here discover a Mycobacterium species MAGM116, that simultaneously performs sulfide oxidation and assimilatory sulfate reduction, reducing ROS by 57.5% and maintaining intracellular redox homeostasis under extreme acidity
Published: 2026-01-19T09:06:02+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.579 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tipei Jia; Yongzhen Peng; Lishan Niu; Zheng Qi; Jinying Xi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68508-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68508-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.579 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sulfide oxidation and sulfate reduction are opposing processes in the microbial sulfur cycle, typically separated to avoid futile cycling. Here, we show that Mycobacterium sp. MAG-M116, identified from a biodesulfurization system under low pH, sulfate-rich, and H2S-overload conditions, simultaneously performs sulfide oxidation and assimilatory sulfate reduction (ASR), challenging this paradigm. Under aerobic conditions, MAG-M116 oxidizes sulfide to elemental sulfur, channeling electrons into the quinone pool to drive forward electron transfer for ATP synthesis and reverse electron transfer (RET) for NADPH generation. ASR, acting as a redox homeostat, captures electrons from leak-prone RET to mitigate electron leakage and reduce reactive oxygen species production by 57.5%. This bidirectional sulfur metabolism enables rapid sulfide detoxification while maintaining intracellular redox homeostasis, allowing Mycobacterium to dominate the community (abundance increasing from 3.5% to 99%). These findings reveal an adaptive strategy wherein coupled opposing redox reactions contribute to maintaining intracellular redox homeostasis under substrate-excess conditions. Microbial sulfur metabolism typically separates sulfide oxidation and sulfate reduction, but this limits adaptation under sulfide-overloaded conditions. Authors here discover a Mycobacterium species MAGM116, that simultaneously performs sulfide oxidation and assimilatory sulfate reduction, reducing ROS by 57.5% and maintaining intracellular redox homeostasis under extreme acidity&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Electric-field-driven CO2 polarization and bioinspired proton blocking unlock CO2 reduction in strong acid without metal cations</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68435-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68435-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:44:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Liwei Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenbin Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hui-Zi Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenjing Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoxue Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiang Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Di Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingming Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suqin Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuhua Lv</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huiqin Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linyu Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongyu Mou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xing Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuchen Hao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenxiu Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qunsheng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jibin Song</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68435-y</prism:doi><description>Metal-cation-free CO2 electroreduction (CO2R) in strong acidic media mitigates CO2 reactant losses, eliminates the risk of metal salt precipitation, and broadens device tolerance compared to acidic, neutral, or alkaline system using metal cations. However, such an acidic environment still poses challenges due to the inert and nonpolar nature of CO2 and intensely competitive hydrogen evolution reaction. Inspired by aquaporins in acidophiles, we engineer sharp-triangle Au nanostructures capped with a hexadecyltrimethylammonium chloride (CTAC) layer enriched with cationic sites. The intense local electric fields generated by the high-curvature tips of Au nanocatalyst polarize CO2 molecules, increasing their dipole moment to facilitate adsorption and activation. Meanwhile, the CTAC layer acts as a proton barrier, suppressing HER by mimicking the proton-blocking mechanism of aquaporins. This dual-function design enables continuous CO2R for 100 hours in a flow electrolyzer at pH 1.0, achieving an energy efficiency of 60% and near-unity Faradaic efficiency for CO production. This bioinspired strategy represents a significant advancement in CO2R technology by integrating rational catalyst design principles. Metal-cation-free CO2 electroreduction in strong acid minimizes reactant loss and salt precipitation yet struggles with CO2 activation and hydrogen evolution competition. Here, the authors report bioinspired sharp gold triangles with a proton-blocking layer that polarize CO2 and suppress hydrogen evolution.
Published: 2026-01-19T07:44:36+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.533 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Liwei Chen; Zhenbin Guo; Hui-Zi Huang; Wenjing Tian; Xiaoxue Chang; Qiang Hu; Di Liu; Chao Sun; Mingming Gao; Suqin Han; Shuhua Lv; Huiqin Zhou; Linyu Hu; Hongyu Mou; Xing Gao; Yuchen Hao; Wenxiu Yang; Qunsheng Li; Bo Wang; Jibin Song&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68435-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68435-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.533 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metal-cation-free CO2 electroreduction (CO2R) in strong acidic media mitigates CO2 reactant losses, eliminates the risk of metal salt precipitation, and broadens device tolerance compared to acidic, neutral, or alkaline system using metal cations. However, such an acidic environment still poses challenges due to the inert and nonpolar nature of CO2 and intensely competitive hydrogen evolution reaction. Inspired by aquaporins in acidophiles, we engineer sharp-triangle Au nanostructures capped with a hexadecyltrimethylammonium chloride (CTAC) layer enriched with cationic sites. The intense local electric fields generated by the high-curvature tips of Au nanocatalyst polarize CO2 molecules, increasing their dipole moment to facilitate adsorption and activation. Meanwhile, the CTAC layer acts as a proton barrier, suppressing HER by mimicking the proton-blocking mechanism of aquaporins. This dual-function design enables continuous CO2R for 100 hours in a flow electrolyzer at pH 1.0, achieving an energy efficiency of 60% and near-unity Faradaic efficiency for CO production. This bioinspired strategy represents a significant advancement in CO2R technology by integrating rational catalyst design principles. Metal-cation-free CO2 electroreduction in strong acid minimizes reactant loss and salt precipitation yet struggles with CO2 activation and hydrogen evolution competition. Here, the authors report bioinspired sharp gold triangles with a proton-blocking layer that polarize CO2 and suppress hydrogen evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Fluid‐Induced Fault Reactivations in Strike‐Slip Regimes: Temporal Constraints From GNSS and Seismological Analysis in the Peloritani Mts and Aeolian Archipelago (Central Mediterranean)</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gc012446</link><guid>10.1029/2025gc012446</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:46:46 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Danilo Messina</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marta Corradino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Graziella Barberi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Valentina Bruno</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mario Mattia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Domenico Patanè</dc:creator><dc:creator>Massimo Rossi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luciano Scarfì</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fabrizio Pepe</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gc012446</prism:doi><description>Abstract Fluids can modify the mechanical properties of rocks, including shear strength and strain behavior. We investigate the timing and magnitude of seismic events during fault motion in strike–slip systems across the Peloritani Mountains (northeastern Sicily) and Aeolian Archipelago using GNSS and seismological data analysis. Results reveal a strain partitioning along the already known crustal–scale NNW–SSE trending right–lateral transtensional deformation zone across the Peloritani Mts and its offshore extension up to Vulcano Island (defined as the Aeolian–Tindari–Letojanni Fault System, ATLFS), and WNW–ESE to NW–SE right–lateral transfer zones located in the western and central sectors of the Aeolian Archipelago. During 2021, the eastern block of the ATLFS underwent a significant velocity increase relative to the fixed western block, varying from 1.6 ± 0.28 mm/y (pre–2021 baseline) to 3.3 ± 0.99 mm/y. The acceleration of the eastern block of the ATLFS was accompanied by increased seismic strain release. It temporally correlated with the fastest ground inflation on Vulcano Island (central Aeolian Archipelago), which in turn coincided with the highest CO 2 flux emission on the island. This correlation, along with evidence of gas emissions in the Peloritani Mts, suggests that enhanced fluid pressure lubricated fault surfaces, thereby facilitating slip along the ATLFS. The fluid–induced slip acceleration was sustained for 9 months and was marked by frequent low–magnitude earthquakes.
Published: 2026-01-19T10:46:46+00:00
Venue: Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems
Score: 0.505 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Danilo Messina; Marta Corradino; Graziella Barberi; Valentina Bruno; Mario Mattia; Domenico Patanè; Massimo Rossi; Luciano Scarfì; Fabrizio Pepe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gc012446"&gt;10.1029/2025gc012446&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.505 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Fluids can modify the mechanical properties of rocks, including shear strength and strain behavior. We investigate the timing and magnitude of seismic events during fault motion in strike–slip systems across the Peloritani Mountains (northeastern Sicily) and Aeolian Archipelago using GNSS and seismological data analysis. Results reveal a strain partitioning along the already known crustal–scale NNW–SSE trending right–lateral transtensional deformation zone across the Peloritani Mts and its offshore extension up to Vulcano Island (defined as the Aeolian–Tindari–Letojanni Fault System, ATLFS), and WNW–ESE to NW–SE right–lateral transfer zones located in the western and central sectors of the Aeolian Archipelago. During 2021, the eastern block of the ATLFS underwent a significant velocity increase relative to the fixed western block, varying from 1.6 ± 0.28 mm/y (pre–2021 baseline) to 3.3 ± 0.99 mm/y. The acceleration of the eastern block of the ATLFS was accompanied by increased seismic strain release. It temporally correlated with the fastest ground inflation on Vulcano Island (central Aeolian Archipelago), which in turn coincided with the highest CO 2 flux emission on the island. This correlation, along with evidence of gas emissions in the Peloritani Mts, suggests that enhanced fluid pressure lubricated fault surfaces, thereby facilitating slip along the ATLFS. The fluid–induced slip acceleration was sustained for 9 months and was marked by frequent low–magnitude earthquakes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Controlled hierarchical self-assembly of hyperbolic paraboloid molecules into two-dimensional superstructures with second-harmonic generation characteristic</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68567-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68567-1</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 02:37:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hongbin Huo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunrong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuedong Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ju-An Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Tian</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68567-1</prism:doi><description>Hyperbolic paraboloid molecules, as systems with remarkable negative Gaussian curvature, have garnered considerable attention in chemistry and materials science due to their unique physicochemical properties. However, controlled organization of these curvature building blocks into well-defined superstructures remains challenging, primarily attributed to the constraints of their inherently contorted structures. Herein, we report the successful formation of hyperbolic-paraboloid-based crystalline two-dimensional (2D) superstructures in a controlled hierarchical manner. Employing a rigid yet flexible molecular design strategy, we guide the hyperbolic-paraboloid molecules through hierarchical self-assembly method from dimers to one-dimensional (1D) supramolecular columns and ultimately to 2D superstructures. Remarkably, these 2D superstructures exhibit strong second harmonic generation (SHG) with excellent polarization dependence. The strongest SHG signals were recorded at 1.5 × 105 for 2D HPS-MT and 1.1 × 105 for 2D HPS-Z, with polarization dependence of the SHG responses reaching 87.5% for 2D HPS-MT and 81% for 2D HPS-Z. Hyperbolic paraboloid molecules possess unique physicochemical properties. However, their controlled organization into well-defined superstructures remains challenging. Here, the authors report a macrocycle with hyperbolic paraboloid topology as building blocks to self-assemble a series of two-dimensional superstructures with four-level hierarchy in a controlled hierarchical manner.
Published: 2026-01-19T02:37:45+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.503 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hongbin Huo; Yunrong Zhang; Xuedong Xiao; Jia He; Ju-An Zhang; Wei Tian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68567-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68567-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.503 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hyperbolic paraboloid molecules, as systems with remarkable negative Gaussian curvature, have garnered considerable attention in chemistry and materials science due to their unique physicochemical properties. However, controlled organization of these curvature building blocks into well-defined superstructures remains challenging, primarily attributed to the constraints of their inherently contorted structures. Herein, we report the successful formation of hyperbolic-paraboloid-based crystalline two-dimensional (2D) superstructures in a controlled hierarchical manner. Employing a rigid yet flexible molecular design strategy, we guide the hyperbolic-paraboloid molecules through hierarchical self-assembly method from dimers to one-dimensional (1D) supramolecular columns and ultimately to 2D superstructures. Remarkably, these 2D superstructures exhibit strong second harmonic generation (SHG) with excellent polarization dependence. The strongest SHG signals were recorded at 1.5 × 105 for 2D HPS-MT and 1.1 × 105 for 2D HPS-Z, with polarization dependence of the SHG responses reaching 87.5% for 2D HPS-MT and 81% for 2D HPS-Z. Hyperbolic paraboloid molecules possess unique physicochemical properties. However, their controlled organization into well-defined superstructures remains challenging. Here, the authors report a macrocycle with hyperbolic paraboloid topology as building blocks to self-assemble a series of two-dimensional superstructures with four-level hierarchy in a controlled hierarchical manner.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>3D Printing of glasses with tunable UV–VIS–IR photoluminescence via low-temperature nanoscale engineering</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68523-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68523-z</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 12:54:54 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Fengxian Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingguo Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiping Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pengwei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ran Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daofu Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zeyu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengzheng Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zixiao Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zeping Ou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kuan Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jin He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Juan Du</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68523-z</prism:doi><description>Recent breakthroughs in three-dimensional (3D) printing of glass have enabled precise shaping of glass structures from macro to microscale while retaining their excellent physical and chemical properties. However, current functional developments in 3D printed glass primarily focus on leveraging its intrinsic optical transparency, with limited exploration of photonics application. 3D-printed glass functionalized by quantum dots (QDs) will hold great promise for creating desired photonic functional macro- and microstructures. However, voxel-precision customization of photonic functions in 3D printed glass by the monodispersed and size-controlled QDs is fundamentally conflict with the high-temperature sintering process required in 3D printed glass. Here, we present a simple, cost-effective method for creating a library of QDs functionalized 3D-printed glasses with tunable UV-VIS-IR photoluminescence (PL) by printing nanoporous glass (NG) followed by low-temperature nanoscale engineering of QDs growth. The integration of uniform and size-controlled QDs imparts 3D printed glass with fine tuning in composition, architecture, and photonic functionalities, while nanoscale engineering of the micro-environment enables precise tailoring of various QDs with enhanced optical performance and stability. This universal approach establishes a benchmark for 3D-printed functional glasses with advanced photonic capabilities. Here authors report 3D printed glass with tunable UV-to-IR emission. The method overcomes thermal limits, integrating various quantum dots into 3D printed complex glass structures to enable advanced photonic functionalities.
Published: 2026-01-19T12:54:54+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.499 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Fengxian Zhou; Yingguo Yang; Kai Feng; Zhiping Hu; Pengwei Wang; Ran Luo; Daofu Wu; Zeyu Zhang; Zhengzheng Liu; Zixiao Xue; Zeping Ou; Kuan Sun; Jin He; Juan Du&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68523-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68523-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.499 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent breakthroughs in three-dimensional (3D) printing of glass have enabled precise shaping of glass structures from macro to microscale while retaining their excellent physical and chemical properties. However, current functional developments in 3D printed glass primarily focus on leveraging its intrinsic optical transparency, with limited exploration of photonics application. 3D-printed glass functionalized by quantum dots (QDs) will hold great promise for creating desired photonic functional macro- and microstructures. However, voxel-precision customization of photonic functions in 3D printed glass by the monodispersed and size-controlled QDs is fundamentally conflict with the high-temperature sintering process required in 3D printed glass. Here, we present a simple, cost-effective method for creating a library of QDs functionalized 3D-printed glasses with tunable UV-VIS-IR photoluminescence (PL) by printing nanoporous glass (NG) followed by low-temperature nanoscale engineering of QDs growth. The integration of uniform and size-controlled QDs imparts 3D printed glass with fine tuning in composition, architecture, and photonic functionalities, while nanoscale engineering of the micro-environment enables precise tailoring of various QDs with enhanced optical performance and stability. This universal approach establishes a benchmark for 3D-printed functional glasses with advanced photonic capabilities. Here authors report 3D printed glass with tunable UV-to-IR emission. The method overcomes thermal limits, integrating various quantum dots into 3D printed complex glass structures to enable advanced photonic functionalities.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Author Correction: Marine phosphorus and atmospheric oxygen were coupled during the Great Oxidation Event</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68615-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68615-w</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 17:23:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Matthew S. Dodd</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haodong Gu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zihu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingcai Hou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aleksey Sadekov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Carlos Alberto Rosière</dc:creator><dc:creator>Franco Pirajno</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lewis Alcott</dc:creator><dc:creator>Frantz Ossa Ossa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Benjamin J. W. Mills</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrey Bekker</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68615-w</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-64194-4 , published online 15 October 2025
Published: 2026-01-19T17:23:00+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.496 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Matthew S. Dodd; Chao Li; Haodong Gu; Zihu Zhang; Mingcai Hou; Aleksey Sadekov; Carlos Alberto Rosière; Franco Pirajno; Lewis Alcott; Frantz Ossa Ossa; Benjamin J. W. Mills; Andrey Bekker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68615-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68615-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.496 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-64194-4 , published online 15 October 2025&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Zinc-based metal halide electrolytes for all-solid-state zinc-metal batteries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68394-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68394-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:13:35 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Sanlue Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Caiyun Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang-Peng Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dun Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuexia Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke-Zhao Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hui-Ming Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cuiping Han</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68394-4</prism:doi><description>The advancement of electrolyte materials is fundamental to the advancement of batteries. While zinc-metal batteries offer compelling advantages in safety, cost, and environmental sustainability, their performance is constrained by conventional aqueous electrolytes. All-solid-state zinc-ion electrolytes, which can inherently address the issues associated with aqueous electrolytes, are promising but yet currently in their nascent stages. Here, we show a composition engineering strategy to design metal halide-based zinc-ion electrolytes, and two types of zinc-based hybrid metal halides, C4N2H12ZnBr4 and C4N2H12ZnCl4, are obtained. Both solid-state electrolytes exhibit good electronically insulating properties and low zinc-migration energy barriers. C4N2H12ZnBr4 demonstrates a high ionic conductivity of 2.9×10−4 S cm−1 at 25 °C and a wide electrochemical window of ~3.74 V, making it suitable for all-solid-state zinc-metal batteries. The C4N2H12ZnBr4 electrolyte also establishes a tight contact with the zinc electrode, thereby minimizing interface resistance for enhanced electrochemical performance. As a result, an all-solid-state Zn | |I2 cell using C4N2H12ZnBr4 electrolyte achieves a high capacity retention of 234.5 mAh g−1 after 200 cycles at 0.2 mA cm−2, with a low capacity degradation rate of 0.056% per cycle. This work provides a design approach for metal halide-based solid electrolytes in zinc-metal batteries. Zinc-metal batteries are restricted by their inherent high activity of aqueous electrolyte. Here, authors report the design of a new class of zinc-based hybrid metal halide solid-state electrolytes, offering a promising avenue for all-solid-state zinc batteries.
Published: 2026-01-19T07:13:35+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.495 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sanlue Hu; Caiyun Chang; Yang-Peng Lin; Jie Li; Dun Wang; Xuexia Lu; Ke-Zhao Du; Hui-Ming Cheng; Cuiping Han&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68394-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68394-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.495 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advancement of electrolyte materials is fundamental to the advancement of batteries. While zinc-metal batteries offer compelling advantages in safety, cost, and environmental sustainability, their performance is constrained by conventional aqueous electrolytes. All-solid-state zinc-ion electrolytes, which can inherently address the issues associated with aqueous electrolytes, are promising but yet currently in their nascent stages. Here, we show a composition engineering strategy to design metal halide-based zinc-ion electrolytes, and two types of zinc-based hybrid metal halides, C4N2H12ZnBr4 and C4N2H12ZnCl4, are obtained. Both solid-state electrolytes exhibit good electronically insulating properties and low zinc-migration energy barriers. C4N2H12ZnBr4 demonstrates a high ionic conductivity of 2.9×10−4 S cm−1 at 25 °C and a wide electrochemical window of ~3.74 V, making it suitable for all-solid-state zinc-metal batteries. The C4N2H12ZnBr4 electrolyte also establishes a tight contact with the zinc electrode, thereby minimizing interface resistance for enhanced electrochemical performance. As a result, an all-solid-state Zn | |I2 cell using C4N2H12ZnBr4 electrolyte achieves a high capacity retention of 234.5 mAh g−1 after 200 cycles at 0.2 mA cm−2, with a low capacity degradation rate of 0.056% per cycle. This work provides a design approach for metal halide-based solid electrolytes in zinc-metal batteries. Zinc-metal batteries are restricted by their inherent high activity of aqueous electrolyte. Here, authors report the design of a new class of zinc-based hybrid metal halide solid-state electrolytes, offering a promising avenue for all-solid-state zinc batteries.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hidden Bioavailable Dissolved Organic Matter in the Deep Northwestern Pacific Ocean</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118190</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl118190</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 06:25:03 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yixian Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaolin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dalin Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuan Shen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl118190</prism:doi><description>Abstract The deep ocean is widely viewed as a stable reservoir of dissolved organic carbon (DOC) that is highly resistant to microbial degradation. However, this paradigm may be oversimplified. In a cross‐latitude survey conducted in the northwestern Pacific Ocean (155°E, 28.5°N–41.5°N), bulk DOC concentrations were found to be relatively constant below 1,000 m with little variation across latitude. Despite this stability, compound‐specific analyses revealed unexpectedly high abundance of hydrolyzable amino acids, up to 1.1% of DOC, at depths of 1,000–4,000 m between 30°N and 36°N. This amino acid enrichment, doubling the typical levels observed in other deep‐sea basins and comparable to upper ocean values, reflected episodic inputs of semi‐labile DOC likely derived from actively settling fresh particles. These findings reveal hidden reservoirs of bioavailable DOC in the deep ocean, a feature not captured by bulk analysis, challenging the conventional view of deep‐sea DOC as predominantly refractory and stable.
Published: 2026-01-18T06:25:03+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.494 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yixian Li; Tao Liu; Xiaolin Li; Dalin Shi; Yuan Shen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118190"&gt;10.1029/2025gl118190&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.494 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The deep ocean is widely viewed as a stable reservoir of dissolved organic carbon (DOC) that is highly resistant to microbial degradation. However, this paradigm may be oversimplified. In a cross‐latitude survey conducted in the northwestern Pacific Ocean (155°E, 28.5°N–41.5°N), bulk DOC concentrations were found to be relatively constant below 1,000 m with little variation across latitude. Despite this stability, compound‐specific analyses revealed unexpectedly high abundance of hydrolyzable amino acids, up to 1.1% of DOC, at depths of 1,000–4,000 m between 30°N and 36°N. This amino acid enrichment, doubling the typical levels observed in other deep‐sea basins and comparable to upper ocean values, reflected episodic inputs of semi‐labile DOC likely derived from actively settling fresh particles. These findings reveal hidden reservoirs of bioavailable DOC in the deep ocean, a feature not captured by bulk analysis, challenging the conventional view of deep‐sea DOC as predominantly refractory and stable.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Resolving energy transfer dynamics in Eu²⁺-activated multi-site phosphors via metaheuristic optimization and physics-informed neural networks</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68549-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68549-3</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:33:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Byung Do Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Young Hoon Seo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Young Cho</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jin Seok Hong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Woon Bae Park</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kee-Sun Sohn</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68549-3</prism:doi><description>Multi-exponential fitting has long been the standard approach for luminescence decay analysis, not because it is physically meaningful but because it offers empirical convenience. Rigorous nonlinear rate-equation models have existed for decades, yet their application was hindered by computational costs. Recent advances in artificial intelligence and high-performance computing now make such models tractable, enabling physically grounded analyses of complex relaxation dynamics. Here we examine donor–acceptor interactions in a prototypical Eu2+-activated multi-site phosphor (La2.544Ca1.456Si12O4.456N16.544:Eu2+) that exhibits wavelength quenching. Metaheuristic-driven Runge–Kutta simulations enabled the extraction of quantitative radiative and non-radiative rate constants, while physics-informed neural networks provided a complementary framework that independently reproduced the experimental decay dynamics. Both approaches converged to consistent rate constants, establishing donor–acceptor transfer as the dominant relaxation pathway over radiative and same-species interactions, offering quantitative, physics-based insight into complex dynamical behaviors beyond phosphors. Multi-exponential fitting is commonly used for photoluminescence (PL) decay despite its limited physical meaning, largely replacing computationally demanding rate-equation models. The authors use AI-assisted simulations and a physics-informed end-to-end framework to fit PL decay data, obtaining results consistent across both approaches.
Published: 2026-01-19T16:33:49+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.493 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Byung Do Lee; Young Hoon Seo; Min Young Cho; Jin Seok Hong; Woon Bae Park; Kee-Sun Sohn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68549-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68549-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.493 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multi-exponential fitting has long been the standard approach for luminescence decay analysis, not because it is physically meaningful but because it offers empirical convenience. Rigorous nonlinear rate-equation models have existed for decades, yet their application was hindered by computational costs. Recent advances in artificial intelligence and high-performance computing now make such models tractable, enabling physically grounded analyses of complex relaxation dynamics. Here we examine donor–acceptor interactions in a prototypical Eu2+-activated multi-site phosphor (La2.544Ca1.456Si12O4.456N16.544:Eu2+) that exhibits wavelength quenching. Metaheuristic-driven Runge–Kutta simulations enabled the extraction of quantitative radiative and non-radiative rate constants, while physics-informed neural networks provided a complementary framework that independently reproduced the experimental decay dynamics. Both approaches converged to consistent rate constants, establishing donor–acceptor transfer as the dominant relaxation pathway over radiative and same-species interactions, offering quantitative, physics-based insight into complex dynamical behaviors beyond phosphors. Multi-exponential fitting is commonly used for photoluminescence (PL) decay despite its limited physical meaning, largely replacing computationally demanding rate-equation models. The authors use AI-assisted simulations and a physics-informed end-to-end framework to fit PL decay data, obtaining results consistent across both approaches.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Short‐Term Effect of Mars‐Like Radiation on Carbon and Oxygen Isotope Compositions of Carbonates</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009384</link><guid>10.1029/2025je009384</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 07:57:01 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Nicolas Randazzo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sang‐Tae Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fabien Stalport</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maikel C. Rheinstäder</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hervé Cottin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Patrice Coll</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025je009384</prism:doi><description>Abstract The stable isotope composition of carbonates records the environmental formation conditions and can indicate potential biosignatures if formed biologically. Martian meteorite carbonates display unusually high δ 13 C values, not explained using known terrestrial processes. Carbonates have been detected across the martian surface, including observations by the Perseverance Rover in Jezero Crater. However, the stable isotope effects of surface irradiation in carbonate minerals remain poorly constrained. We investigated the influence of ultraviolet (UV) and non‐UV radiation on δ 13 C and δ 18 O values of carbonates under both Low Earth Orbit (LEO) and laboratory conditions. Three natural carbonates, two calcites (Iceland spar, Bolivian stromatolite) and one aragonite (French microbialite), were exposed to LEO UV and non‐UV radiation for 29 ± 4 hr. Laboratory experiments employed reagent‐grade calcite and natural aragonite exposed to UV under N 2 atmospheres at 6 mbar (4.5 torr) or 1.73 mbar (1.3 torr) for 24–70 hr in the McMaster Planetary Simulator (MPS). Most carbonates showed no significant radiation‐induced changes in their δ 13 C and δ 18 O values. However, three cases exhibited minor stable isotope shifts, including carbon and oxygen isotope effects in LEO and MPS carbonates, an oxygen isotope effect in the LEO‐UV‐exposed French microbialite, and carbon isotope effects in two UV‐exposed MPS calcites. These results suggest that short‐term radiation cannot explain the 13 C enrichment in martian meteorites but may initiate subtle stable isotope effects. This study establishes a baseline for radiation‐induced stable isotope effects in carbonates, informing interpretations of martian carbonate isotopes, biosignature preservation potential, and analyses planned for Mars Sample Return.
Published: 2026-01-19T07:57:01+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets
Score: 0.491 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Nicolas Randazzo; Sang‐Tae Kim; Fabien Stalport; Maikel C. Rheinstäder; Hervé Cottin; Patrice Coll&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009384"&gt;10.1029/2025je009384&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.491 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The stable isotope composition of carbonates records the environmental formation conditions and can indicate potential biosignatures if formed biologically. Martian meteorite carbonates display unusually high δ 13 C values, not explained using known terrestrial processes. Carbonates have been detected across the martian surface, including observations by the Perseverance Rover in Jezero Crater. However, the stable isotope effects of surface irradiation in carbonate minerals remain poorly constrained. We investigated the influence of ultraviolet (UV) and non‐UV radiation on δ 13 C and δ 18 O values of carbonates under both Low Earth Orbit (LEO) and laboratory conditions. Three natural carbonates, two calcites (Iceland spar, Bolivian stromatolite) and one aragonite (French microbialite), were exposed to LEO UV and non‐UV radiation for 29 ± 4 hr. Laboratory experiments employed reagent‐grade calcite and natural aragonite exposed to UV under N 2 atmospheres at 6 mbar (4.5 torr) or 1.73 mbar (1.3 torr) for 24–70 hr in the McMaster Planetary Simulator (MPS). Most carbonates showed no significant radiation‐induced changes in their δ 13 C and δ 18 O values. However, three cases exhibited minor stable isotope shifts, including carbon and oxygen isotope effects in LEO and MPS carbonates, an oxygen isotope effect in the LEO‐UV‐exposed French microbialite, and carbon isotope effects in two UV‐exposed MPS calcites. These results suggest that short‐term radiation cannot explain the 13 C enrichment in martian meteorites but may initiate subtle stable isotope effects. This study establishes a baseline for radiation‐induced stable isotope effects in carbonates, informing interpretations of martian carbonate isotopes, biosignature preservation potential, and analyses planned for Mars Sample Return.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Bioinspired flexible sensing-processing-visualizing integrated system towards tactile-visual signal recognition</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67316-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67316-0</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 10:02:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhen Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiasong Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yangbin Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Runzhen Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qinghong Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiayu Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kejia You</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongyang Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuan Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yue Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Deli Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liangxu Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fushan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Huang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67316-0</prism:doi><description>The rapid growth of flexible Internet of Things devices and multisensory human-computer interaction necessitates advanced systems capable of multimodal data sensing, processing, and feedback in an intelligent and energy-efficient manner. However, conventional architectures face limitations in energy inefficiency and interface mismatch due to the fragmented architecture of sensing, processing, and feedback units. Inspired by biological sensory systems, we introduce an MXene-based flexible dual-mode sensing-processing-visualizing integrated system into a single wearable device through a hierarchical MXene platform combining piezoelectric nanogenerators (mechanosensation), optoelectronic synapses (visual processing), and color-shifting quantum dot light-emitting diodes (optical feedback) with optimized interfaces. The wearable integrated system demonstrates tactile-visual signal recognition capabilities, biological self-protection behavior to adapt to environmental stimuli, dynamic trajectory recognition, and spatial positioning for motion recognition, which are highly desired in multisensory interaction. The bio-inspired material-architecture-function co-design strategy and integrated system promote the development of wearable neuromorphic hardware, edge computing, and intelligent human-machine interaction. The authors present a wearable MXene-based sensing-processing-visualizing integrated system for tactile-visual recognition, multisensory interaction, trajectory recognition, and real-time feedback.
Published: 2026-01-19T10:02:19+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.483 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhen Wang; Jiasong Lin; Yangbin Zhu; Runzhen Sun; Qinghong Lin; Xin Hu; Jiayu Sun; Yi Jiang; Kejia You; Hongyang Fu; Xuan Guo; Yue Wang; Deli Li; Liangxu Lin; Fushan Li; Yang Liu; Yi Zhao; Wei Huang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67316-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67316-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.483 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rapid growth of flexible Internet of Things devices and multisensory human-computer interaction necessitates advanced systems capable of multimodal data sensing, processing, and feedback in an intelligent and energy-efficient manner. However, conventional architectures face limitations in energy inefficiency and interface mismatch due to the fragmented architecture of sensing, processing, and feedback units. Inspired by biological sensory systems, we introduce an MXene-based flexible dual-mode sensing-processing-visualizing integrated system into a single wearable device through a hierarchical MXene platform combining piezoelectric nanogenerators (mechanosensation), optoelectronic synapses (visual processing), and color-shifting quantum dot light-emitting diodes (optical feedback) with optimized interfaces. The wearable integrated system demonstrates tactile-visual signal recognition capabilities, biological self-protection behavior to adapt to environmental stimuli, dynamic trajectory recognition, and spatial positioning for motion recognition, which are highly desired in multisensory interaction. The bio-inspired material-architecture-function co-design strategy and integrated system promote the development of wearable neuromorphic hardware, edge computing, and intelligent human-machine interaction. The authors present a wearable MXene-based sensing-processing-visualizing integrated system for tactile-visual recognition, multisensory interaction, trajectory recognition, and real-time feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Interfacial evaporation-induced localized multi-field coupling enables efficient co-recovery of freshwater and nitrates</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68365-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68365-9</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 13:16:56 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhen Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruibin Ning</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haobin Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiqiang Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiajun Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tian Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Swee Ching Tan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68365-9</prism:doi><description>Recovering nitrate from surface water can help address interconnected environmental, resource, and energy challenges. In response, we have developed a bioinspired photothermal evaporation platform (BPEP) for the efficient co-recovery of low-concentration nitrate and freshwater. Through the evaporation-induced localized multi-field (flowing, concentration, temperature) enhancement effect, the BPEP achieves a high nitrate recovery capacity of 8510 g m-2 under 1 sun illumination, approximately 6.7 times higher than under dark conditions. The flowing field is identified as the dominant contributor, accounting for nearly 80% of the total enhancement. In outdoor testing, BPEP demonstrates a high nitrate recovery of around 25.9 mg m-2, with a daily water collection rate of about 8.46 kg m-2. The extracted nitrate by BPEP can be further converted into nitrogen fertilizer via catalytic processes, thereby promoting plant growth. Overall,&amp;nbsp;BPEP offers an integrated strategy to recover nitrate and freshwater, addressing pressing issues in global sustainable development. Recovering nitrate from surface water can help address interconnected environmental, resource, and energy challenges. A bioinspired photothermal evaporation platform enabling the co-recovery of low-concentration nitrate and freshwater is proposed.
Published: 2026-01-19T13:16:56+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.481 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhen Yu; Lei Shi; Ruibin Ning; Haobin Huang; Zhiqiang Sun; Jiajun Chen; Tian Zhou; Swee Ching Tan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68365-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68365-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.481 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recovering nitrate from surface water can help address interconnected environmental, resource, and energy challenges. In response, we have developed a bioinspired photothermal evaporation platform (BPEP) for the efficient co-recovery of low-concentration nitrate and freshwater. Through the evaporation-induced localized multi-field (flowing, concentration, temperature) enhancement effect, the BPEP achieves a high nitrate recovery capacity of 8510 g m-2 under 1 sun illumination, approximately 6.7 times higher than under dark conditions. The flowing field is identified as the dominant contributor, accounting for nearly 80% of the total enhancement. In outdoor testing, BPEP demonstrates a high nitrate recovery of around 25.9 mg m-2, with a daily water collection rate of about 8.46 kg m-2. The extracted nitrate by BPEP can be further converted into nitrogen fertilizer via catalytic processes, thereby promoting plant growth. Overall,&amp;amp;nbsp;BPEP offers an integrated strategy to recover nitrate and freshwater, addressing pressing issues in global sustainable development. Recovering nitrate from surface water can help address interconnected environmental, resource, and energy challenges. A bioinspired photothermal evaporation platform enabling the co-recovery of low-concentration nitrate and freshwater is proposed.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Coral tissue depth reconstructed using skeletal microstructural offsets is driven by environmental stress</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03114-2</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03114-2</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 17:37:06 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>James Vincent</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tom Sheldrake</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03114-2</prism:doi><description>Abstract Coral tissue depth reflects organismal health and is influenced by environmental stressors. Reconstructing its past variability on inter- and intra-annual timescales, however, is not yet possible. Here we reconstructed seasonal tissue depth by measuring spatial offsets between growth cycles in corallite porosity and theca geochemistry (Lithium/Magnesium and Barium/Calcium ratios) of a single Siderastrea siderea core collected in Barbados. We show spatial offsets and thus tissue depth vary systematically over multiyear timescales, with decreasing values associated with thermal stress that impact extension rate and calcification in subsequent growth cycles. Large environmental disturbances such as the 2021 volcanic eruption of La Soufrière (St. Vincent) also impact tissue depth, in this case likely due to the release of bioactive metals upon ash deposition. This study investigates the robustness of the offset signal within a single colony and with further validation across multiple colonies could help reconstruct regional to global environmental and ecological stressors.
Published: 2026-01-19T17:37:06+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.478 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; James Vincent; Tom Sheldrake&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03114-2"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03114-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.478 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Coral tissue depth reflects organismal health and is influenced by environmental stressors. Reconstructing its past variability on inter- and intra-annual timescales, however, is not yet possible. Here we reconstructed seasonal tissue depth by measuring spatial offsets between growth cycles in corallite porosity and theca geochemistry (Lithium/Magnesium and Barium/Calcium ratios) of a single Siderastrea siderea core collected in Barbados. We show spatial offsets and thus tissue depth vary systematically over multiyear timescales, with decreasing values associated with thermal stress that impact extension rate and calcification in subsequent growth cycles. Large environmental disturbances such as the 2021 volcanic eruption of La Soufrière (St. Vincent) also impact tissue depth, in this case likely due to the release of bioactive metals upon ash deposition. This study investigates the robustness of the offset signal within a single colony and with further validation across multiple colonies could help reconstruct regional to global environmental and ecological stressors.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Floating science stations: my month on a research vessel looking after buoys</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00189-5</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-026-00189-5</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 12:01:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Christine Ro</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-026-00189-5</prism:doi><description>Physical oceanographer Melina M. Martinez finds ways to gather ocean data off the coast of Argentina. Physical oceanographer Melina M. Martinez finds ways to gather ocean data off the coast of Argentina.
Published: 2026-01-19T12:01:41+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.473 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Christine Ro&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00189-5"&gt;10.1038/d41586-026-00189-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.473 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical oceanographer Melina M. Martinez finds ways to gather ocean data off the coast of Argentina. Physical oceanographer Melina M. Martinez finds ways to gather ocean data off the coast of Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Enhanced proton conductivity in azole-functionalized three-dimensional crystalline covalent organic frameworks</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67873-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67873-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:53:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Aiping Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Changyan Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongliang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kuizhan Shao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunyi Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Qin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinlong Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongying Zang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhongmin Su</dc:creator><dc:creator>Donglin Jiang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67873-4</prism:doi><description>Proton conduction pathways and mechanisms in covalent organic frameworks (COFs) have long been obscured by polycrystalline disorder. Here we report a solvent-free melt-phase post-synthetic modification (PSM) strategy that enables precise functionalization of three-dimensional single-crystalline COFs while preserving crystallinity. This methodology overcomes the limitations of solvent-mediated PSM by operating above the melting point of azole reagents, ensuring homogeneous pore accessibility without solvent occlusion. Applied to archetypal imine-linked COF-300, the method achieves crystallographically resolved conversion of fragile imine bonds (C = N, 1.245 Å) into robust amine linkages (C–N, 1.415 Å), concurrently covalently anchoring of proton-conductive azoles (C–N, 1.487 Å) on the COFs skeleton. The resulting azole-functionalized COFs (COF-300-1,2,3-triazole, COF-300-1,2,4-triazole, COF-300-pyrazole) exhibit intrinsic anhydrous superprotonic conductivity reaching 4.35 × 10−3 S cm−1 at 170 °C, with low activation energies (0.153–0.186 eV). Atomic-resolution crystallography and DFT calculations reveal that rigid hydrogen-bond networks eliminate thermal barriers for proton hopping, establishing a definitive structure-property correlation for proton transport in single-crystal COFs. This work pioneers a versatile platform for functionalizing 3D crystalline porous materials under solvent-free conditions. Polycrystalline disorder often obscures the proton conduction pathways and mechanisms in covalent organic frameworks. Here, the authors functionalize 3D crystalline covalent organic frameworks under solvent-free conditions achieving anhydrous superprotonic conductivity and studied the mechanism behind.
Published: 2026-01-19T04:53:55+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.473 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Aiping Yao; Changyan Zhu; Jun Liu; Hongliang Xu; Kuizhan Shao; Chunyi Sun; Chao Qin; Xinlong Wang; Hongying Zang; Zhongmin Su; Donglin Jiang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67873-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67873-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.473 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proton conduction pathways and mechanisms in covalent organic frameworks (COFs) have long been obscured by polycrystalline disorder. Here we report a solvent-free melt-phase post-synthetic modification (PSM) strategy that enables precise functionalization of three-dimensional single-crystalline COFs while preserving crystallinity. This methodology overcomes the limitations of solvent-mediated PSM by operating above the melting point of azole reagents, ensuring homogeneous pore accessibility without solvent occlusion. Applied to archetypal imine-linked COF-300, the method achieves crystallographically resolved conversion of fragile imine bonds (C = N, 1.245 Å) into robust amine linkages (C–N, 1.415 Å), concurrently covalently anchoring of proton-conductive azoles (C–N, 1.487 Å) on the COFs skeleton. The resulting azole-functionalized COFs (COF-300-1,2,3-triazole, COF-300-1,2,4-triazole, COF-300-pyrazole) exhibit intrinsic anhydrous superprotonic conductivity reaching 4.35 × 10−3 S cm−1 at 170 °C, with low activation energies (0.153–0.186 eV). Atomic-resolution crystallography and DFT calculations reveal that rigid hydrogen-bond networks eliminate thermal barriers for proton hopping, establishing a definitive structure-property correlation for proton transport in single-crystal COFs. This work pioneers a versatile platform for functionalizing 3D crystalline porous materials under solvent-free conditions. Polycrystalline disorder often obscures the proton conduction pathways and mechanisms in covalent organic frameworks. Here, the authors functionalize 3D crystalline covalent organic frameworks under solvent-free conditions achieving anhydrous superprotonic conductivity and studied the mechanism behind.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Annual Weather Patterns Drive Large Pulses of Saline Submarine Groundwater Discharge and Major Summer Inputs of Nutrients to the South Atlantic Bight</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022962</link><guid>10.1029/2025jc022962</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 15:14:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jacob Vincent</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alicia M. Wilson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Willard S. Moore</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rachel K. Thomas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Angela N. Knapp</dc:creator><dc:creator>Susan Q. Lang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Samantha B. Joye</dc:creator><dc:creator>James L. Pinckney</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jc022962</prism:doi><description>Abstract Submarine groundwater discharge (SGD) is a significant source of nutrients to continental shelf waters. Increasing evidence suggests that most of this flow is saline (∼seawater salinity) and occurs across broad continental shelves, making it challenging to observe. Using new, cost‐effective heat‐tracer methods and geochemical analyses of subseafloor saline groundwater, we found that offshore saline SGD delivers repeated pulses of nutrients to the overlying South Atlantic Bight (SAB) water column in the summer. Thermal time‐series measurements were collected below the sandy seafloor 10–15 km offshore of Charleston, SC, during three consecutive summers. Up to seven pulses of saline SGD occurred each summer. Discharge velocities ranged from 1 to 8 cm day −1 . Pulses of SGD coincided with upwelling‐favorable winds related to annual shifts of the North Atlantic Subtropical High and with winds from storm activity. We observed spatial and temporal variability between SGD pulses from analogous sites 5–10 km apart. Cumulative summertime SGD in 2019 corresponded to 65%–70% of the radium‐based estimates of SGD offshore of South Carolina and was similar in magnitude to the input from regional river discharge. Thermal and geochemical analyses indicate two‐way seawater‐groundwater exchange across the seafloor, reflecting infiltration of seawater into the seafloor and SGD to overlying seawater. Geochemical analyses confirmed high nutrient concentrations in SGD compared to the overlying water column and river water. The δ 15 N of total dissolved nitrogen and δ 13 C of dissolved inorganic carbon in groundwater suggest significant contributions from mineralized organic matter with a geochemical composition distinct from overlying seawater.
Published: 2026-01-18T15:14:09+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans
Score: 0.468 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jacob Vincent; Alicia M. Wilson; Willard S. Moore; Rachel K. Thomas; Angela N. Knapp; Susan Q. Lang; Samantha B. Joye; James L. Pinckney&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022962"&gt;10.1029/2025jc022962&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.468 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Submarine groundwater discharge (SGD) is a significant source of nutrients to continental shelf waters. Increasing evidence suggests that most of this flow is saline (∼seawater salinity) and occurs across broad continental shelves, making it challenging to observe. Using new, cost‐effective heat‐tracer methods and geochemical analyses of subseafloor saline groundwater, we found that offshore saline SGD delivers repeated pulses of nutrients to the overlying South Atlantic Bight (SAB) water column in the summer. Thermal time‐series measurements were collected below the sandy seafloor 10–15 km offshore of Charleston, SC, during three consecutive summers. Up to seven pulses of saline SGD occurred each summer. Discharge velocities ranged from 1 to 8 cm day −1 . Pulses of SGD coincided with upwelling‐favorable winds related to annual shifts of the North Atlantic Subtropical High and with winds from storm activity. We observed spatial and temporal variability between SGD pulses from analogous sites 5–10 km apart. Cumulative summertime SGD in 2019 corresponded to 65%–70% of the radium‐based estimates of SGD offshore of South Carolina and was similar in magnitude to the input from regional river discharge. Thermal and geochemical analyses indicate two‐way seawater‐groundwater exchange across the seafloor, reflecting infiltration of seawater into the seafloor and SGD to overlying seawater. Geochemical analyses confirmed high nutrient concentrations in SGD compared to the overlying water column and river water. The δ 15 N of total dissolved nitrogen and δ 13 C of dissolved inorganic carbon in groundwater suggest significant contributions from mineralized organic matter with a geochemical composition distinct from overlying seawater.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Disruption of iron homeostasis sensitizes pancreatic cancer to irreversible electroporation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68585-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68585-z</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 23:15:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Linrong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shihao Su</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhishan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuguo Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yugang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hui Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Long</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Yin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Zhao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68585-z</prism:doi><description>Irreversible electroporation (IRE) is an ablative treatment for pancreatic cancer. It utilizes high-intensity pulsed electric field (PEF) to eliminate cancer cells by irreversibly disrupting cell membranes. However, PEF intensity is distributed unevenly; and cancer cells may survive in regions where it falls below the threshold of complete ablation. We find that iron-base metal organic framework nanoparticles (MOF-Fe) sensitize pancreatic cancer cells to PEF by inducing iron overload and ferroptosis. But their efficacy is diminished by the upregulation of ferritin heavy chain 1 (FTH1), a cellular response to restore iron homeostasis. C20U4V, a proteolysis targeting chimera (PROTAC) derived from arachidonic acid, degrades FTH1 and potentiates MOF-Fe-induced ferroptosis. It is then encapsulated in reactive oxygen species (ROS)-responsive micelles. The resulting M-C20U4V, when combined with MOF-Fe, efficiently induces ferroptosis and boosts PEF ablation efficacy. Therefore, disruption of iron homeostasis represents a potential strategy to lower the risk of tumor recurrence after IRE. Irreversible electroporation (IRE) is a treatment for pancreatic cancer, but its efficacy is limited by uneven electric field distribution. Here, the authors show that combining iron-based nanoparticles and PROTAC-mediated degradation of ferritin heavy chain 1 (FTH1) enhances IRE efficacy by inducing ferroptosis.
Published: 2026-01-19T23:15:26+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.465 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Linrong Li; Shihao Su; Zhishan Wang; Shuguo Sun; Yugang Wang; Hui Xu; Xin Long; Tao Yin; Jun Zhao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68585-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68585-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.465 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Irreversible electroporation (IRE) is an ablative treatment for pancreatic cancer. It utilizes high-intensity pulsed electric field (PEF) to eliminate cancer cells by irreversibly disrupting cell membranes. However, PEF intensity is distributed unevenly; and cancer cells may survive in regions where it falls below the threshold of complete ablation. We find that iron-base metal organic framework nanoparticles (MOF-Fe) sensitize pancreatic cancer cells to PEF by inducing iron overload and ferroptosis. But their efficacy is diminished by the upregulation of ferritin heavy chain 1 (FTH1), a cellular response to restore iron homeostasis. C20U4V, a proteolysis targeting chimera (PROTAC) derived from arachidonic acid, degrades FTH1 and potentiates MOF-Fe-induced ferroptosis. It is then encapsulated in reactive oxygen species (ROS)-responsive micelles. The resulting M-C20U4V, when combined with MOF-Fe, efficiently induces ferroptosis and boosts PEF ablation efficacy. Therefore, disruption of iron homeostasis represents a potential strategy to lower the risk of tumor recurrence after IRE. Irreversible electroporation (IRE) is a treatment for pancreatic cancer, but its efficacy is limited by uneven electric field distribution. Here, the authors show that combining iron-based nanoparticles and PROTAC-mediated degradation of ferritin heavy chain 1 (FTH1) enhances IRE efficacy by inducing ferroptosis.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Editorial Expression of Concern: En passant neurotrophic action of an intermediate axonal target in the developing mammalian CNS</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10080-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-10080-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 16:01:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marc Tessier-Lavigne</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-10080-4</prism:doi><description>Author notes Hao Wang Present address: Merck Research Labs, WP26-265, West Point, Pennsylvania, USA Marc Tessier-Lavigne Present address: Department of Biology, Stanford University, Stanford, California, USA Authors and Affiliations Howard HughesMedical Institute, Departments of Anatomy and of Biochemistry and Biophysics, University of California, San Francisco, California, USA Hao Wang &amp; Marc Tessier-Lavigne Authors Hao Wang View author publications
Published: 2026-01-19T16:01:41+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.455 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hao Wang; Marc Tessier-Lavigne&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10080-4"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-10080-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.455 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Author notes Hao Wang Present address: Merck Research Labs, WP26-265, West Point, Pennsylvania, USA Marc Tessier-Lavigne Present address: Department of Biology, Stanford University, Stanford, California, USA Authors and Affiliations Howard HughesMedical Institute, Departments of Anatomy and of Biochemistry and Biophysics, University of California, San Francisco, California, USA Hao Wang &amp;amp; Marc Tessier-Lavigne Authors Hao Wang View author publications&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Predictive design of stretchable electrodes with strain-insensitive performance via robotics- and machine learning-integrated workflow</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68484-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68484-3</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:44:40 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Haochen Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiongyu Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tianle Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Elizabeth A. Norris</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joshua M. Little</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiayue Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Snehi Shrestha</dc:creator><dc:creator>Edison Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shenqiang Ren</dc:creator><dc:creator>Teng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Po-Yen Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68484-3</prism:doi><description>Innovations in wearable electronics and soft robotics hinge significantly on the development of stretchable electrodes. However, a persistent challenge lies in balancing high stretchability, functional performance, and strain insensitivity. Conventional approaches, such as design of experiments and trial-and-error methods, often rely on time-consuming and labor-intensive experiments to navigate a vast and complex parameter space. To overcome this, we establish an integrated workflow merging robot-automated experimentation, machine learning predictions, and finite element simulations to enable the predictive design of stretchable electrodes with strain-insensitive performance. Initially, we construct an ensemble of artificial neural networks through a two-stage workflow, including feasible parameter space definition and active learning loops. Leveraging the prediction model and two-scale simulations, a microtextured stretchable nanocomposite is discovered as a strain-stable platform. Conformal deposition of a thin gold layer showcases metal-like conductivity, high resistance-insensitive stretchability, and robust durability. Furthermore, electrodeposition of Zn and MnO2 on gold conductors enables a stretchable Zn||MnO2 battery, exhibiting large elongation and strain-insensitive electrochemical performance. This machine intelligence-driven approach expedites the multi-parameter optimization of stretchable electrodes, achieving strain-invariant functionalities. Stretchable electrodes are essential for wearable electronics and soft robots, yet their performance always degrades under strain. Here, authors use robotics- and machine learning integrated workflow to design microtextured nanocomposites for strain-insensitive gold conductors and zinc batteries.
Published: 2026-01-19T11:44:40+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.454 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Haochen Yang; Qiongyu Chen; Tianle Chen; Yang Li; Elizabeth A. Norris; Joshua M. Little; Jiayue Sun; Snehi Shrestha; Edison Chen; Shenqiang Ren; Teng Li; Po-Yen Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68484-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68484-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.454 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innovations in wearable electronics and soft robotics hinge significantly on the development of stretchable electrodes. However, a persistent challenge lies in balancing high stretchability, functional performance, and strain insensitivity. Conventional approaches, such as design of experiments and trial-and-error methods, often rely on time-consuming and labor-intensive experiments to navigate a vast and complex parameter space. To overcome this, we establish an integrated workflow merging robot-automated experimentation, machine learning predictions, and finite element simulations to enable the predictive design of stretchable electrodes with strain-insensitive performance. Initially, we construct an ensemble of artificial neural networks through a two-stage workflow, including feasible parameter space definition and active learning loops. Leveraging the prediction model and two-scale simulations, a microtextured stretchable nanocomposite is discovered as a strain-stable platform. Conformal deposition of a thin gold layer showcases metal-like conductivity, high resistance-insensitive stretchability, and robust durability. Furthermore, electrodeposition of Zn and MnO2 on gold conductors enables a stretchable Zn||MnO2 battery, exhibiting large elongation and strain-insensitive electrochemical performance. This machine intelligence-driven approach expedites the multi-parameter optimization of stretchable electrodes, achieving strain-invariant functionalities. Stretchable electrodes are essential for wearable electronics and soft robots, yet their performance always degrades under strain. Here, authors use robotics- and machine learning integrated workflow to design microtextured nanocomposites for strain-insensitive gold conductors and zinc batteries.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Author Correction: Autophagy-deficient macrophages exacerbate cisplatin-induced mitochondrial dysfunction and kidney injury via miR-195a-5p-SIRT3 axis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68421-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68421-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:41:20 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yujia Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Longhui Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingchao Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fei Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuyun Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guangneng Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xi Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingqiu Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingping Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Younan Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanrong Lu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68421-4</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-47842-z , published online 23 May 2024
Published: 2026-01-19T14:41:20+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.452 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yujia Yuan; Longhui Yuan; Jingchao Yang; Fei Liu; Shuyun Liu; Lan Li; Guangneng Liao; Xi Tang; Jingqiu Cheng; Jingping Liu; Younan Chen; Yanrong Lu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68421-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68421-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.452 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-47842-z , published online 23 May 2024&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A nanosystem targeting tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1 for continuous spatiotemporal idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis therapy</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68398-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68398-0</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 12:54:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chuyu Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guihong Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanlin Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenguang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhongjie Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruiqi Ming</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shujun Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lili Huang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68398-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF), a progressive, life-threatening disease marked by excessive collagen deposition, severe tissue injury, and dysregulated oxidative stress, poses a major threat to human health. Despite clinical advances, current therapies have limited anti-fibrotic efficacy. Here we show a reactive oxygen species (ROS)-responsive nanosystem targeting tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1 (TIMP-1) for spatiotemporally precise IPF treatment. Anti-TIMP-1 antibodies (aT) are conjugated to mesenchymal stem cell-derived exosomes (Mexo) via ROS-cleavable phenylboronic acid ester linkers (cl), yielding Mexo-cl-aT. Following intratracheal administration, cl linkers are selectively cleaved by elevated ROS in the IPF microenvironment, enabling ROS scavenging while releasing Mexo and aT to mediate tissue repair and collagen degradation, respectively. We demonstrate that a single dose of Mexo-cl-aT exerts robust therapeutic efficacy against IPF in a bleomycin-induced mouse model of advanced-stage fibrosis, thereby validating this nanosystem as a safe and efficient candidate for next-generation IPF therapies.
Published: 2026-01-19T12:54:58+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.447 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chuyu Li; Guihong Lu; Hanlin Chen; Chenguang Wang; Zhongjie Wang; Ruiqi Ming; Shujun Liu; Lili Huang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68398-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68398-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.447 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF), a progressive, life-threatening disease marked by excessive collagen deposition, severe tissue injury, and dysregulated oxidative stress, poses a major threat to human health. Despite clinical advances, current therapies have limited anti-fibrotic efficacy. Here we show a reactive oxygen species (ROS)-responsive nanosystem targeting tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase-1 (TIMP-1) for spatiotemporally precise IPF treatment. Anti-TIMP-1 antibodies (aT) are conjugated to mesenchymal stem cell-derived exosomes (Mexo) via ROS-cleavable phenylboronic acid ester linkers (cl), yielding Mexo-cl-aT. Following intratracheal administration, cl linkers are selectively cleaved by elevated ROS in the IPF microenvironment, enabling ROS scavenging while releasing Mexo and aT to mediate tissue repair and collagen degradation, respectively. We demonstrate that a single dose of Mexo-cl-aT exerts robust therapeutic efficacy against IPF in a bleomycin-induced mouse model of advanced-stage fibrosis, thereby validating this nanosystem as a safe and efficient candidate for next-generation IPF therapies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Author Correction: Mutual inhibition between EPFL2 and auxin extends the intervals of periodic leaf morphogenesis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68518-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68518-w</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:14:18 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Toshiaki Tameshige</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takeshi Tsuchida</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuuki Matsushita</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuki Doll</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kaisei Maruyama</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takemoto Agui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mitsuhiro Aida</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroyuki Kasahara</dc:creator><dc:creator>Keiko U. Torii</dc:creator><dc:creator>Naoyuki Uchida</dc:creator><dc:creator>Koichi Fujimoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Momoko Ikeuchi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68518-w</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-65792-y , published online 13 November 2025
Published: 2026-01-19T06:14:18+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.445 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Toshiaki Tameshige; Takeshi Tsuchida; Yuuki Matsushita; Yuki Doll; Kaisei Maruyama; Takemoto Agui; Mitsuhiro Aida; Hiroyuki Kasahara; Keiko U. Torii; Naoyuki Uchida; Koichi Fujimoto; Momoko Ikeuchi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68518-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68518-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.445 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-65792-y , published online 13 November 2025&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>I’m going to halve my publication output. You should consider slow science, too</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-04061-w</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-025-04061-w</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:06:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Adrian Barnett</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-025-04061-w</prism:doi><description>If we don’t slow down, the research enterprise is going to crash, argues Adrian Barnett. If we don’t slow down, the research enterprise is going to crash, argues Adrian Barnett.
Published: 2026-01-19T11:06:26+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.437 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Adrian Barnett&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-04061-w"&gt;10.1038/d41586-025-04061-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.437 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we don’t slow down, the research enterprise is going to crash, argues Adrian Barnett. If we don’t slow down, the research enterprise is going to crash, argues Adrian Barnett.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>In-memory analog computing for non-negative matrix factorization</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68609-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68609-8</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 15:23:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shiqing Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yubiao Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pushen Zuo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongxiang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lunshuai Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniele Ielmini</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhong Sun</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68609-8</prism:doi><description>Non-negative matrix factorization (NMF) is a powerful technique for extracting latent structures from high-dimensional data, with applications spanning recommender systems, bioinformatics, and image processing. However, conventional digital hardware struggles to efficiently handle large-scale NMF due to computational complexity and memory bottlenecks. In this work, we propose an in-memory analog NMF solver based on a reconfigurable compact generalized inverse circuit, optimized using the conductance compensation principle. This circuit significantly reduces power consumption by minimizing the number of operational amplifiers while supporting various non-negative regression constraints. By integrating the alternating non-negative least squares algorithm, we achieve efficient and accurate factorization with a limited number of iterations. Experimental validation demonstrates the effectiveness of our analog NMF solver in real-world tasks, including image compression and collaborative filtering-based recommender systems, achieving high accuracy with orders-of-magnitude improvements in speed and energy efficiency over FPGA- and GPU-based digital solvers. These results highlight the potential of analog matrix computing for enabling real-time, large-scale NMF applications. The implementation of non-negative matrix factorization–a powerful technique finding hidden patterns in high-dimensional data – remains challenging due to computational complexity. Wang et al. report an in-memory analogy solver, enabling accurate factorization with fast operation at low power consumption.
Published: 2026-01-19T15:23:33+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.435 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shiqing Wang; Yubiao Luo; Pushen Zuo; Yongxiang Li; Lunshuai Pan; Daniele Ielmini; Zhong Sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68609-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68609-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.435 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-negative matrix factorization (NMF) is a powerful technique for extracting latent structures from high-dimensional data, with applications spanning recommender systems, bioinformatics, and image processing. However, conventional digital hardware struggles to efficiently handle large-scale NMF due to computational complexity and memory bottlenecks. In this work, we propose an in-memory analog NMF solver based on a reconfigurable compact generalized inverse circuit, optimized using the conductance compensation principle. This circuit significantly reduces power consumption by minimizing the number of operational amplifiers while supporting various non-negative regression constraints. By integrating the alternating non-negative least squares algorithm, we achieve efficient and accurate factorization with a limited number of iterations. Experimental validation demonstrates the effectiveness of our analog NMF solver in real-world tasks, including image compression and collaborative filtering-based recommender systems, achieving high accuracy with orders-of-magnitude improvements in speed and energy efficiency over FPGA- and GPU-based digital solvers. These results highlight the potential of analog matrix computing for enabling real-time, large-scale NMF applications. The implementation of non-negative matrix factorization–a powerful technique finding hidden patterns in high-dimensional data – remains challenging due to computational complexity. Wang et al. report an in-memory analogy solver, enabling accurate factorization with fast operation at low power consumption.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Forget formalism: mathematics was built on infighting and emotional turmoil</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00187-7</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-026-00187-7</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 11:01:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ananyo Bhattacharya</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-026-00187-7</prism:doi><description>A fast-paced book captures how theory and formal proof intertwined with the personal lives of prominent mathematicians. A fast-paced book captures how theory and formal proof intertwined with the personal lives of prominent mathematicians.
Published: 2026-01-19T11:01:26+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.432 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ananyo Bhattacharya&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00187-7"&gt;10.1038/d41586-026-00187-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.432 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fast-paced book captures how theory and formal proof intertwined with the personal lives of prominent mathematicians. A fast-paced book captures how theory and formal proof intertwined with the personal lives of prominent mathematicians.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Central amygdala single-nucleus atlas reveals chromatin and gene transcription dynamics in human alcohol use disorder</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68351-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68351-1</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 04:44:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Che Yu Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ahyeon Hwang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Delaney McRiley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jaywon Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Genevieve Thibodeau</dc:creator><dc:creator>Catharine Duman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiangyu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mario Skarica</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jensine Coudriet</dc:creator><dc:creator>Siwei Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rosemarie Terwilliger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexa-Nicole Sliby</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiawei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tuan Nguyen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yujing Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongyu Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ziheng Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yutong Lei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingxin Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jill R. Glausier</dc:creator><dc:creator>David A. Lewis</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joel Gelernter</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul E. Holtzheimer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hang Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongyu Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Summer Thompson</dc:creator><dc:creator>John H. Krystal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alicia Che</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jane R. Taylor</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Matthew J. Girgenti</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68351-1</prism:doi><description>Abstract Regulation of gene expression is a highly coordinated process in both the healthy and pathological brain with unique patterns across a multitude of cell types. Here we present a multi-omic single nucleus study of ~175,000 nuclei from 50 donors with alcohol use disorder (AUD) and control donors without AUD, profiling cell type specific gene expression and chromatin accessibility in the human central amygdala. We identify all major CNS cell types and neuronal subtypes and find inhibitory neurons are particularly affected by AUD. We find high numbers of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) including GABRA2 , GRM8 , and NCAM1 and show significant enrichment for AUD risk genes within these DEGs. We identified 51,431 cell type-specific, disease associated candidate cis -regulatory elements including an interneuron-associated set of chromatin loops at the AUD risk gene CALN1 . Transcription factor footprinting identified Kruppel-like factors upstream of AUD GWAS genes and DEGs. Finally, we also perform cell type-specific fine mapping for AUD GWAS to prioritize variants within functional genomic elements.
Published: 2026-01-19T04:44:55+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.428 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Che Yu Lee; Ahyeon Hwang; Delaney McRiley; Jaywon Lee; Genevieve Thibodeau; Catharine Duman; Xiangyu Zhang; Mario Skarica; Jensine Coudriet; Siwei Xu; Rosemarie Terwilliger; Alexa-Nicole Sliby; Jiawei Wang; Tuan Nguyen; Yujing Liu; Hongyu Li; Yi Dai; Ziheng Duan; Yutong Lei; Yingxin Lin; Jill R. Glausier; David A. Lewis; Joel Gelernter; Paul E. Holtzheimer; Ke Xu; Hang Zhou; Hongyu Zhao; Summer Thompson; John H. Krystal; Alicia Che; Jane R. Taylor; Jing Zhang; Matthew J. Girgenti&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68351-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68351-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.428 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Regulation of gene expression is a highly coordinated process in both the healthy and pathological brain with unique patterns across a multitude of cell types. Here we present a multi-omic single nucleus study of ~175,000 nuclei from 50 donors with alcohol use disorder (AUD) and control donors without AUD, profiling cell type specific gene expression and chromatin accessibility in the human central amygdala. We identify all major CNS cell types and neuronal subtypes and find inhibitory neurons are particularly affected by AUD. We find high numbers of differentially expressed genes (DEGs) including GABRA2 , GRM8 , and NCAM1 and show significant enrichment for AUD risk genes within these DEGs. We identified 51,431 cell type-specific, disease associated candidate cis -regulatory elements including an interneuron-associated set of chromatin loops at the AUD risk gene CALN1 . Transcription factor footprinting identified Kruppel-like factors upstream of AUD GWAS genes and DEGs. Finally, we also perform cell type-specific fine mapping for AUD GWAS to prioritize variants within functional genomic elements.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Author Correction: GWAS for systemic sclerosis identifies six novel susceptibility loci including one in the Fcγ receptor region</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68405-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68405-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 14:41:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yuki Ishikawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nao Tanaka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshihide Asano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Masanari Kodera</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuichiro Shirai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mitsuteru Akahoshi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Minoru Hasegawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takashi Matsushita</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kazuyoshi Saito</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sei-ichiro Motegi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hajime Yoshifuji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ayumi Yoshizaki</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tomohiro Kohmoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kae Takagi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Akira Oka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miho Kanda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshihito Tanaka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yumi Ito</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kazuhisa Nakano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroshi Kasamatsu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Akira Utsunomiya</dc:creator><dc:creator>Akiko Sekiguchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroaki Niiro</dc:creator><dc:creator>Masatoshi Jinnin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Katsunari Makino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takamitsu Makino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hironobu Ihn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Motohisa Yamamoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chisako Suzuki</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroki Takahashi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emi Nishida</dc:creator><dc:creator>Akimichi Morita</dc:creator><dc:creator>Toshiyuki Yamamoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manabu Fujimoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuya Kondo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daisuke Goto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takayuki Sumida</dc:creator><dc:creator>Naho Ayuzawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hidetoshi Yanagida</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tetsuya Horita</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tatsuya Atsumi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hirahito Endo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshihito Shima</dc:creator><dc:creator>Atsushi Kumanogoh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Hirata</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nao Otomo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroyuki Suetsugu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshinao Koike</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kohei Tomizuka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Soichiro Yoshino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoxi Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuji Ito</dc:creator><dc:creator>Keiko Hikino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Akari Suzuki</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yukihide Momozawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shiro Ikegawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshiya Tanaka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Osamu Ishikawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kazuhiko Takehara</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takeshi Torii</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shinichi Sato</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yukinori Okada</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tsuneyo Mimori</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fumihiko Matsuda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Koichi Matsuda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tiffany Amariuta</dc:creator><dc:creator>Issei Imoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Keitaro Matsuo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Masataka Kuwana</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yasushi Kawaguchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Koichiro Ohmura</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chikashi Terao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68405-4</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-44541-z , published online 31 January 2024
Published: 2026-01-19T14:41:19+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.428 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yuki Ishikawa; Nao Tanaka; Yoshihide Asano; Masanari Kodera; Yuichiro Shirai; Mitsuteru Akahoshi; Minoru Hasegawa; Takashi Matsushita; Kazuyoshi Saito; Sei-ichiro Motegi; Hajime Yoshifuji; Ayumi Yoshizaki; Tomohiro Kohmoto; Kae Takagi; Akira Oka; Miho Kanda; Yoshihito Tanaka; Yumi Ito; Kazuhisa Nakano; Hiroshi Kasamatsu; Akira Utsunomiya; Akiko Sekiguchi; Hiroaki Niiro; Masatoshi Jinnin; Katsunari Makino; Takamitsu Makino; Hironobu Ihn; Motohisa Yamamoto; Chisako Suzuki; Hiroki Takahashi; Emi Nishida; Akimichi Morita; Toshiyuki Yamamoto; Manabu Fujimoto; Yuya Kondo; Daisuke Goto; Takayuki Sumida; Naho Ayuzawa; Hidetoshi Yanagida; Tetsuya Horita; Tatsuya Atsumi; Hirahito Endo; Yoshihito Shima; Atsushi Kumanogoh; Jun Hirata; Nao Otomo; Hiroyuki Suetsugu; Yoshinao Koike; Kohei Tomizuka; Soichiro Yoshino; Xiaoxi Liu; Shuji Ito; Keiko Hikino; Akari Suzuki; Yukihide Momozawa; Shiro Ikegawa; Yoshiya Tanaka; Osamu Ishikawa; Kazuhiko Takehara; Takeshi Torii; Shinichi Sato; Yukinori Okada; Tsuneyo Mimori; Fumihiko Matsuda; Koichi Matsuda; Tiffany Amariuta; Issei Imoto; Keitaro Matsuo; Masataka Kuwana; Yasushi Kawaguchi; Koichiro Ohmura; Chikashi Terao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68405-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68405-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.428 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-023-44541-z , published online 31 January 2024&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hydrogel with cell-cell adhesion cues enhances neural regeneration</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68632-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68632-9</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 03:04:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiaoxuan Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuxuan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengke Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuxin Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yulan Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyue Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>He Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuewa Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rong Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoling Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>QianXing Zhuang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yifan Ge</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jue Ling</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yumin Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68632-9</prism:doi><description>Cell-cell adhesion is crucial for maintaining cell functions and the integrity of tissue structure in organisms. However, cell-cell adhesion cues have not been effectively replicated in biomaterials and the associated mechanisms that enhance neural regeneration remained largely unexplored. Here, we present a diffusive N-cadherin functionalized hydrogel system, which provided cell-cell adhesion cues to modulate intercellular communications to significantly promote the formation of active neural network via thrombospondin-1 mediated neural communication and activation of TGF-β/Smad pathway. The dynamic assembly of N-cadherin at cell-hydrogel interface driven by adhered neurons effectively facilitated the reshaping of membrane protrusions to initiate intercellular adherens junctions. Further, this hydrogel system promisingly promoted neurological function recovery in rats following traumatic brain injury. Our study provides the principle of replicating diffusive cell adhesion molecules to mediate cell-cell adhesion in hydrogels, which may have broad applications in developing engineered biomaterials aimed at modulating cell fates in regeneration of various tissues. Cell-cell adhesion plays critical roles in maintaining and regulating cellular functions. Here, authors present a diffusive N-cadherin functionalized hydrogel that provides cell-cell adhesion cues to modulate intercellular communication to promote neural regeneration for treatment of traumatic brain injury.
Published: 2026-01-19T03:04:44+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.422 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiaoxuan Tang; Shuxuan Zhang; Mengke Liu; Yuxin Liang; Yulan Fan; Xinyue Sun; He Chang; Xuewa Yang; Rong Zhu; Xiaoling Jin; QianXing Zhuang; Yifan Ge; Jue Ling; Yumin Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68632-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68632-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.422 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cell-cell adhesion is crucial for maintaining cell functions and the integrity of tissue structure in organisms. However, cell-cell adhesion cues have not been effectively replicated in biomaterials and the associated mechanisms that enhance neural regeneration remained largely unexplored. Here, we present a diffusive N-cadherin functionalized hydrogel system, which provided cell-cell adhesion cues to modulate intercellular communications to significantly promote the formation of active neural network via thrombospondin-1 mediated neural communication and activation of TGF-β/Smad pathway. The dynamic assembly of N-cadherin at cell-hydrogel interface driven by adhered neurons effectively facilitated the reshaping of membrane protrusions to initiate intercellular adherens junctions. Further, this hydrogel system promisingly promoted neurological function recovery in rats following traumatic brain injury. Our study provides the principle of replicating diffusive cell adhesion molecules to mediate cell-cell adhesion in hydrogels, which may have broad applications in developing engineered biomaterials aimed at modulating cell fates in regeneration of various tissues. Cell-cell adhesion plays critical roles in maintaining and regulating cellular functions. Here, authors present a diffusive N-cadherin functionalized hydrogel that provides cell-cell adhesion cues to modulate intercellular communication to promote neural regeneration for treatment of traumatic brain injury.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>