<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 23:33:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>The Mantle Fe3+/ΣFe Ratio Has Doubled Since the Early Archean</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66969-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66969-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 10:01:40 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiao-Xi Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen-Yong Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Taras Gerya</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia-Cheng Tian</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66969-1</prism:doi><description>Abstract How mantle redox state developed, particularly the mantle source associated with mid-ocean ridge-like settings, remains a subject of ongoing debate. Here, we employ thermodynamic-thermomechanical numerical simulations to explore the redox properties of melts formed under mid-ocean ridge-like settings in both Archean and modern conditions. By comparing these results with a global database of mid-ocean ridge-like rocks extending back to 3.8 Ga, we reconstruct the mantle’s redox evolution since the early Archean. Using the whole-rock Fe³⁺/ΣFe ratio as a robust redox proxy, derived from integrated numerical modeling and thermodynamic inversion, we find that the mantle’s average Fe³⁺/ΣFe ratio has approximately doubled since the early Archean. Our calculations further indicate that ultra-low-oxygen-fugacity mantle domains in modern oceanic lithosphere reflect an initially reduced origin rather than deeper or hotter melting. Our results suggest that Earth’s oxygenation and tectono-magmatic evolution may have been coupled.
Published: 2026-01-14T10:01:40+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.675 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiao-Xi Zhu; Wen-Yong Duan; Taras Gerya; Xin Zhou; Jia-Cheng Tian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66969-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66969-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.675 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract How mantle redox state developed, particularly the mantle source associated with mid-ocean ridge-like settings, remains a subject of ongoing debate. Here, we employ thermodynamic-thermomechanical numerical simulations to explore the redox properties of melts formed under mid-ocean ridge-like settings in both Archean and modern conditions. By comparing these results with a global database of mid-ocean ridge-like rocks extending back to 3.8 Ga, we reconstruct the mantle’s redox evolution since the early Archean. Using the whole-rock Fe³⁺/ΣFe ratio as a robust redox proxy, derived from integrated numerical modeling and thermodynamic inversion, we find that the mantle’s average Fe³⁺/ΣFe ratio has approximately doubled since the early Archean. Our calculations further indicate that ultra-low-oxygen-fugacity mantle domains in modern oceanic lithosphere reflect an initially reduced origin rather than deeper or hotter melting. Our results suggest that Earth’s oxygenation and tectono-magmatic evolution may have been coupled.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Paleoproterozoic ultrahigh-temperature metamorphic evolution of Alxa Block, North China Craton: Insights from phase equilibria modeling, garnet trace element chemistry, and monazite geochronology</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38583.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38583.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 19:49:25 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lei Zou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guang-Yu Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shu-Juan Jiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>M.P. Manu Prasanth</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ping-Hua Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing-Hui Guo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38583.1</prism:doi><description>Ultrahigh-temperature (UHT) granulites offer valuable insights into the extreme thermal and tectonic evolution of orogenic belts. However, pervasive diffusive re-equilibration, accessory mineral dissolution, and post-peak recrystallization under sustained UHT conditions typically obliterate peak petrographic, mineralogical, and geochronological signatures in these granulites. To address this preservation challenge, we integrate petrography, phase equilibrium modeling, garnet trace elements, and in situ monazite U-Pb geochronology for a pelitic granulite with a characteristic mineral assemblage of garnet + spinel in the Alxa Block of the western Khondalite Belt, North China Craton. Our work constrains the peak pressure-temperature (P-T) conditions of ∼990−1000 °C/8.4−9.4 kbar, with a near isobaric cooling retrograde P-T path for the pelitic granulite, which reveals two-stage garnet growth including a prograde peritectic and retrograde cooling phase. By establishing the growth sequence between monazite and garnet microdomains, we obtained the near-UHT metamorphic age of 1916 Ma from the inclusion-type monazites entrapped within garnet, shielding monazite’s chronometers from resetting and dissolution. The findings from this study, when integrated with regional metamorphic data, reveal a protracted suprasolidus heating duration of ∼40 m.y., followed by retrograde cooling, which persisted for &amp;gt;100 m.y. These findings indicate prolonged extreme thermal regimes in the lower crust and ultrahot collisional orogenic processes in the Khondalite Belt during the Paleoproterozoic.
Published: 2026-01-13T19:49:25+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.632 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lei Zou; Guang-Yu Huang; Shu-Juan Jiao; M.P. Manu Prasanth; Ping-Hua Liu; Jing-Hui Guo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38583.1"&gt;10.1130/b38583.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.632 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultrahigh-temperature (UHT) granulites offer valuable insights into the extreme thermal and tectonic evolution of orogenic belts. However, pervasive diffusive re-equilibration, accessory mineral dissolution, and post-peak recrystallization under sustained UHT conditions typically obliterate peak petrographic, mineralogical, and geochronological signatures in these granulites. To address this preservation challenge, we integrate petrography, phase equilibrium modeling, garnet trace elements, and in situ monazite U-Pb geochronology for a pelitic granulite with a characteristic mineral assemblage of garnet + spinel in the Alxa Block of the western Khondalite Belt, North China Craton. Our work constrains the peak pressure-temperature (P-T) conditions of ∼990−1000 °C/8.4−9.4 kbar, with a near isobaric cooling retrograde P-T path for the pelitic granulite, which reveals two-stage garnet growth including a prograde peritectic and retrograde cooling phase. By establishing the growth sequence between monazite and garnet microdomains, we obtained the near-UHT metamorphic age of 1916 Ma from the inclusion-type monazites entrapped within garnet, shielding monazite’s chronometers from resetting and dissolution. The findings from this study, when integrated with regional metamorphic data, reveal a protracted suprasolidus heating duration of ∼40 m.y., followed by retrograde cooling, which persisted for &amp;amp;gt;100 m.y. These findings indicate prolonged extreme thermal regimes in the lower crust and ultrahot collisional orogenic processes in the Khondalite Belt during the Paleoproterozoic.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Weak mantle wedge causes mantle exhumation punctuated with discrete oceanic crust in the Tyrrhenian basin</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68052-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68052-1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 16:54:42 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hao Su</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Leng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sascha Brune</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68052-1</prism:doi><description>The Continent-Ocean Transition (COT) in the young Tyrrhenian basin documents mantle exhumation punctuated with multiple episodes of discrete oceanic crust formation. This observation challenges prevailing models of magma-poor COTs, which typically describe mantle exhumation preceding the emplacement of oceanic crust. Notably, this COT developed without the conventional conditions associated with magma-poor rifted margins, such as slow rifting velocities and chemically depleted mantle sources. A key observation is the low shear-wave velocity observed in the uppermost mantle of the Tyrrhenian basin and its adjacent onshore regions, which correlates with subduction-related volcanism, suggesting the presence of a hydrated mantle wedge with low rheological strength. Here, we show that, based on 3D magmatic-thermomechanical numerical modeling, the episodic formation of oceanic crust within the Tyrrhenian basin’s COT results from the mechanical weakness of the mantle. The lithospheric mantle is exhumed to the surface through exhumation channels initiated within the weak mantle zone. The subsequent flow of partially molten mantle toward these channels leads to the development of multiple short-lived spreading centers. Our findings shed light on characteristics and mechanisms shaping the COT of marginal basins, where their opening is influenced by subduction processes. This study shows that the mechanical weakness of the mantle in the Tyrrhenian Basin leads to its exhumation at the continent-ocean transition, which is simultaneously punctuated with discrete oceanic crust.
Published: 2026-01-13T16:54:42+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.619 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hao Su; Wei Leng; Jie Liao; Sascha Brune&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68052-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68052-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.619 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Continent-Ocean Transition (COT) in the young Tyrrhenian basin documents mantle exhumation punctuated with multiple episodes of discrete oceanic crust formation. This observation challenges prevailing models of magma-poor COTs, which typically describe mantle exhumation preceding the emplacement of oceanic crust. Notably, this COT developed without the conventional conditions associated with magma-poor rifted margins, such as slow rifting velocities and chemically depleted mantle sources. A key observation is the low shear-wave velocity observed in the uppermost mantle of the Tyrrhenian basin and its adjacent onshore regions, which correlates with subduction-related volcanism, suggesting the presence of a hydrated mantle wedge with low rheological strength. Here, we show that, based on 3D magmatic-thermomechanical numerical modeling, the episodic formation of oceanic crust within the Tyrrhenian basin’s COT results from the mechanical weakness of the mantle. The lithospheric mantle is exhumed to the surface through exhumation channels initiated within the weak mantle zone. The subsequent flow of partially molten mantle toward these channels leads to the development of multiple short-lived spreading centers. Our findings shed light on characteristics and mechanisms shaping the COT of marginal basins, where their opening is influenced by subduction processes. This study shows that the mechanical weakness of the mantle in the Tyrrhenian Basin leads to its exhumation at the continent-ocean transition, which is simultaneously punctuated with discrete oceanic crust.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Widespread abyssal turbidites record megathrust earthquake-triggered landslides and coseismic deformation in the Cascadia subduction zone</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx6028</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adx6028</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 18:59:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jenna C. Hill</dc:creator><dc:creator>Janet T. Watt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Charles K. Paull</dc:creator><dc:creator>David W. Caress</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel S. Brothers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kevin Arizmendi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Roberto Gwiazda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jared Kluesner</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eve Lundsten</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nora M. Nieminski</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jason S. Padgett</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jennifer B. Paduan</dc:creator><dc:creator>George Snyder</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adx6028</prism:doi><description>Abyssal marine turbidites provide some of the longest and most spatially extensive records of subduction zone earthquake recurrence globally; however, correlation of these deposits over long distances and interpretation of synchronous emplacement requires both an understanding of the turbidite generating systems and precise dating. Here, we present an integrated suite of high-resolution bathymetry, subbottom profiles, and sediment cores from combined autonomous underwater vehicle, remotely operated vehicle, and ship-based studies at a key paleoseismic site in the southern Cascadia subduction zone. We demonstrate how widespread, earthquake-triggered landslides on the lower slope deposit discrete, proximal mass transport deposits (MTDs) that grade offshore into complex, interfingered abyssal turbidites, which correspond to records of megathrust earthquake history. We propose accretion and oversteepening of thrust folds on the lower slope both preconditions the slope to fail and provides a perpetual source of unstable material to fail during every earthquake cycle. Furthermore, we suggest the periodic and pervasive landsliding indicates coseismic deformation of the outer accretionary wedge during megathrust rupture.
Published: 2026-01-14T18:59:36+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.602 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jenna C. Hill; Janet T. Watt; Charles K. Paull; David W. Caress; Daniel S. Brothers; Kevin Arizmendi; Roberto Gwiazda; Jared Kluesner; Eve Lundsten; Nora M. Nieminski; Jason S. Padgett; Jennifer B. Paduan; George Snyder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx6028"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adx6028&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.602 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abyssal marine turbidites provide some of the longest and most spatially extensive records of subduction zone earthquake recurrence globally; however, correlation of these deposits over long distances and interpretation of synchronous emplacement requires both an understanding of the turbidite generating systems and precise dating. Here, we present an integrated suite of high-resolution bathymetry, subbottom profiles, and sediment cores from combined autonomous underwater vehicle, remotely operated vehicle, and ship-based studies at a key paleoseismic site in the southern Cascadia subduction zone. We demonstrate how widespread, earthquake-triggered landslides on the lower slope deposit discrete, proximal mass transport deposits (MTDs) that grade offshore into complex, interfingered abyssal turbidites, which correspond to records of megathrust earthquake history. We propose accretion and oversteepening of thrust folds on the lower slope both preconditions the slope to fail and provides a perpetual source of unstable material to fail during every earthquake cycle. Furthermore, we suggest the periodic and pervasive landsliding indicates coseismic deformation of the outer accretionary wedge during megathrust rupture.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Insights into the genetic diversity and metallogenic environment of rare-metal pegmatites in Bailongshan, Karakorum (western China)</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38621.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38621.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 19:49:32 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiaoyan Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liyun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinxiang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yahui Yue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Deng Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lin Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenqing Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenxi Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoling Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lin Ding</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38621.1</prism:doi><description>The closure of the Paleotethyan Ocean in the northern Tibetan Plateau formed a world-class rare-metal (Li, Be, Rb, Nb, and Ta) pegmatite metallogenic belt within the Dahongliutan-Hohxil-Songpan-Ganzi terrane of western China. Spodumene-rich pegmatites are hosted in the folded Triassic turbidites and often associated with Late Triassic−earliest Jurassic I-type and S-type granites. However, the parental affinity of these spodumene-rich pegmatites—whether from I-type or S-type granites—remains debated. To resolve this, we conducted geochronological and geochemical analyses of diorites, granodiorites, leucogranites, spodumene-free pegmatites, and spodumene-rich pegmatites from the Bailongshan ore field. Zircon U-Pb dating results show that the diorites intruded at 217.5−210.1 Ma, granodiorites at 212.3−205.0 Ma, and leucogranites at 215.1−196.2 Ma. Columbite U-Pb ages indicate emplacement of spodumene-free pegmatites at 220.9−196.2 Ma and spodumene-rich pegmatites at 213.9−194.7 Ma, suggesting synchronous magmatism during the Late Triassic−earliest Jurassic. Geochemically, hornblende-rich diorites and hornblende-bearing granodiorites show low SiO2, high MgO, metaluminous to weakly peraluminous signatures (Alumina Saturation Index [A/CNK] = 0.59−1.13), and calc-alkaline characteristics, and are typically I-type granites. Leucogranites containing muscovite, garnet, and tourmaline exhibit high SiO2, low MgO, strongly peraluminous signatures (A/CNK = 1.16−1.34), and high-K, calc-alkaline affinities. They are typically S-type granites, which show higher Rb/Sr and Rb/Ba ratios, indicating sedimentary rocks as their protoliths. Isotopically, S-type granites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.7111−0.7149; εNd(t) = −11.0 to −10.3; εHf(t) = −8.4 to −2.7] and pegmatites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.7182−0.7189; εNd(t) = −11.7 to −10.7; εHf(t) = −9.2 to −0.9] exhibit more enriched isotope compositions, similar to those of the wall-rock turbidites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.70803−0.7173; εNd(t) = −13.1 to −3.2], and are distinctly different from I-type granites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.7084−0.7098; εNd(t) = −6.8 to −6.3; εHf(t) = −6.2 to +0.9]. This implies that the pegmatites are derived from the S-type granites, not the I-type granites. The low temperatures (&amp;lt;750 °C) estimated by the Ti-in-zircon thermometer for both I- and S-type granites suggest that S-type granites were likely derived from fluid-fluxed melting of the Triassic turbidites, favoring extraction of rare metals from staurolite, biotite, and muscovite in metaturbidites during anatexis. The coeval I-type granites provided the external heat and exotic volatiles, promoting staurolite and mica breakdown in the metaturbidites and thus facilitating the release of rare metals into the S-type leucogranitic melts. This suggests that although rare-metal pegmatite mineralization in Bailongshan is primarily related to S-type granites, I-type granites also played a contributing role. The formation of the coeval Late Triassic−earliest Jurassic barren I-type and fertile S-type granites in Bailongshan is attributed to final bidirectional subduction, slab rollback, and delamination of the Paleotethyan oceanic slab.
Published: 2026-01-13T19:49:32+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.588 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiaoyan Xu; Liyun Zhang; Jinxiang Li; Yahui Yue; Deng Zeng; Lin Liu; Fang Xu; Wenqing Ding; Jing Xie; Chao Wang; Wenxi Zhao; Tao Chen; Xiaoling Wei; Lin Ding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38621.1"&gt;10.1130/b38621.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.588 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The closure of the Paleotethyan Ocean in the northern Tibetan Plateau formed a world-class rare-metal (Li, Be, Rb, Nb, and Ta) pegmatite metallogenic belt within the Dahongliutan-Hohxil-Songpan-Ganzi terrane of western China. Spodumene-rich pegmatites are hosted in the folded Triassic turbidites and often associated with Late Triassic−earliest Jurassic I-type and S-type granites. However, the parental affinity of these spodumene-rich pegmatites—whether from I-type or S-type granites—remains debated. To resolve this, we conducted geochronological and geochemical analyses of diorites, granodiorites, leucogranites, spodumene-free pegmatites, and spodumene-rich pegmatites from the Bailongshan ore field. Zircon U-Pb dating results show that the diorites intruded at 217.5−210.1 Ma, granodiorites at 212.3−205.0 Ma, and leucogranites at 215.1−196.2 Ma. Columbite U-Pb ages indicate emplacement of spodumene-free pegmatites at 220.9−196.2 Ma and spodumene-rich pegmatites at 213.9−194.7 Ma, suggesting synchronous magmatism during the Late Triassic−earliest Jurassic. Geochemically, hornblende-rich diorites and hornblende-bearing granodiorites show low SiO2, high MgO, metaluminous to weakly peraluminous signatures (Alumina Saturation Index [A/CNK] = 0.59−1.13), and calc-alkaline characteristics, and are typically I-type granites. Leucogranites containing muscovite, garnet, and tourmaline exhibit high SiO2, low MgO, strongly peraluminous signatures (A/CNK = 1.16−1.34), and high-K, calc-alkaline affinities. They are typically S-type granites, which show higher Rb/Sr and Rb/Ba ratios, indicating sedimentary rocks as their protoliths. Isotopically, S-type granites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.7111−0.7149; εNd(t) = −11.0 to −10.3; εHf(t) = −8.4 to −2.7] and pegmatites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.7182−0.7189; εNd(t) = −11.7 to −10.7; εHf(t) = −9.2 to −0.9] exhibit more enriched isotope compositions, similar to those of the wall-rock turbidites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.70803−0.7173; εNd(t) = −13.1 to −3.2], and are distinctly different from I-type granites [87Sr/86Sri = 0.7084−0.7098; εNd(t) = −6.8 to −6.3; εHf(t) = −6.2 to +0.9]. This implies that the pegmatites are derived from the S-type granites, not the I-type granites. The low temperatures (&amp;amp;lt;750 °C) estimated by the Ti-in-zircon thermometer for both I- and S-type granites suggest that S-type granites were likely derived from fluid-fluxed melting of the Triassic turbidites, favoring extraction of rare metals from staurolite, biotite, and muscovite in metaturbidites during anatexis. The coeval I-type granites provided the external heat and exotic volatiles, promoting staurolite and mica breakdown in the metaturbidites and thus facilitating the release of rare metals into the S-type leucogranitic melts. This suggests that although rare-metal pegmatite mineralization in Bailongshan is primarily related to S-type granites, I-type granites also played a contributing role. The formation of the coeval Late Triassic−earliest Jurassic barren I-type and fertile S-type granites in Bailongshan is attributed to final bidirectional subduction, slab rollback, and delamination of the Paleotethyan oceanic slab.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Evidence for diverse anaerobic metabolisms in 3.7-billion-year-old marine detrital sediments</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03188-6</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03188-6</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 06:46:12 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Austin Jarl Boyd</dc:creator><dc:creator>Magnus August Ravn Harding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Elizabeth Ann Bell</dc:creator><dc:creator>Minik Thorleif Rosing</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tue Hassenkam</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03188-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract Abundant graphitized organic matter within 3.7-billion-year-old sediments in the Isua Supracrustal Belt comprises the oldest remnants of life. This organic matter could have provided a favorable substrate for anaerobically respiring microbes, though their existence in the early Archean remains uncertain. Here we assess whether anaerobic respiration, linked to reduction of iron and sulfur, operated within these ancient sediments. We analyzed carbon and sulfur isotope data from pelagic and turbiditic sedimentary rocks, sampled from a rock core, and used petrography and iron concentrations to provide geological context. Carbon isotopic compositions indicate respiration of organic compounds, with lighter values associated with iron-rich samples, consistent with respiration coupled to iron reduction. Sulfide grains in pelagic layers have isotopic compositions consistent with reduction of atmospherically produced elemental sulfur, possibly with minor contributions from sulfate reduction during sedimentary hiatuses. These results suggest that early Archean ecosystems were sustained by multiple, interacting microbial metabolisms.
Published: 2026-01-13T06:46:12+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.577 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Austin Jarl Boyd; Magnus August Ravn Harding; Elizabeth Ann Bell; Minik Thorleif Rosing; Tue Hassenkam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03188-6"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03188-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.577 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Abundant graphitized organic matter within 3.7-billion-year-old sediments in the Isua Supracrustal Belt comprises the oldest remnants of life. This organic matter could have provided a favorable substrate for anaerobically respiring microbes, though their existence in the early Archean remains uncertain. Here we assess whether anaerobic respiration, linked to reduction of iron and sulfur, operated within these ancient sediments. We analyzed carbon and sulfur isotope data from pelagic and turbiditic sedimentary rocks, sampled from a rock core, and used petrography and iron concentrations to provide geological context. Carbon isotopic compositions indicate respiration of organic compounds, with lighter values associated with iron-rich samples, consistent with respiration coupled to iron reduction. Sulfide grains in pelagic layers have isotopic compositions consistent with reduction of atmospherically produced elemental sulfur, possibly with minor contributions from sulfate reduction during sedimentary hiatuses. These results suggest that early Archean ecosystems were sustained by multiple, interacting microbial metabolisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Geology and genesis of the Siahouki intermediate-sulfidation epithermal Cu-Au-Ag deposit, SE Iran: Constraints from fluid inclusions and S-O-C isotopes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-111</link><guid>10.1144/jgs2025-111</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:46:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ali Shahabinejad</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hossein-Ali Tajeddin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Majid Ghaderi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of the Geological Society</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1144/jgs2025-111</prism:doi><description>The Siahouki Cu-Au-Ag deposit is situated approximately 50 km northwest of Bam in the southern Urumieh-Dokhtar magmatic arc. Mineralization is hosted by Eocene dacitic and andesitic tuffs that have undergone extensive silicic, argillic, and propylitic alteration. Ore deposition primarily occurs in NW-SE-trending, fault-controlled quartz-carbonate ± sulfide veins. Based on field observations, petrography, and microanalytical data, five hydrothermal stages are defined: (I) early distal argillic-propylitic alteration; (II) the principal Cu-Au-Ag stage; (III) late Au enrichment; (IV) mineralization dominated by calcite; and (V) supergene oxidation and secondary enrichment. Fluid inclusions show homogenization temperatures of 112-331 °C and salinities of 0.9-10.1 wt.% NaCl equiv. Stable isotope constraints confirm a mixed magmatic-meteoric origin for the ore-forming fluids. Sulfur isotope compositions of pyrite, chalcopyrite, and tetrahedrite ( δ ³⁴S = −5.4 to +0.5‰) indicate a dominantly magmatic sulfur source. Oxygen isotope values ( δ ¹⁸O fluid = −1.4 to +1.8‰) calculated from quartz-water equilibrium indicate significant meteoric water mixing. Carbon isotopes ( δ ¹³C = −0.8 to +0.0‰) from hydrothermal calcite further suggest limited carbonate wall-rock interaction. Collectively, these data indicate that ore deposition was controlled by episodic boiling and fluid mixing during the transition from magmatic-hydrothermal to meteoric-dominated conditions, defining the Siahouki deposit as an intermediate-sulfidation epithermal system.
Published: 2026-01-14T12:46:16+00:00
Venue: Journal of the Geological Society
Score: 0.575 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ali Shahabinejad; Hossein-Ali Tajeddin; Majid Ghaderi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of the Geological Society&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-111"&gt;10.1144/jgs2025-111&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.575 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Siahouki Cu-Au-Ag deposit is situated approximately 50 km northwest of Bam in the southern Urumieh-Dokhtar magmatic arc. Mineralization is hosted by Eocene dacitic and andesitic tuffs that have undergone extensive silicic, argillic, and propylitic alteration. Ore deposition primarily occurs in NW-SE-trending, fault-controlled quartz-carbonate ± sulfide veins. Based on field observations, petrography, and microanalytical data, five hydrothermal stages are defined: (I) early distal argillic-propylitic alteration; (II) the principal Cu-Au-Ag stage; (III) late Au enrichment; (IV) mineralization dominated by calcite; and (V) supergene oxidation and secondary enrichment. Fluid inclusions show homogenization temperatures of 112-331 °C and salinities of 0.9-10.1 wt.% NaCl equiv. Stable isotope constraints confirm a mixed magmatic-meteoric origin for the ore-forming fluids. Sulfur isotope compositions of pyrite, chalcopyrite, and tetrahedrite ( δ ³⁴S = −5.4 to +0.5‰) indicate a dominantly magmatic sulfur source. Oxygen isotope values ( δ ¹⁸O fluid = −1.4 to +1.8‰) calculated from quartz-water equilibrium indicate significant meteoric water mixing. Carbon isotopes ( δ ¹³C = −0.8 to +0.0‰) from hydrothermal calcite further suggest limited carbonate wall-rock interaction. Collectively, these data indicate that ore deposition was controlled by episodic boiling and fluid mixing during the transition from magmatic-hydrothermal to meteoric-dominated conditions, defining the Siahouki deposit as an intermediate-sulfidation epithermal system.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A wideband tunable, nonreciprocal bandpass filter using magnetostatic surface waves with zero static power consumption</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68289-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68289-4</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 19:52:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xingyu Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yixiao Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shun Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yijie Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dengyang Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuxian Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chin-Yu Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mark G. Allen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Roy H. Olsson</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68289-4</prism:doi><description>Modern wireless systems demand compact, power-efficient radio frequency (RF) front-end components that support wideband tunability and nonreciprocity. We present a class of miniature bandpass filter that achieves both continuously tunable frequency operation (4.0–17.7 GHz) and high nonreciprocity ( &amp;gt; 25 dB), all within a compact size of 1.07 cm³. The filter employs a microfabricated 18 µm thick Yttrium Iron Garnet (YIG) waveguide with meander-line aluminum transducers, enabling low-loss unidirectional propagation via magnetostatic surface waves. Leveraging a benzocyclobutene planarization fabrication process, this study enables a dispersion profile unique to thick YIG films, resulting in enhanced filter skirt performance with minimal spurious modes. Frequency tuning is enabled by a zero-static-power magnetic bias circuit using transient current pulses, eliminating continuous power consumption. The filter demonstrates low insertion loss (3–5 dB), high out-of-band rejection ( &amp;gt; 30 dB), narrow bandwidth (100–200 MHz), robust power handling ( &amp;gt; 10.4 dBm), and high linearity (IIP3 &amp;gt; 26 dBm). This work demonstrates the first miniature RF filter combining ultrawide tunability (4–18 GHz) and high nonreciprocity, achieving low loss, zero static power, and compact size (1 cc).
Published: 2026-01-14T19:52:23+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.567 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xingyu Du; Yixiao Ding; Shun Yao; Yijie Ding; Dengyang Lu; Shuxian Wu; Chin-Yu Chang; Xuan Wang; Mark G. Allen; Roy H. Olsson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68289-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68289-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.567 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern wireless systems demand compact, power-efficient radio frequency (RF) front-end components that support wideband tunability and nonreciprocity. We present a class of miniature bandpass filter that achieves both continuously tunable frequency operation (4.0–17.7 GHz) and high nonreciprocity ( &amp;amp;gt; 25 dB), all within a compact size of 1.07 cm³. The filter employs a microfabricated 18 µm thick Yttrium Iron Garnet (YIG) waveguide with meander-line aluminum transducers, enabling low-loss unidirectional propagation via magnetostatic surface waves. Leveraging a benzocyclobutene planarization fabrication process, this study enables a dispersion profile unique to thick YIG films, resulting in enhanced filter skirt performance with minimal spurious modes. Frequency tuning is enabled by a zero-static-power magnetic bias circuit using transient current pulses, eliminating continuous power consumption. The filter demonstrates low insertion loss (3–5 dB), high out-of-band rejection ( &amp;amp;gt; 30 dB), narrow bandwidth (100–200 MHz), robust power handling ( &amp;amp;gt; 10.4 dBm), and high linearity (IIP3 &amp;amp;gt; 26 dBm). This work demonstrates the first miniature RF filter combining ultrawide tunability (4–18 GHz) and high nonreciprocity, achieving low loss, zero static power, and compact size (1 cc).&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Davemaoite Elasticity Reveals Slab‐Induced Heterogeneity in the Mantle Transition Zone</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118147</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl118147</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 06:59:11 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yingxin Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyue Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongzhou Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luo Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhu Mao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ningyu Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Denglei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chaoshuai Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cheng Qian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingzhan Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuzhu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takayuki Ishii</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl118147</prism:doi><description>Abstract The observed 2%–7% low‐shear velocity ( V S ) anomalies near the subducted slab at the bottom mantle transition zone (MTZ) indicate strong lateral heterogeneity, which is commonly attributed to subducted oceanic crust. However, davemaoite, a major constituent of the subducted oceanic crust, has been poorly constrained in its elasticity, hindering accurate velocity modeling and obscuring the origin of these low‐velocity features. Here we report single‐crystal elasticity of Ti‐bearing davemaoite with the composition of Ca(Si 0.57 Ti 0.43 )O 3 under high pressure‐temperature and found that Ti incorporation significantly reduces velocities and alters the pressure dependence of the shear modulus. Further velocity modeling demonstrated that subducted crusts with varying Ti content have seismic signatures of 1.7(2)–6.8(5)% low‐ V S at the bottom MTZ, consistent with the observed low‐ V S structure in the region. These findings highlight the role of slab‐derived chemical heterogeneity in generating mantle seismic anomalies and provide new experimental constraints on the structure and dynamics of the deep Earth.
Published: 2026-01-14T06:59:11+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.566 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yingxin Yu; Xinyue Zhang; Dongzhou Zhang; Luo Li; Zhu Mao; Ningyu Sun; Denglei Wang; Jing Li; Chaoshuai Zhao; Cheng Qian; Yingzhan Wei; Xinyang Li; Yuzhu Wang; Takayuki Ishii&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118147"&gt;10.1029/2025gl118147&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.566 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The observed 2%–7% low‐shear velocity ( V S ) anomalies near the subducted slab at the bottom mantle transition zone (MTZ) indicate strong lateral heterogeneity, which is commonly attributed to subducted oceanic crust. However, davemaoite, a major constituent of the subducted oceanic crust, has been poorly constrained in its elasticity, hindering accurate velocity modeling and obscuring the origin of these low‐velocity features. Here we report single‐crystal elasticity of Ti‐bearing davemaoite with the composition of Ca(Si 0.57 Ti 0.43 )O 3 under high pressure‐temperature and found that Ti incorporation significantly reduces velocities and alters the pressure dependence of the shear modulus. Further velocity modeling demonstrated that subducted crusts with varying Ti content have seismic signatures of 1.7(2)–6.8(5)% low‐ V S at the bottom MTZ, consistent with the observed low‐ V S structure in the region. These findings highlight the role of slab‐derived chemical heterogeneity in generating mantle seismic anomalies and provide new experimental constraints on the structure and dynamics of the deep Earth.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A reversed latitudinal ocean oxygen gradient in the Proterozoic Eon</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01896-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41561-025-01896-w</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:01:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ruliang He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexandre Pohl</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xingliang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ashley Prow-Fleischer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan L. Payne</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuhai Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andy Ridgwell</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zunli Lu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Geoscience</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41561-025-01896-w</prism:doi><description>Major changes in the oxygenation of the atmosphere and ocean have been suggested to trigger the taxonomic diversification and ecological expansion of complex life, including animals, during the Neoproterozoic–Palaeozoic transition. However, testing this hypothesis is hampered by the paucity of quantitative constraints on the oceanic oxygen availability at that time. Here we show how the spatial pattern of I/Ca ratios in marine carbonates—a proxy for dissolved oxygen in the local upper ocean—provides a fingerprint of the oxygenation state of Earth’s surface. Spatial analyses on published I/Ca ratios spanning the past 2,000 million years show that the latitudinal gradient of oxygen concentrations in the upper ocean was reversed in the Proterozoic eon relative to the modern pattern of decreasing oxygen concentrations from the mid-latitudes to the Equator. Using an Earth system model, we identify that the Proterozoic I/Ca latitudinal pattern is associated with a biosphere-controlled distribution of oxygen in the upper ocean at a low atmospheric oxygen level, and the transition to a modern pattern in the I/Ca proxy may correspond to a threshold of around 1% of today’s atmospheric oxygen concentration. Dissolved oxygen levels in the Proterozoic surface ocean decreased from the Equator towards the mid–high latitudes, the opposite of the modern latitudinal gradient, according to a compilation of I/Ca proxy records and Earth system modelling.
Published: 2026-01-13T10:01:41+00:00
Venue: Nature Geoscience
Score: 0.555 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ruliang He; Alexandre Pohl; Xingliang Zhang; Chao Chang; Ashley Prow-Fleischer; Jonathan L. Payne; Shuhai Xiao; Andy Ridgwell; Zunli Lu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Geoscience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01896-w"&gt;10.1038/s41561-025-01896-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.555 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Major changes in the oxygenation of the atmosphere and ocean have been suggested to trigger the taxonomic diversification and ecological expansion of complex life, including animals, during the Neoproterozoic–Palaeozoic transition. However, testing this hypothesis is hampered by the paucity of quantitative constraints on the oceanic oxygen availability at that time. Here we show how the spatial pattern of I/Ca ratios in marine carbonates—a proxy for dissolved oxygen in the local upper ocean—provides a fingerprint of the oxygenation state of Earth’s surface. Spatial analyses on published I/Ca ratios spanning the past 2,000 million years show that the latitudinal gradient of oxygen concentrations in the upper ocean was reversed in the Proterozoic eon relative to the modern pattern of decreasing oxygen concentrations from the mid-latitudes to the Equator. Using an Earth system model, we identify that the Proterozoic I/Ca latitudinal pattern is associated with a biosphere-controlled distribution of oxygen in the upper ocean at a low atmospheric oxygen level, and the transition to a modern pattern in the I/Ca proxy may correspond to a threshold of around 1% of today’s atmospheric oxygen concentration. Dissolved oxygen levels in the Proterozoic surface ocean decreased from the Equator towards the mid–high latitudes, the opposite of the modern latitudinal gradient, according to a compilation of I/Ca proxy records and Earth system modelling.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>An electrically injected solid-state surface acoustic wave phonon laser</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09950-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09950-8</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 16:01:20 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Alexander Wendt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Matthew J. Storey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael Miller</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dalton Anderson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eric Chatterjee</dc:creator><dc:creator>William Horrocks</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brandon Smith</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ping-Show Wong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shawn Arterburn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas A. Friedmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lisa Hackett</dc:creator><dc:creator>Matt Eichenfield</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09950-8</prism:doi><description>Surface acoustic waves (SAWs) enable a wide array of technologies, including radiofrequency filters1,2, chemical and biological sensors3–5, acousto-optic devices6–8, acoustic control of microfluidic flow in lab-on-a-chip systems9–11 and quantum phononics12–19. Although numerous methods exist for generating SAWs, they each have intrinsic limitations that inhibit performance, operation at high frequencies and use in systems constrained in size, weight and power. Here we present a completely solid-state, single-chip SAW phonon laser consisting of a lithium niobate SAW resonator with an internal, d.c. electrically injected and broadband semiconductor gain medium with &amp;lt;0.15 mm2 footprint. Below the threshold bias of 36 V, the device behaves as a resonant amplifier, and above it exhibits self-sustained coherent oscillation, linewidth narrowing and high output powers. A continuous on-chip acoustic output power of up to −6.1 dBm is generated at 1 GHz with a resolution-limited linewidth of &amp;lt;77 Hz and a carrier phase noise of −57 dBc Hz−1 at 1 kHz offset. Through detailed modelling, we show pathways for improving the performance of these devices, including mHz linewidths, high power efficiencies and footprints under 550 μm2 at 10 GHz. This demonstration paves the way for ultrahigh-frequency SAW sources on-chip and highly miniaturized SAW-based systems that can be operated without an external radiofrequency source. A completely solid-state, single-chip, microwave-frequency surface acoustic wave phonon laser can generate coherent phonons from thermal noise or resonantly amplify injected phonons using only a direct current bias field.
Published: 2026-01-14T16:01:20+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.552 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Alexander Wendt; Matthew J. Storey; Michael Miller; Dalton Anderson; Eric Chatterjee; William Horrocks; Brandon Smith; Ping-Show Wong; Shawn Arterburn; Thomas A. Friedmann; Lisa Hackett; Matt Eichenfield&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09950-8"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09950-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.552 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surface acoustic waves (SAWs) enable a wide array of technologies, including radiofrequency filters1,2, chemical and biological sensors3–5, acousto-optic devices6–8, acoustic control of microfluidic flow in lab-on-a-chip systems9–11 and quantum phononics12–19. Although numerous methods exist for generating SAWs, they each have intrinsic limitations that inhibit performance, operation at high frequencies and use in systems constrained in size, weight and power. Here we present a completely solid-state, single-chip SAW phonon laser consisting of a lithium niobate SAW resonator with an internal, d.c. electrically injected and broadband semiconductor gain medium with &amp;amp;lt;0.15 mm2 footprint. Below the threshold bias of 36 V, the device behaves as a resonant amplifier, and above it exhibits self-sustained coherent oscillation, linewidth narrowing and high output powers. A continuous on-chip acoustic output power of up to −6.1 dBm is generated at 1 GHz with a resolution-limited linewidth of &amp;amp;lt;77 Hz and a carrier phase noise of −57 dBc Hz−1 at 1 kHz offset. Through detailed modelling, we show pathways for improving the performance of these devices, including mHz linewidths, high power efficiencies and footprints under 550 μm2 at 10 GHz. This demonstration paves the way for ultrahigh-frequency SAW sources on-chip and highly miniaturized SAW-based systems that can be operated without an external radiofrequency source. A completely solid-state, single-chip, microwave-frequency surface acoustic wave phonon laser can generate coherent phonons from thermal noise or resonantly amplify injected phonons using only a direct current bias field.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Near field optical visualization of the nanoscale phase percolation dynamics of a VO2 oscillator</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68300-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68300-y</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 10:52:42 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kajal Tiwari</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhong Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yishen Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ajesh Kollakuzhiyil Gopi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jae-Chun Jeon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stuart S. P. Parkin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68300-y</prism:doi><description>Abstract Self-sustained resistance oscillation in vanadium dioxide (VO 2 ) are of significant interest for phase-based information encoding applications. However, the underlying mechanism behind the current-induced insulator-to-metal phase oscillation and its spatiotemporal dynamics remains elusive. Here, using high-resolution near-field optical imaging, we uncover distinct current-induced phase transition pathways in VO 2 (001) thin films. We show that the formation of a persistent metallic patch within active region, defined as the area between the electrodes in a two-terminal model device serves as a prerequisite for oscillations. In this region, transient conductive filaments as narrow as 140 nm bridge the patch to the electrodes. Additionally, we observe oscillation modulated optical signals that extend well beyond the active region, providing clear evidence for a mechanism that would couple neighboring oscillators. Our work provides direct insight into the percolation dynamics that controls the oscillatory state of a VO 2 oscillator, paving the way to optimally designed oxide electronics.
Published: 2026-01-14T10:52:42+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.548 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kajal Tiwari; Zhong Wang; Yishen Xie; Ajesh Kollakuzhiyil Gopi; Jae-Chun Jeon; Ke Xiao; Stuart S. P. Parkin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68300-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68300-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.548 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Self-sustained resistance oscillation in vanadium dioxide (VO 2 ) are of significant interest for phase-based information encoding applications. However, the underlying mechanism behind the current-induced insulator-to-metal phase oscillation and its spatiotemporal dynamics remains elusive. Here, using high-resolution near-field optical imaging, we uncover distinct current-induced phase transition pathways in VO 2 (001) thin films. We show that the formation of a persistent metallic patch within active region, defined as the area between the electrodes in a two-terminal model device serves as a prerequisite for oscillations. In this region, transient conductive filaments as narrow as 140 nm bridge the patch to the electrodes. Additionally, we observe oscillation modulated optical signals that extend well beyond the active region, providing clear evidence for a mechanism that would couple neighboring oscillators. Our work provides direct insight into the percolation dynamics that controls the oscillatory state of a VO 2 oscillator, paving the way to optimally designed oxide electronics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magma evolution and ascent mechanisms at inflated spreading ridges in backarc settings: The Marsili seamount (Tyrrhenian Sea, Italy)</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38339.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38339.1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 20:51:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Emanuela Gennaro</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gianluca Iezzi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luca Cocchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guido Ventura</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38339.1</prism:doi><description>Marsili axial volcano is the largest submarine volcanic complex in the Euro-Mediterranean area and represents an inflated spreading ridge built up in a slow spreading backarc setting. An updated geochemical dataset (major oxides, trace elements, and Sr, Nd, and Pb isotopes) unveils that the Marsili rocks evolve from prevailing island arc and oceanic island basalts to trachytes by fractional crystallization. The heterogeneous parent Marsili magmas are cogenetic to those of the neighbor Aeolian volcanic arc, both of which lie within the Tyrrhenian basin off southern Italy. Petrological and independent geophysical models reveal the depth of the Marsili magma storage zones and the temperature, pressure, oxygen fugacity, and H2O conditions of the magmas. The Marsili plumbing system develops from the upper mantle to the shallower oceanic crust. Silica-poor magmas accumulate in reservoirs at the boundary between the upper and lower oceanic crust, whereas SiO2-rich magmas preferentially accumulate in sill-like reservoirs at the Moho depth. Results of geochemical, geophysical, and thermo-rheological models reveal a reversed plumbing system in which the more viscous SiO2-rich magmas are more limited in reaching the surface with respect to the less viscous SiO2-poor suspensions. The different cooling rate of the two end-member magmas also plays a role. The apparently unusual structure of the Marsili plumbing system could serve as a model for understanding other slow spreading ridges in backarc settings.
Published: 2026-01-14T20:51:36+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.548 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Emanuela Gennaro; Gianluca Iezzi; Luca Cocchi; Guido Ventura&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38339.1"&gt;10.1130/b38339.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.548 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marsili axial volcano is the largest submarine volcanic complex in the Euro-Mediterranean area and represents an inflated spreading ridge built up in a slow spreading backarc setting. An updated geochemical dataset (major oxides, trace elements, and Sr, Nd, and Pb isotopes) unveils that the Marsili rocks evolve from prevailing island arc and oceanic island basalts to trachytes by fractional crystallization. The heterogeneous parent Marsili magmas are cogenetic to those of the neighbor Aeolian volcanic arc, both of which lie within the Tyrrhenian basin off southern Italy. Petrological and independent geophysical models reveal the depth of the Marsili magma storage zones and the temperature, pressure, oxygen fugacity, and H2O conditions of the magmas. The Marsili plumbing system develops from the upper mantle to the shallower oceanic crust. Silica-poor magmas accumulate in reservoirs at the boundary between the upper and lower oceanic crust, whereas SiO2-rich magmas preferentially accumulate in sill-like reservoirs at the Moho depth. Results of geochemical, geophysical, and thermo-rheological models reveal a reversed plumbing system in which the more viscous SiO2-rich magmas are more limited in reaching the surface with respect to the less viscous SiO2-poor suspensions. The different cooling rate of the two end-member magmas also plays a role. The apparently unusual structure of the Marsili plumbing system could serve as a model for understanding other slow spreading ridges in backarc settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Decoding the gradient-distributed colour centers in electrochromic WO3</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68046-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68046-z</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 12:04:57 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Sikang Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jizhe Cui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuchu Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaocong Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingyue Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Quanpan Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kun Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanan Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rongji Jiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rui-Tao Wen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Can Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiyang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rong Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wandong Xing</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68046-z</prism:doi><description>The optical properties of electrochromic windows can be modulated by embedding electrons and ions simultaneously to realize energy-saving functions. However, the microscopic electrochromic mechanism in cathode materials remains controversial. Herein, we have discovered that the single-crystal WO3 nanosheets exhibit thickness-dependent electrochromic characteristics. The multislice electron ptychography experiments revealed that the colour centers in electrochromic WO3 are associated with lattice distortions, and the density of the colour centers decreases from surface to bulk. Moreover, the heterogeneous distribution of polarons induces a phase transition from monoclinic to tetragonal and cubic structures, which in turn causes the band gap of the WO3 nanosheets to follow a volcano-type trend. This phenomenon elucidates the colour shift of the electrode from yellow to blue or black as the thickness of the nanosheets decreases. By visualizing the actual colour centers of electrochromic materials, our findings provide an optimal framework for the development of high-performance electrochromic devices. Multislice electron ptychography reveals that gradient-distributed ions induce progressive lattice distortions from bulk to surface, driving monoclinic γ-WO3 electrochromic materials to transform into tetragonal and cubic phases and forming the gradient-distributed colour centers.
Published: 2026-01-14T12:04:57+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.546 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sikang Xue; Jizhe Cui; Chuchu Zhou; Min Shen; Xiaocong Liang; Mingyue Wang; Quanpan Zhao; Yan Ye; Kun Xu; Yanan Zhao; Rongji Jiao; Rui-Tao Wen; Can Yang; Zhiyang Yu; Rong Yu; Wandong Xing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68046-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68046-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.546 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The optical properties of electrochromic windows can be modulated by embedding electrons and ions simultaneously to realize energy-saving functions. However, the microscopic electrochromic mechanism in cathode materials remains controversial. Herein, we have discovered that the single-crystal WO3 nanosheets exhibit thickness-dependent electrochromic characteristics. The multislice electron ptychography experiments revealed that the colour centers in electrochromic WO3 are associated with lattice distortions, and the density of the colour centers decreases from surface to bulk. Moreover, the heterogeneous distribution of polarons induces a phase transition from monoclinic to tetragonal and cubic structures, which in turn causes the band gap of the WO3 nanosheets to follow a volcano-type trend. This phenomenon elucidates the colour shift of the electrode from yellow to blue or black as the thickness of the nanosheets decreases. By visualizing the actual colour centers of electrochromic materials, our findings provide an optimal framework for the development of high-performance electrochromic devices. Multislice electron ptychography reveals that gradient-distributed ions induce progressive lattice distortions from bulk to surface, driving monoclinic γ-WO3 electrochromic materials to transform into tetragonal and cubic phases and forming the gradient-distributed colour centers.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Elasticity of silicate glasses along the MgSiO3–FeAlO3 join</title><link>https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2025-9982</link><guid>10.2138/am-2025-9982</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:04:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jia-Sen Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laura Schultz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenhao Su</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongzhan Fei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Biao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenyi Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tomoo Katsura</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jin S. Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>American Mineralogist</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.2138/am-2025-9982</prism:doi><description>Abstract The density and elastic properties of silicate melts are critical for understanding planetary differentiation and magma ocean dynamics. In this study, we measured the elastic properties of MgSiO3–FeAlO3 glasses with varying FeAlO3 contents (0–40 mol%), which we use as room-temperature analogs for planetary magma ocean melts, to elucidate the effects of Fe and Al on the melt elasticity, density, and viscosity. With increasing FeAlO3 content, glass density and elastic moduli increase, while acoustic velocities decrease. The lower molar volumes observed in Fe-rich glasses are consistent with enhanced elastic modulus and polymerization. We also found that normalized compressibility (∂V/∂P)S increases linearly with the non-bridging oxygen per tetrahedral cation (NBO/T) but decreases with FeAlO3 content. These results demonstrate that variations in glass composition, particularly FeAlO3 content, exert a strong control on physical properties and indicates that analogous compositional effects likely occur in silicate melts, with significant consequences for magma ocean crystallization dynamics.
Published: 2026-01-13T17:04:27+00:00
Venue: American Mineralogist
Score: 0.537 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jia-Sen Hu; Laura Schultz; Wenhao Su; Hongzhan Fei; Biao Wang; Wenyi Zhou; Tomoo Katsura; Jin S. Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; American Mineralogist&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.2138/am-2025-9982"&gt;10.2138/am-2025-9982&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.537 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The density and elastic properties of silicate melts are critical for understanding planetary differentiation and magma ocean dynamics. In this study, we measured the elastic properties of MgSiO3–FeAlO3 glasses with varying FeAlO3 contents (0–40 mol%), which we use as room-temperature analogs for planetary magma ocean melts, to elucidate the effects of Fe and Al on the melt elasticity, density, and viscosity. With increasing FeAlO3 content, glass density and elastic moduli increase, while acoustic velocities decrease. The lower molar volumes observed in Fe-rich glasses are consistent with enhanced elastic modulus and polymerization. We also found that normalized compressibility (∂V/∂P)S increases linearly with the non-bridging oxygen per tetrahedral cation (NBO/T) but decreases with FeAlO3 content. These results demonstrate that variations in glass composition, particularly FeAlO3 content, exert a strong control on physical properties and indicates that analogous compositional effects likely occur in silicate melts, with significant consequences for magma ocean crystallization dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Interphase electron redistribution induced by confined transformation in PtPdBiSn nanoplates for efficient ethanol oxidation electrocatalysis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68352-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68352-0</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 07:34:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Mingjie Shao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aimin Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huameng Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haifeng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoqing Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengwang Zhu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68352-0</prism:doi><description>Noble metal-based core/shell catalysts show great promise for ethanol oxidation reaction (EOR) through regulated dehydrogenation or bond-breaking, yet their performance remains constrained by limited interphase electron interactions accessible through conventional structure-conserving modulation strategies. Herein, we report a strategy of confined heterostructural transformation within the core to enhance interphase electron interactions, electrochemically transforming ordered hexagonal close-packed (HCP)/ face-centered cubic (FCC) PtPdBiSn nanoplates into disordered hexagonal non-close-packed (H-nCP)/FCC heterostructured catalyst for efficient EOR. Advanced characterization and density functional theory (DFT) calculations reveal that the confined transformation induces interphase electron redistribution: electron transfer from core to shell. This effect reconfigures the electronic structure, optimizing intermediates
Published: 2026-01-13T07:34:23+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.535 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mingjie Shao; Aimin Wang; Huameng Fu; Haifeng Zhang; Xiaoqing Huang; Zhengwang Zhu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68352-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68352-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.535 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noble metal-based core/shell catalysts show great promise for ethanol oxidation reaction (EOR) through regulated dehydrogenation or bond-breaking, yet their performance remains constrained by limited interphase electron interactions accessible through conventional structure-conserving modulation strategies. Herein, we report a strategy of confined heterostructural transformation within the core to enhance interphase electron interactions, electrochemically transforming ordered hexagonal close-packed (HCP)/ face-centered cubic (FCC) PtPdBiSn nanoplates into disordered hexagonal non-close-packed (H-nCP)/FCC heterostructured catalyst for efficient EOR. Advanced characterization and density functional theory (DFT) calculations reveal that the confined transformation induces interphase electron redistribution: electron transfer from core to shell. This effect reconfigures the electronic structure, optimizing intermediates&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Growth of non-layered 2D transition metal nitrides enabled by transient chloride templates</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68321-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68321-7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:34:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Liqiong He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingwei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengyang Cai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruiting Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shengnan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunhao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi-Yuan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiarong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bilu Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68321-7</prism:doi><description>Abstract 2D transition metal nitrides (TMNs) have attracted significant attention due to their magnetic, electrical, and chemical properties at atomic thickness. However, the synthesis of 2D TMNs is still challenging, due to their strong isotropic metal-nitrogen bonding networks. Here, we report a universal synthesis of non-layered 2D TMN family by using corresponding metastable metal chlorides as transient templates. This approach takes advantage of the layered structures and low conversion energy barriers of transition metal chlorides (TMCls) to grow 2D TMNs. Fifteen types of 2D TMNs and their alloys were synthesized, demonstrating the versatility of this method. The 2D TMN family exhibits tunable magnetic characteristics ranging from antiferromagnet to hard magnet, which can be modulated by their composition. This work overcomes previous synthesis limitations, thus offering a pathway to explore fundamental properties of 2D TMNs and accelerate their applications.
Published: 2026-01-14T09:34:15+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.532 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Liqiong He; Jingwei Wang; Zhengyang Cai; Ruiting Liu; Shengnan Li; Yunhao Zhang; Zhi-Yuan Zhang; Jiarong Liu; Bilu Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68321-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68321-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.532 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract 2D transition metal nitrides (TMNs) have attracted significant attention due to their magnetic, electrical, and chemical properties at atomic thickness. However, the synthesis of 2D TMNs is still challenging, due to their strong isotropic metal-nitrogen bonding networks. Here, we report a universal synthesis of non-layered 2D TMN family by using corresponding metastable metal chlorides as transient templates. This approach takes advantage of the layered structures and low conversion energy barriers of transition metal chlorides (TMCls) to grow 2D TMNs. Fifteen types of 2D TMNs and their alloys were synthesized, demonstrating the versatility of this method. The 2D TMN family exhibits tunable magnetic characteristics ranging from antiferromagnet to hard magnet, which can be modulated by their composition. This work overcomes previous synthesis limitations, thus offering a pathway to explore fundamental properties of 2D TMNs and accelerate their applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magneto-ionic control of magnetism through voltage-driven carbon transport</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68283-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68283-w</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:44:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Z. Tan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Z. Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>S. Privitera</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. O. Liedke</dc:creator><dc:creator>E. Hirschmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Wagner</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. L. Costa-Krämer</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Quintana</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Garcia-Tort</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. Herrero-Martín</dc:creator><dc:creator>Y. F. Mei</dc:creator><dc:creator>X. Z. Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>H. Tan</dc:creator><dc:creator>I. Fina</dc:creator><dc:creator>F. Sánchez</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Arredondo-López</dc:creator><dc:creator>F. Ibrahim</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. Chshiev</dc:creator><dc:creator>E. Longo</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. Rovirola</dc:creator><dc:creator>F. Macià</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. F. Lopeandia</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. Nogués</dc:creator><dc:creator>E. Pellicer</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. Sort</dc:creator><dc:creator>E. Menéndez</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68283-w</prism:doi><description>Control of magnetism through voltage-driven ionic processes (i.e., magneto-ionics) holds potential for next-generation memories and computing. This stems from its non-volatility, flexibility in adjusting the magnitude and speed of magnetic modulation, and energy efficiency. Since magneto-ionics depends on factors like ionic radius and electronegativity, identifying alternative mobile ions is crucial to embrace new phenomena and applications. Here, the feasibility of C as a prospective magneto-ionic ion is investigated in a Fe-C system by electrolyte gating. In contrast to most magneto-ionic systems, Fe-C presents a reversible dual-ion mechanism: Fe and C act as cation and anion, respectively, moving uniformly in opposite directions under an applied electric field. This leads to a significant increase in saturation magnetization ( &amp;gt; 5-fold) with magneto-ionic rates larger than 1 emu·cm−3·s−1, and a 25-fold increase in coercivity. Since carbides exhibit minimal cytotoxicity, this introduces a biocompatible dimension to magneto-ionics, paving the way for the convergence of spintronics and biotechnology. There has been a recent interest in control of magnetism via ionic transport. The appeal of such magneto-ionic control lies in its extent, non-volatility and potential energy-efficiency, however, the number of systems showing such behaviour is limited. Here, Tan, Ma, and coauthors demonstrate magneto-ionic control through Carbon transport.
Published: 2026-01-13T17:44:58+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.529 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Z. Tan; Z. Ma; S. Privitera; M. O. Liedke; E. Hirschmann; A. Wagner; J. L. Costa-Krämer; A. Quintana; A. Garcia-Tort; J. Herrero-Martín; Y. F. Mei; X. Z. Chen; H. Tan; I. Fina; F. Sánchez; A. Arredondo-López; F. Ibrahim; M. Chshiev; E. Longo; M. Rovirola; F. Macià; A. F. Lopeandia; J. Nogués; E. Pellicer; J. Sort; E. Menéndez&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68283-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68283-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.529 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Control of magnetism through voltage-driven ionic processes (i.e., magneto-ionics) holds potential for next-generation memories and computing. This stems from its non-volatility, flexibility in adjusting the magnitude and speed of magnetic modulation, and energy efficiency. Since magneto-ionics depends on factors like ionic radius and electronegativity, identifying alternative mobile ions is crucial to embrace new phenomena and applications. Here, the feasibility of C as a prospective magneto-ionic ion is investigated in a Fe-C system by electrolyte gating. In contrast to most magneto-ionic systems, Fe-C presents a reversible dual-ion mechanism: Fe and C act as cation and anion, respectively, moving uniformly in opposite directions under an applied electric field. This leads to a significant increase in saturation magnetization ( &amp;amp;gt; 5-fold) with magneto-ionic rates larger than 1 emu·cm−3·s−1, and a 25-fold increase in coercivity. Since carbides exhibit minimal cytotoxicity, this introduces a biocompatible dimension to magneto-ionics, paving the way for the convergence of spintronics and biotechnology. There has been a recent interest in control of magnetism via ionic transport. The appeal of such magneto-ionic control lies in its extent, non-volatility and potential energy-efficiency, however, the number of systems showing such behaviour is limited. Here, Tan, Ma, and coauthors demonstrate magneto-ionic control through Carbon transport.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ancient landscape evolution tracked through cosmogenic krypton in detrital zircon</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2516058122</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2516058122</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:47:13 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Maximilian Dröllner</dc:creator><dc:creator>Milo Barham</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher L. Kirkland</dc:creator><dc:creator>Taryn Scharf</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sabrina Niemeyer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tibor J. Dunai</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2516058122</prism:doi><description>Cosmogenic nuclides have revolutionized our quantitative understanding of landscape evolution via measurements of near-surface erosion, exposure, and burial. Here, we integrate stable cosmogenic krypton in detrital zircon with U–Pb geochronology to extend the temporal limits of cosmogenic nuclide applications and reconstruct Eocene landscape evolution from drill cores of placer deposits in southern Australia. Zircon U–Pb crystallization ages are interpreted to reflect paleodrainage from a deeply weathered ~800,000 km 2 hinterland and transport via a ~1,000 km littoral drift system. The measured cosmogenic 78 Kr concentration of detrital zircon samples ranges from ~6.4 × 10 5 to 1.8 × 10 7 atoms per gram, suggesting low paleodenudation rates of 0.3 to 0.7 m per My [interquartile range (IQR)]. Such low denudation rates are below those expected by comparison to modern analogs and point to underestimation due to re-exposure during sediment transport and shallow storage. Expressing the concentrations as apparent exposure times, which approximate the near-surface integrated residence time, yields estimates of 0.9 to 2.1 My (IQR). In the stratigraphic and mineralogical context, the dataset records a shift from compositionally mature placers with uniformly high residence times (~1.6 My) to less mature placers with stratigraphically variable residence times (~0.7 to 2.7 My). We infer a shift from prolonged sediment storage, during which the mineral assemblage was modified, to a more dynamic transport regime with higher net transfer rates. The timing suggests eustatic and tectonic forcing, and cosmogenic krypton captures this transition, aiding reconstruction of how ancient landscapes and the sedimentary record coevolve.
Published: 2026-01-13T17:47:13+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.527 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Maximilian Dröllner; Milo Barham; Christopher L. Kirkland; Taryn Scharf; Sabrina Niemeyer; Tibor J. Dunai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2516058122"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2516058122&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.527 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cosmogenic nuclides have revolutionized our quantitative understanding of landscape evolution via measurements of near-surface erosion, exposure, and burial. Here, we integrate stable cosmogenic krypton in detrital zircon with U–Pb geochronology to extend the temporal limits of cosmogenic nuclide applications and reconstruct Eocene landscape evolution from drill cores of placer deposits in southern Australia. Zircon U–Pb crystallization ages are interpreted to reflect paleodrainage from a deeply weathered ~800,000 km 2 hinterland and transport via a ~1,000 km littoral drift system. The measured cosmogenic 78 Kr concentration of detrital zircon samples ranges from ~6.4 × 10 5 to 1.8 × 10 7 atoms per gram, suggesting low paleodenudation rates of 0.3 to 0.7 m per My [interquartile range (IQR)]. Such low denudation rates are below those expected by comparison to modern analogs and point to underestimation due to re-exposure during sediment transport and shallow storage. Expressing the concentrations as apparent exposure times, which approximate the near-surface integrated residence time, yields estimates of 0.9 to 2.1 My (IQR). In the stratigraphic and mineralogical context, the dataset records a shift from compositionally mature placers with uniformly high residence times (~1.6 My) to less mature placers with stratigraphically variable residence times (~0.7 to 2.7 My). We infer a shift from prolonged sediment storage, during which the mineral assemblage was modified, to a more dynamic transport regime with higher net transfer rates. The timing suggests eustatic and tectonic forcing, and cosmogenic krypton captures this transition, aiding reconstruction of how ancient landscapes and the sedimentary record coevolve.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The East Australian Potassic Suite: Petrology, Bulk Chemistry, and Origin</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1093/petrology/egag002</link><guid>10.1093/petrology/egag002</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 12:31:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Anthony W Lanati</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joshua J Shea</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephen F Foley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marthe Klöcking</dc:creator><dc:creator>Arno Rohrbach</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephan Klemme</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1093/petrology/egag002</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Eastern Australian Potassic Suite (EAPS) is an alkaline volcanic province made up of over 20 widely dispersed outcrops that extend almost 700 km, inferred to form the southern portion of the Cosgrove continental hotspot track. In contrast to the large basaltic volcanic complexes to the east and north, the EAPS occurs exclusively as mafic potassium–rich occurrences with inferred low–volume expressions with outcrop extents on the order of hundreds of metres to a few kilometres. These localities mostly occur on lithosphere thicker than 120 km suggesting that the lithosphere–asthenosphere boundary may have a strong influence on their depth of generation. The primary felsic mineral in these rocks is leucite, which has previously seen the EAPS defined as leucitites in constantly evolving classifications of exotic, but potentially economically significant alkaline rocks. However, this classification does not reflect their chemical or genetic affinity. In this study, we undertake a systematic re–evaluation of these occurrences with the aim of understanding their source enrichment processes and melting conditions. Newly acquired major, trace, and volatile element whole–rock data shows that the EAPS is chemically variable, but exceptionally enriched in potassium compared to other East Australian volcanism, with high K2O/Na2O and MgO (Av.: K2O 4.98 wt%; K2O/Na2O 3.23; K/Na 2.12; MgO 12.14 wt%). We report the only complete volatile element data for the EAPS which show the lavas are similarly enriched in nitrogen compared to other lamproites, while being more CO2-rich despite being partially degassed (N: 44–350 ppm; CO2: 1129–10274 ppm). Despite not occurring on a craton, the EAPS trace element patterns and chemistry most closely resemble cratonic (anorogenic) lamproites. Additionally, the mineralogy, major and trace element concentrations closely match the classification criteria for lamproites. Trace element ratios of these near-primary mantle melts have a primitive signature generated from a highly enriched source that has previously undergone a degree of mixed silicate–carbonatite metasomatism. The most likely source for these rocks based on these new data is a hydrous phlogopite–bearing and olivine–poor assemblage that originates in the garnet stability field (i.e. phlogopite–garnet–pyroxenite). The inherited titanian affinity and elevated phosphorus contents of these magmas suggest apatite and oxide minerals were also present in the source. This new data helps inform interpretations of regional variations in melt generation and mantle source mineralogy in the highly heterogeneous metasomatised mantle beneath eastern Australia. We further suggest that the mechanisms that generated the EAPS likely include a combination of edge–driven convection and shear–driven upwelling as well as channelised melt flow which contributed to metasomatic depletion and refertilisation cycles. These cycles are synonymous with the initial stages of continental destabilisation that could develop toward rifting.
Published: 2026-01-13T12:31:21+00:00
Venue: Journal of Petrology
Score: 0.527 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Anthony W Lanati; Joshua J Shea; Stephen F Foley; Marthe Klöcking; Arno Rohrbach; Stephan Klemme&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/petrology/egag002"&gt;10.1093/petrology/egag002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.527 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Eastern Australian Potassic Suite (EAPS) is an alkaline volcanic province made up of over 20 widely dispersed outcrops that extend almost 700 km, inferred to form the southern portion of the Cosgrove continental hotspot track. In contrast to the large basaltic volcanic complexes to the east and north, the EAPS occurs exclusively as mafic potassium–rich occurrences with inferred low–volume expressions with outcrop extents on the order of hundreds of metres to a few kilometres. These localities mostly occur on lithosphere thicker than 120 km suggesting that the lithosphere–asthenosphere boundary may have a strong influence on their depth of generation. The primary felsic mineral in these rocks is leucite, which has previously seen the EAPS defined as leucitites in constantly evolving classifications of exotic, but potentially economically significant alkaline rocks. However, this classification does not reflect their chemical or genetic affinity. In this study, we undertake a systematic re–evaluation of these occurrences with the aim of understanding their source enrichment processes and melting conditions. Newly acquired major, trace, and volatile element whole–rock data shows that the EAPS is chemically variable, but exceptionally enriched in potassium compared to other East Australian volcanism, with high K2O/Na2O and MgO (Av.: K2O 4.98 wt%; K2O/Na2O 3.23; K/Na 2.12; MgO 12.14 wt%). We report the only complete volatile element data for the EAPS which show the lavas are similarly enriched in nitrogen compared to other lamproites, while being more CO2-rich despite being partially degassed (N: 44–350 ppm; CO2: 1129–10274 ppm). Despite not occurring on a craton, the EAPS trace element patterns and chemistry most closely resemble cratonic (anorogenic) lamproites. Additionally, the mineralogy, major and trace element concentrations closely match the classification criteria for lamproites. Trace element ratios of these near-primary mantle melts have a primitive signature generated from a highly enriched source that has previously undergone a degree of mixed silicate–carbonatite metasomatism. The most likely source for these rocks based on these new data is a hydrous phlogopite–bearing and olivine–poor assemblage that originates in the garnet stability field (i.e. phlogopite–garnet–pyroxenite). The inherited titanian affinity and elevated phosphorus contents of these magmas suggest apatite and oxide minerals were also present in the source. This new data helps inform interpretations of regional variations in melt generation and mantle source mineralogy in the highly heterogeneous metasomatised mantle beneath eastern Australia. We further suggest that the mechanisms that generated the EAPS likely include a combination of edge–driven convection and shear–driven upwelling as well as channelised melt flow which contributed to metasomatic depletion and refertilisation cycles. These cycles are synonymous with the initial stages of continental destabilisation that could develop toward rifting.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Synthetic gain for electron-beam spectroscopy</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68189-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68189-z</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 17:53:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yongliang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kebo Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zetao Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yixin Sha</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zeling Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xudong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shu Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shimeng Gong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yiqin Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huigao Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68189-z</prism:doi><description>Electron-beam microscopy and spectroscopy featuring atomic-scale spatial resolution have become essential tools used daily in almost all branches of nanoscale science and technology. As a natural supercontinuum source of light, free electrons couple with phonons, plasmons, electron-hole pairs, inter- and intra-band transitions, and inner-shell ionization. The multiple excitations, intertwined with the intricate nature of nanostructured samples, present significant challenges in isolating specific spectral characteristics amidst complex experimental backgrounds. Here we introduce the approach of synthetic complex frequency waves to mitigate these challenges in free-electron–light interaction. The complex frequency waves, created through causality-informed coherent superposition of real-frequency waves induced by free electrons, offer virtual gain to offset material losses. This amplifies and enhances spectral features, as confirmed by our electron energy loss and cathodoluminescence measurements on multilayer membranes, suspended nanoparticles, and film-coupled nanostructures. Strikingly, we reveal that our approach can retrieve resonance excitation completely buried underneath the zero-loss peak, substantially enhance the quality of hyperspectral imaging, and resolve entangled multiple-photon–electron events in their quantum interaction. Our findings indicate the versatile utility of complex frequency waves in various electron-beam spectroscopy and their promising diagnostic capabilities in free-electron quantum optics. This work introduces synthetic gain to electron-beam spectroscopy, greatly enhancing spectral resolution and revealing hidden features, enabling advances in nanoscale analysis and free electron-based quantum optics under challenging signal conditions.
Published: 2026-01-14T17:53:50+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.525 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yongliang Chen; Kebo Zeng; Zetao Xie; Yixin Sha; Zeling Chen; Xudong Zhang; Shu Yang; Shimeng Gong; Yiqin Chen; Huigao Duan; Shuang Zhang; Yi Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68189-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68189-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.525 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electron-beam microscopy and spectroscopy featuring atomic-scale spatial resolution have become essential tools used daily in almost all branches of nanoscale science and technology. As a natural supercontinuum source of light, free electrons couple with phonons, plasmons, electron-hole pairs, inter- and intra-band transitions, and inner-shell ionization. The multiple excitations, intertwined with the intricate nature of nanostructured samples, present significant challenges in isolating specific spectral characteristics amidst complex experimental backgrounds. Here we introduce the approach of synthetic complex frequency waves to mitigate these challenges in free-electron–light interaction. The complex frequency waves, created through causality-informed coherent superposition of real-frequency waves induced by free electrons, offer virtual gain to offset material losses. This amplifies and enhances spectral features, as confirmed by our electron energy loss and cathodoluminescence measurements on multilayer membranes, suspended nanoparticles, and film-coupled nanostructures. Strikingly, we reveal that our approach can retrieve resonance excitation completely buried underneath the zero-loss peak, substantially enhance the quality of hyperspectral imaging, and resolve entangled multiple-photon–electron events in their quantum interaction. Our findings indicate the versatile utility of complex frequency waves in various electron-beam spectroscopy and their promising diagnostic capabilities in free-electron quantum optics. This work introduces synthetic gain to electron-beam spectroscopy, greatly enhancing spectral resolution and revealing hidden features, enabling advances in nanoscale analysis and free electron-based quantum optics under challenging signal conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Trapping of single atoms in metasurface optical tweezer arrays</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09961-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09961-5</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 16:01:32 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Aaron Holman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuan Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ximo Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiahao Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingxuan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zezheng Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bojeong Seo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nanfang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sebastian Will</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09961-5</prism:doi><description>Optical tweezer arrays have emerged as a key experimental platform1,2 for quantum computation3,4, quantum simulation5,6 and quantum metrology7,8, enabling unprecedented levels of control over single atoms and molecules. The ability to scale such arrays has become a defining challenge. Typically, optical tweezer arrays are generated using acousto-optic deflectors or liquid-crystal spatial light modulators. Fundamental limitations in optical resolution have constrained array sizes to about 10,000 traps9. Metasurfaces10,11, planar photonic devices comprising millions of subwavelength pixels, provide an intriguing alternative for the generation of optical tweezer arrays12. Here we demonstrate the trapping of single strontium atoms in optical tweezer arrays generated via holographic metasurfaces. We realize two-dimensional arrays with more than 100 single atoms, arranged in arbitrary geometries with trap spacings as small as 1.5 μm. The arrays have a high uniformity in terms of trap depth, trap frequency and positional accuracy, rivalling or surpassing existing approaches. This is enabled by highly efficient holographic metasurfaces fabricated from high-refractive-index materials, silicon-rich silicon nitride and titanium dioxide. Through analytical and numerical methods, we find that the subwavelength pixel sizes of these metasurfaces allow scaling of tweezer arrays far beyond current capabilities. As a demonstration, we realize an optical tweezer array with 360,000 traps. These advances overcome a critical barrier to realizing scalable&amp;nbsp;neutral-atom quantum technologies. Single strontium atoms are trapped in optical tweezer arrays generated via holographic metasurfaces, overcoming a critical barrier to realizing scalable neutral-atom quantum technologies.
Published: 2026-01-14T16:01:32+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.522 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Aaron Holman; Yuan Xu; Ximo Sun; Jiahao Wu; Mingxuan Wang; Zezheng Zhu; Bojeong Seo; Nanfang Yu; Sebastian Will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09961-5"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09961-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.522 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optical tweezer arrays have emerged as a key experimental platform1,2 for quantum computation3,4, quantum simulation5,6 and quantum metrology7,8, enabling unprecedented levels of control over single atoms and molecules. The ability to scale such arrays has become a defining challenge. Typically, optical tweezer arrays are generated using acousto-optic deflectors or liquid-crystal spatial light modulators. Fundamental limitations in optical resolution have constrained array sizes to about 10,000 traps9. Metasurfaces10,11, planar photonic devices comprising millions of subwavelength pixels, provide an intriguing alternative for the generation of optical tweezer arrays12. Here we demonstrate the trapping of single strontium atoms in optical tweezer arrays generated via holographic metasurfaces. We realize two-dimensional arrays with more than 100 single atoms, arranged in arbitrary geometries with trap spacings as small as 1.5 μm. The arrays have a high uniformity in terms of trap depth, trap frequency and positional accuracy, rivalling or surpassing existing approaches. This is enabled by highly efficient holographic metasurfaces fabricated from high-refractive-index materials, silicon-rich silicon nitride and titanium dioxide. Through analytical and numerical methods, we find that the subwavelength pixel sizes of these metasurfaces allow scaling of tweezer arrays far beyond current capabilities. As a demonstration, we realize an optical tweezer array with 360,000 traps. These advances overcome a critical barrier to realizing scalable&amp;amp;nbsp;neutral-atom quantum technologies. Single strontium atoms are trapped in optical tweezer arrays generated via holographic metasurfaces, overcoming a critical barrier to realizing scalable neutral-atom quantum technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Global subsidence of river deltas</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09928-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09928-6</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 16:01:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>L. O. Ohenhen</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. Shirzaei</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. L. Davis</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Tiwari</dc:creator><dc:creator>R. Nicholls</dc:creator><dc:creator>O. Dasho</dc:creator><dc:creator>N. Sadhasivam</dc:creator><dc:creator>K. Seeger</dc:creator><dc:creator>S. Werth</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. J. Chadwick</dc:creator><dc:creator>F. Onyike</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. Lucy</dc:creator><dc:creator>C. Atkins</dc:creator><dc:creator>S. Daramola</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Ankamah</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. S. J. Minderhoud</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. Olsemann</dc:creator><dc:creator>G. C. Yemele</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09928-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract River deltas sustain dense human populations, major economic centres and vital ecosystems worldwide 1,2 . Rising sea levels and subsiding land threaten the sustainability of these valuable landscapes with relative sea-level rise and associated flood, land loss and salinization hazards 1–3 . Despite these risks, vulnerability assessments are impeded by the lack of contemporary, high-resolution, delta-wide subsidence observations 4 . Here we present spatially variable surface-elevation changes across 40 global deltas using interferometric synthetic aperture radar. Using this dataset, we quantify delta surface-elevation loss and show the prevalence and severity of subsidence in river deltas worldwide. Our analysis of three key anthropogenic drivers of delta elevation changes shows that groundwater storage has the strongest relative influence on vertical land motion in 10 of the 40 deltas. The other deltas are either influenced by multiple drivers or dominated by sediment flux or urban expansion. Furthermore, we find that contemporary subsidence surpasses absolute (geocentric) sea-level rise as the dominant driver of relative sea-level rise for most deltas over the twenty-first century. These findings suggest the need for targeted interventions addressing subsidence as an immediate and localized challenge, in parallel with broader efforts to mitigate and adapt to climate change-driven global sea-level rise.
Published: 2026-01-14T16:01:27+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.513 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; L. O. Ohenhen; M. Shirzaei; J. L. Davis; A. Tiwari; R. Nicholls; O. Dasho; N. Sadhasivam; K. Seeger; S. Werth; A. J. Chadwick; F. Onyike; J. Lucy; C. Atkins; S. Daramola; A. Ankamah; P. S. J. Minderhoud; J. Olsemann; G. C. Yemele&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09928-6"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09928-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.513 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract River deltas sustain dense human populations, major economic centres and vital ecosystems worldwide 1,2 . Rising sea levels and subsiding land threaten the sustainability of these valuable landscapes with relative sea-level rise and associated flood, land loss and salinization hazards 1–3 . Despite these risks, vulnerability assessments are impeded by the lack of contemporary, high-resolution, delta-wide subsidence observations 4 . Here we present spatially variable surface-elevation changes across 40 global deltas using interferometric synthetic aperture radar. Using this dataset, we quantify delta surface-elevation loss and show the prevalence and severity of subsidence in river deltas worldwide. Our analysis of three key anthropogenic drivers of delta elevation changes shows that groundwater storage has the strongest relative influence on vertical land motion in 10 of the 40 deltas. The other deltas are either influenced by multiple drivers or dominated by sediment flux or urban expansion. Furthermore, we find that contemporary subsidence surpasses absolute (geocentric) sea-level rise as the dominant driver of relative sea-level rise for most deltas over the twenty-first century. These findings suggest the need for targeted interventions addressing subsidence as an immediate and localized challenge, in parallel with broader efforts to mitigate and adapt to climate change-driven global sea-level rise.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Neural phase microscopy with metasurface optics for real-time and nanoscale quantitative phase imaging</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68151-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68151-z</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 15:48:39 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Gun-Yeal Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Changhyun Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manu Gopakumar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Youngjin Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Byoungho Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoonchan Jeong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gordon Wetzstein</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68151-z</prism:doi><description>Quantitative phase imaging (QPI) enables non-invasive analysis of transparent specimens across biomedicine, materials science, and neuroscience. However, conventional hardware relies on complex architectures with multi-shot acquisition that preclude compact, real-time operation, while phase-retrieval software often yields degraded image quality, is environmentally sensitive, and runs slowly. Here, we introduce a compact, fast, high-resolution QPI platform that addresses these challenges by integrating nanophotonic metasurfaces with artificial intelligence (AI). Our metasurface optics simplifies the optical architecture by replacing bulky optics and modulators, enabling single-shot acquisition and a drastic reduction in form factor. We develop physics-informed AI models that correct optical aberrations, compensate for imperfections in nanofabrication and alignment, and restore nanoscale quantitative phase information in real-time. The system achieves nanoscale resolution better than 840 nm at 74 Hz within a single, thin optical layer. Our unique combination of nanophotonic hardware and AI algorithms advances QPI technology towards portable, precise, real-time phase imaging. The authors introduce a compact, fast and high-resolution quantitative phase imaging system which integrates nanophotonic metasurfaces with artificial intelligence (AI)-driven algorithms. They demonstrate nanoscale resolution better than 840 nm at a 74 Hz frame rate, all within a single thin optical layer.
Published: 2026-01-13T15:48:39+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.513 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Gun-Yeal Lee; Changhyun Kim; Manu Gopakumar; Youngjin Kim; Byoungho Lee; Yoonchan Jeong; Gordon Wetzstein&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68151-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68151-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.513 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quantitative phase imaging (QPI) enables non-invasive analysis of transparent specimens across biomedicine, materials science, and neuroscience. However, conventional hardware relies on complex architectures with multi-shot acquisition that preclude compact, real-time operation, while phase-retrieval software often yields degraded image quality, is environmentally sensitive, and runs slowly. Here, we introduce a compact, fast, high-resolution QPI platform that addresses these challenges by integrating nanophotonic metasurfaces with artificial intelligence (AI). Our metasurface optics simplifies the optical architecture by replacing bulky optics and modulators, enabling single-shot acquisition and a drastic reduction in form factor. We develop physics-informed AI models that correct optical aberrations, compensate for imperfections in nanofabrication and alignment, and restore nanoscale quantitative phase information in real-time. The system achieves nanoscale resolution better than 840 nm at 74 Hz within a single, thin optical layer. Our unique combination of nanophotonic hardware and AI algorithms advances QPI technology towards portable, precise, real-time phase imaging. The authors introduce a compact, fast and high-resolution quantitative phase imaging system which integrates nanophotonic metasurfaces with artificial intelligence (AI)-driven algorithms. They demonstrate nanoscale resolution better than 840 nm at a 74 Hz frame rate, all within a single thin optical layer.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Solvent-mediated partial ionicity enhances mechanical nanosizing effect of Mg-based hydrogen storage alloys</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68390-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68390-8</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 09:47:54 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tianpeng Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengjie Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuan Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qun Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qian Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yangfan Lu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68390-8</prism:doi><description>The high ductility of Mg has posed major challenges for nanofabrication utilizing mechanical ball-milling. While the addition of organic solvents is effective, it has been unclear how they improve the ball-milling effect by modifying the material’s surface properties. Herein, we report that the solvent-mediated partial ionicity plays an important role in enhancing the nanosizing effect of Mg87.5Ni5.5Y7 alloy. This approach enables the Mg87.5Ni5.5Y7 particles to be 88 times smaller than those of the solvent-free procedure. The Mg87.5Ni5.5Y7 nanoparticles underwent complete dehydrogenation in 3 min at 300 °C and in 17 min at 240 °C, which can be stably cycled at least for 500 times. Solvent (THF) adsorption on Mg induces Mgδ+‒Mgδ− dipole structure. This increases the surface hardness of Mg-based alloy and maximizes the ball milling-driven structural deformation, thereby facilitating ion migration. Mg‒Mg bond breaking is caused by the resulting Coulombic repulsion between Mg atoms. These findings provide an affordable approach for nanoparticle fabrication of highly ductile materials. The work highlights the role of solvent-mediated ionicity in modifying surface hardness of Mg-Ni-Y alloy, which facilitates the production of nanoparticles ~88 times smaller than milled powder without solvent processing, resulting in a scalable production method for metallic nanoparticles.
Published: 2026-01-14T09:47:54+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.510 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tianpeng Sun; Zhengjie Tang; Jiang Liu; Xuan Sun; Qun Luo; Yu Zhang; Qian Li; Yangfan Lu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68390-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68390-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.510 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high ductility of Mg has posed major challenges for nanofabrication utilizing mechanical ball-milling. While the addition of organic solvents is effective, it has been unclear how they improve the ball-milling effect by modifying the material’s surface properties. Herein, we report that the solvent-mediated partial ionicity plays an important role in enhancing the nanosizing effect of Mg87.5Ni5.5Y7 alloy. This approach enables the Mg87.5Ni5.5Y7 particles to be 88 times smaller than those of the solvent-free procedure. The Mg87.5Ni5.5Y7 nanoparticles underwent complete dehydrogenation in 3 min at 300 °C and in 17 min at 240 °C, which can be stably cycled at least for 500 times. Solvent (THF) adsorption on Mg induces Mgδ+‒Mgδ− dipole structure. This increases the surface hardness of Mg-based alloy and maximizes the ball milling-driven structural deformation, thereby facilitating ion migration. Mg‒Mg bond breaking is caused by the resulting Coulombic repulsion between Mg atoms. These findings provide an affordable approach for nanoparticle fabrication of highly ductile materials. The work highlights the role of solvent-mediated ionicity in modifying surface hardness of Mg-Ni-Y alloy, which facilitates the production of nanoparticles ~88 times smaller than milled powder without solvent processing, resulting in a scalable production method for metallic nanoparticles.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mosaic lateral heterostructures in two-dimensional perovskite</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09949-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09949-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 16:01:34 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shuchen Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuan Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linghai Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongsheng Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaoming Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaxin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zehua He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanjun Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenjian Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yue Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shangfeng Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Letian Dou</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09949-1</prism:doi><description>Lateral heterostructures are important for exploring exotic physics, developing new devices and achieving device miniaturization1–8. Endo-epitaxial growth occurring in patterned templates presents a promising strategy to realize extensive patterned areas in heterostructures, as recently demonstrated with two-dimensional (2D) covalent materials9–13. However, the conventional lithography and etching processes used to prepare patterned templates are too aggressive for 2D lead halide perovskites, owing to their inherently soft and unstable ionic lattice14–16. Here we create square holes of controllable size within 2D lead halide perovskites, enabling the fabrication of continuous lateral heterostructures over large areas. We demonstrate that the square holes form through spontaneous etching, a process initiated by internal strain and stabilized along the [100]/[010] crystallographic direction. Furthermore, the size of the square holes can be controlled by adjusting the etching time and temperature. Moreover, by incorporating a rapid solvent evaporation growth technique, the edges of the square holes act as templates for epitaxial growth of another type of perovskite, incorporating different halide or metal ions. Finally, we realized a series of mosaic lateral heterostructures that can emit various colours for light-emitting devices. This synthesis of diverse 2D perovskite mosaic lateral heterostructures provides valuable insights into the structural characteristics of perovskites and offers a versatile material platform for the development of complex integrated emitting devices. Colourful patterns in two-dimensional lead halide perovskites are created by letting them self-etch into tiny squares that can template epitaxial growth.
Published: 2026-01-14T16:01:34+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.508 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shuchen Zhang; Yuan Lu; Linghai Zhang; Hongsheng Shi; Xiao Wang; Zhaoming Wang; Jiaxin Li; Zehua He; Kang Wang; Ke Ma; Hanjun Yang; Chenjian Lin; Yue Hu; Shangfeng Yang; Yi Yu; Letian Dou&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09949-1"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09949-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.508 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lateral heterostructures are important for exploring exotic physics, developing new devices and achieving device miniaturization1–8. Endo-epitaxial growth occurring in patterned templates presents a promising strategy to realize extensive patterned areas in heterostructures, as recently demonstrated with two-dimensional (2D) covalent materials9–13. However, the conventional lithography and etching processes used to prepare patterned templates are too aggressive for 2D lead halide perovskites, owing to their inherently soft and unstable ionic lattice14–16. Here we create square holes of controllable size within 2D lead halide perovskites, enabling the fabrication of continuous lateral heterostructures over large areas. We demonstrate that the square holes form through spontaneous etching, a process initiated by internal strain and stabilized along the [100]/[010] crystallographic direction. Furthermore, the size of the square holes can be controlled by adjusting the etching time and temperature. Moreover, by incorporating a rapid solvent evaporation growth technique, the edges of the square holes act as templates for epitaxial growth of another type of perovskite, incorporating different halide or metal ions. Finally, we realized a series of mosaic lateral heterostructures that can emit various colours for light-emitting devices. This synthesis of diverse 2D perovskite mosaic lateral heterostructures provides valuable insights into the structural characteristics of perovskites and offers a versatile material platform for the development of complex integrated emitting devices. Colourful patterns in two-dimensional lead halide perovskites are created by letting them self-etch into tiny squares that can template epitaxial growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Lewis acid-triggered hydroxyl spillover enables selective urea electrooxidation to nitrite with concurrent energy-saving hydrogen production</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68302-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68302-w</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 15:48:32 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chao Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunchao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yali Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan-Qin Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feilong Gong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68302-w</prism:doi><description>Nitrite (NO2⁻) is a high-value chemical pivotal to agriculture and pharmaceuticals, yet its conventional via the Ostwald process is energy-intensive and polluting. Electrochemical urea oxidation reaction (UOR) offers a sustainable NO2⁻ synthesis pathway with concurrent energy-saving hydrogen (H2) production, but suffers from non-selective N2/CO2 pathways. Here, we report Cr3+ Lewis acid sites in Ni3S2 that act as hydroxyl (OH⁻) pumps, dynamically spilling OH⁻ to adjacent Ni sites via a Lewis acid-base interaction. This triggers a urea-to-NO2⁻ pathway, achieving a NO2⁻ yield of 120.98 mg h-1 cm-2 (600 mA cm-2). The OH⁻ spillover accelerates C-N cleavage while suppressing N-N coupling, enabling energy-saving H2 production (3.7 kWh m-3 at 500 mA cm-2) and Zn-urea-air batteries (charging potential 288 mV lower than Zn-air). Techno-economic analysis reveals $1,210.5 per ton of urea processed at 400 mA cm-2. This work establishes OH⁻ spillover as a universal design principle for selective electrocatalysis. Electrochemical urea oxidation can coproduce nitrite and H2, but it typically lacks selectivity. Here, the authors address this issue by designing doped Lewis acid sites to trigger a hydroxyl spillover mechanism, resulting in highly selective nitrite production and efficient energy conversion.
Published: 2026-01-13T15:48:32+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.507 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chao Fan; Meng Zhang; Yunchao Li; Yali Zhang; Yan-Qin Wang; Feilong Gong; Jian Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68302-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68302-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.507 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nitrite (NO2⁻) is a high-value chemical pivotal to agriculture and pharmaceuticals, yet its conventional via the Ostwald process is energy-intensive and polluting. Electrochemical urea oxidation reaction (UOR) offers a sustainable NO2⁻ synthesis pathway with concurrent energy-saving hydrogen (H2) production, but suffers from non-selective N2/CO2 pathways. Here, we report Cr3+ Lewis acid sites in Ni3S2 that act as hydroxyl (OH⁻) pumps, dynamically spilling OH⁻ to adjacent Ni sites via a Lewis acid-base interaction. This triggers a urea-to-NO2⁻ pathway, achieving a NO2⁻ yield of 120.98 mg h-1 cm-2 (600 mA cm-2). The OH⁻ spillover accelerates C-N cleavage while suppressing N-N coupling, enabling energy-saving H2 production (3.7 kWh m-3 at 500 mA cm-2) and Zn-urea-air batteries (charging potential 288 mV lower than Zn-air). Techno-economic analysis reveals $1,210.5 per ton of urea processed at 400 mA cm-2. This work establishes OH⁻ spillover as a universal design principle for selective electrocatalysis. Electrochemical urea oxidation can coproduce nitrite and H2, but it typically lacks selectivity. Here, the authors address this issue by designing doped Lewis acid sites to trigger a hydroxyl spillover mechanism, resulting in highly selective nitrite production and efficient energy conversion.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Triassic–Jurassic environmental instability on the subtropical eastern Tethyan margin linked to low-latitude dinosaur dispersal</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03083-6</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03083-6</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 07:59:47 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jianbo Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi-Ning Niu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rongyao Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan-Ling Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen-Jie Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ya-Ming Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hai-Lu You</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xing Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shu-Zhong Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhuo Feng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03083-6</prism:doi><description>The Triassic–Jurassic transition marks a critical interval, witnessing major biotic turnovers, including the rise of dinosaurs and the end-Triassic mass extinction, triggered by the Central Atlantic Magmatic Province. However, the volcanism linked to terrestrial ecosystem disturbance and dinosaur distribution remains poorly constrained. Here we present an integrated dataset of chemostratigraphic and astrochronological records for a continental drill core from the Kunming Basin in Yunnan Province of Southwest China, where rich dinosaur assemblages have been previously identified. Three negative carbon isotope excursions coupled with volcanogenic mercury anomalies confirm pulsed volcanism-induced environmental impacts on this subtropical terrestrial setting and placement of the Triassic–Jurassic boundary. Critically, the earliest regional sauropodomorph fossils occurred at ~200.17 Ma, indicating post-extinction colonization in low palaeolatitudes by medium- to large-bodied dinosaurs. Large-scale volcanism-induced stressors, potentially coupled with increased climate seasonality, likely created ecological opportunities facilitating dinosaur expansion in the earliest Jurassic. Early regional sauropodomorph fossils from 200.17 Ma suggest post-Triassic mass extinction dinosaur colonization in low paleolatitudes, likely due to Central Atlantic Magmatic Province stressors and increased climate seasonality, according to chemostratigraphic and astrochronological analysis of a core from the Kunming Basin in China.
Published: 2026-01-13T07:59:47+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.507 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jianbo Chen; Yi-Ning Niu; Rongyao Ma; Yan-Ling Zhou; Wen-Jie Liu; Ya-Ming Wang; Hai-Lu You; Xing Xu; Shu-Zhong Shen; Zhuo Feng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03083-6"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03083-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.507 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Triassic–Jurassic transition marks a critical interval, witnessing major biotic turnovers, including the rise of dinosaurs and the end-Triassic mass extinction, triggered by the Central Atlantic Magmatic Province. However, the volcanism linked to terrestrial ecosystem disturbance and dinosaur distribution remains poorly constrained. Here we present an integrated dataset of chemostratigraphic and astrochronological records for a continental drill core from the Kunming Basin in Yunnan Province of Southwest China, where rich dinosaur assemblages have been previously identified. Three negative carbon isotope excursions coupled with volcanogenic mercury anomalies confirm pulsed volcanism-induced environmental impacts on this subtropical terrestrial setting and placement of the Triassic–Jurassic boundary. Critically, the earliest regional sauropodomorph fossils occurred at ~200.17 Ma, indicating post-extinction colonization in low palaeolatitudes by medium- to large-bodied dinosaurs. Large-scale volcanism-induced stressors, potentially coupled with increased climate seasonality, likely created ecological opportunities facilitating dinosaur expansion in the earliest Jurassic. Early regional sauropodomorph fossils from 200.17 Ma suggest post-Triassic mass extinction dinosaur colonization in low paleolatitudes, likely due to Central Atlantic Magmatic Province stressors and increased climate seasonality, according to chemostratigraphic and astrochronological analysis of a core from the Kunming Basin in China.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Efficient and stable catalytic hydrolysis of perfluorocarbon enabled by SO2-mediated proton supply</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68386-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68386-4</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 10:25:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingkang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaojian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Edoardo Mariani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junwei Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Changxu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hui Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhang Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liyuan Chai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michelle L. Coote</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emiliano Cortés</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68386-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract Catalytic hydrolysis is an effective strategy for decomposing tetrafluoromethane (CF 4 ), one of the most chemically inert per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). A key challenge in this process lies in enhancing proton availability to facilitate efficient and stable C–F bond activation while ensuring long-term catalyst stability. Here we present an SO 2 -driven approach to significantly enhance H 2 O dissociation and proton-supplying through the in situ formation of Al–HSO 4 and Ga–HS species. Combined experimental and theoretical investigations reveal that these species not only lower the energy barrier for C–F bond activation but also promote active site regeneration by facilitating defluorination, thus effectively overcoming catalyst deactivation. As a result, the optimized catalyst enables complete CF 4 decomposition at a low temperature of 550°C, with stable operation for over 2500 hours. This work establishes a new paradigm for regulating proton transfer and offers a viable route for the efficient, durable degradation of gaseous PFAS.
Published: 2026-01-14T10:25:26+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.504 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hang Zhang; Tao Luo; Yingkang Chen; Xiaojian Wang; Edoardo Mariani; Kang Liu; Junwei Fu; Changxu Liu; Hui Liu; Zhang Lin; Liyuan Chai; Michelle L. Coote; Emiliano Cortés; Min Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68386-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68386-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.504 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Catalytic hydrolysis is an effective strategy for decomposing tetrafluoromethane (CF 4 ), one of the most chemically inert per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances (PFAS). A key challenge in this process lies in enhancing proton availability to facilitate efficient and stable C–F bond activation while ensuring long-term catalyst stability. Here we present an SO 2 -driven approach to significantly enhance H 2 O dissociation and proton-supplying through the in situ formation of Al–HSO 4 and Ga–HS species. Combined experimental and theoretical investigations reveal that these species not only lower the energy barrier for C–F bond activation but also promote active site regeneration by facilitating defluorination, thus effectively overcoming catalyst deactivation. As a result, the optimized catalyst enables complete CF 4 decomposition at a low temperature of 550°C, with stable operation for over 2500 hours. This work establishes a new paradigm for regulating proton transfer and offers a viable route for the efficient, durable degradation of gaseous PFAS.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Coherent nonlinear X-ray four-photon interaction with core-shell electrons</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09911-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09911-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 16:01:24 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ana Sofia Morillo-Candas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sven Augustin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eduard Prat</dc:creator><dc:creator>Antoine Sarracini</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonas Knurr</dc:creator><dc:creator>Serhane Zerdane</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhibin Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ningchen Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marc Rebholz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hankai Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunpei Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinhua Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Elnaz Zyaee</dc:creator><dc:creator>David Rohrbach</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrea Cannizzo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andre Al-Haddad</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kirsten Schnorr</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christian Ott</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Feurer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christoph Bostedt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Pfeifer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gregor Knopp</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09911-1</prism:doi><description>Coherent nonlinear light–matter interaction with X-rays gives access to a regime in ultrafast spectroscopy in which atomic resolution meets femtosecond and attosecond timescales1,2. Particularly, X-ray four-wave mixing, involving several resonant transitions in a single coherent nonlinear process, has the potential to provide information on the electronic states coupling, coherent electron motion, correlation and dynamics, with state and site selectivity3–5. Here we demonstrate coherent, background-free four-photon interactions with core-shell electrons using single broadband X-ray pulses from a free-electron laser. The all-X-ray four-wave mixing signals, measured in gaseous neon, arise from doubly resonant nonlinear processes involving Raman transitions6, including X-ray coherent anti-Stokes electronic Raman scattering. The 2D spectral maps (photon-in/photon-out) represent a step towards multidimensional correlation spectroscopy at the atomic scale. Using a multicolour time-delayed X-ray pulse scheme, we further demonstrate the feasibility of extending the proposed methodology to the ultrafast time domain. These results reveal potential for studying localized electron dynamics in multiple systems, from biomolecules to correlated quantum materials, with applications in areas such as energy conversion, biomedical imaging and quantum information technologies. Using single broadband X-ray pulses from a free-electron laser on a gaseous neon target, coherent, nonlinear four-photon interactions with core–shell electrons is demonstrated, representing a strategy for multidimensional correlation spectroscopy at the atomic scale.
Published: 2026-01-14T16:01:24+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.503 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ana Sofia Morillo-Candas; Sven Augustin; Eduard Prat; Antoine Sarracini; Jonas Knurr; Serhane Zerdane; Zhibin Sun; Ningchen Yang; Marc Rebholz; Hankai Zhang; Yunpei Deng; Xinhua Xie; Elnaz Zyaee; David Rohrbach; Andrea Cannizzo; Andre Al-Haddad; Kirsten Schnorr; Christian Ott; Thomas Feurer; Christoph Bostedt; Thomas Pfeifer; Gregor Knopp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09911-1"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09911-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.503 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coherent nonlinear light–matter interaction with X-rays gives access to a regime in ultrafast spectroscopy in which atomic resolution meets femtosecond and attosecond timescales1,2. Particularly, X-ray four-wave mixing, involving several resonant transitions in a single coherent nonlinear process, has the potential to provide information on the electronic states coupling, coherent electron motion, correlation and dynamics, with state and site selectivity3–5. Here we demonstrate coherent, background-free four-photon interactions with core-shell electrons using single broadband X-ray pulses from a free-electron laser. The all-X-ray four-wave mixing signals, measured in gaseous neon, arise from doubly resonant nonlinear processes involving Raman transitions6, including X-ray coherent anti-Stokes electronic Raman scattering. The 2D spectral maps (photon-in/photon-out) represent a step towards multidimensional correlation spectroscopy at the atomic scale. Using a multicolour time-delayed X-ray pulse scheme, we further demonstrate the feasibility of extending the proposed methodology to the ultrafast time domain. These results reveal potential for studying localized electron dynamics in multiple systems, from biomolecules to correlated quantum materials, with applications in areas such as energy conversion, biomedical imaging and quantum information technologies. Using single broadband X-ray pulses from a free-electron laser on a gaseous neon target, coherent, nonlinear four-photon interactions with core–shell electrons is demonstrated, representing a strategy for multidimensional correlation spectroscopy at the atomic scale.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>