<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 23:43:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Protracted subduction and slab rollback of the Paleo-Asian Ocean during the late Paleozoic: Insight from polyphase metamorphism in the Baoyintu Group, central-western Inner Mongolia</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38668.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38668.1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 20:51:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shuang Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinrui Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chris Yakymchuk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunjing Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hang Chu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yidan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuan Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38668.1</prism:doi><description>Understanding the relationship between tectonic patterns and metamorphic processes generated by subduction is essential for reconstructing the evolutionary history of orogenic systems. However, these connections can be obscured by poly-metamorphism that overprints or erases evidence of earlier metamorphism. To evaluate the role of continuous subduction on overprinting previous metamorphic events, we examine the subduction dynamics of the Paleo-Asian Ocean during the late Paleozoic. This evaluation is based on evidence of multi-stage metamorphism, including high-, medium-, and low-pressure type metamorphism identified from the metasedimentary rocks in the Baoyintu Group terrane of central-western Inner Mongolia, China. We use petrographic observations, phase equilibrium modeling, and U-Pb and Rb-Sr geochronology. High-pressure metamorphic mineral assemblages from the Baoyintu Group include chlorite, garnet, phengite, rutile, and quartz. Medium-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, biotite, garnet, muscovite, staurolite, kyanite, plagioclase, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Low-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, garnet, biotite, muscovite, andalusite, sillimanite, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Phase equilibrium modeling suggests apparent pressure-temperature conditions of ∼14−19 kbar and 510−580 °C for the high-pressure metamorphism, ∼5−10 kbar and 575−770 °C for the medium-pressure metamorphism, and ∼3−7 kbar and 565−750 °C for the low-pressure metamorphism. In situ mica Rb-Sr geochronology yields a metamorphic age for the high-pressure phase of ca. 369 Ma; rutile U-Pb geochronology of medium-pressure metamorphism yields a metamorphic age of ca. 399 Ma. Monazite and rutile U-Pb geochronology of the low-pressure assemblage indicates a metamorphic age of ca. 267−252 Ma. Devonian high- and medium-pressure belts are distributed in a northeast-southwest direction, consistent with the timing of magmatic events in the Baoyintu Group during subduction. The Permian low-pressure belt is oriented east-west, partially overprinting the high- and medium-temperature belts, and is contemporaneous with magmatic events related to extension. These results suggest that the subduction boundary of the Paleo-Asian Ocean in this region was northeast-southwest during the Devonian and shifted to east-west during the late-stage subduction in the Permian. This study reveals that irregularities along subduction boundaries can lead to multiple orogenic events, prompting a re-evaluation of inferring complex tectonic processes from polymetamorphosed rocks.
Published: 2026-01-09T20:51:21+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.592 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shuang Tang; Jinrui Zhang; Chris Yakymchuk; Chunjing Wei; Hang Chu; Yidan Wang; Yuan Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38668.1"&gt;10.1130/b38668.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.592 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the relationship between tectonic patterns and metamorphic processes generated by subduction is essential for reconstructing the evolutionary history of orogenic systems. However, these connections can be obscured by poly-metamorphism that overprints or erases evidence of earlier metamorphism. To evaluate the role of continuous subduction on overprinting previous metamorphic events, we examine the subduction dynamics of the Paleo-Asian Ocean during the late Paleozoic. This evaluation is based on evidence of multi-stage metamorphism, including high-, medium-, and low-pressure type metamorphism identified from the metasedimentary rocks in the Baoyintu Group terrane of central-western Inner Mongolia, China. We use petrographic observations, phase equilibrium modeling, and U-Pb and Rb-Sr geochronology. High-pressure metamorphic mineral assemblages from the Baoyintu Group include chlorite, garnet, phengite, rutile, and quartz. Medium-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, biotite, garnet, muscovite, staurolite, kyanite, plagioclase, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Low-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, garnet, biotite, muscovite, andalusite, sillimanite, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Phase equilibrium modeling suggests apparent pressure-temperature conditions of ∼14−19 kbar and 510−580 °C for the high-pressure metamorphism, ∼5−10 kbar and 575−770 °C for the medium-pressure metamorphism, and ∼3−7 kbar and 565−750 °C for the low-pressure metamorphism. In situ mica Rb-Sr geochronology yields a metamorphic age for the high-pressure phase of ca. 369 Ma; rutile U-Pb geochronology of medium-pressure metamorphism yields a metamorphic age of ca. 399 Ma. Monazite and rutile U-Pb geochronology of the low-pressure assemblage indicates a metamorphic age of ca. 267−252 Ma. Devonian high- and medium-pressure belts are distributed in a northeast-southwest direction, consistent with the timing of magmatic events in the Baoyintu Group during subduction. The Permian low-pressure belt is oriented east-west, partially overprinting the high- and medium-temperature belts, and is contemporaneous with magmatic events related to extension. These results suggest that the subduction boundary of the Paleo-Asian Ocean in this region was northeast-southwest during the Devonian and shifted to east-west during the late-stage subduction in the Permian. This study reveals that irregularities along subduction boundaries can lead to multiple orogenic events, prompting a re-evaluation of inferring complex tectonic processes from polymetamorphosed rocks.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The major ion chemistry of seawater was closely coupled to the long-term carbon cycle during the Cenozoic</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2511781122</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2511781122</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:46:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>David Evans</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yair Rosenthal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan Erez</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hagar Hauzer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laura J. Cotton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoli Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Romi Nambiar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter Stassen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul N. Pearson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Willem Renema</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pratul Kumar Saraswati</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan A. Todd</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wolfgang Müller</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hagit P. Affek</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2511781122</prism:doi><description>A ~fivefold decrease in the atmospheric concentration of CO 2 took place during the Cenozoic. This has often been viewed within the context of silicate weathering changes, although the specific contributions of the potential drivers remain poorly understood. Indeed, it has been alternatively argued that changes in the sea floor spreading rate contributed to the Cenozoic p CO 2 decline, although the magnitude of the decrease means that this is unlikely to account for the entirety of the p CO 2 change. One previously overlooked factor is the concomitant change in the major element composition of seawater, especially the concentration of calcium ([Ca 2+ sw ]), which is typically viewed as responding to processes such as weathering, rather than representing a driver in and of itself. Here, we present the first detailed record of the Cenozoic major ion chemistry of seawater and show that [Ca 2+ sw ] has the potential to control key processes that impact the carbon cycle. Although our record cannot determine whether CO 2 is causally driven by [Ca 2+ sw ], carbon cycle box modeling identifies that this may have been the case. Whether or not [Ca 2+ sw ] indeed directly drove p CO 2 during the Cenozoic principally depends on the strength of the silicate weathering feedback and the magnitude of any possible changes in organic carbon burial, both of which could overwhelm a [Ca 2+ sw ]-driven impact on the carbon cycle. As such, determining the sensitivity of the weathering–climate relationship on million-year timescales is key to resolving whether factors such as seawater major ion composition are important carbon cycle drivers.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:46:07+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.584 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; David Evans; Yair Rosenthal; Jonathan Erez; Hagar Hauzer; Laura J. Cotton; Xiaoli Zhou; Romi Nambiar; Peter Stassen; Paul N. Pearson; Willem Renema; Pratul Kumar Saraswati; Jonathan A. Todd; Wolfgang Müller; Hagit P. Affek&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2511781122"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2511781122&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.584 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ~fivefold decrease in the atmospheric concentration of CO 2 took place during the Cenozoic. This has often been viewed within the context of silicate weathering changes, although the specific contributions of the potential drivers remain poorly understood. Indeed, it has been alternatively argued that changes in the sea floor spreading rate contributed to the Cenozoic p CO 2 decline, although the magnitude of the decrease means that this is unlikely to account for the entirety of the p CO 2 change. One previously overlooked factor is the concomitant change in the major element composition of seawater, especially the concentration of calcium ([Ca 2+ sw ]), which is typically viewed as responding to processes such as weathering, rather than representing a driver in and of itself. Here, we present the first detailed record of the Cenozoic major ion chemistry of seawater and show that [Ca 2+ sw ] has the potential to control key processes that impact the carbon cycle. Although our record cannot determine whether CO 2 is causally driven by [Ca 2+ sw ], carbon cycle box modeling identifies that this may have been the case. Whether or not [Ca 2+ sw ] indeed directly drove p CO 2 during the Cenozoic principally depends on the strength of the silicate weathering feedback and the magnitude of any possible changes in organic carbon burial, both of which could overwhelm a [Ca 2+ sw ]-driven impact on the carbon cycle. As such, determining the sensitivity of the weathering–climate relationship on million-year timescales is key to resolving whether factors such as seawater major ion composition are important carbon cycle drivers.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Decoupling slab gliding and lattice contraction in Na layered oxides to enable high-voltage Na-ion batteries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68238-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68238-7</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 09:07:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qinhao Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fanghua Ning</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuan Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fanjie Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruijuan Qi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guofeng Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haoyang Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongfei Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shigang Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tu Lan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinsong Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingchun Lyu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huaican Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen Wen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenpeng Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiujun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yufeng Zhao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68238-7</prism:doi><description>Layered transition metal oxide cathodes (NaxTMO2) demonstrate a classic type of cathode for Sodium-ion batteries (SIBs), however their practical application faces a long-standing challenge of irreversible phase transitions at high voltages, which causes unsatisfied specific energy and cycling stability, particularly for P-type (Na+ located at prismatic sites) cathodes. This phenomenon is conventionally ascribed to the Na+ re-coordination from prismatic to octahedral (O-type) configuration upon Na+ extraction, whereby the TMO2 slab gliding and abrupt c-lattice change are always coupled, and a straightforward solution to this situation remains elusive. Here, we reveal that, the TMO2 slab gliding and the lattice contraction can be decoupled, and the rapid lattice contraction under high state-of-charge underlies the fundamental origin for the irreversible phase transitions. By pre-engineering 15.8% O-type stacking faults to a P-type Na0.7Mn0.8Ni0.2O2, the dramatic volume variation and irreversible phase transitions at high voltage (4.5 V vs. Na+/Na) can be primarily eliminated. This work advances the understanding on the phase transitions at deep desodiation states, and paves up a feasible way to realize high-energy layered oxides. Phase transitions in Na layered transition metal oxide materials involving slab gliding and considerable lattice parameter changes limit the battery cycling life, especially at high voltages. Here, authors pre-engineer 15.8% O-type stacking faults to a P-type Na0.7Mn0.8Ni0.2O2, improving stability and enabling an electrode specific energy of 635 Wh kg-1 with 600-cycle life.
Published: 2026-01-10T09:07:00+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.572 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qinhao Shi; Fanghua Ning; Xuan Yu; Fanjie Xia; Ruijuan Qi; Guofeng Cheng; Yi Qiu; Haoyang Liang; Hongfei Zheng; Tao Zhang; Shigang Lu; Tu Lan; Jinsong Wu; Yingchun Lyu; Huaican Chen; Wen Wen; Zhenpeng Yao; Jiujun Zhang; Jun Lu; Yufeng Zhao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68238-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68238-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.572 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Layered transition metal oxide cathodes (NaxTMO2) demonstrate a classic type of cathode for Sodium-ion batteries (SIBs), however their practical application faces a long-standing challenge of irreversible phase transitions at high voltages, which causes unsatisfied specific energy and cycling stability, particularly for P-type (Na+ located at prismatic sites) cathodes. This phenomenon is conventionally ascribed to the Na+ re-coordination from prismatic to octahedral (O-type) configuration upon Na+ extraction, whereby the TMO2 slab gliding and abrupt c-lattice change are always coupled, and a straightforward solution to this situation remains elusive. Here, we reveal that, the TMO2 slab gliding and the lattice contraction can be decoupled, and the rapid lattice contraction under high state-of-charge underlies the fundamental origin for the irreversible phase transitions. By pre-engineering 15.8% O-type stacking faults to a P-type Na0.7Mn0.8Ni0.2O2, the dramatic volume variation and irreversible phase transitions at high voltage (4.5 V vs. Na+/Na) can be primarily eliminated. This work advances the understanding on the phase transitions at deep desodiation states, and paves up a feasible way to realize high-energy layered oxides. Phase transitions in Na layered transition metal oxide materials involving slab gliding and considerable lattice parameter changes limit the battery cycling life, especially at high voltages. Here, authors pre-engineer 15.8% O-type stacking faults to a P-type Na0.7Mn0.8Ni0.2O2, improving stability and enabling an electrode specific energy of 635 Wh kg-1 with 600-cycle life.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Well-connected basalt sequences as potential reservoirs for large-scale carbon sequestration revealed by strontium isotopes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 13:48:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Stéphane Polteau</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. Craig Smalley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vani N. Devegowda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ingar Johansen</dc:creator><dc:creator>John M. Millett</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marija P. Rosenqvist</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mohamed Mansour Abdelmalak</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sverre Planke</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7</prism:doi><description>Abstract Permanent storage of gigatons of carbon in basalt requires thick, uncompartmentalized sequences that allow lateral dissipation of CO 2 away from injection sites. Here we assess the presence of flow barriers by evaluating the variations in 87 Sr/ 86 Sr patterns in pore water, a method used extensively in sedimentary successions. Present-day pore water 87 Sr/ 86 Sr was measured from residual salts in core samples, while past water compositions were reconstructed from carbonate cements of different ages. We reveal smooth and uninterrupted trends in strontium isotopes through a 100 m thick basalt section indicating a common fluid reservoir unaffected by low-permeability massive lava flow interiors. The data further indicate that unconsolidated overburden sediments act as a good seal preventing seawater to mix with in situ pore water, and buoyant supercritical CO 2 to leak. Finally, basaltic sequences form viable targets for CO 2 storage and suggests that fractures may bypass low-permeability units to create a well-connected reservoir system.
Published: 2026-01-09T13:48:16+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.571 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Stéphane Polteau; P. Craig Smalley; Vani N. Devegowda; Ingar Johansen; John M. Millett; Marija P. Rosenqvist; Mohamed Mansour Abdelmalak; Sverre Planke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.571 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Permanent storage of gigatons of carbon in basalt requires thick, uncompartmentalized sequences that allow lateral dissipation of CO 2 away from injection sites. Here we assess the presence of flow barriers by evaluating the variations in 87 Sr/ 86 Sr patterns in pore water, a method used extensively in sedimentary successions. Present-day pore water 87 Sr/ 86 Sr was measured from residual salts in core samples, while past water compositions were reconstructed from carbonate cements of different ages. We reveal smooth and uninterrupted trends in strontium isotopes through a 100 m thick basalt section indicating a common fluid reservoir unaffected by low-permeability massive lava flow interiors. The data further indicate that unconsolidated overburden sediments act as a good seal preventing seawater to mix with in situ pore water, and buoyant supercritical CO 2 to leak. Finally, basaltic sequences form viable targets for CO 2 storage and suggests that fractures may bypass low-permeability units to create a well-connected reservoir system.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mantle heterogeneity and complicated melt migration revealed by chemical gradients across the dunite-harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite, South Tibet</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 01:14:46 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhen-Yu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuan-Zhou Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo-Da Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5</prism:doi><description>Dunite channels are critical pathways for melt extraction and migration within the asthenosphere. Although their formation within mantle peridotite sequences is often attributed to melt-rock interaction, the underlying physical processes remain poorly constrained. This study examines variations in both major and trace elements across a dunite-harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite to better understand these physical processes. Geochemical profiles across the dunite-harzburgite transect reveal concentration gradients near the dunite-harzburgite contact, particularly within the harzburgite. Such compositional variations were interpreted through two-dimensional numerical simulations, coupled with diffusion and advection in porous media. The results indicate that trace element gradients in olivine can be produced by a melt flow along the dunite–harzburgite boundary with lateral advection from dunite to harzburgite, which is consistent with those observed in the field. Trace element patterns of the interstitial clinopyroxene grains within the dunite suggest their crystallization from a final pulse of percolating melt through the channel during the waning stage of the melt transport system, which probably occurred shortly before the ophiolite obduction. Integrating these results with previous studies on mafic–ultramafic rocks in the Moho Transition Zone (MTZ), we propose that the dunite–harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite was initially generated in the asthenosphere beneath an ultra-slow spreading ridge, which subsequently experienced a multi-stage history of melt migration and melt–rock interaction during progressive mantle upwelling. Such a complex history significantly influenced the lithological and geochemical architecture of the MTZ of the ophiolite. Overall, results from this study demonstrate that both dunites and their surrounding harzburgites bear variable concentration gradients, resulting from both mantle heterogeneity and variations in melt compositions within individual dunite channel.
Published: 2026-01-09T01:14:46+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.563 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhen-Yu Zhang; Chuan-Zhou Liu; Yan Liang; Tong Liu; Chang Zhang; Bo-Da Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.563 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunite channels are critical pathways for melt extraction and migration within the asthenosphere. Although their formation within mantle peridotite sequences is often attributed to melt-rock interaction, the underlying physical processes remain poorly constrained. This study examines variations in both major and trace elements across a dunite-harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite to better understand these physical processes. Geochemical profiles across the dunite-harzburgite transect reveal concentration gradients near the dunite-harzburgite contact, particularly within the harzburgite. Such compositional variations were interpreted through two-dimensional numerical simulations, coupled with diffusion and advection in porous media. The results indicate that trace element gradients in olivine can be produced by a melt flow along the dunite–harzburgite boundary with lateral advection from dunite to harzburgite, which is consistent with those observed in the field. Trace element patterns of the interstitial clinopyroxene grains within the dunite suggest their crystallization from a final pulse of percolating melt through the channel during the waning stage of the melt transport system, which probably occurred shortly before the ophiolite obduction. Integrating these results with previous studies on mafic–ultramafic rocks in the Moho Transition Zone (MTZ), we propose that the dunite–harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite was initially generated in the asthenosphere beneath an ultra-slow spreading ridge, which subsequently experienced a multi-stage history of melt migration and melt–rock interaction during progressive mantle upwelling. Such a complex history significantly influenced the lithological and geochemical architecture of the MTZ of the ophiolite. Overall, results from this study demonstrate that both dunites and their surrounding harzburgites bear variable concentration gradients, resulting from both mantle heterogeneity and variations in melt compositions within individual dunite channel.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The role of crustal magmatism in the formation and the evolution of orogenic plateaus</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38190.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38190.1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 20:40:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Mihai N. Ducea</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter G. DeCelles</dc:creator><dc:creator>James B. Chapman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan R. Delph</dc:creator><dc:creator>Barbara Carrapa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lucian Petrescu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kevin M. Ward</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pablo Rossel</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38190.1</prism:doi><description>Here we review regional geological, petrological, geochemical, and geophysical data from the Central Andean plateau (comprising two distinct areas, the Altiplano and Puna) and its defunct North American sibling, the Nevadaplano, as well as to a lesser extent Tibet, to show that magmatism in the middle crust of orogenic plateaus plays an important role in the development of relief and high elevation and drives the mechanical behavior of these features. We show that in situ, mostly S-type melting is an intrinsic feature of plateaus and that these melts can reside in the crust for millions to tens of millions of years without freezing just below a critical melt fraction. Some of these in situ partial melt masses escape their source regions and erupt at the surface. The chemical evolution of volcanic masses produced by partial escape from these migmatites can be predicted by simple forward petrologic calculations. Extensive migmatite in sub-plateau middle crust also contributes to the mechanical weakness of plateaus and their buoyancy. In addition, magmatism from the underlying mantle wedge can further sustain the life of these extensive partial melting zones. Additional, much deeper melt accumulation zones exist close to the bottom of these thick-crusted domains, but we have much less information about their evolution and chemistry; they are probably similar to the deepest crustal root zones of the frontal arcs. We also suggest that there is a link between the ability of Li, B, Cs, and other elements to be concentrated in S-type leucogranites of the extensive migmatite blanket of the middle crust and the concentration of Li (and other metals) in brines and ultimately in the salars of the Central Andean plateau. Hydrothermal activity directly related to the present day Altiplano-Puna magma body or the recent equivalents on South America’s plateau may have leaked these incompatible elements into the former lakes that are now hosting the largest concentrations of Li on the planet.
Published: 2026-01-09T20:40:27+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.555 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mihai N. Ducea; Peter G. DeCelles; James B. Chapman; Jonathan R. Delph; Barbara Carrapa; Lucian Petrescu; Kevin M. Ward; Pablo Rossel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38190.1"&gt;10.1130/b38190.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.555 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we review regional geological, petrological, geochemical, and geophysical data from the Central Andean plateau (comprising two distinct areas, the Altiplano and Puna) and its defunct North American sibling, the Nevadaplano, as well as to a lesser extent Tibet, to show that magmatism in the middle crust of orogenic plateaus plays an important role in the development of relief and high elevation and drives the mechanical behavior of these features. We show that in situ, mostly S-type melting is an intrinsic feature of plateaus and that these melts can reside in the crust for millions to tens of millions of years without freezing just below a critical melt fraction. Some of these in situ partial melt masses escape their source regions and erupt at the surface. The chemical evolution of volcanic masses produced by partial escape from these migmatites can be predicted by simple forward petrologic calculations. Extensive migmatite in sub-plateau middle crust also contributes to the mechanical weakness of plateaus and their buoyancy. In addition, magmatism from the underlying mantle wedge can further sustain the life of these extensive partial melting zones. Additional, much deeper melt accumulation zones exist close to the bottom of these thick-crusted domains, but we have much less information about their evolution and chemistry; they are probably similar to the deepest crustal root zones of the frontal arcs. We also suggest that there is a link between the ability of Li, B, Cs, and other elements to be concentrated in S-type leucogranites of the extensive migmatite blanket of the middle crust and the concentration of Li (and other metals) in brines and ultimately in the salars of the Central Andean plateau. Hydrothermal activity directly related to the present day Altiplano-Puna magma body or the recent equivalents on South America’s plateau may have leaked these incompatible elements into the former lakes that are now hosting the largest concentrations of Li on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Programmable polariton canalization in reconfigurable metasurfaces</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea0072</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aea0072</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoqiang Su</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fusheng Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuqian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yaping Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pablo Alonso-González</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiafang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiahua Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiwei Guo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aea0072</prism:doi><description>The topological transition of polariton dispersion in twisted van der Waals layers at the photonic magic angle results in the diffraction-less and collimated propagation state, termed canalization regime. This type of robust transport of polaritons (i.e., polariton canalization) holds promise for subwavelength control of energy flows. However, the lack of in situ dynamic tunability of canalized polaritons hinders such control because the canalization direction is fixed in the fabricated device. Here, we overcome this limitation by demonstrating programmable polariton canalization in a reconfigurable single-layer metasurface. By engineering the orientation of metasurface unit cells, the direction of canalized magnetic polaritons can be programmed along any in-plane direction (i.e., dynamic all-angle tunability). On-demand steering of canalized polaritons allows customized near-field patterns to be obtained at any desired location—a proof of concept for canalization-based information display applications. These findings offer opportunities to transcend conventional diffraction constraints for integrated photonic devices, thus opening the door for photonic applications where on-demand control is crucial.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.549 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yang Xu; Xiaoqiang Su; Fusheng Deng; Yuqian Wang; Yaping Yang; Pablo Alonso-González; Hong Chen; Jiafang Li; Jiahua Duan; Zhiwei Guo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea0072"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aea0072&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.549 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topological transition of polariton dispersion in twisted van der Waals layers at the photonic magic angle results in the diffraction-less and collimated propagation state, termed canalization regime. This type of robust transport of polaritons (i.e., polariton canalization) holds promise for subwavelength control of energy flows. However, the lack of in situ dynamic tunability of canalized polaritons hinders such control because the canalization direction is fixed in the fabricated device. Here, we overcome this limitation by demonstrating programmable polariton canalization in a reconfigurable single-layer metasurface. By engineering the orientation of metasurface unit cells, the direction of canalized magnetic polaritons can be programmed along any in-plane direction (i.e., dynamic all-angle tunability). On-demand steering of canalized polaritons allows customized near-field patterns to be obtained at any desired location—a proof of concept for canalization-based information display applications. These findings offer opportunities to transcend conventional diffraction constraints for integrated photonic devices, thus opening the door for photonic applications where on-demand control is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Phase equilibria modelling and geochronology of Ediacaran-Cambrian granites in West Garo Hills, Assam-Meghalaya Gneissic Complex, NE India: implications for East Gondwana assembly</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02284-8</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02284-8</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 03:33:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Rhituparna Gogoi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pranjit Hazarika</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dewashish Upadhyay</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02284-8</prism:doi><description>The Assam-Meghalaya Gneissic Complex (AMGC) in northeast India represents the eastern fringe of the Precambrian Indian Shield and comprises Meso- to Neoproterozoic migmatitic quartzofeldspathic gneisses, foliated granitoids, metapelites and Ediacaran-Cambrian granites. Our work focuses on the petrogenesis of garnet-bearing and garnet-absent granites of the West Garo Hills (WGH), in the westernmost AMGC, that are intrusive into basement quartzofeldspathic gneisses (QFG) and foliated granitoids. We use phase equilibria modelling to evaluate whether partial melting of basement rocks could have produced the Ediacaran-Cambrian granites in the area. Textural and chemical characteristics of garnet support a magmatic origin. Phase equilibria modelling, carried out on garnet-bearing granite, indicates that the garnet core composition equilibrated at ∼7.5&amp;nbsp;kb/830°C, while rim composition record ∼5.3&amp;nbsp;kb/730°C. Phase equilibria modelling suggests that the QFG and metapelite basement rocks were metamorphosed at ∼5.5&amp;nbsp;kb/750°C and ~ 5.7&amp;nbsp;kb/740°C, respectively. U-Pb dating of monazite and xenotime in the granite, the host QFG, and pegmatites yielded comparable 591 − 542&amp;nbsp;Ma, 582 − 540&amp;nbsp;Ma and 562 − 460&amp;nbsp;Ma ages, respectively, which date the timing of high-grade metamorphism and granite emplacement during Pan-African orogenesis. Our melt-reintegrated phase equilibria modelling suggests that partial melting of basement QFG and associated metapelite with varying degrees of fractional crystallization could produce melts having composition similar to those of the granites in the WGH. A comparison of the modelled melt compositions with the compiled granite data from the entire AMGC suggests that basement QFG-derived melts can largely explain the composition of the Ediacaran-Cambrian granites.
Published: 2026-01-10T03:33:44+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.548 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Rhituparna Gogoi; Pranjit Hazarika; Dewashish Upadhyay&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02284-8"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02284-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.548 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Assam-Meghalaya Gneissic Complex (AMGC) in northeast India represents the eastern fringe of the Precambrian Indian Shield and comprises Meso- to Neoproterozoic migmatitic quartzofeldspathic gneisses, foliated granitoids, metapelites and Ediacaran-Cambrian granites. Our work focuses on the petrogenesis of garnet-bearing and garnet-absent granites of the West Garo Hills (WGH), in the westernmost AMGC, that are intrusive into basement quartzofeldspathic gneisses (QFG) and foliated granitoids. We use phase equilibria modelling to evaluate whether partial melting of basement rocks could have produced the Ediacaran-Cambrian granites in the area. Textural and chemical characteristics of garnet support a magmatic origin. Phase equilibria modelling, carried out on garnet-bearing granite, indicates that the garnet core composition equilibrated at ∼7.5&amp;amp;nbsp;kb/830°C, while rim composition record ∼5.3&amp;amp;nbsp;kb/730°C. Phase equilibria modelling suggests that the QFG and metapelite basement rocks were metamorphosed at ∼5.5&amp;amp;nbsp;kb/750°C and ~ 5.7&amp;amp;nbsp;kb/740°C, respectively. U-Pb dating of monazite and xenotime in the granite, the host QFG, and pegmatites yielded comparable 591 − 542&amp;amp;nbsp;Ma, 582 − 540&amp;amp;nbsp;Ma and 562 − 460&amp;amp;nbsp;Ma ages, respectively, which date the timing of high-grade metamorphism and granite emplacement during Pan-African orogenesis. Our melt-reintegrated phase equilibria modelling suggests that partial melting of basement QFG and associated metapelite with varying degrees of fractional crystallization could produce melts having composition similar to those of the granites in the WGH. A comparison of the modelled melt compositions with the compiled granite data from the entire AMGC suggests that basement QFG-derived melts can largely explain the composition of the Ediacaran-Cambrian granites.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Controlling the sign of optical forces using metaoptics</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 04:34:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Adeel Afridi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bruno Melo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nadine Meyer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Romain Quidant</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract Precise manipulation of small objects using light holds transformative potential across diverse fields. While research in optical trapping and manipulation predominantly relies on the attraction of solid matter to light intensity maxima, here we demonstrate that meta-optics enables a departure from this accepted behavior. Specifically, we present deterministic control over the sign of optical forces exerted on a metasurface integrated on a suspended silicon nanomembrane. By tailoring the geometry of the constituent meta-atoms, we engineer the coherent superposition of their multipolar modes, and consequently, the net optical force experienced by the metasurface within a phase-controlled optical standing wave. In excellent agreement with 3D numerical simulations, we experimentally realize both attractive and repulsive forces on distinct metasurface designs, directly mirroring the behavior of two-level systems interacting with optical fields. This work establishes a versatile platform for the optical control of nanoscale mechanical systems, opening alternative avenues for both fundamental research and engineering.
Published: 2026-01-09T04:34:07+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.540 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Adeel Afridi; Bruno Melo; Nadine Meyer; Romain Quidant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.540 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Precise manipulation of small objects using light holds transformative potential across diverse fields. While research in optical trapping and manipulation predominantly relies on the attraction of solid matter to light intensity maxima, here we demonstrate that meta-optics enables a departure from this accepted behavior. Specifically, we present deterministic control over the sign of optical forces exerted on a metasurface integrated on a suspended silicon nanomembrane. By tailoring the geometry of the constituent meta-atoms, we engineer the coherent superposition of their multipolar modes, and consequently, the net optical force experienced by the metasurface within a phase-controlled optical standing wave. In excellent agreement with 3D numerical simulations, we experimentally realize both attractive and repulsive forces on distinct metasurface designs, directly mirroring the behavior of two-level systems interacting with optical fields. This work establishes a versatile platform for the optical control of nanoscale mechanical systems, opening alternative avenues for both fundamental research and engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Improved air-sea CO
                    &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
                    flux estimates from sailboat measurements</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz1502</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adz1502</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jacqueline Behncke</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tatiana Ilyina</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fatemeh Chegini</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter Landschützer</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adz1502</prism:doi><description>Despite their importance in the climate system, remote ocean regions and their ability to absorb anthropogenic carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) remain highly uncertain. To address this issue, citizen science initiatives, including sailboats, expand the observational network. Using observing system simulations and novel sailboat tracks, we demonstrate how integrating sailboat data improves estimates of ocean carbon uptake. While we underestimate the ocean carbon sink when mimicking real-world sampling, adding available sailboat data does not substantially improve reconstructions. Nevertheless, increased sampling reveals a stronger carbon sink, particularly between 40°S and 60°S. The improvement persists with hypothetical measurement uncertainties, but substantial differences arise depending on whether positive or negative biases are applied to the race track data. While we show that two additional circumnavigations already improve the ocean mean sink estimate, we further highlight the finding that the additional data remain insufficient to correct the overestimated CO 2 sink trend, calling for continuation of the ongoing data collection.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.532 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jacqueline Behncke; Tatiana Ilyina; Fatemeh Chegini; Peter Landschützer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz1502"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adz1502&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.532 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite their importance in the climate system, remote ocean regions and their ability to absorb anthropogenic carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) remain highly uncertain. To address this issue, citizen science initiatives, including sailboats, expand the observational network. Using observing system simulations and novel sailboat tracks, we demonstrate how integrating sailboat data improves estimates of ocean carbon uptake. While we underestimate the ocean carbon sink when mimicking real-world sampling, adding available sailboat data does not substantially improve reconstructions. Nevertheless, increased sampling reveals a stronger carbon sink, particularly between 40°S and 60°S. The improvement persists with hypothetical measurement uncertainties, but substantial differences arise depending on whether positive or negative biases are applied to the race track data. While we show that two additional circumnavigations already improve the ocean mean sink estimate, we further highlight the finding that the additional data remain insufficient to correct the overestimated CO 2 sink trend, calling for continuation of the ongoing data collection.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Regular-wrinkling tunable MXene lattice for electromagnetic interference shielding</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68035-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68035-2</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 08:23:43 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Juntao Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi-Ling Hou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pengfei Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Cai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenming Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenhao Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yufeng Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin C. Koo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pei-Yan Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Min Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingjie Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guang-Sheng Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68035-2</prism:doi><description>Protecting sensitive equipment from electromagnetic radiation damage requires the development of high-performance electromagnetic interference shielding films. As the film thickness is reduced to micro/nano scales, electromagnetic interference shielding capability generally decreases rapidly due to the weaker reflection. As a result, enhanced electromagnetic interference shielding performance in sub-μm thin films remains as an unsolved challenge. Inspired by the naturally wrinkling of fruit skin, we propose a homogeneous strain strategy to achieve self-wrinkling-induced lattice-structured MXene by uniform polymer shrinkage due to dehydration. Uniform wrinkle amplitude can be tuned from 0.8 to 6 μm, which results in additional surface scattering of electromagnetic-waves and electrical conduction paths. The obtained lattice-structured films demonstrate an excellent electromagnetic interference shielding of up to 81.5 dB for a thickness of 17 μm, maintaining high electromagnetic interference shielding performance and stability after enduring various harsh testing conditions. These results demonstrate the potential of wrinkling-induced, surface regular patterns for improving the electromagnetic interference shielding performance of ultra-thin films based on conventional materials. This study reports self-wrinkling MXene films with lattice structures achieving exceptional electromagnetic interference shielding (81.5 dB at 17 μm), offering ultra-thin protection for sensitive electronics.
Published: 2026-01-10T08:23:43+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.530 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shan Zhang; Juntao Wu; Zhi-Ling Hou; Pengfei Hu; Bo Cai; Chenming Liang; Lu Zhou; Wenhao Liang; Yufeng Xue; Martin C. Koo; Pei-Yan Zhao; Li-Min Liu; Mingjie Liu; Guang-Sheng Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68035-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68035-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.530 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Protecting sensitive equipment from electromagnetic radiation damage requires the development of high-performance electromagnetic interference shielding films. As the film thickness is reduced to micro/nano scales, electromagnetic interference shielding capability generally decreases rapidly due to the weaker reflection. As a result, enhanced electromagnetic interference shielding performance in sub-μm thin films remains as an unsolved challenge. Inspired by the naturally wrinkling of fruit skin, we propose a homogeneous strain strategy to achieve self-wrinkling-induced lattice-structured MXene by uniform polymer shrinkage due to dehydration. Uniform wrinkle amplitude can be tuned from 0.8 to 6 μm, which results in additional surface scattering of electromagnetic-waves and electrical conduction paths. The obtained lattice-structured films demonstrate an excellent electromagnetic interference shielding of up to 81.5 dB for a thickness of 17 μm, maintaining high electromagnetic interference shielding performance and stability after enduring various harsh testing conditions. These results demonstrate the potential of wrinkling-induced, surface regular patterns for improving the electromagnetic interference shielding performance of ultra-thin films based on conventional materials. This study reports self-wrinkling MXene films with lattice structures achieving exceptional electromagnetic interference shielding (81.5 dB at 17 μm), offering ultra-thin protection for sensitive electronics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seismicity diagnostic of permeability creation from centimeter to subkilometer scales in crystalline rock during shear stimulation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5201</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.ady5201</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pengliang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Agathe Eijsink</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junpeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chris Marone</dc:creator><dc:creator>Derek Elsworth</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.ady5201</prism:doi><description>Permeability evolves dynamically in the crust and mediates important natural and industrial processes in the subsurface. Episodic microearthquakes generate porosity and, thus, permeability by creating or reactivating fractures. We constrain the form of the scaling relationship linking seismic moment ( M 0 ) to incremental permeability generation ( Δ k ) through a series of laboratory fault reactivation experiments with absolute constraint on seismic moment. We demonstrate Δ k − M 0 proportionality at centimeter scale but confirm predictive power-law scaling using a first-order model as Δ k = λ M 0 2 / 3 from centimeter to subkilometer scale. Stress drop, fault roughness, and deformation modulus condition the prefactor λ , extending over 10 decades for reasonable natural parameter ranges. However, observed permeabilities are much more tightly constrained, with λ spanning only two orders of magnitude over length scales from centimeter to subkilometer, suggesting interdependencies in the controlling variables and rendering the relation as diagnostic in predicting fluid flow in crustal reservoirs.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.530 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pengliang Yu; Agathe Eijsink; Junpeng Wang; Chris Marone; Derek Elsworth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5201"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.ady5201&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.530 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Permeability evolves dynamically in the crust and mediates important natural and industrial processes in the subsurface. Episodic microearthquakes generate porosity and, thus, permeability by creating or reactivating fractures. We constrain the form of the scaling relationship linking seismic moment ( M 0 ) to incremental permeability generation ( Δ k ) through a series of laboratory fault reactivation experiments with absolute constraint on seismic moment. We demonstrate Δ k − M 0 proportionality at centimeter scale but confirm predictive power-law scaling using a first-order model as Δ k = λ M 0 2 / 3 from centimeter to subkilometer scale. Stress drop, fault roughness, and deformation modulus condition the prefactor λ , extending over 10 decades for reasonable natural parameter ranges. However, observed permeabilities are much more tightly constrained, with λ spanning only two orders of magnitude over length scales from centimeter to subkilometer, suggesting interdependencies in the controlling variables and rendering the relation as diagnostic in predicting fluid flow in crustal reservoirs.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Geothermal effect on riverine molybdenum isotopes: Implications for its riverine input into the ocean</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38393.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38393.1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 20:39:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhibing Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lian Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinlong Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gangjian Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ti Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yiwei Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Le Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38393.1</prism:doi><description>Molybdenum (Mo) isotopes preserved in marine sediments serve as a premier proxy for reconstructing Earth’s oxygenation history. However, their reliability depends on accurately deciphering the mechanisms driving spatiotemporal variations in Mo isotopes in river water—the ocean’s dominant Mo source. Chemical weathering of continental rocks is widely recognized as the primary control on δ98Mo values in the dissolved riverine flux. Nevertheless, continental geothermal inputs, which discharge into major river networks along tectonically active zones worldwide, may exert an additional, yet underexplored control on riverine Mo isotope signatures. This study presents the first systematic time-series investigation of geothermal impacts on riverine δ98Mo, utilizing the tectonically active Liuxihe River Basin (South China) as a natural laboratory. Our findings reveal that geothermal inputs along fault zones dramatically alter riverine Mo isotopes, depressing δ98Mo values from a weathering baseline of 0.99‰ to as low as −0.99‰, a 2‰ shift exceeding all previously documented riverine variations. Mixing models indicate that geothermal sources can contribute up to 56% of dissolved Mo in affected river segments. Given the ubiquity of continental geothermal systems along major plate boundaries and intracontinental fault zones, this previously unrecognized control may fundamentally transform our understanding of the global riverine Mo flux. These results carry significant implications for refining global Mo budgets to incorporate isotopically light continental geothermal inputs and for reinterpreting paleo-redox records by considering variable riverine end members rather than fixed crustal values.
Published: 2026-01-09T20:39:23+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.527 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhibing Wang; Lian Peng; Jie Li; Jinlong Ma; Gangjian Wei; Ti Zeng; Feng Ye; Yiwei Chen; Le Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38393.1"&gt;10.1130/b38393.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.527 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molybdenum (Mo) isotopes preserved in marine sediments serve as a premier proxy for reconstructing Earth’s oxygenation history. However, their reliability depends on accurately deciphering the mechanisms driving spatiotemporal variations in Mo isotopes in river water—the ocean’s dominant Mo source. Chemical weathering of continental rocks is widely recognized as the primary control on δ98Mo values in the dissolved riverine flux. Nevertheless, continental geothermal inputs, which discharge into major river networks along tectonically active zones worldwide, may exert an additional, yet underexplored control on riverine Mo isotope signatures. This study presents the first systematic time-series investigation of geothermal impacts on riverine δ98Mo, utilizing the tectonically active Liuxihe River Basin (South China) as a natural laboratory. Our findings reveal that geothermal inputs along fault zones dramatically alter riverine Mo isotopes, depressing δ98Mo values from a weathering baseline of 0.99‰ to as low as −0.99‰, a 2‰ shift exceeding all previously documented riverine variations. Mixing models indicate that geothermal sources can contribute up to 56% of dissolved Mo in affected river segments. Given the ubiquity of continental geothermal systems along major plate boundaries and intracontinental fault zones, this previously unrecognized control may fundamentally transform our understanding of the global riverine Mo flux. These results carry significant implications for refining global Mo budgets to incorporate isotopically light continental geothermal inputs and for reinterpreting paleo-redox records by considering variable riverine end members rather than fixed crustal values.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Understanding oxygen transfer on ceria with Pt single atoms for surface reaction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 10:43:13 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yunji Choi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Seokhyun Choung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jaebeom Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jae-eon Hwang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hyeon Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunkyung Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeongjin Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeong Young Park</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeong Woo Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hyunjoo Lee</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5</prism:doi><description>Reducible metal oxides are widely used in surface reactions, primarily due to their ability to activate and transfer oxygen. Ceria, known for its rapid Ce3+/Ce4+ redox property, is well-known to follow Mars van Krevelen mechanism. In this study, we prepare Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 catalysts with different ceria domain sizes of 3.7, 5.6, and 7.3 nm to understand oxygen transfer, mainly O2 activation and lattice oxygen transfer. The ceria domains are isolated on the alumina, preventing oxygen transfer between the ceria. Pt single atomic structures are meticulously prepared to exclude O2 activation on Pt nanoparticles and provide uniform active sites. Interestingly, the activity trend for CO oxidation is reversed in O2-rich and O2-deficient conditions. O2 activation occurs efficiently in small ceria domains of 3.7 nm. In contrast, larger ceria domains exhibit less O2 activation but significant lattice oxygen transfer. This behavior is also modeled using large-scale molecular dynamics simulations with a neural network potential trained on first-principles data. Based on these understanding, the catalyst for methane oxidation is proposed by accelerating O2 activation in O2-rich condition. This work provides an impactful platform for understanding metal oxide catalysts. Ceria enables oxygen transfer, but size effects complicate design. Here the authors build Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 with isolated CeO2 domains (3.7–7.3 nm) and Pt single atoms, showing small domains favor O2 activation, larger ones lattice-O transfer, guiding CO or methane oxidation.
Published: 2026-01-09T10:43:13+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.524 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yunji Choi; Seokhyun Choung; Jaebeom Han; Jae-eon Hwang; Hyeon Jin; Yunkyung Kim; Jeongjin Kim; Jeong Young Park; Jeong Woo Han; Hyunjoo Lee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.524 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reducible metal oxides are widely used in surface reactions, primarily due to their ability to activate and transfer oxygen. Ceria, known for its rapid Ce3+/Ce4+ redox property, is well-known to follow Mars van Krevelen mechanism. In this study, we prepare Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 catalysts with different ceria domain sizes of 3.7, 5.6, and 7.3 nm to understand oxygen transfer, mainly O2 activation and lattice oxygen transfer. The ceria domains are isolated on the alumina, preventing oxygen transfer between the ceria. Pt single atomic structures are meticulously prepared to exclude O2 activation on Pt nanoparticles and provide uniform active sites. Interestingly, the activity trend for CO oxidation is reversed in O2-rich and O2-deficient conditions. O2 activation occurs efficiently in small ceria domains of 3.7 nm. In contrast, larger ceria domains exhibit less O2 activation but significant lattice oxygen transfer. This behavior is also modeled using large-scale molecular dynamics simulations with a neural network potential trained on first-principles data. Based on these understanding, the catalyst for methane oxidation is proposed by accelerating O2 activation in O2-rich condition. This work provides an impactful platform for understanding metal oxide catalysts. Ceria enables oxygen transfer, but size effects complicate design. Here the authors build Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 with isolated CeO2 domains (3.7–7.3 nm) and Pt single atoms, showing small domains favor O2 activation, larger ones lattice-O transfer, guiding CO or methane oxidation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A three-in-one strategy for lithium recovery and upcycling of spent cathode materials</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67912-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67912-0</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 14:24:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yue Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaohong Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weiguang Lv</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongbin Cao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi Sun</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67912-0</prism:doi><description>The recycling of spent lithium-ion batteries is essential for sustainable development&amp;nbsp;of clean energy industry. Traditional recycling&amp;nbsp;methods face challenges such as high energy/chemical consumption and limited adaptability. This study introduces a ‘Three-in-One’ strategy that leverages mechanochemical (MC) treatment to enhance lithium recovery, transition metal upgrading, and CO2 sequestration. MC treatment induces micro-segregation of lithium and transition metals, resulting in a structurally disordered material with a Li-rich surface, facilitating selective lithium extraction. Subsequently,&amp;nbsp;CO2 is used&amp;nbsp;as the sole reagent and lithium leaching efficiency exceeding 95% is achieved&amp;nbsp;by forming lithium bicarbonate. Conducted under ambient conditions without additional grinding aids or leaching reagents, this method minimizes environmental impact.&amp;nbsp;Transition metals are simultaneously transformed into high-performance oxygen evolution reaction (OER) catalysts, demonstrating an overpotential of 322 mV at a current density of 10 mA cm-2. These catalysts maintain stability over 200 h of operation. This approach not only provides an efficient pathway for lithium recovery but also upcycles spent cathode materials into valuable catalysts, supporting sustainable energy conversion technologies. The strategy is particularly effective for high-Ni cathode systems, offering significant practical advantages. Recycling lithium-ion batteries is crucial for sustainability. Here, authors develop a “Three-in-One” strategy using mechanochemical treatment to recover over 95% lithium, upgrade transition metals into catalysts, and sequester CO2, offering an efficient and environmentally friendly recycling solution.
Published: 2026-01-10T14:24:09+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.520 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yue Wang; Xiaohong Zheng; Weiguang Lv; Li Li; Hongbin Cao; Zhi Sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67912-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67912-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.520 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recycling of spent lithium-ion batteries is essential for sustainable development&amp;amp;nbsp;of clean energy industry. Traditional recycling&amp;amp;nbsp;methods face challenges such as high energy/chemical consumption and limited adaptability. This study introduces a ‘Three-in-One’ strategy that leverages mechanochemical (MC) treatment to enhance lithium recovery, transition metal upgrading, and CO2 sequestration. MC treatment induces micro-segregation of lithium and transition metals, resulting in a structurally disordered material with a Li-rich surface, facilitating selective lithium extraction. Subsequently,&amp;amp;nbsp;CO2 is used&amp;amp;nbsp;as the sole reagent and lithium leaching efficiency exceeding 95% is achieved&amp;amp;nbsp;by forming lithium bicarbonate. Conducted under ambient conditions without additional grinding aids or leaching reagents, this method minimizes environmental impact.&amp;amp;nbsp;Transition metals are simultaneously transformed into high-performance oxygen evolution reaction (OER) catalysts, demonstrating an overpotential of 322 mV at a current density of 10 mA cm-2. These catalysts maintain stability over 200 h of operation. This approach not only provides an efficient pathway for lithium recovery but also upcycles spent cathode materials into valuable catalysts, supporting sustainable energy conversion technologies. The strategy is particularly effective for high-Ni cathode systems, offering significant practical advantages. Recycling lithium-ion batteries is crucial for sustainability. Here, authors develop a “Three-in-One” strategy using mechanochemical treatment to recover over 95% lithium, upgrade transition metals into catalysts, and sequester CO2, offering an efficient and environmentally friendly recycling solution.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A sample dredged from the Alpha Ridge records evidence of an emergent volcanic setting at 90 Ma</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 13:51:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Marie-Claude Williamson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Grace E. Shephard</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Boggild</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rebecca Carey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul B. Hamilton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dawn Kellett</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel Miggins</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anthony A. P. Koppers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Derek H. C. Wilton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel J. MacDonald</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dominique Weis</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuangquan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brian L. Cousens</dc:creator><dc:creator>Simon E. Jackson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Duane C. Petts</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher M. Lawley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Erica Massey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lotte M. Larsen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wilfried Jokat</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeff Harris</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z</prism:doi><description>Abstract Recovering geological samples from the deep basins and ridges of the central Arctic Ocean presents significant challenges because of remote access and thick ice cover. During the 2016 Canada-Sweden Polar Expedition to the Arctic Ocean, volcaniclastic breccia was dredged from the Alpha Ridge, part of an underwater mountain chain extending from the Canadian polar margin to the Siberian shelf. Argon geochronology of plagioclase crystals within glassy lava fragments dates the sample to 90.4 ± 0.26 Ma. The geochemical composition of basalt clasts in the volcaniclastic breccia closely resembles that of igneous rocks from the High Arctic Large Igneous Province suggesting that the Alpha Ridge was an active volcanic feature within the circum-Arctic in the Late Cretaceous. Our results support lava–water interactions in a littoral environment, driven by the growth and emergence of a central igneous platform and accompanied by eruptive activity at constructional volcanic edifices along its margins.
Published: 2026-01-09T13:51:41+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.516 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Marie-Claude Williamson; Grace E. Shephard; Kai Boggild; Rebecca Carey; Paul B. Hamilton; Dawn Kellett; Daniel Miggins; Anthony A. P. Koppers; Derek H. C. Wilton; Daniel J. MacDonald; Dominique Weis; Shuangquan Zhang; Brian L. Cousens; Simon E. Jackson; Duane C. Petts; Christopher M. Lawley; Erica Massey; Lotte M. Larsen; Wilfried Jokat; Jeff Harris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.516 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Recovering geological samples from the deep basins and ridges of the central Arctic Ocean presents significant challenges because of remote access and thick ice cover. During the 2016 Canada-Sweden Polar Expedition to the Arctic Ocean, volcaniclastic breccia was dredged from the Alpha Ridge, part of an underwater mountain chain extending from the Canadian polar margin to the Siberian shelf. Argon geochronology of plagioclase crystals within glassy lava fragments dates the sample to 90.4 ± 0.26 Ma. The geochemical composition of basalt clasts in the volcaniclastic breccia closely resembles that of igneous rocks from the High Arctic Large Igneous Province suggesting that the Alpha Ridge was an active volcanic feature within the circum-Arctic in the Late Cretaceous. Our results support lava–water interactions in a littoral environment, driven by the growth and emergence of a central igneous platform and accompanied by eruptive activity at constructional volcanic edifices along its margins.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Room-temperature high-efficiency spin injection via van der Waals tunnel contact</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67989-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67989-7</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 08:23:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shiming Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fuchen Hou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tingyu Qu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lianying Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhipeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bosen Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guowen Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Barbaros Özyilmaz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huolin Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Libo Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junhao Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Deyi Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rong Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67989-7</prism:doi><description>Efficient and reliable spin injection at room temperature with scalability is crucial for spintronic applications but remains challenging. Direct ferromagnetic metal deposition on two-dimensional materials often leads to inefficient transparent contacts. Here, we introduce an indium buffer layer between ferromagnetic cobalt (Co) and graphene to establish high-efficiency van der Waals (vdW) tunnel contacts. This buffer layer facilitates a physisorption interface between Co and graphene with a well-defined vdW gap, which functions as an effective spin tunnel barrier. Through buffer layer thickness optimization, we achieved a room-temperature spin injection efficiency of approximately 25% in graphene, comparable to the best single-crystalline oxide-tunnel-barrier-based devices, alongside explicit nonlocal spin valve signals and Hanle spin precession. We further demonstrate the scalability of our approach through uniform performance across multi-channel graphene spin valves and its versatility by achieving efficient spin injection in semiconducting MoS2 with an average efficiency of about 19.7%. Our strategy offers a simple, cost-efficient, and industry-compatible method for future large-scale and efficient spintronic applications. Researchers developed a simple, industry-compatible method using an indium buffer layer between cobalt and 2D materials to form vdWs tunnel contacts. This achieved high spin injection efficiency in both graphene and MoS2, enabling future large-scale spintronic devices.
Published: 2026-01-10T08:23:44+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.511 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shiming Huang; Fuchen Hou; Tingyu Qu; Lianying Zhu; Zhipeng Wang; Bo Zhang; Bosen Wang; Chao Wang; Guowen Yuan; Xiao Chang; Barbaros Özyilmaz; Huolin Huang; Feng Zhang; Libo Gao; Junhao Lin; Deyi Fu; Rong Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67989-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67989-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.511 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Efficient and reliable spin injection at room temperature with scalability is crucial for spintronic applications but remains challenging. Direct ferromagnetic metal deposition on two-dimensional materials often leads to inefficient transparent contacts. Here, we introduce an indium buffer layer between ferromagnetic cobalt (Co) and graphene to establish high-efficiency van der Waals (vdW) tunnel contacts. This buffer layer facilitates a physisorption interface between Co and graphene with a well-defined vdW gap, which functions as an effective spin tunnel barrier. Through buffer layer thickness optimization, we achieved a room-temperature spin injection efficiency of approximately 25% in graphene, comparable to the best single-crystalline oxide-tunnel-barrier-based devices, alongside explicit nonlocal spin valve signals and Hanle spin precession. We further demonstrate the scalability of our approach through uniform performance across multi-channel graphene spin valves and its versatility by achieving efficient spin injection in semiconducting MoS2 with an average efficiency of about 19.7%. Our strategy offers a simple, cost-efficient, and industry-compatible method for future large-scale and efficient spintronic applications. Researchers developed a simple, industry-compatible method using an indium buffer layer between cobalt and 2D materials to form vdWs tunnel contacts. This achieved high spin injection efficiency in both graphene and MoS2, enabling future large-scale spintronic devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Minimal impact of recent decline in C4 vegetation abundance on atmospheric carbon isotopic composition</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03102-6</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03102-6</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 13:54:39 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Aliénor Lavergne</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sandy P. Harrison</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kamolphat Atsawawaranunt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ning Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Iain Colin Prentice</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03102-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract Changes in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations, climate, and land management influence the abundance and distribution of C 3 and C 4 plants, yet their impact on the global carbon cycle remains uncertain. Here, we use a parsimonious model of C 3 and C 4 plant distribution, based on optimality principles, combined with a simplified representation of the global carbon cycle, to assess how shifts in plant abundances driven by carbon dioxide and climate affect global gross primary production, land carbon isotope discrimination, and the isotopic composition of atmospheric carbon dioxide. We estimate that the proportion of C 4 plants in total biomass declined from about 16% to 12% between 1982 and 2016, despite an increase in the abundance of C 4 crops. This decline reflects the reduced competitive advantage of C 4 photosynthesis in a carbon dioxide-enriched atmosphere. As a result, global gross primary production rose by approximately 16.5 ± 1.8 petagrams of carbon, and land carbon isotope discrimination increased by 0.017 ± 0.001‰ per year. Accounting for changes in C 3 and C 4 abundances reduces the difference between observed and modeled trends in atmospheric carbon isotope composition, but does not fully explain the observed decrease, pointing to additional, unaccounted drivers.
Published: 2026-01-10T13:54:39+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.504 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Aliénor Lavergne; Sandy P. Harrison; Kamolphat Atsawawaranunt; Ning Dong; Iain Colin Prentice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03102-6"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03102-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.504 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Changes in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations, climate, and land management influence the abundance and distribution of C 3 and C 4 plants, yet their impact on the global carbon cycle remains uncertain. Here, we use a parsimonious model of C 3 and C 4 plant distribution, based on optimality principles, combined with a simplified representation of the global carbon cycle, to assess how shifts in plant abundances driven by carbon dioxide and climate affect global gross primary production, land carbon isotope discrimination, and the isotopic composition of atmospheric carbon dioxide. We estimate that the proportion of C 4 plants in total biomass declined from about 16% to 12% between 1982 and 2016, despite an increase in the abundance of C 4 crops. This decline reflects the reduced competitive advantage of C 4 photosynthesis in a carbon dioxide-enriched atmosphere. As a result, global gross primary production rose by approximately 16.5 ± 1.8 petagrams of carbon, and land carbon isotope discrimination increased by 0.017 ± 0.001‰ per year. Accounting for changes in C 3 and C 4 abundances reduces the difference between observed and modeled trends in atmospheric carbon isotope composition, but does not fully explain the observed decrease, pointing to additional, unaccounted drivers.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magnetization generation and giant nonlinear transport at symmetry-engineered interfaces</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 04:24:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hang-Bo Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen-Yu Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi-Ning Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng-Hao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eoin Moynihan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ana M. Sanchez</dc:creator><dc:creator>WenGuang Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshihiro Iwasa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marin Alexe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming-Min Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1</prism:doi><description>Abstract Interfaces in heterostructures possess inherent inversion asymmetry and display diverse physical effects, however, the pristine in-plane mirror symmetries of the constituent layers are usually preserved at the interface. On-demand manipulation of these symmetries remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate a strategy to control the in-plane mirror symmetries of interfaces by engineering the crystallographic orientation of heterostructures. We design a workhorse system with a new orientation, i.e., the LaAlO 3 /SrTiO 3 heterostructure with metallic interfaces in the (112)-plane. Such a high index orientation leads to the breaking of all the pristine mirror symmetries except the mirror plane perpendicular to the $$[1\bar{1}0]$$ [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] direction ( $${M}_{[1\bar{1}0]}$$ M [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] ), resulting in the C s point symmetry with a metallic conduction. Consequently, this interface exhibits a giant nonlinear Hall effect characterized by a large Berry curvature dipole, a circular photogalvanic effect, and current-induced out-of-plane magnetization, all functional at room temperature. The magnitude of the nonlinear Hall effect rivals the Weyl and Dirac systems. Our work establishes a new strategy in exploring emerging electronic properties with nontrivial quantum geometry by designing the interface symmetry.
Published: 2026-01-09T04:24:36+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.503 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hang-Bo Zhang; Zhen-Yu Ding; Yi-Ning Xie; Zheng-Hao Li; Eoin Moynihan; Ana M. Sanchez; WenGuang Zhu; Yang Gao; Yoshihiro Iwasa; Marin Alexe; Ming-Min Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.503 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Interfaces in heterostructures possess inherent inversion asymmetry and display diverse physical effects, however, the pristine in-plane mirror symmetries of the constituent layers are usually preserved at the interface. On-demand manipulation of these symmetries remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate a strategy to control the in-plane mirror symmetries of interfaces by engineering the crystallographic orientation of heterostructures. We design a workhorse system with a new orientation, i.e., the LaAlO 3 /SrTiO 3 heterostructure with metallic interfaces in the (112)-plane. Such a high index orientation leads to the breaking of all the pristine mirror symmetries except the mirror plane perpendicular to the $$[1\bar{1}0]$$ [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] direction ( $${M}_{[1\bar{1}0]}$$ M [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] ), resulting in the C s point symmetry with a metallic conduction. Consequently, this interface exhibits a giant nonlinear Hall effect characterized by a large Berry curvature dipole, a circular photogalvanic effect, and current-induced out-of-plane magnetization, all functional at room temperature. The magnitude of the nonlinear Hall effect rivals the Weyl and Dirac systems. Our work establishes a new strategy in exploring emerging electronic properties with nontrivial quantum geometry by designing the interface symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Unlocking limited electric double-layer capacity via electrochemically-driven continuous partial desolvations in carbon nanopores</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 09:47:30 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Sicheng Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zerui Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Binhao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuting Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dafu Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yimei Ouyang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kun Lan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhangquan Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guiming Zhong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dong-Liang Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiulong Wei</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0</prism:doi><description>Electrochemical capacitors are primarily limited by the low electric double-layer storage capacity and narrow operating window that avoids the formation of solid electrolyte interface layers. Herein, we demonstrate that electric double-layer adsorption of solvated Na+ in carbon nanopores is achievable under a large offset potential of −2.95 V vs. potential of zero charge in diethylene-glycol-dimethyl-ether electrolyte, even accompanying with the as-formed solid electrolyte interface layers. The largely enlarged offset potential in situ drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, which largely reduces the average solvation numbers from 2.1 to 0.6, leading to a high electric double-layer capacitance of 172 F g−1, a high capacity of 508 C g−1 and high initial coulombic efficiency of 92.2% at 0.1 A g−1 (0.5 mA cm−2), together with high-rate capability and long-term cycling stability. Thereby, such increased electric double-layer charge storage enables the redesign and assembly of sodium-ion capacitor pouch cells that display a high specific density of 40 Wh kg−1 (on cell level) and 30,000 cycles at a fast (dis)charging rate of 51 C (20 mA cm−2). Such sodium-ion capacitors are assembled without any pretreatments that are beneficial for scale-up fabrications in industry. Electrochemical capacitors are limited by low capacity. Here, authors report that the increased offset potential from potential of zero charge electrochemically drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, leading to largely increased electric double-layer capacitance and capacity.
Published: 2026-01-09T09:47:30+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.503 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sicheng Fan; Zerui Yan; Binhao Wang; Yuting Song; Dafu Tang; Huan Liu; Yimei Ouyang; Kun Lan; Zhangquan Peng; Guiming Zhong; Dong-Liang Peng; Qiulong Wei&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.503 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrochemical capacitors are primarily limited by the low electric double-layer storage capacity and narrow operating window that avoids the formation of solid electrolyte interface layers. Herein, we demonstrate that electric double-layer adsorption of solvated Na+ in carbon nanopores is achievable under a large offset potential of −2.95 V vs. potential of zero charge in diethylene-glycol-dimethyl-ether electrolyte, even accompanying with the as-formed solid electrolyte interface layers. The largely enlarged offset potential in situ drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, which largely reduces the average solvation numbers from 2.1 to 0.6, leading to a high electric double-layer capacitance of 172 F g−1, a high capacity of 508 C g−1 and high initial coulombic efficiency of 92.2% at 0.1 A g−1 (0.5 mA cm−2), together with high-rate capability and long-term cycling stability. Thereby, such increased electric double-layer charge storage enables the redesign and assembly of sodium-ion capacitor pouch cells that display a high specific density of 40 Wh kg−1 (on cell level) and 30,000 cycles at a fast (dis)charging rate of 51 C (20 mA cm−2). Such sodium-ion capacitors are assembled without any pretreatments that are beneficial for scale-up fabrications in industry. Electrochemical capacitors are limited by low capacity. Here, authors report that the increased offset potential from potential of zero charge electrochemically drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, leading to largely increased electric double-layer capacitance and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Enhancing hydrovoltaic power generation through coupled heat and light-driven surface charge dynamics</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 19:16:34 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tarique Anwar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Giulia Tagliabue</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8</prism:doi><description>Abstract Harnessing natural evaporation offers a sustainable pathway for next-generation energy technologies. We present a unified physical and experimental framework for evaporation-driven hydrovoltaic (EDHV) systems that decouples and controls the key interfacial processes underlying electricity generation from heat and sunlight. An intermediate ion-conducting layer separates the evaporative top interface from the silicon–dielectric nanopillar array, enabling independent modulation of evaporation, ion transport, and interfacial chemical equilibrium. This strategy enhances performance and clarifies mechanisms governing thermal and photo-induced charge generation, improving ion migration and electricity output. We develop a predictive equivalent-circuit model that captures process coupling through an analytically derived transfer capacitance. Our results show that capacitive photocharging and thermally modulated surface equilibria—rather than faradaic or photothermal effects—dominate energy conversion. The device achieves 1 V open-circuit voltage and 0.25 W/m² power density, with silicon doping and dielectric choice further boosting performance. These findings inform EDHV optimization across environmental and material conditions.
Published: 2026-01-09T19:16:34+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.501 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tarique Anwar; Giulia Tagliabue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.501 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Harnessing natural evaporation offers a sustainable pathway for next-generation energy technologies. We present a unified physical and experimental framework for evaporation-driven hydrovoltaic (EDHV) systems that decouples and controls the key interfacial processes underlying electricity generation from heat and sunlight. An intermediate ion-conducting layer separates the evaporative top interface from the silicon–dielectric nanopillar array, enabling independent modulation of evaporation, ion transport, and interfacial chemical equilibrium. This strategy enhances performance and clarifies mechanisms governing thermal and photo-induced charge generation, improving ion migration and electricity output. We develop a predictive equivalent-circuit model that captures process coupling through an analytically derived transfer capacitance. Our results show that capacitive photocharging and thermally modulated surface equilibria—rather than faradaic or photothermal effects—dominate energy conversion. The device achieves 1 V open-circuit voltage and 0.25 W/m² power density, with silicon doping and dielectric choice further boosting performance. These findings inform EDHV optimization across environmental and material conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Channelized melt beneath Antarctic ice shelves previously underestimated</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02537-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41558-025-02537-1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 10:02:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ann-Sofie P. Zinck</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stef Lhermitte</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin G. Wearing</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bert Wouters</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Climate Change</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41558-025-02537-1</prism:doi><description>While of critical importance for coastal communities, Antarctica’s future sea-level contribution remains highly uncertain. This uncertainty largely stems from the complex interaction between the ocean and the ice shelves, which is both difficult to observe and model. To better understand and constrain land-ice response to reduced buttressing exerted by ice shelves, efforts are needed to fully comprehend basal melt rates and their impact on ice shelf weakening and retreat. Here we present high-resolution basal melt maps (50 m) of vulnerable ice shelves based on a combination of stereo imagery and satellite altimetry, revealing pronounced channelized melting patterns whose melt rates were previously substantially underestimated (42–50%), which could result in faster channel breakthrough. Accurately simulating small-scale dynamics in ice-sheet models remains challenging but is essential for accurate sea-level rise projections. Channelized subsurface melting is an important process in the dynamics of ice shelves. Here the authors present observational data from Antarctic ice shelves and show that their basal melt is up to 50% higher than previously assumed.
Published: 2026-01-09T10:02:33+00:00
Venue: Nature Climate Change
Score: 0.499 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ann-Sofie P. Zinck; Stef Lhermitte; Martin G. Wearing; Bert Wouters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Climate Change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02537-1"&gt;10.1038/s41558-025-02537-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.499 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While of critical importance for coastal communities, Antarctica’s future sea-level contribution remains highly uncertain. This uncertainty largely stems from the complex interaction between the ocean and the ice shelves, which is both difficult to observe and model. To better understand and constrain land-ice response to reduced buttressing exerted by ice shelves, efforts are needed to fully comprehend basal melt rates and their impact on ice shelf weakening and retreat. Here we present high-resolution basal melt maps (50 m) of vulnerable ice shelves based on a combination of stereo imagery and satellite altimetry, revealing pronounced channelized melting patterns whose melt rates were previously substantially underestimated (42–50%), which could result in faster channel breakthrough. Accurately simulating small-scale dynamics in ice-sheet models remains challenging but is essential for accurate sea-level rise projections. Channelized subsurface melting is an important process in the dynamics of ice shelves. Here the authors present observational data from Antarctic ice shelves and show that their basal melt is up to 50% higher than previously assumed.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Supersaturation-engineered wafer-scale growth of anisotropic 2D organic crystals for uniform polarimetric sensing</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2522805123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2522805123</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:46:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xianfeng Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xianshuo Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ximeng Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunli Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lingjie Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaofeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pichao Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dong Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiansheng Jie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fangxu Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rongjin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenping Hu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2522805123</prism:doi><description>Organic single crystals endowed with intrinsic anisotropy hold great promise for the realization of miniaturized, polarization-sensitive photodetectors. However, conventional dip-coating approaches struggle to produce wafer-scale single-crystalline films, as the supersaturation conditions optimized for nucleation invariably conflict with those required for crystal growth, leading to fragmented domains and compromised device performance. Here, we introduce an in situ seeded dip coating (SDC) strategy that overcomes this limitation by engineering supersaturation to temporally decouple nucleation from crystal growth. This enables the scalable production of ultrathin two-dimensional molecular crystal (2DMC) films with exceptional uniformity across wafer dimensions. Organic field-effect transistor arrays fabricated from these 2DMCs exhibit high average charge carrier mobility (14.5 cm 2 V −1 s −1 ) and spatial homogeneity, evidenced by an ultralow mobility coefficient of variation (CV) of 4.5%. These arrays demonstrate robust polarization sensitivity with an average dichroic ratio (DR) of 2.2 and a low DR CV of 8.6%. Capitalizing on this uniformity, we constructed dual-device pixel units capable of full-range 180° polarization angle identification, enabling direct application in polarization-encoded optical encryption. The SDC technique provides a scalable pathway for practical high-performance organic polarization-sensitive optoelectronics.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:46:07+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.494 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xianfeng Shen; Xianshuo Wu; Ximeng Yao; Chunli Ma; Lingjie Sun; Zhaofeng Wang; Pichao Gao; Dong Zeng; Wei Deng; Jiansheng Jie; Fangxu Yang; Rongjin Li; Wenping Hu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2522805123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2522805123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.494 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organic single crystals endowed with intrinsic anisotropy hold great promise for the realization of miniaturized, polarization-sensitive photodetectors. However, conventional dip-coating approaches struggle to produce wafer-scale single-crystalline films, as the supersaturation conditions optimized for nucleation invariably conflict with those required for crystal growth, leading to fragmented domains and compromised device performance. Here, we introduce an in situ seeded dip coating (SDC) strategy that overcomes this limitation by engineering supersaturation to temporally decouple nucleation from crystal growth. This enables the scalable production of ultrathin two-dimensional molecular crystal (2DMC) films with exceptional uniformity across wafer dimensions. Organic field-effect transistor arrays fabricated from these 2DMCs exhibit high average charge carrier mobility (14.5 cm 2 V −1 s −1 ) and spatial homogeneity, evidenced by an ultralow mobility coefficient of variation (CV) of 4.5%. These arrays demonstrate robust polarization sensitivity with an average dichroic ratio (DR) of 2.2 and a low DR CV of 8.6%. Capitalizing on this uniformity, we constructed dual-device pixel units capable of full-range 180° polarization angle identification, enabling direct application in polarization-encoded optical encryption. The SDC technique provides a scalable pathway for practical high-performance organic polarization-sensitive optoelectronics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Time-resolved X-ray imaging of the current filamentation instability in solid-density plasmas</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67160-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67160-2</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 17:44:47 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Christopher Schoenwaelder</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexis Marret</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stefan Assenbaum</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chandra B. Curry</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eric Cunningham</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gilliss Dyer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stefan Funk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Griffin D. Glenn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sebastian Goede</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dimitri Khaghani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin Rehwald</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ulrich Schramm</dc:creator><dc:creator>Franziska Treffert</dc:creator><dc:creator>Milenko Vescovi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Karl Zeil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Siegfried H. Glenzer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Frederico Fiuza</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maxence Gauthier</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67160-2</prism:doi><description>Abstract The streaming of energetic charged particles can magnetize astrophysical and laboratory plasmas via the current filamentation instability. Despite its importance, the experimental characterization of this instability has remained a challenge. Here, we report an experiment combining a high-intensity optical laser with a high-brightness X-ray free electron laser that successfully images the instability in solid-density plasmas with 200 nm spatial and 50 fs temporal resolution. We characterize the development of μm-scale filamentary structures and their evolution over tens of picoseconds through a non-linear merging process. The measured plasma density modulations and long merging time reveal the critical importance of space-charge effects and ion motion on this electron-driven instability. Supporting theoretical analysis and kinetic simulations help distinguish the relative role of space-charge and resistive effects. Our findings indicate that magnetic fields on the order of 10 megagauss are produced, with important implications for transport and radiation emission of energetic particles in plasmas.
Published: 2026-01-09T17:44:47+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.493 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Christopher Schoenwaelder; Alexis Marret; Stefan Assenbaum; Chandra B. Curry; Eric Cunningham; Gilliss Dyer; Stefan Funk; Griffin D. Glenn; Sebastian Goede; Dimitri Khaghani; Martin Rehwald; Ulrich Schramm; Franziska Treffert; Milenko Vescovi; Karl Zeil; Siegfried H. Glenzer; Frederico Fiuza; Maxence Gauthier&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67160-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67160-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.493 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The streaming of energetic charged particles can magnetize astrophysical and laboratory plasmas via the current filamentation instability. Despite its importance, the experimental characterization of this instability has remained a challenge. Here, we report an experiment combining a high-intensity optical laser with a high-brightness X-ray free electron laser that successfully images the instability in solid-density plasmas with 200 nm spatial and 50 fs temporal resolution. We characterize the development of μm-scale filamentary structures and their evolution over tens of picoseconds through a non-linear merging process. The measured plasma density modulations and long merging time reveal the critical importance of space-charge effects and ion motion on this electron-driven instability. Supporting theoretical analysis and kinetic simulations help distinguish the relative role of space-charge and resistive effects. Our findings indicate that magnetic fields on the order of 10 megagauss are produced, with important implications for transport and radiation emission of energetic particles in plasmas.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Inelastic Dilatancy as a Mechanism for Coseismic Fluid Depressurization of a Shallow Fault Zone</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031896</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb031896</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 17:35:06 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ruei‐Jiun Hung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Matthew Weingarten</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuo Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Steven M. Day</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb031896</prism:doi><description>Abstract Hydrologic observations and experimental studies indicate that inelastic dilation from coseismic fault damage can cause substantial pore pressure reduction, yet most near‐fault hydromechanical models ignore such inelastic effects. Here, we present a 3‐D groundwater flow model incorporating the effects of inelastic dilation based on an earthquake dynamic rupture model with inelastic off‐fault deformation, both on pore pressure and permeability enhancement. Our results show that inelastic dilation causes mostly notable depressurization within ∼1 km off the fault at shallow depths (
Published: 2026-01-10T17:35:06+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.491 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ruei‐Jiun Hung; Matthew Weingarten; Shuo Ma; Steven M. Day&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031896"&gt;10.1029/2025jb031896&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.491 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Hydrologic observations and experimental studies indicate that inelastic dilation from coseismic fault damage can cause substantial pore pressure reduction, yet most near‐fault hydromechanical models ignore such inelastic effects. Here, we present a 3‐D groundwater flow model incorporating the effects of inelastic dilation based on an earthquake dynamic rupture model with inelastic off‐fault deformation, both on pore pressure and permeability enhancement. Our results show that inelastic dilation causes mostly notable depressurization within ∼1 km off the fault at shallow depths (&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Universal modulus-free transfer of scalable laser-induced graphene for electronic skins</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68131-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68131-3</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 13:36:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yuyao Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ziguan Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qincheng Sheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Depeng Kong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuyang Miao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hui Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gaoyang Pang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haibo Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linghai Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Geng Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Zou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huayong Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kaichen Xu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68131-3</prism:doi><description>Electronic skin (E-skin) with multifunctionality and large-scale features is highly desirable for human-machine interactions and wearable health monitoring. Laser-induced graphene (LIG) affords such devices with tailorable physical and chemical properties. However, relatively high Young’s modulus of precursors that derive LIG hinders its application scenarios. Here, we report a universal cryogenic transfer approach for LIG via regulating the glass transition temperature or freezing point of the transfer media. The thermal expansion-induced interlocking, ease&amp;nbsp;of interfacial separation and strong electrostatic interactions within the multiple graphene layers explain the transfer mechanisms. This contributes to the high-quality transfer of LIG onto elastomers, hydrogels and fabrics infused with various fluids. The thickness of typical elastomer can be down to 6.7 μm with its Young’s modulus ranging from 4.5 MPa to 3.9 kPa. Using this transfer technique, we create large-scale and double-layer E-skins integrated on a humanoid robot face, achieving emotional interactions with humans. The proposed strategy for merging LIG with broad categories of media affords on-demand designs of wearable and implantable electronics. This study reports a universally cryogenic stripping strategy for transferring laser-induced graphene onto diverse surfaces without modulus limitations. The thickness of typical receiver elastomers can be reduced to 6.7 μm for large-scale electronic skins.
Published: 2026-01-10T13:36:41+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.487 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yuyao Lu; Ziguan Jin; Qincheng Sheng; Depeng Kong; Chuyang Miao; Hui Wu; Gaoyang Pang; Haibo Xie; Linghai Xie; Geng Yang; Jun Zou; Huayong Yang; Wei Huang; Kaichen Xu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68131-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68131-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.487 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electronic skin (E-skin) with multifunctionality and large-scale features is highly desirable for human-machine interactions and wearable health monitoring. Laser-induced graphene (LIG) affords such devices with tailorable physical and chemical properties. However, relatively high Young’s modulus of precursors that derive LIG hinders its application scenarios. Here, we report a universal cryogenic transfer approach for LIG via regulating the glass transition temperature or freezing point of the transfer media. The thermal expansion-induced interlocking, ease&amp;amp;nbsp;of interfacial separation and strong electrostatic interactions within the multiple graphene layers explain the transfer mechanisms. This contributes to the high-quality transfer of LIG onto elastomers, hydrogels and fabrics infused with various fluids. The thickness of typical elastomer can be down to 6.7 μm with its Young’s modulus ranging from 4.5 MPa to 3.9 kPa. Using this transfer technique, we create large-scale and double-layer E-skins integrated on a humanoid robot face, achieving emotional interactions with humans. The proposed strategy for merging LIG with broad categories of media affords on-demand designs of wearable and implantable electronics. This study reports a universally cryogenic stripping strategy for transferring laser-induced graphene onto diverse surfaces without modulus limitations. The thickness of typical receiver elastomers can be reduced to 6.7 μm for large-scale electronic skins.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Efficient lead-free antimony halide light-emitting diodes with 22% external quantum efficiency via a binary host-guest architecture</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz5689</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adz5689</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jinyang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kele Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiajia Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fanglong Yuan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adz5689</prism:doi><description>Lead halide emitters hold great promise for next-generation light-emitting diodes (LEDs), but their heavy metal toxicity poses major barriers to commercialization. Therefore, developing efficient lead-free metal halide LEDs is highly desirable but remains a big challenge. Here, we report solution-processed lead-free antimony halide–based LEDs with an external quantum efficiency of 22% and a current efficiency of 55.84 candelas per ampere. The exceptional device performance is achieved through a binary host-guest architecture using a zero-dimensional organic-inorganic antimony(III) halide, which exhibits bright emission with a near-unity photoluminescence quantum yield. Optical and photophysical studies combined with theoretical calculations reveal the mechanism underlying its highly efficient self-trapped exciton emission. Efficient LEDs were achieved by doping (AylPPh 3 ) 2 SbCl 5 into a binary host system, which improved film morphology, enhanced charge carrier mobility, and achieved better carrier balance. These enhancements resulted in substantially superior device performance compared to nondoped LEDs with (AylPPh 3 ) 2 SbCl 5 as a neat emissive layer.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.475 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jinyang Li; Kele Liao; Jiajia Zhang; Fanglong Yuan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz5689"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adz5689&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.475 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lead halide emitters hold great promise for next-generation light-emitting diodes (LEDs), but their heavy metal toxicity poses major barriers to commercialization. Therefore, developing efficient lead-free metal halide LEDs is highly desirable but remains a big challenge. Here, we report solution-processed lead-free antimony halide–based LEDs with an external quantum efficiency of 22% and a current efficiency of 55.84 candelas per ampere. The exceptional device performance is achieved through a binary host-guest architecture using a zero-dimensional organic-inorganic antimony(III) halide, which exhibits bright emission with a near-unity photoluminescence quantum yield. Optical and photophysical studies combined with theoretical calculations reveal the mechanism underlying its highly efficient self-trapped exciton emission. Efficient LEDs were achieved by doping (AylPPh 3 ) 2 SbCl 5 into a binary host system, which improved film morphology, enhanced charge carrier mobility, and achieved better carrier balance. These enhancements resulted in substantially superior device performance compared to nondoped LEDs with (AylPPh 3 ) 2 SbCl 5 as a neat emissive layer.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Manganese catalyzed oximation of hydrocarbons to oximes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66576-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66576-0</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 10:22:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Menghui Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoxin Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaotian Weilian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rucao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexander Steiner</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huaming Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianliang Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chaoqun Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66576-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract Oximes are used in many scientific and industrial domains, ranging from organic synthesis through biotechnology to materials science. Traditionally, their synthesis necessitates the use of hydrocarbons with specific functional groups, such as carbonyls, which are often more challenging and expensive to obtain compared to their non-functionalized counterparts. Here we introduce an approach that enables the synthesis of oximes from hydrocarbons via the oxidative oximation of methylene C-H bonds — the most prevalent molecular unit in the world of molecules. Under the catalysis of a manganese complex with hydrogen peroxide as the oxidant and hydroxylamine sulfate as the amine source, we demonstrate that a diverse array of molecules — from simple chemicals like propane and cyclohexane to complex compounds such as the antimalarial drug artemisinin — can be oximated at methylene C-H bonds with synthetically significant yields under mild conditions. The catalyst displays a good level of functionality tolerance and often predictable site selectivity in complex molecule settings. Our approach opens an avenue for oxime synthesis and is anticipated to have broad applications in the production of fine and commodity chemicals, bioactive molecules, and new materials.
Published: 2026-01-09T10:22:17+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.475 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Menghui Song; Hong Li; Li Xie; Xiaoxin Zhang; Xiaotian Weilian; Rucao Wang; Alexander Steiner; Huaming Sun; Chao Wang; Jianliang Xiao; Chaoqun Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66576-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66576-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.475 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Oximes are used in many scientific and industrial domains, ranging from organic synthesis through biotechnology to materials science. Traditionally, their synthesis necessitates the use of hydrocarbons with specific functional groups, such as carbonyls, which are often more challenging and expensive to obtain compared to their non-functionalized counterparts. Here we introduce an approach that enables the synthesis of oximes from hydrocarbons via the oxidative oximation of methylene C-H bonds — the most prevalent molecular unit in the world of molecules. Under the catalysis of a manganese complex with hydrogen peroxide as the oxidant and hydroxylamine sulfate as the amine source, we demonstrate that a diverse array of molecules — from simple chemicals like propane and cyclohexane to complex compounds such as the antimalarial drug artemisinin — can be oximated at methylene C-H bonds with synthetically significant yields under mild conditions. The catalyst displays a good level of functionality tolerance and often predictable site selectivity in complex molecule settings. Our approach opens an avenue for oxime synthesis and is anticipated to have broad applications in the production of fine and commodity chemicals, bioactive molecules, and new materials.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Responses of extreme fire weather to CO
                    &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
                    emission reductions and underlying mechanisms</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adw4705</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adw4705</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yujin Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Seung-Ki Min</dc:creator><dc:creator>Soon-Il An</dc:creator><dc:creator>Seungmok Paik</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sanjit Kumar Mondal</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adw4705</prism:doi><description>While previous studies have reported an increase in future fire weather under global warming scenarios, there is still a limited understanding on how it may evolve under mitigation scenarios. Using idealized emission-driven climate simulations, this analysis examines changes in the extreme fire weather conditions under net-zero emission (ZeroE) and net-negative emission (NegE) scenarios. Compared to peak CO 2 levels, the NegE scenario achieves substantially greater fire danger mitigation, particularly in climatologically high-fire-danger regions, because of lower temperatures and increased relative humidity. In contrast, the ZeroE scenario leaves fire danger elevated globally, especially in Northern low-latitude regions. Regional responses are shaped by differences in atmospheric moisture supply, influenced by changes in the strength of the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation and the latitudinal position of the intertropical convergence zone. These findings highlight the crucial role of aggressive CO 2 removal strategies in mitigating fire weather dangers and underscore the limitations of ZeroEs alone in addressing global wildfire challenges.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.471 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yujin Kim; Seung-Ki Min; Soon-Il An; Seungmok Paik; Sanjit Kumar Mondal&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adw4705"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adw4705&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.471 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While previous studies have reported an increase in future fire weather under global warming scenarios, there is still a limited understanding on how it may evolve under mitigation scenarios. Using idealized emission-driven climate simulations, this analysis examines changes in the extreme fire weather conditions under net-zero emission (ZeroE) and net-negative emission (NegE) scenarios. Compared to peak CO 2 levels, the NegE scenario achieves substantially greater fire danger mitigation, particularly in climatologically high-fire-danger regions, because of lower temperatures and increased relative humidity. In contrast, the ZeroE scenario leaves fire danger elevated globally, especially in Northern low-latitude regions. Regional responses are shaped by differences in atmospheric moisture supply, influenced by changes in the strength of the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation and the latitudinal position of the intertropical convergence zone. These findings highlight the crucial role of aggressive CO 2 removal strategies in mitigating fire weather dangers and underscore the limitations of ZeroEs alone in addressing global wildfire challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A self-assembled molecule directs ordered α-FAPbI3 for n-i-p perovskite solar cells</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68214-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68214-1</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 09:05:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qingyun He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junbo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengyang Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chongyu Zhong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiangru Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengzhu Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pinghui Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Renzhi Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tianshi Qin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fangfang Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68214-1</prism:doi><description>Formamidinium lead iodide (FAPbI3) perovskite is a leading candidate for high-efficiency solar cells, but its application is hindered by the kinetic instability of its α-phase crystallization. Here, a highly effective strategy for directing the ordered crystallization of α-FAPbI3 in the n-i-p architecture is developed by incorporating a self-assembled molecule (SAM) into the anti-solvent, unlike conventional phosphate-based SAMs requiring polar protic solvents, the -SCN SAM are processed from non-polar, aprotic solvents compatible with perovskite surfaces. An in-situ formed, self-assembled layer acts as a dynamic template, guiding the top-down crystallization process to yield highly ordered α-phase films. Through a series of in-situ measurements, it is rigorously demonstrated that this SAM treatment suppresses undesirable intermediate phases, accelerates the δ-to-α transition, and strategically slows crystal growth, promoting highly ordered films. This meticulously designed strategy culminates in high-quality perovskite films, enabling single-junction devices with a champion power conversion efficiency (PCE) of 26.18% (certified at 25.67%) and mini-modules with a PCE of 21.70%. These results underscore the power of directed self-assembly in fabricating highly efficient and stable n-i-p perovskite solar cells. Formamidinium lead iodide perovskite holds promise for high-efficiency solar cells, but the kinetic instability of its α-phase crystallization remains an issue. He et al. report a strategy for directing the crystallization process in a n-i-p architecture and champion power conversion efficiency of 26.18%.
Published: 2026-01-10T09:05:58+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.470 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qingyun He; Junbo Wang; Mengyang Wu; Chongyu Zhong; Lei Li; Xiangru Zhao; Mengzhu Ding; Pinghui Yang; Renzhi Li; Wei Huang; Tianshi Qin; Fangfang Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68214-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68214-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.470 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formamidinium lead iodide (FAPbI3) perovskite is a leading candidate for high-efficiency solar cells, but its application is hindered by the kinetic instability of its α-phase crystallization. Here, a highly effective strategy for directing the ordered crystallization of α-FAPbI3 in the n-i-p architecture is developed by incorporating a self-assembled molecule (SAM) into the anti-solvent, unlike conventional phosphate-based SAMs requiring polar protic solvents, the -SCN SAM are processed from non-polar, aprotic solvents compatible with perovskite surfaces. An in-situ formed, self-assembled layer acts as a dynamic template, guiding the top-down crystallization process to yield highly ordered α-phase films. Through a series of in-situ measurements, it is rigorously demonstrated that this SAM treatment suppresses undesirable intermediate phases, accelerates the δ-to-α transition, and strategically slows crystal growth, promoting highly ordered films. This meticulously designed strategy culminates in high-quality perovskite films, enabling single-junction devices with a champion power conversion efficiency (PCE) of 26.18% (certified at 25.67%) and mini-modules with a PCE of 21.70%. These results underscore the power of directed self-assembly in fabricating highly efficient and stable n-i-p perovskite solar cells. Formamidinium lead iodide perovskite holds promise for high-efficiency solar cells, but the kinetic instability of its α-phase crystallization remains an issue. He et al. report a strategy for directing the crystallization process in a n-i-p architecture and champion power conversion efficiency of 26.18%.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>