<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:01:35 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Isotopic evidence for volatile loss driven by South Pole-Aitken basin–forming impact</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2515408123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2515408123</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 20:02:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Heng-Ci Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen-Jun Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dingshuai Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan-Hong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yangting Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xian-Hua Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fu-Yuan Wu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2515408123</prism:doi><description>Recent studies suggest that the lunar farside experienced a magma ocean evolution similar to that of the nearside. Thus, the nearside-farside dichotomy, such as volcanism and crustal thickness, is likely related to the South Pole-Aitken (SPA) basin–forming impact. Although the noritic clasts found in Chang’e-6 (CE6) samples may originate from crustal remelting induced by the SPA impact, how (and whether) the lunar mantle was modified by this event remains unclear. Here, we present the first high-precision iron (Fe) and potassium (K) isotopic measurements of CE6 low-Ti basalts, revealing higher δ 56 Fe (0.13 to 0.21‰) and δ 41 K (0 to 0.09‰) in these basalts compared to their Apollo and Chang’e-5 (CE5) counterparts (δ 56 Fe: 0 to 0.11‰; δ 41 K: −0.29 to −0.04‰). The heavy Fe and K isotopic signatures are unlikely to be derived from cosmogenic effects or the addition of impactor-derived materials. Instead, the heavy Fe isotopes can be explained by partial melting and fractional crystallization processes. For K isotopes, however, the data require that the mantle source beneath the SPA basin had a heavier K isotopic composition than that of the nearside mantle, most likely resulting from evaporation caused by the SPA-forming impact. Our results thus provide robust evidence for significant impact-induced modification of the lunar mantle and demonstrate that large-scale impacts may have played a key role in creating lunar asymmetry.
Published: 2026-01-12T20:02:21+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.594 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Heng-Ci Tian; Chi Zhang; Wen-Jun Li; Dingshuai Xue; Jing Wang; Wei Yang; Yan-Hong Liu; Yangting Lin; Xian-Hua Li; Fu-Yuan Wu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2515408123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2515408123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.594 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent studies suggest that the lunar farside experienced a magma ocean evolution similar to that of the nearside. Thus, the nearside-farside dichotomy, such as volcanism and crustal thickness, is likely related to the South Pole-Aitken (SPA) basin–forming impact. Although the noritic clasts found in Chang’e-6 (CE6) samples may originate from crustal remelting induced by the SPA impact, how (and whether) the lunar mantle was modified by this event remains unclear. Here, we present the first high-precision iron (Fe) and potassium (K) isotopic measurements of CE6 low-Ti basalts, revealing higher δ 56 Fe (0.13 to 0.21‰) and δ 41 K (0 to 0.09‰) in these basalts compared to their Apollo and Chang’e-5 (CE5) counterparts (δ 56 Fe: 0 to 0.11‰; δ 41 K: −0.29 to −0.04‰). The heavy Fe and K isotopic signatures are unlikely to be derived from cosmogenic effects or the addition of impactor-derived materials. Instead, the heavy Fe isotopes can be explained by partial melting and fractional crystallization processes. For K isotopes, however, the data require that the mantle source beneath the SPA basin had a heavier K isotopic composition than that of the nearside mantle, most likely resulting from evaporation caused by the SPA-forming impact. Our results thus provide robust evidence for significant impact-induced modification of the lunar mantle and demonstrate that large-scale impacts may have played a key role in creating lunar asymmetry.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Locating the atoms at the hard-soft interface of gold nanoparticles</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68113-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68113-5</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:40:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Weilun Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bryan D. Esser</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenming Tong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zifei Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi Tong Liew</dc:creator><dc:creator>Georgios Varnavides</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anchal Yadav</dc:creator><dc:creator>Colin Ophus</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul Mulvaney</dc:creator><dc:creator>Changlin Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Scott D. Findlay</dc:creator><dc:creator>Timothy Petersen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alison M. Funston</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joanne Etheridge</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68113-5</prism:doi><description>Surface structure affects the growth, shape and properties of nanoparticles. In wet chemical syntheses, metal additives and surfactants are used to modify surfaces and guide nanocrystal growth. To understand this process, it is critical to understand how the surface structure, and hence its energy, is modified. However, measuring the type and arrangement of atoms at hard-soft interfaces on nanoscale surfaces, especially in the presence of surfactants, is extremely challenging. Here, we determine the atomic structure of the hard-soft interface in a metallic nanoparticle by developing low-dose imaging conditions in four-dimensional scanning transmission electron microscopy that are preferentially sensitive to surface adatoms. By revealing experimentally the copper additives and bromide surfactant counterion at the surface of a gold nanocuboid and quantifying their interatomic distances, our direct, low-dose imaging method provides atomic-level understanding of chemically sophisticated nanomaterial surface structures. These measurements of the atomic structure of the hard-soft interface provide the information necessary to understand and quantify surface chemistries and energies and their pivotal role in nanocrystal growth. Surface controls nanocrystal growth, but atomic-scale hard-soft interfaces are hard to measure. Here, the authors develop electron microscopy methods to reveal the position of metal adatoms and surfactant counterions on gold nanocuboid surfaces.
Published: 2026-01-12T08:40:19+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.556 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Weilun Li; Bryan D. Esser; Wenming Tong; Zifei Chen; Zhi Tong Liew; Georgios Varnavides; Anchal Yadav; Colin Ophus; Paul Mulvaney; Changlin Zheng; Scott D. Findlay; Timothy Petersen; Alison M. Funston; Joanne Etheridge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68113-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68113-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.556 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surface structure affects the growth, shape and properties of nanoparticles. In wet chemical syntheses, metal additives and surfactants are used to modify surfaces and guide nanocrystal growth. To understand this process, it is critical to understand how the surface structure, and hence its energy, is modified. However, measuring the type and arrangement of atoms at hard-soft interfaces on nanoscale surfaces, especially in the presence of surfactants, is extremely challenging. Here, we determine the atomic structure of the hard-soft interface in a metallic nanoparticle by developing low-dose imaging conditions in four-dimensional scanning transmission electron microscopy that are preferentially sensitive to surface adatoms. By revealing experimentally the copper additives and bromide surfactant counterion at the surface of a gold nanocuboid and quantifying their interatomic distances, our direct, low-dose imaging method provides atomic-level understanding of chemically sophisticated nanomaterial surface structures. These measurements of the atomic structure of the hard-soft interface provide the information necessary to understand and quantify surface chemistries and energies and their pivotal role in nanocrystal growth. Surface controls nanocrystal growth, but atomic-scale hard-soft interfaces are hard to measure. Here, the authors develop electron microscopy methods to reveal the position of metal adatoms and surfactant counterions on gold nanocuboid surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>All-fibre-coupled terahertz single-pixel imaging for biomedical applications</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68290-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68290-x</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:33:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Sen Mou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rayko I. Stantchev</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sonal Saxena</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huiliang Ou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shreeya Rane</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sophie L. Pain</dc:creator><dc:creator>John D. Murphy</dc:creator><dc:creator>Euan Hendry</dc:creator><dc:creator>James Lloyd-Hughes</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emma Pickwell-MacPherson</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68290-x</prism:doi><description>Abstract Real-time, non-invasive imaging techniques are essential for advancing biomedical diagnostics and material analysis, yet existing terahertz (THz) systems often suffer from limited speed, bulky designs, and poor adaptability to in situ environments. Addressing these challenges, we present a fully fibre-coupled THz attenuated total internal reflection single-pixel imaging system, offering a compact, flexible, and robust platform for non-destructive spectroscopy and in vivo imaging. This all-fibre architecture enables seamless integration for in situ biomedical applications, including measurements directly on patients. Central to our design is a THz spatial light modulator based on an unpassivated silicon wafer, facilitating high-speed modulation and enabling video-rate imaging with a spatial resolution down to 360 μ m. Despite being in the reflection geometry and using fibre-coupled light, our system achieves an imaging throughput exceeding 30,000 pixels per second for 64-by-64 images - over five-fold higher than the state of the art - representing a substantial improvement in real-time THz imaging capabilities.
Published: 2026-01-12T17:33:41+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.547 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sen Mou; Rayko I. Stantchev; Sonal Saxena; Huiliang Ou; Shreeya Rane; Sophie L. Pain; John D. Murphy; Euan Hendry; James Lloyd-Hughes; Emma Pickwell-MacPherson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68290-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68290-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.547 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Real-time, non-invasive imaging techniques are essential for advancing biomedical diagnostics and material analysis, yet existing terahertz (THz) systems often suffer from limited speed, bulky designs, and poor adaptability to in situ environments. Addressing these challenges, we present a fully fibre-coupled THz attenuated total internal reflection single-pixel imaging system, offering a compact, flexible, and robust platform for non-destructive spectroscopy and in vivo imaging. This all-fibre architecture enables seamless integration for in situ biomedical applications, including measurements directly on patients. Central to our design is a THz spatial light modulator based on an unpassivated silicon wafer, facilitating high-speed modulation and enabling video-rate imaging with a spatial resolution down to 360 μ m. Despite being in the reflection geometry and using fibre-coupled light, our system achieves an imaging throughput exceeding 30,000 pixels per second for 64-by-64 images - over five-fold higher than the state of the art - representing a substantial improvement in real-time THz imaging capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Diffractive magic cube network with super-high capacity enabled by mechanical reconfiguration</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68310-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68310-w</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 01:03:59 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Peijie Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fubei Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuanfeng Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingzhe Chong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zongkun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qian Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junjie Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruhao Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhongwang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingbo Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ji Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunhua Tan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68310-w</prism:doi><description>Free-space wavefront manipulation devices have emerged as powerful platforms for advanced optical information systems. In response to the challenges posed by the exponential growth of optical information, optical multiplexing and dynamic reconfigurable devices are being actively explored to the enhance system capacity. Among them, coarse-grained mechanically reconfigurable mechanism offers a cost-effective and low-complexity approach for capacity enhancement. However, the channel numbers achieved in current studies are insufficient for practical applications because of inadequate mechanical transformations and suboptimal optimization models. In this article, a diffractive magic cube network (DMCN) is proposed to advance the multiplexing capacity of mechanically reconfigurable system. We utilized the diffractive deep neural network (D2NN) model to jointly optimize the subset of channels generated by the combination of three mechanical operations, permutation, translation, and rotation. The 144-channel holograms, 108-channel single/double focus, 60-channel single/multi-mode OAM beam generation were experimentally demonstrated using diffractive optical elements (DOEs). An equivalent connectivity law was formulated to improve model scalability. Our strategy not only provides a novel paradigm to improve system capacity to super-high level with low crosstalk, but also paves the way for new advancements in optical storage, computing, communication, and photolithography. Mechanically reconfigurable mechanisms offer a cost-effective, low-complexity approach to build high-capacity multiplexing wavefront modulation devices, yet current studies achieve insufficient channel numbers for practical applications due to limited mechanical transformations and suboptimal optimization models. Here, authors propose a diffractive magic cube network to address this challenge.
Published: 2026-01-11T01:03:59+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.536 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Peijie Feng; Fubei Liu; Yuanfeng Liu; Mingzhe Chong; Zongkun Zhang; Qian Zhao; Junjie Li; Ruhao Pan; Zhongwang Wang; Jingbo Sun; Ji Zhou; Yunhua Tan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68310-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68310-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.536 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free-space wavefront manipulation devices have emerged as powerful platforms for advanced optical information systems. In response to the challenges posed by the exponential growth of optical information, optical multiplexing and dynamic reconfigurable devices are being actively explored to the enhance system capacity. Among them, coarse-grained mechanically reconfigurable mechanism offers a cost-effective and low-complexity approach for capacity enhancement. However, the channel numbers achieved in current studies are insufficient for practical applications because of inadequate mechanical transformations and suboptimal optimization models. In this article, a diffractive magic cube network (DMCN) is proposed to advance the multiplexing capacity of mechanically reconfigurable system. We utilized the diffractive deep neural network (D2NN) model to jointly optimize the subset of channels generated by the combination of three mechanical operations, permutation, translation, and rotation. The 144-channel holograms, 108-channel single/double focus, 60-channel single/multi-mode OAM beam generation were experimentally demonstrated using diffractive optical elements (DOEs). An equivalent connectivity law was formulated to improve model scalability. Our strategy not only provides a novel paradigm to improve system capacity to super-high level with low crosstalk, but also paves the way for new advancements in optical storage, computing, communication, and photolithography. Mechanically reconfigurable mechanisms offer a cost-effective, low-complexity approach to build high-capacity multiplexing wavefront modulation devices, yet current studies achieve insufficient channel numbers for practical applications due to limited mechanical transformations and suboptimal optimization models. Here, authors propose a diffractive magic cube network to address this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Atomically precise ligand engineering of gold nanoparticles via interphase mass transfer</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68345-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68345-z</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 11:17:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bihan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaorong Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Moshuqi Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiaofeng Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianping Xie</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68345-z</prism:doi><description>Precise surface engineering of gold nanoclusters (Au NCs) is critical for bioimaging. However, conventional methods often compromise the structural integrity of Au NCs or result in uncontrolled ligand distribution due to rapid reaction kinetics and etching side reactions. Herein, we develop an interphase-assisted ligand exchange method, which leverages mass transfer resistance between immiscible phases to precisely control the mass transfer of ligands. This approach significantly suppresses side etching while maintaining exchange kinetics, enabling high-yield, structure-preserving substitution of diverse thiol ligands on Au NCs. By systematically introducing p-aminothiophenol (p-ATP) ligands, we reveal that increasing p-ATP density on Au25 NCs shifts their biodistribution in female BALB/c nude mice from liver and spleen to kidneys, highlighting the tunability of organ targeting through ligand engineering. The methodology developed here not only boosts the surface engineering to molecular resolution, but also provides a platform for studying ligand effects of metal nanomaterials at the same resolution. Precise surface engineering of nanoparticles is essential for advancing bioimaging technologies, yet achieving atomically controlled ligand functionalization remains a challenge. Here, the authors develop an interphase-assisted ligand exchange method, which leverages mass transfer resistance between immiscible phases to precisely control the concentration of foreign ligands interacting with gold nanoclusters.
Published: 2026-01-12T11:17:23+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.531 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bihan Zhang; Feng Xiao; Xiaorong Song; Moshuqi Zhu; Qiaofeng Yao; Jianping Xie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68345-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68345-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.531 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Precise surface engineering of gold nanoclusters (Au NCs) is critical for bioimaging. However, conventional methods often compromise the structural integrity of Au NCs or result in uncontrolled ligand distribution due to rapid reaction kinetics and etching side reactions. Herein, we develop an interphase-assisted ligand exchange method, which leverages mass transfer resistance between immiscible phases to precisely control the mass transfer of ligands. This approach significantly suppresses side etching while maintaining exchange kinetics, enabling high-yield, structure-preserving substitution of diverse thiol ligands on Au NCs. By systematically introducing p-aminothiophenol (p-ATP) ligands, we reveal that increasing p-ATP density on Au25 NCs shifts their biodistribution in female BALB/c nude mice from liver and spleen to kidneys, highlighting the tunability of organ targeting through ligand engineering. The methodology developed here not only boosts the surface engineering to molecular resolution, but also provides a platform for studying ligand effects of metal nanomaterials at the same resolution. Precise surface engineering of nanoparticles is essential for advancing bioimaging technologies, yet achieving atomically controlled ligand functionalization remains a challenge. Here, the authors develop an interphase-assisted ligand exchange method, which leverages mass transfer resistance between immiscible phases to precisely control the concentration of foreign ligands interacting with gold nanoclusters.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Cooperative atomic motion during shear deformation in metallic glass</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68308-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68308-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 17:09:28 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yoshinori Shiihara</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takuya Iwashita</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nozumu Adachi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshikazu Todaka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takeshi Egami</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68308-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract Elucidating mechanical deformation in glassy materials at the atomic level is challenging due to their disordered atomic structure. Using our frozen-atom analysis of the simulation data, we reveal that anelastic deformation in CuZr metallic glasses is fundamentally driven by cooperative atomic motions of tens of atoms elastically linked to one another, forming trigger groups. They initiate localized rearrangements, which can cascade into plastic flow. These cores show no clear structural or elastic precursors in the initial configuration, challenging the idea that deformation occurs in defective regions. Instead, deformation events are highly stochastic and transient, driven by collective atomic motion. This finding not only reshapes our understanding of glassy material deformation mechanisms but also highlights cooperative motion as a key factor in avalanche-like phenomena governing the behavior of disordered systems across multiple scales.
Published: 2026-01-12T17:09:28+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.519 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yoshinori Shiihara; Takuya Iwashita; Nozumu Adachi; Yoshikazu Todaka; Takeshi Egami&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68308-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68308-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.519 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Elucidating mechanical deformation in glassy materials at the atomic level is challenging due to their disordered atomic structure. Using our frozen-atom analysis of the simulation data, we reveal that anelastic deformation in CuZr metallic glasses is fundamentally driven by cooperative atomic motions of tens of atoms elastically linked to one another, forming trigger groups. They initiate localized rearrangements, which can cascade into plastic flow. These cores show no clear structural or elastic precursors in the initial configuration, challenging the idea that deformation occurs in defective regions. Instead, deformation events are highly stochastic and transient, driven by collective atomic motion. This finding not only reshapes our understanding of glassy material deformation mechanisms but also highlights cooperative motion as a key factor in avalanche-like phenomena governing the behavior of disordered systems across multiple scales.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Non-polar nanocluster confinement engineering realizes high capacitive energy storage in Pb-free high-entropy relaxors</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68301-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68301-x</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:46:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Aiwen Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zehao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiang Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tengfei Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ao Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liqiang He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ning Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuewen Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinchu Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaokuo Er</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruzhong Zuo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68301-x</prism:doi><description>Dielectric ceramic capacitors with ultrahigh power density have become indispensable in modern power electronics, yet the persistent challenge of achieving superior energy density with high energy efficiency remains a critical bottleneck for practical applications. Herein, we propose an effective non-polar nanocluster confinement strategy through phase-field simulation-guided design of high-entropy (Bi0.2Na0.2Ba0.2Sr0.2Ca0.2)(Ti1-xSnx)O3 lead-free relaxor ferroelectrics. The incorporation of Sn4+ ions with low ionic polarizability leads to the formation of localized non-ferroelectric perovskite units, which constitute robust non-polar nanoclusters, being further stabilized and rendered immobile against electric fields by the substantial local random fields inherent to the high-entropy configuration. Consequently, these engineered non-polar nanoclusters serve as effective pinning centers to impede the merging and growth of polar nanodomains under electric fields, thereby reconciling the inherent conflict between polarization enhancement and hysteresis reduction. The optimized composition (x = 0.06) exhibits a high recoverable energy density of ~18.5 J·cm-3 together with an ultrahigh energy efficiency of ~92.4% in multilayer ceramic capacitors, representing a competitive combination among lead-free counterparts. This approach not only establishes a viable paradigm for next-generation energy storage dielectrics but also provides fundamental insights for designing functional materials with tailored electrical properties. The authors reconcile the conflict between polarization and hysteresis by confining polarization response of non-polar nanoclusters in high-entropy relaxors, thus improving the energy storage properties of multilayer ceramic capacitors.
Published: 2026-01-12T08:46:36+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.515 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Aiwen Xie; Zehao Li; Xiang Wu; Tengfei Hu; Ao Tian; Yi Zhang; Liqiang He; Ning Liu; Xin Gao; Xuewen Jiang; Xinchu Xie; Xiaokuo Er; Ruzhong Zuo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68301-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68301-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.515 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dielectric ceramic capacitors with ultrahigh power density have become indispensable in modern power electronics, yet the persistent challenge of achieving superior energy density with high energy efficiency remains a critical bottleneck for practical applications. Herein, we propose an effective non-polar nanocluster confinement strategy through phase-field simulation-guided design of high-entropy (Bi0.2Na0.2Ba0.2Sr0.2Ca0.2)(Ti1-xSnx)O3 lead-free relaxor ferroelectrics. The incorporation of Sn4+ ions with low ionic polarizability leads to the formation of localized non-ferroelectric perovskite units, which constitute robust non-polar nanoclusters, being further stabilized and rendered immobile against electric fields by the substantial local random fields inherent to the high-entropy configuration. Consequently, these engineered non-polar nanoclusters serve as effective pinning centers to impede the merging and growth of polar nanodomains under electric fields, thereby reconciling the inherent conflict between polarization enhancement and hysteresis reduction. The optimized composition (x = 0.06) exhibits a high recoverable energy density of ~18.5 J·cm-3 together with an ultrahigh energy efficiency of ~92.4% in multilayer ceramic capacitors, representing a competitive combination among lead-free counterparts. This approach not only establishes a viable paradigm for next-generation energy storage dielectrics but also provides fundamental insights for designing functional materials with tailored electrical properties. The authors reconcile the conflict between polarization and hysteresis by confining polarization response of non-polar nanoclusters in high-entropy relaxors, thus improving the energy storage properties of multilayer ceramic capacitors.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ancient ‘snowball’ Earth had frigidly briny seas</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-04081-6</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-025-04081-6</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:56:44 +0000</pubDate><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-025-04081-6</prism:doi><description>Ocean temperatures well below freezing in Earth’s deep-past glacial phases imply some very salty waters. Ocean temperatures well below freezing in Earth’s deep-past glacial phases imply some very salty waters.
Published: 2026-01-12T09:56:44+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.514 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-04081-6"&gt;10.1038/d41586-025-04081-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.514 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ocean temperatures well below freezing in Earth’s deep-past glacial phases imply some very salty waters. Ocean temperatures well below freezing in Earth’s deep-past glacial phases imply some very salty waters.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Closing the carbon mismatch</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01906-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41561-025-01906-x</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:02:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xujia Jiang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Geoscience</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41561-025-01906-x</prism:doi><description>Authors and Affiliations Nature Geoscience https://www.nature.com/ngeo/ Xujia Jiang Authors Xujia Jiang View author publications
Published: 2026-01-12T16:02:15+00:00
Venue: Nature Geoscience
Score: 0.512 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xujia Jiang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Geoscience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01906-x"&gt;10.1038/s41561-025-01906-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.512 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authors and Affiliations Nature Geoscience https://www.nature.com/ngeo/ Xujia Jiang Authors Xujia Jiang View author publications&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Harnessing acoustic topology for dynamic control of liquid crystal defects</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68001-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68001-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:23:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ke-Hui Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zefei Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Ting Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sen-Sen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuejia Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qing Huo Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu-Jian Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68001-y</prism:doi><description>Topological soft matter systems rely on controllable defect structures to encode functionality, yet robust, large-scale, and reconfigurable manipulation strategies remain elusive. Here we present a versatile acoustic platform for dynamic control of liquid crystal defect arrays via engineered topological wavefields. By coherently superimposing surface acoustic waves, we generate spatially structured potential landscapes and acoustic streaming vortices that interact with the molecular orientation field of liquid crystals, enabling dynamic reconfiguration of topological defects. Tuning the acoustic parameter space allows precise modulation of defect density, symmetry, morphology, and spatial positioning. A theoretical framework based on Ginzburg-Landau modeling and free energy minimization captures the formation of vortex-induced instabilities and associated topological textures. The platform operates across diverse liquid crystal compositions, demonstrating material generality. This acoustically driven approach offers a scalable strategy for programmable topological structure in soft matter, with potential applications in reconfigurable photonic devices and active material systems. Topological defects can be used to encode functionalities in soft matter systems. Here, authors dynamically reconfigure an acoustic lattice to create programmable topological defect arrays. The resulting velocity fields and steady acoustic streaming realign the director, enabling reversible control of defect properties and their translation.
Published: 2026-01-12T08:23:33+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.512 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ke-Hui Wu; Zefei Sun; Li-Ting Zhu; Sen-Sen Li; Xuejia Hu; Qing Huo Liu; Lu-Jian Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68001-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68001-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.512 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topological soft matter systems rely on controllable defect structures to encode functionality, yet robust, large-scale, and reconfigurable manipulation strategies remain elusive. Here we present a versatile acoustic platform for dynamic control of liquid crystal defect arrays via engineered topological wavefields. By coherently superimposing surface acoustic waves, we generate spatially structured potential landscapes and acoustic streaming vortices that interact with the molecular orientation field of liquid crystals, enabling dynamic reconfiguration of topological defects. Tuning the acoustic parameter space allows precise modulation of defect density, symmetry, morphology, and spatial positioning. A theoretical framework based on Ginzburg-Landau modeling and free energy minimization captures the formation of vortex-induced instabilities and associated topological textures. The platform operates across diverse liquid crystal compositions, demonstrating material generality. This acoustically driven approach offers a scalable strategy for programmable topological structure in soft matter, with potential applications in reconfigurable photonic devices and active material systems. Topological defects can be used to encode functionalities in soft matter systems. Here, authors dynamically reconfigure an acoustic lattice to create programmable topological defect arrays. The resulting velocity fields and steady acoustic streaming realign the director, enabling reversible control of defect properties and their translation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seeing Roman life through water: Exploring Pompeii’s public baths via carbonate deposits</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2517276122</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2517276122</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 20:02:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Gül Sürmelihindi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cees Passchier</dc:creator><dc:creator>Monika Trümper</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Heide</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christoph Spötl</dc:creator><dc:creator>Denis Scholz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael Weber</dc:creator><dc:creator>Friedrich Hawemann</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2517276122</prism:doi><description>The ancient city of Pompeii, destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in AD 79, shows technological improvements to its water supply after becoming a Roman colony. Its inhabitants relied on wells for their water supply prior to the installation of a Roman aqueduct. Carbonate incrustations deposited in various components of the city’s hydraulic infrastructure, including the aqueduct, its water towers, the well shafts, and pools of the public baths. The stable isotope and trace element composition of these carbonates differ markedly between structures supplied by wells and those fed by the aqueduct, reflecting the contrasting origins of their source waters. While the aqueduct was fed by karst springs, the wells tapped into highly mineralized groundwater from volcanic deposits. These geochemical distinctions allow for a detailed reconstruction of Pompeii’s water management system, particularly the transition from well- to aqueduct-based water supply. The periodicity of δ 13 C variations in carbonate crusts sampled from well, pools, and drainage channels of the Republican Baths offers insights into the operation and maintenance of the facility. δ 13 C values show a sharp drop from wells to bathing pools, suggesting contamination by human waste and implying that the bath water was not regularly replenished in the Republican Baths.
Published: 2026-01-12T20:02:21+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.504 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Gül Sürmelihindi; Cees Passchier; Monika Trümper; Thomas Heide; Christoph Spötl; Denis Scholz; Michael Weber; Friedrich Hawemann&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2517276122"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2517276122&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.504 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ancient city of Pompeii, destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in AD 79, shows technological improvements to its water supply after becoming a Roman colony. Its inhabitants relied on wells for their water supply prior to the installation of a Roman aqueduct. Carbonate incrustations deposited in various components of the city’s hydraulic infrastructure, including the aqueduct, its water towers, the well shafts, and pools of the public baths. The stable isotope and trace element composition of these carbonates differ markedly between structures supplied by wells and those fed by the aqueduct, reflecting the contrasting origins of their source waters. While the aqueduct was fed by karst springs, the wells tapped into highly mineralized groundwater from volcanic deposits. These geochemical distinctions allow for a detailed reconstruction of Pompeii’s water management system, particularly the transition from well- to aqueduct-based water supply. The periodicity of δ 13 C variations in carbonate crusts sampled from well, pools, and drainage channels of the Republican Baths offers insights into the operation and maintenance of the facility. δ 13 C values show a sharp drop from wells to bathing pools, suggesting contamination by human waste and implying that the bath water was not regularly replenished in the Republican Baths.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Quantum enhanced metrology based on flipping trajectory of cold Rydberg gases</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67921-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67921-z</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:46:35 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ya-Jun Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng-Yuan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shi-Yao Shao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qing Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Han-Chao Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tian-Yu Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi-Feng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia-Dou Nan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi-Ming Yin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dong-Yang Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiao-Qiao Fang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guang-Can Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Hua Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dong-Sheng Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bao-Sen Shi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67921-z</prism:doi><description>The dynamical trajectory of a dissipative Rydberg many-body system could be flipped under a microwave field driving, displaying an enhanced sensitivity. This is because the intersection of the folded hysteresis trajectories exhibits a sharp peak near the phase transition, amplifying the response to small changes in the microwave field. Here, we demonstrate an experiment of enhanced metrology through flipping the hysteresis trajectory in a cold atomic system, displaying an approach to improve sensitivity by the gap-closing points. By measuring the intersection points of hysteresis trajectories versus Rabi frequency of the microwave field, we quantify the equivalent sensitivity to be 1.6(5) nV&amp;nbsp;cm−1Hz−1/2. The measurement is also dependent on the interaction time, optical depth and principal quantum number since the long-range interaction between Rydberg atoms could dramatically change the shape of hysteresis trajectories. The reported results suggest that flipping trajectory features in cold Rydberg many-body systems could advance sensing and metrology applications. Dissipative many body systems provide quantum-enhanced sensitivity to external near gap-closing points. Here, the authors demonstrate record sensitivity in a Rydberg-atomic platform in correspondence of folded hysteresis trajectories under external microwave driving
Published: 2026-01-12T08:46:35+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.494 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ya-Jun Wang; Jun Zhang; Zheng-Yuan Zhang; Shi-Yao Shao; Qing Li; Han-Chao Chen; Yu Ma; Tian-Yu Han; Qi-Feng Wang; Jia-Dou Nan; Yi-Ming Yin; Dong-Yang Zhu; Qiao-Qiao Fang; Chao Yu; Xin Liu; Guang-Can Guo; Bang Liu; Li-Hua Zhang; Dong-Sheng Ding; Bao-Sen Shi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67921-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67921-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.494 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dynamical trajectory of a dissipative Rydberg many-body system could be flipped under a microwave field driving, displaying an enhanced sensitivity. This is because the intersection of the folded hysteresis trajectories exhibits a sharp peak near the phase transition, amplifying the response to small changes in the microwave field. Here, we demonstrate an experiment of enhanced metrology through flipping the hysteresis trajectory in a cold atomic system, displaying an approach to improve sensitivity by the gap-closing points. By measuring the intersection points of hysteresis trajectories versus Rabi frequency of the microwave field, we quantify the equivalent sensitivity to be 1.6(5) nV&amp;amp;nbsp;cm−1Hz−1/2. The measurement is also dependent on the interaction time, optical depth and principal quantum number since the long-range interaction between Rydberg atoms could dramatically change the shape of hysteresis trajectories. The reported results suggest that flipping trajectory features in cold Rydberg many-body systems could advance sensing and metrology applications. Dissipative many body systems provide quantum-enhanced sensitivity to external near gap-closing points. Here, the authors demonstrate record sensitivity in a Rydberg-atomic platform in correspondence of folded hysteresis trajectories under external microwave driving&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A tin fluoride-free, efficient and durable tin-lead perovskite solar cell</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-65445-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-65445-0</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:28:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Haobo Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenxiao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianhong Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuyang Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuemin Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunfei Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengbo Cui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sheng Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaodong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junfeng Fang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-65445-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract The photo-thermal stability of tin-lead perovskite solar cells remains a major challenge. SnF 2 is commonly used to inhibit Sn 2+ oxidation and reduce hole density, however, the stability of devices remains poor. Here, we found that the poor stability partially results from an adverse effect of SnF 2 , which reacts with formamidine iodide during photo-thermal treatments. This reaction leads to degradation of perovskite and release of hydrofluoric acid, which corrodes electrodes. To address this issue, we develop a strategy that combines lead powder in precursor with PbF 2 post-treatment, replacing the role of SnF 2 as in film formation and surface defect passivation, respectively. The d-electron polarization in Pb 2+ strengthens its bond with F ⁻ , making it react inert to perovskite. In this work, the efficiency of SnF 2 -free devices increases from 16.43% to 24.07%. The cells retain 60% of their initial efficiency after 550 hours operating at 85 °C under maximum power point.
Published: 2026-01-12T18:28:14+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.488 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Haobo Yuan; Wenxiao Zhang; Feng Wang; Jianhong Xu; Yuyang Hu; Xuemin Guo; Yunfei Li; Bo Feng; Zhengbo Cui; Wen Li; Sheng Fu; Xiaodong Li; Feng Gao; Junfeng Fang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-65445-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-65445-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.488 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The photo-thermal stability of tin-lead perovskite solar cells remains a major challenge. SnF 2 is commonly used to inhibit Sn 2+ oxidation and reduce hole density, however, the stability of devices remains poor. Here, we found that the poor stability partially results from an adverse effect of SnF 2 , which reacts with formamidine iodide during photo-thermal treatments. This reaction leads to degradation of perovskite and release of hydrofluoric acid, which corrodes electrodes. To address this issue, we develop a strategy that combines lead powder in precursor with PbF 2 post-treatment, replacing the role of SnF 2 as in film formation and surface defect passivation, respectively. The d-electron polarization in Pb 2+ strengthens its bond with F ⁻ , making it react inert to perovskite. In this work, the efficiency of SnF 2 -free devices increases from 16.43% to 24.07%. The cells retain 60% of their initial efficiency after 550 hours operating at 85 °C under maximum power point.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Enhancing carbon sinks in China using a spatially-optimized forestation strategy</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68288-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68288-5</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 05:44:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yanli Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Pugh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Evgenios Agathokleous</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fangmin Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephen Sitch</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weibin You</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wangya Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stefan Olin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shirong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoyi Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pedro Cabral</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pengsen Sun</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68288-5</prism:doi><description>China plans expanding 49.5 million hectares of new forests by 2050 to strengthen carbon sequestration. However, estimates of the carbon benefits from this expansion rarely consider the effect of ‘forest edge’, where tree mortality increases under intensified stress from wind, drought, pests, and fire. Here we show that proximity to forest edges substantially reduces biomass carbon storage, and develop a spatial optimization strategy that prioritizes planting in areas that minimize edge effects. Our projections show that forestation optimized for edge effects results in a 51% increase in carbon gain (986 ± 22 Tg by 2060), with approximately half of the total gain driven by reduced edge effects. These findings demonstrate that ignoring edge effects can significantly overestimate carbon sink potential and highlight spatially optimized forestation as a pathway to maximize climate mitigation and ecological benefits. The study shows forests near edges store less carbon due to higher environmental stress. Spatial optimization of new forest plantations could boost carbon storage by 986 Tg by 2060, with 53% of the gain from reducing edge effects.
Published: 2026-01-12T05:44:21+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.484 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yanli Dong; Zhen Yu; Thomas Pugh; Evgenios Agathokleous; Fangmin Zhang; Stephen Sitch; Weibin You; Wangya Han; Stefan Olin; Shirong Liu; Guoyi Zhou; Pedro Cabral; Pengsen Sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68288-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68288-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.484 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;China plans expanding 49.5 million hectares of new forests by 2050 to strengthen carbon sequestration. However, estimates of the carbon benefits from this expansion rarely consider the effect of ‘forest edge’, where tree mortality increases under intensified stress from wind, drought, pests, and fire. Here we show that proximity to forest edges substantially reduces biomass carbon storage, and develop a spatial optimization strategy that prioritizes planting in areas that minimize edge effects. Our projections show that forestation optimized for edge effects results in a 51% increase in carbon gain (986 ± 22 Tg by 2060), with approximately half of the total gain driven by reduced edge effects. These findings demonstrate that ignoring edge effects can significantly overestimate carbon sink potential and highlight spatially optimized forestation as a pathway to maximize climate mitigation and ecological benefits. The study shows forests near edges store less carbon due to higher environmental stress. Spatial optimization of new forest plantations could boost carbon storage by 986 Tg by 2060, with 53% of the gain from reducing edge effects.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Binary mineral nanoparticles enable intravascular delivery of metal ions to tumors for metalloimmunotherapy</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68279-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68279-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:52:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bao Loc Nguyen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ngoc Duy Le</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thi Oanh Oanh Nguyen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daehyeon Ahn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Basavaraj Rudragouda Patil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Beomsu Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cao Dai Phung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Duc-Vinh Pham</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jung Min Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiwoo Hong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jae-Hoon Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sae Kwang Ku</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeonghwan Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jong Oh Kim</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68279-y</prism:doi><description>Although disruptions in metal ion homeostasis leading to severe cellular damage and regulated cell death are a promising strategy for cancer immunotherapy, challenges in overloading these ions to tumor cells without premature release have limited their therapeutic applications. In this study, we develop binary mineral nanoparticles incorporating both Ca2+ and Na+ ions to enhance the cytotoxic effects of ion interference in cancer immunotherapy. Engineered using a microfluidic system for uniform size distribution and scalability, these nanoparticles exhibit pH-sensitive ion release. Systemically administered, they preferentially accumulate in tumors, elevating intracellular Ca2+ and Na+ levels and inducing immunogenic cell death without calcium channel activators or other small-molecule inducers. Our binary mineral nanoparticles significantly enhance antitumor immunity, especially when combined with an immune checkpoint inhibitor, leading to long-term immunity and inhibition of metastasis. This nanotechnology-enabled synergistic delivery of Ca²⁺ and Na⁺ ions represents a promising adjunct to existing metalloimmunotherapy strategies for cancer eradication. Cell death induced by metal ions is promising for cancer immunotherapy but sometimes limited by effective loading/release into tumor sites. Here this group reports a binary mineral nanoparticles incorporating both Ca2+ and Na+ ions to enhance the cytotoxic effects of ion interference in cancer immunotherapy.
Published: 2026-01-12T15:52:55+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.475 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bao Loc Nguyen; Ngoc Duy Le; Thi Oanh Oanh Nguyen; Daehyeon Ahn; Basavaraj Rudragouda Patil; Beomsu Kim; Cao Dai Phung; Duc-Vinh Pham; Jung Min Lee; Jiwoo Hong; Jae-Hoon Chang; Sae Kwang Ku; Jeonghwan Kim; Jong Oh Kim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68279-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68279-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.475 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although disruptions in metal ion homeostasis leading to severe cellular damage and regulated cell death are a promising strategy for cancer immunotherapy, challenges in overloading these ions to tumor cells without premature release have limited their therapeutic applications. In this study, we develop binary mineral nanoparticles incorporating both Ca2+ and Na+ ions to enhance the cytotoxic effects of ion interference in cancer immunotherapy. Engineered using a microfluidic system for uniform size distribution and scalability, these nanoparticles exhibit pH-sensitive ion release. Systemically administered, they preferentially accumulate in tumors, elevating intracellular Ca2+ and Na+ levels and inducing immunogenic cell death without calcium channel activators or other small-molecule inducers. Our binary mineral nanoparticles significantly enhance antitumor immunity, especially when combined with an immune checkpoint inhibitor, leading to long-term immunity and inhibition of metastasis. This nanotechnology-enabled synergistic delivery of Ca²⁺ and Na⁺ ions represents a promising adjunct to existing metalloimmunotherapy strategies for cancer eradication. Cell death induced by metal ions is promising for cancer immunotherapy but sometimes limited by effective loading/release into tumor sites. Here this group reports a binary mineral nanoparticles incorporating both Ca2+ and Na+ ions to enhance the cytotoxic effects of ion interference in cancer immunotherapy.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A waterproof and ultra-elastic thermoelectric foam for underwater human signal detection</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68055-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68055-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:26:05 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Wendi Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao-Lei Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyang He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suiyuan Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengzu Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ding Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoyun Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongnan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liming Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaohong Qin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi-Gang Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68055-y</prism:doi><description>Underwater tasks such as ocean exploration and emergency rescue demand advanced wearable sensors. However, multifunctional underwater sensors capable of integrating self-powered signal transmission, effective thermal-moisture regulation, and multi-signal decoupling remain unreported. Here, we present a three-dimensional multi-functional thermoelectric device composed of highly porous polyurethane foam coated with a waterproof conductive layer made from single-walled carbon nanotubes, poly(3,4-ethylenedioxythiophene)-polystyrene sulfonate, and waterborne polyurethane. Hydrogen bonding between the sulfonate groups in poly(3,4-ethylenedioxythiophene)-polystyrene sulfonate and the -NH groups in waterborne polyurethane enhances water resistance (contact angle of 112°) and mechanical durability under repeated compression (20,000 cycles), while achieving an ultra-fast response time of 40 ms. The device exhibits high breathability (406 mm s−1) owing to its porous three-dimensional architecture. Additionally, it enables precise temperature sensing with a resolution of 0.05 K and a response time of 400 ms. Importantly, it successfully decouples temperature and strain signals in underwater environments. Leveraging its waterproof and signal-decoupling capabilities, we further demonstrate a fully integrated underwater monitoring and interaction system encompassing sensing hardware and decision-making logic. This work represents a significant advancement in wearable underwater electronics and offers another perspective for reliable, real-time human-machine interaction in aquatic settings. Multifunctional underwater sensors with integrated self-powered signal transmission, effective thermal-moisture regulation, and multi-signal decoupling are desirable of underwater tasks. Here, the authors report a three-dimensional thermoelectric device composed of porous polyurethane foam coated with a waterproof conductive layer for human-machine interaction in aquatic settings.
Published: 2026-01-12T18:26:05+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.472 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Wendi Liu; Xiao-Lei Shi; Xinyang He; Suiyuan Zhu; Zhen Li; Chengzu Li; Ding Zhang; Meng Li; Xiaoyun Wu; Hongnan Zhang; Liming Wang; Xiaohong Qin; Zhi-Gang Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68055-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68055-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.472 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underwater tasks such as ocean exploration and emergency rescue demand advanced wearable sensors. However, multifunctional underwater sensors capable of integrating self-powered signal transmission, effective thermal-moisture regulation, and multi-signal decoupling remain unreported. Here, we present a three-dimensional multi-functional thermoelectric device composed of highly porous polyurethane foam coated with a waterproof conductive layer made from single-walled carbon nanotubes, poly(3,4-ethylenedioxythiophene)-polystyrene sulfonate, and waterborne polyurethane. Hydrogen bonding between the sulfonate groups in poly(3,4-ethylenedioxythiophene)-polystyrene sulfonate and the -NH groups in waterborne polyurethane enhances water resistance (contact angle of 112°) and mechanical durability under repeated compression (20,000 cycles), while achieving an ultra-fast response time of 40 ms. The device exhibits high breathability (406 mm s−1) owing to its porous three-dimensional architecture. Additionally, it enables precise temperature sensing with a resolution of 0.05 K and a response time of 400 ms. Importantly, it successfully decouples temperature and strain signals in underwater environments. Leveraging its waterproof and signal-decoupling capabilities, we further demonstrate a fully integrated underwater monitoring and interaction system encompassing sensing hardware and decision-making logic. This work represents a significant advancement in wearable underwater electronics and offers another perspective for reliable, real-time human-machine interaction in aquatic settings. Multifunctional underwater sensors with integrated self-powered signal transmission, effective thermal-moisture regulation, and multi-signal decoupling are desirable of underwater tasks. Here, the authors report a three-dimensional thermoelectric device composed of porous polyurethane foam coated with a waterproof conductive layer for human-machine interaction in aquatic settings.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Fate of Pomeranchuk effect in ultrahigh magnetic fields</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67053-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67053-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 18:36:37 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Naofumi Matsuyama</dc:creator><dc:creator>So Yokomori</dc:creator><dc:creator>Toshihiro Nomura</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuto Ishii</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroaki Hayashi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hajime Ishikawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kazuki Matsui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hatsumi Mori</dc:creator><dc:creator>Koichi Kindo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yasuhiro H. Matsuda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shusaku Imajo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67053-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Pomeranchuk effect is a counterintuitive phenomenon where liquid helium-3 ( 3 He) solidifies under specific pressures, not when cooled, but when heated. This behaviour originates from the magnetic entropy of nuclear spins, suggesting a magnetic field should influence it. However, its detailed response to magnetic fields remains elusive due to the small nuclear magneton of 3 He and lack of analogous fermion systems. Here, we show that an electron system also exhibit the Pomeranchuk effect, where the Fermi liquid state solidifies in a high magnetic field, unlike conventional electron systems where a field melts an electron solid into a metal. Remarkably, the electron system displays a reentrant liquid state in ultrahigh fields. These responses are explained by changes in magnetic entropy and magnetisation, extending the underlying physics to 3 He. Our findings clarify magnetic-field impact on the Pomeranchuk effect and open avenues for magnetic control of chemical interactions.
Published: 2026-01-12T18:36:37+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.470 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Naofumi Matsuyama; So Yokomori; Toshihiro Nomura; Yuto Ishii; Hiroaki Hayashi; Hajime Ishikawa; Kazuki Matsui; Hatsumi Mori; Koichi Kindo; Yasuhiro H. Matsuda; Shusaku Imajo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67053-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67053-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.470 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Pomeranchuk effect is a counterintuitive phenomenon where liquid helium-3 ( 3 He) solidifies under specific pressures, not when cooled, but when heated. This behaviour originates from the magnetic entropy of nuclear spins, suggesting a magnetic field should influence it. However, its detailed response to magnetic fields remains elusive due to the small nuclear magneton of 3 He and lack of analogous fermion systems. Here, we show that an electron system also exhibit the Pomeranchuk effect, where the Fermi liquid state solidifies in a high magnetic field, unlike conventional electron systems where a field melts an electron solid into a metal. Remarkably, the electron system displays a reentrant liquid state in ultrahigh fields. These responses are explained by changes in magnetic entropy and magnetisation, extending the underlying physics to 3 He. Our findings clarify magnetic-field impact on the Pomeranchuk effect and open avenues for magnetic control of chemical interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Shock demagnetization in an ambient magnetic field at the Dhala impact structure, India</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03164-6</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03164-6</guid><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jan 2026 00:03:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ambrish Kumar Pandey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Amar Agarwal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gaurav Joshi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Satish Sangode</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mamilla Venkateshwarlu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03164-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract Impact-generated shock waves can modify the remanent magnetization preserved in target rocks, yet their effects remain poorly constrained. Here we examine how shock waves modify rock magnetization by analysing unshocked granitoids and diorites, and shock-affected monomict breccia and impact melt rock of the Paleoproterozoic Dhala impact structure in India. Microscopic, thermomagnetic and hysteresis analyses were used to identify magnetic minerals and their domain states. Remanent magnetization and demagnetization experiments were performed to evaluate shock effects on the palaeomagnetic behaviour of impact-generated and unshocked target rocks. The unshocked rocks contain strong and stable magnetization carried by titanomagnetite. In contrast, the monomict breccia carries titanomagnetite and titanohematite and shows extremely weak and unstable magnetization, consistent with shock-related grain-size reduction and microfracturing. Impact melt rocks display intermediate behaviour, with titanomagnetite, titanohematite and pyrrhotite as magnetic carriers. These results show that shock can substantially reduce crustal magnetization. The results help to explain weak magnetic signatures at terrestrial and planetary impact structures, even in the presence of an ambient magnetic field.
Published: 2026-01-11T00:03:55+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.470 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ambrish Kumar Pandey; Amar Agarwal; Gaurav Joshi; Satish Sangode; Mamilla Venkateshwarlu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03164-6"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03164-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.470 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Impact-generated shock waves can modify the remanent magnetization preserved in target rocks, yet their effects remain poorly constrained. Here we examine how shock waves modify rock magnetization by analysing unshocked granitoids and diorites, and shock-affected monomict breccia and impact melt rock of the Paleoproterozoic Dhala impact structure in India. Microscopic, thermomagnetic and hysteresis analyses were used to identify magnetic minerals and their domain states. Remanent magnetization and demagnetization experiments were performed to evaluate shock effects on the palaeomagnetic behaviour of impact-generated and unshocked target rocks. The unshocked rocks contain strong and stable magnetization carried by titanomagnetite. In contrast, the monomict breccia carries titanomagnetite and titanohematite and shows extremely weak and unstable magnetization, consistent with shock-related grain-size reduction and microfracturing. Impact melt rocks display intermediate behaviour, with titanomagnetite, titanohematite and pyrrhotite as magnetic carriers. These results show that shock can substantially reduce crustal magnetization. The results help to explain weak magnetic signatures at terrestrial and planetary impact structures, even in the presence of an ambient magnetic field.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Living sensor display implanted on skin for long-term biomarker monitoring</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67384-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67384-2</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:01:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jun Sawayama</dc:creator><dc:creator>Makoto Takeo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuki Takayama</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miki Takase</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hoshimi Aoyagi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aki Takimoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Saki Mizutani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maiko Onuki</dc:creator><dc:creator>Satoshi Ikeo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shogo Nagata</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miho Ogawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Koji Yano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takashi Tsuji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shoji Takeuchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroyuki Fujita</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67384-2</prism:doi><description>This study introduces an approach to biomarker monitoring through the development of a “Living Sensor Display” implanted on the skin, designed for long-term, continuous tracking of biomarkers, such as inflammatory cytokines. By leveraging the natural high selectivity and sensitivity of keratinocyte stem cells (KSCs) to environmental stimuli, we genetically engineered these cells to express fluorescent proteins in response to specific biomarker signals, specifically TNF-α signalling. This innovation allows for the real-time, non-invasive observation, with the only invasive step being the initial implantation, of biomarker levels directly from the skin surface. We constructed tissue-engineered skin with genetically modified KSCs and transplanted it onto mice, where it successfully engrafted long-term, matured to mimic human skin structures, and responsively indicated the presence of TNF-α through visible fluorescence. This living sensor could repeatedly detect inflammatory responses induced by TNF-α and lipopolysaccharides, highlighting its potential for monitoring various physiological and pathological processes over extended periods. This Living&amp;nbsp;sensor display holds promise for advancing health monitoring and disease prevention strategies by enabling continuous, sensitive, and specific in vivo biomarker tracking. Long-term, continuous tracking of biomarkers, such as inflammatory cytokines, is key for disease prevention. By leveraging the natural high selectivity and sensitivity of keratinocyte stem cells, the authors genetically engineered cells to express fluorescent proteins in response to specific biomarkers.
Published: 2026-01-12T10:01:58+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.469 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jun Sawayama; Makoto Takeo; Yuki Takayama; Miki Takase; Hoshimi Aoyagi; Aki Takimoto; Saki Mizutani; Maiko Onuki; Satoshi Ikeo; Shogo Nagata; Miho Ogawa; Koji Yano; Takashi Tsuji; Shoji Takeuchi; Hiroyuki Fujita&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67384-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67384-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.469 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study introduces an approach to biomarker monitoring through the development of a “Living Sensor Display” implanted on the skin, designed for long-term, continuous tracking of biomarkers, such as inflammatory cytokines. By leveraging the natural high selectivity and sensitivity of keratinocyte stem cells (KSCs) to environmental stimuli, we genetically engineered these cells to express fluorescent proteins in response to specific biomarker signals, specifically TNF-α signalling. This innovation allows for the real-time, non-invasive observation, with the only invasive step being the initial implantation, of biomarker levels directly from the skin surface. We constructed tissue-engineered skin with genetically modified KSCs and transplanted it onto mice, where it successfully engrafted long-term, matured to mimic human skin structures, and responsively indicated the presence of TNF-α through visible fluorescence. This living sensor could repeatedly detect inflammatory responses induced by TNF-α and lipopolysaccharides, highlighting its potential for monitoring various physiological and pathological processes over extended periods. This Living&amp;amp;nbsp;sensor display holds promise for advancing health monitoring and disease prevention strategies by enabling continuous, sensitive, and specific in vivo biomarker tracking. Long-term, continuous tracking of biomarkers, such as inflammatory cytokines, is key for disease prevention. By leveraging the natural high selectivity and sensitivity of keratinocyte stem cells, the authors genetically engineered cells to express fluorescent proteins in response to specific biomarkers.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A general one-step protocol to generate impermeable fluorescent HaloTag substrates for in situ live cell application and super-resolution imaging</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68134-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68134-0</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 04:15:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kilian Roßmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ulrich Pabst</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bianca C. Baciu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Siqi Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christiane Huhn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christina Holmboe Olesen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maria Kowald</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eleni Tapp</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marie Bieck</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ramona Birke</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brenda C. Shields</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pyeonghwa Jeong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiyong Hong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael R. Tadross</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joshua Levitz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin Lehmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Noa Lipstein</dc:creator><dc:creator>Johannes Broichhagen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68134-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract Visualization of proteins can be achieved by genetically grafting HaloTag Protein (HTP) into the protein of interest followed by incubation with a dye-linked HaloTag Ligand (HTL). This approach allows for use of fluorophores optimized for specific optical techniques or of cell-impermeable dyes to selectively label cell surface proteins. However, these two goals often conflict, as many high-performing dyes exhibit membrane permeability. Here we show that several dye-HTL reagents can be made cell-impermeable by inserting a charged sulfonate directly into the HTL, leaving the dye moiety unperturbed, using a one-step protocol. We validate such compounds, termed dye-SHTL (dye shuttle), in living cells, and demonstrate exclusive membrane staining. In transduced primary hippocampal neurons, we label a neuromodulatory receptor with dyes optimized for stimulated emission by depletion super-resolution microscopy, allowing accuracy in distinguishing surface versus internal receptors of the presynaptic terminal. This approach offers broad utility for surface-specific protein labelling.
Published: 2026-01-12T04:15:16+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.468 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kilian Roßmann; Ulrich Pabst; Bianca C. Baciu; Siqi Sun; Christiane Huhn; Christina Holmboe Olesen; Maria Kowald; Eleni Tapp; Marie Bieck; Ramona Birke; Brenda C. Shields; Pyeonghwa Jeong; Jiyong Hong; Michael R. Tadross; Joshua Levitz; Martin Lehmann; Noa Lipstein; Johannes Broichhagen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68134-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68134-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.468 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Visualization of proteins can be achieved by genetically grafting HaloTag Protein (HTP) into the protein of interest followed by incubation with a dye-linked HaloTag Ligand (HTL). This approach allows for use of fluorophores optimized for specific optical techniques or of cell-impermeable dyes to selectively label cell surface proteins. However, these two goals often conflict, as many high-performing dyes exhibit membrane permeability. Here we show that several dye-HTL reagents can be made cell-impermeable by inserting a charged sulfonate directly into the HTL, leaving the dye moiety unperturbed, using a one-step protocol. We validate such compounds, termed dye-SHTL (dye shuttle), in living cells, and demonstrate exclusive membrane staining. In transduced primary hippocampal neurons, we label a neuromodulatory receptor with dyes optimized for stimulated emission by depletion super-resolution microscopy, allowing accuracy in distinguishing surface versus internal receptors of the presynaptic terminal. This approach offers broad utility for surface-specific protein labelling.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Sequence-encoded layered heteroleptic metalla-[2]catenanes for programmable supramolecular function</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68348-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68348-w</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:56:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ya-Wen Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hai-Ning Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming-Xia Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying-Feng Han</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68348-w</prism:doi><description>Molecular information encoded within supramolecular frameworks offers a powerful paradigm for directing emergent function beyond the genetic code, but systematic investigations into alternative spatial configurations and their consequences remain scarce. Here we use metalla-[2]catenanes to probe sequence–function relationships in layered architectures. By combining two or three size-matched N-heterocyclic carbene ligands with Ag(I) nodes, we selectively construct heteroleptic metalla-[2]catenanes through both direct assembly and supramolecular fusion pathways. X-ray crystallographic analysis unambiguously confirms the targeted sequences, while semiempirical and density functional theory calculations reveal their thermodynamic preference over alternative isomers. Photothermal conversion studies further demonstrate that sequence-specific charge-transfer interactions yield distinct macroscopic responses. Collectively, these results identify heteroleptic metalla-[2]catenanes as a robust model for elucidating how spatial arrangement governs system-level behavior and for advancing molecular coding principles in functional supramolecular design. Molecular information encoded within supramolecular frameworks offers a powerful paradigm for directing emergent function beyond the genetic code, but systematic investigations into alternative spatial configurations and their consequences remain scarce. Here the authors use metalla-[2]catenanes to probe sequence–function relationships in layered architectures.
Published: 2026-01-12T09:56:44+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.467 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ya-Wen Zhang; Hai-Ning Zhang; Ming-Xia Wang; Xin Li; Ying-Feng Han&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68348-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68348-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.467 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molecular information encoded within supramolecular frameworks offers a powerful paradigm for directing emergent function beyond the genetic code, but systematic investigations into alternative spatial configurations and their consequences remain scarce. Here we use metalla-[2]catenanes to probe sequence–function relationships in layered architectures. By combining two or three size-matched N-heterocyclic carbene ligands with Ag(I) nodes, we selectively construct heteroleptic metalla-[2]catenanes through both direct assembly and supramolecular fusion pathways. X-ray crystallographic analysis unambiguously confirms the targeted sequences, while semiempirical and density functional theory calculations reveal their thermodynamic preference over alternative isomers. Photothermal conversion studies further demonstrate that sequence-specific charge-transfer interactions yield distinct macroscopic responses. Collectively, these results identify heteroleptic metalla-[2]catenanes as a robust model for elucidating how spatial arrangement governs system-level behavior and for advancing molecular coding principles in functional supramolecular design. Molecular information encoded within supramolecular frameworks offers a powerful paradigm for directing emergent function beyond the genetic code, but systematic investigations into alternative spatial configurations and their consequences remain scarce. Here the authors use metalla-[2]catenanes to probe sequence–function relationships in layered architectures.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Weakening mountain vegetation aspect asymmetry due to altered energy conditions</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02542-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41558-025-02542-4</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:02:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qing Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Tian</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Climate Change</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41558-025-02542-4</prism:doi><description>Topography in mountain areas redistributes the incoming solar radiation and determines water availability, creating microclimates and forming distinct habitat conditions within short distances. How this local topography modulates the impacts of climate change on the growth of vegetation on mountains at large scales remains unclear. Here we quantify the difference in vegetation density between polar-facing and equatorial-facing slopes (defined as aspect asymmetry) across the Northern Hemisphere and find a weakening trend of aspect asymmetry from 2003 to 2024. For regions that show higher vegetation density on the polar-facing slopes, the magnitude, area and seasonal duration of aspect asymmetry all decreased, implying a reduction in water control on vegetation growth. Further analyses show that the observed changes in vegetation aspect asymmetry are attributable to hydrothermal conditions, and are dominated by solar radiation and temperature in particular. Our findings highlight changes in an underexplored but important part of mountain ecosystems, with implications for ecological stability under climate change. The authors quantify long-term (2003–2024) changes in Northern Hemisphere mountain aspect asymmetry—the difference in vegetation density between polar-facing and equatorial-facing slopes. They show a weakening trend, linked to changing hydrothermal conditions.
Published: 2026-01-12T10:02:26+00:00
Venue: Nature Climate Change
Score: 0.467 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qing Tian; Feng Tian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Climate Change&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41558-025-02542-4"&gt;10.1038/s41558-025-02542-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.467 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topography in mountain areas redistributes the incoming solar radiation and determines water availability, creating microclimates and forming distinct habitat conditions within short distances. How this local topography modulates the impacts of climate change on the growth of vegetation on mountains at large scales remains unclear. Here we quantify the difference in vegetation density between polar-facing and equatorial-facing slopes (defined as aspect asymmetry) across the Northern Hemisphere and find a weakening trend of aspect asymmetry from 2003 to 2024. For regions that show higher vegetation density on the polar-facing slopes, the magnitude, area and seasonal duration of aspect asymmetry all decreased, implying a reduction in water control on vegetation growth. Further analyses show that the observed changes in vegetation aspect asymmetry are attributable to hydrothermal conditions, and are dominated by solar radiation and temperature in particular. Our findings highlight changes in an underexplored but important part of mountain ecosystems, with implications for ecological stability under climate change. The authors quantify long-term (2003–2024) changes in Northern Hemisphere mountain aspect asymmetry—the difference in vegetation density between polar-facing and equatorial-facing slopes. They show a weakening trend, linked to changing hydrothermal conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Scenario-based forecast of the evolution of 75 years of unrest at Campi Flegrei caldera (Italy)</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03140-0</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03140-0</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 10:02:11 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Luca Caricchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Charline Lormand</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stefano Carlino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tommaso Pivetta</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guy Simpson</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03140-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract Campi Flegrei last erupted in 1538 and periods of increased seismicity, gas emission and ground deformation occurred in the 50’s, 70’s 80’s and are ongoing since 2005. The eventual culmination of the unrest in an eruption, would directly impact on 2 million people living in the region, making it of critical concern for scientists, authorities and the public. Here, we use existing data, thermal modelling and calculations of the physical properties of magma, to provide plausible future scenarios, under the assumption that magma injection at 4-5 km depth is responsible for the unrest episodes recorded since 1950. Our calculations suggest that a critically pressurised reservoir containing potentially eruptible magma is present today at ~ 4 km depth. However, a major impediment to eruption is the reservoir volume, which would need 2-3 decades to grow to the size of the one that fed the last eruption of Campi Flegrei in 1538.
Published: 2026-01-12T10:02:11+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.458 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Luca Caricchi; Charline Lormand; Stefano Carlino; Tommaso Pivetta; Guy Simpson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03140-0"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03140-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.458 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Campi Flegrei last erupted in 1538 and periods of increased seismicity, gas emission and ground deformation occurred in the 50’s, 70’s 80’s and are ongoing since 2005. The eventual culmination of the unrest in an eruption, would directly impact on 2 million people living in the region, making it of critical concern for scientists, authorities and the public. Here, we use existing data, thermal modelling and calculations of the physical properties of magma, to provide plausible future scenarios, under the assumption that magma injection at 4-5 km depth is responsible for the unrest episodes recorded since 1950. Our calculations suggest that a critically pressurised reservoir containing potentially eruptible magma is present today at ~ 4 km depth. However, a major impediment to eruption is the reservoir volume, which would need 2-3 decades to grow to the size of the one that fed the last eruption of Campi Flegrei in 1538.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Reversible lipid-mediated pH-gating of connexin-46/50 by cryo-EM</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68311-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68311-9</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:43:24 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Joshua M. Jarodsky</dc:creator><dc:creator>Janette B. Myers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Steve L. Reichow</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68311-9</prism:doi><description>Gap junctions, formed by connexin proteins, establish direct electrical and metabolic coupling between cells, enabling coordinated tissue responses. These channels universally respond to intracellular pH changes, closing under acidic conditions to limit the spread of cytotoxic signals during cellular stress, such as ischemia. Using cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM), we uncover insights into the structural mechanism of pH-gating in native lens connexin-46/50 (Cx46/50) gap junctions. Mild acidification drives lipid infiltration into the channel pore, displacing the N-terminal (NT) domain and stabilizing pore closure. Lipid involvement is shown to be both essential and fully reversible. Structural transitions involve an ensemble of gated states formed through non-cooperative NT domain movement as well as minor populations of a distinct destabilized open-state. These findings provide molecular insights into pH-gating dynamics, illustrating how structural changes may regulate gap junction function under cellular stress and linking Cx46/50 dysregulation to age-related cataract formation. Gap junctions close in response to intracellular acidification. Using cryo-EM, the authors reveal a reversible gating mechanism in Cx46/50, where lipid entry into the pore displaces a gating helix and induces pH-dependent conformational closure.
Published: 2026-01-12T15:43:24+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.453 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Joshua M. Jarodsky; Janette B. Myers; Steve L. Reichow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68311-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68311-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.453 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gap junctions, formed by connexin proteins, establish direct electrical and metabolic coupling between cells, enabling coordinated tissue responses. These channels universally respond to intracellular pH changes, closing under acidic conditions to limit the spread of cytotoxic signals during cellular stress, such as ischemia. Using cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-EM), we uncover insights into the structural mechanism of pH-gating in native lens connexin-46/50 (Cx46/50) gap junctions. Mild acidification drives lipid infiltration into the channel pore, displacing the N-terminal (NT) domain and stabilizing pore closure. Lipid involvement is shown to be both essential and fully reversible. Structural transitions involve an ensemble of gated states formed through non-cooperative NT domain movement as well as minor populations of a distinct destabilized open-state. These findings provide molecular insights into pH-gating dynamics, illustrating how structural changes may regulate gap junction function under cellular stress and linking Cx46/50 dysregulation to age-related cataract formation. Gap junctions close in response to intracellular acidification. Using cryo-EM, the authors reveal a reversible gating mechanism in Cx46/50, where lipid entry into the pore displaces a gating helix and induces pH-dependent conformational closure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Desilylative allylation of 3,3-borylsilylpropene under metallaphotoredox catalysis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68269-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68269-0</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 16:30:35 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Longfei Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haojie Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Minglong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Renyi Diao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lifang Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi-Liang Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chao Feng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68269-0</prism:doi><description>Chemoselective functionalization of hetero-gem-dimetalloid represents an attractive strategy in terms of diversity-oriented synthesis. In particular, desilylative functionalization of gem-silylboronate esters remains a challenging task and existing solutions heavily relied on ionic reactions. Herein, we report a desilylative functionalization of allylic gem-silylboronate esters with aldehydes under synergistic photoredox and chromium(II) catalysis. With different substrates, both α- and γ-functionalization are realized with exclusive regioselectivity and diastereoselectivity, which is dictated by the chair-like transition state of predominant isomer of CrIII allyl intermediate. Moreover, γ-functionalization products bearing CF2 unit are acquired when gem-difluoroalkene-containing substrates are employed. In the presence of chiral ligand, enantioselective allylation of aldehydes is successfully accomplished, affording alkenylated 1,2-diols after oxidative workup with excellent regio-, diastereo- and enantioselectivity. The current protocol displays wide substrate generality and broad functional group compatibility. In addition, diverse post-transformations converted obtained products into a variety of valuable structures. Chemoselective functionalization of hetero-gem-dimetalloid represents an attractive strategy in terms of diversity-oriented synthesis. Here, the authors report a desilylative functionalization of allylic gem-silylboronate esters with aldehydes under synergistic photoredox and chromium(II) catalysis.
Published: 2026-01-12T16:30:35+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.440 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Longfei Liu; Haojie Li; Minglong Zhang; Renyi Diao; Lifang Tian; Chi Zhang; Yu Zhang; Zhi-Liang Shen; Kai Guo; Chao Feng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68269-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68269-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.440 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chemoselective functionalization of hetero-gem-dimetalloid represents an attractive strategy in terms of diversity-oriented synthesis. In particular, desilylative functionalization of gem-silylboronate esters remains a challenging task and existing solutions heavily relied on ionic reactions. Herein, we report a desilylative functionalization of allylic gem-silylboronate esters with aldehydes under synergistic photoredox and chromium(II) catalysis. With different substrates, both α- and γ-functionalization are realized with exclusive regioselectivity and diastereoselectivity, which is dictated by the chair-like transition state of predominant isomer of CrIII allyl intermediate. Moreover, γ-functionalization products bearing CF2 unit are acquired when gem-difluoroalkene-containing substrates are employed. In the presence of chiral ligand, enantioselective allylation of aldehydes is successfully accomplished, affording alkenylated 1,2-diols after oxidative workup with excellent regio-, diastereo- and enantioselectivity. The current protocol displays wide substrate generality and broad functional group compatibility. In addition, diverse post-transformations converted obtained products into a variety of valuable structures. Chemoselective functionalization of hetero-gem-dimetalloid represents an attractive strategy in terms of diversity-oriented synthesis. Here, the authors report a desilylative functionalization of allylic gem-silylboronate esters with aldehydes under synergistic photoredox and chromium(II) catalysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Featured Cover</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1111/jmg.70031</link><guid>10.1111/jmg.70031</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:11:13 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>T. Mackay‐Champion</dc:creator><dc:creator>I. P. Cawood</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Metamorphic Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1111/jmg.70031</prism:doi><description>The cover image is based on the article An Inverse Method for Quantifying Petrological Parameters and Uncertainty in Phase Equilibrium Modelling by Ian Cawood and T. Mackay-Champion, https://doi.org/...
Published: 2026-01-12T09:11:13+00:00
Venue: Journal of Metamorphic Geology
Score: 0.439 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; T. Mackay‐Champion; I. P. Cawood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Metamorphic Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/jmg.70031"&gt;10.1111/jmg.70031&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.439 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cover image is based on the article An Inverse Method for Quantifying Petrological Parameters and Uncertainty in Phase Equilibrium Modelling by Ian Cawood and T. Mackay-Champion, https://doi.org/...&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Less NO
                    &lt;sub&gt;x&lt;/sub&gt;
                    emission reductions are a potential cause for low effectiveness of sulfate aerosol reductions in China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2523101123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2523101123</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 20:02:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhe Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huan Xi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ningning Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengnan Cen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pengfei Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel Rosenfeld</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shaocai Yu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2523101123</prism:doi><description>Less NOx emission reductions are a potential cause for low effectiveness of sulfate aerosol reductions in China
Published: 2026-01-12T20:02:21+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.437 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhe Song; Huan Xi; Ningning Yao; Lang Chen; Zhengnan Cen; Pengfei Li; Daniel Rosenfeld; Shaocai Yu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2523101123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2523101123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.437 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less NOx emission reductions are a potential cause for low effectiveness of sulfate aerosol reductions in China&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hypoxia-driven remodeling of SELENOP+ macrophages shapes T cell dynamics and promotes ovarian cancer metastasis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67859-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67859-2</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 15:08:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qing Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenzhao Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tianhao Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Siyang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qian Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xueying Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuangyan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linru Quan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuli Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shimin Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bin Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jixin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuanzhang Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chaoyang Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Zhou</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67859-2</prism:doi><description>Abstract High-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSOC) is characterized by extensive transcoelomic dissemination and the accumulation of ascites. However, how site-specific tumor microenvironment (TME) drives progression remains unknown. Here we show the co-occurrence and spatial co-localization of SELENOP + macrophages and precursor exhausted CD8 + T cells and demonstrate that SELENOP + macrophages activate T cells via selenoprotein P in vitro and in vivo. We further identify a dynamic transition in the SELENOP + / SPP1 + macrophage populations as tumor metastasis, driven by increased hypoxia malignant epithelial cells through VEGFA-EPHB2 signaling. We also reveal that anti-VEGFA intervention controls ovarian tumor growth by increasing SELENOP + macrophages and cytotoxicity of CD8 + T cells in vivo. Taken together, these findings spotlight the role of tumor-induced TME remodeling in subverting immune-mediated tumor control and thus facilitating HGSOC metastasis in females. Collectively, our results provide a foundation for the development of targeted therapeutic interventions aimed at impeding HGSOC metastatic trajectory.
Published: 2026-01-12T15:08:49+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.436 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qing Liu; Chenzhao Feng; Tianhao Wu; Siyang Zhang; Xinyi Wang; Qian Zhao; Xueying Song; Shuangyan Liu; Linru Quan; Yuli Zhang; Shimin Zhang; Bin Yang; Jixin Li; Gang Chen; Xuanzhang Huang; Chaoyang Sun; Xin Zhou&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67859-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67859-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.436 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract High-grade serous ovarian cancer (HGSOC) is characterized by extensive transcoelomic dissemination and the accumulation of ascites. However, how site-specific tumor microenvironment (TME) drives progression remains unknown. Here we show the co-occurrence and spatial co-localization of SELENOP + macrophages and precursor exhausted CD8 + T cells and demonstrate that SELENOP + macrophages activate T cells via selenoprotein P in vitro and in vivo. We further identify a dynamic transition in the SELENOP + / SPP1 + macrophage populations as tumor metastasis, driven by increased hypoxia malignant epithelial cells through VEGFA-EPHB2 signaling. We also reveal that anti-VEGFA intervention controls ovarian tumor growth by increasing SELENOP + macrophages and cytotoxicity of CD8 + T cells in vivo. Taken together, these findings spotlight the role of tumor-induced TME remodeling in subverting immune-mediated tumor control and thus facilitating HGSOC metastasis in females. Collectively, our results provide a foundation for the development of targeted therapeutic interventions aimed at impeding HGSOC metastatic trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Reply to Song et al.: Acidity-sensitive chemistry promotes sulfate formation in East Asia</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2524655123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2524655123</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 20:02:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yu-Chi Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shohei Hattori</dc:creator><dc:creator>Syuichi Itahashi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan-Lin Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2524655123</prism:doi><description>We developed a strategy to identify gut bacteria functionally linked to the development of multiple sclerosis (MS). To minimize confounders, we analyzed microbiota composition in a large cohort of monozygotic twins discordant for MS and ... We developed a two-tiered strategy aiming to identify gut bacteria functionally linked to the development of multiple sclerosis (MS). First, we compared gut microbial profiles in a cohort of 81 monozygotic twins discordant for MS. This approach allowed to ...
Published: 2026-01-12T20:02:21+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.433 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yu-Chi Lin; Shohei Hattori; Syuichi Itahashi; Yan-Lin Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2524655123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2524655123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.433 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed a strategy to identify gut bacteria functionally linked to the development of multiple sclerosis (MS). To minimize confounders, we analyzed microbiota composition in a large cohort of monozygotic twins discordant for MS and ... We developed a two-tiered strategy aiming to identify gut bacteria functionally linked to the development of multiple sclerosis (MS). First, we compared gut microbial profiles in a cohort of 81 monozygotic twins discordant for MS. This approach allowed to ...&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Fresh starts: how to thrive when you leave academia</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00085-y</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-026-00085-y</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 09:02:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Josie Glausiusz</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-026-00085-y</prism:doi><description>Do your New Year resolutions include a plan to leave higher education? These researchers explain how to reinvent your career. Do your New Year resolutions include a plan to leave higher education? These researchers explain how to reinvent your career.
Published: 2026-01-12T09:02:19+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.431 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Josie Glausiusz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-026-00085-y"&gt;10.1038/d41586-026-00085-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.431 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do your New Year resolutions include a plan to leave higher education? These researchers explain how to reinvent your career. Do your New Year resolutions include a plan to leave higher education? These researchers explain how to reinvent your career.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>