<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 23:39:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Transformation of silica-rich to carbonated silicate melts in a big mantle wedge revealed by geochemistry of mantle xenoliths</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7</link><guid>10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:59:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pengtao Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunguang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenliang Xu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science China Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7</prism:doi><description>Carbonated silicate melts transport oxidized carbon from the deep to shallow mantle, and thus play an important role in the deep carbon cycle. However, it is unclear how carbonated silicate melts are formed. Here, we report whole-rock major and trace element, and Mg-Zn-Fe isotope, and in situ olivine and clinopyroxene Mg isotope data for peridotites and pyroxenites in Cenozoic alkaline basalts from Shulan and Yitong, Northeast China, to reveal the formation mechanisms of carbonated silicate melts. As residues of the primitive mantle, most of the Shulan and Yitong (spinel) harzburgite and lherzolite have relatively lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn than the mantle values, and show LREE-enriched patterns. These features indicate that these peridotites have been modified by carbonated silicate melt, transforming them into carbonated peridotites. The Shulan websterites exhibit metasomatic textures, and most of their whole-rock and in situ δ26Mg values are lower than the mantle values, which also supports the presence of a carbonated lithospheric mantle. The Yitong cumulate orthopyroxenites, representing silica-rich melts, have lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn values than mantle peridotites, implying that recycled carbonate has been involved in these silica-rich melts. The Yitong cumulate wehrlites and (olivine) websterites display major element compositions similar to those of carbonated peridotite melts, coupled with low whole-rock and clinopyroxene δ26Mg values, high δ66Zn and δ57Fe values, indicating the occurrence of carbonated silicate melts. The transition from orthopyroxenites to (olivine) websterites is marked by the decreasing of their whole-rock δ26Mg, δ57Fe values and Zn/Fe ratios and increasing of their δ66Zn values, along with decreasing of their crystallization temperatures, suggesting that silica-rich melts were gradually transformed into carbonated silicate melts via continuous interaction with carbonated peridotite. Our findings demonstrate that silica-rich melts from the stagnant slab can extract carbon from pre-existing carbonated mantle within the big mantle wedge.
Published: 2026-01-28T05:59:09+00:00
Venue: Science China Earth Sciences
Score: 0.679 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pengtao Xu; Jie Tang; Feng Wang; Chunguang Wang; Wenliang Xu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science China Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7"&gt;10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.679 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbonated silicate melts transport oxidized carbon from the deep to shallow mantle, and thus play an important role in the deep carbon cycle. However, it is unclear how carbonated silicate melts are formed. Here, we report whole-rock major and trace element, and Mg-Zn-Fe isotope, and in situ olivine and clinopyroxene Mg isotope data for peridotites and pyroxenites in Cenozoic alkaline basalts from Shulan and Yitong, Northeast China, to reveal the formation mechanisms of carbonated silicate melts. As residues of the primitive mantle, most of the Shulan and Yitong (spinel) harzburgite and lherzolite have relatively lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn than the mantle values, and show LREE-enriched patterns. These features indicate that these peridotites have been modified by carbonated silicate melt, transforming them into carbonated peridotites. The Shulan websterites exhibit metasomatic textures, and most of their whole-rock and in situ δ26Mg values are lower than the mantle values, which also supports the presence of a carbonated lithospheric mantle. The Yitong cumulate orthopyroxenites, representing silica-rich melts, have lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn values than mantle peridotites, implying that recycled carbonate has been involved in these silica-rich melts. The Yitong cumulate wehrlites and (olivine) websterites display major element compositions similar to those of carbonated peridotite melts, coupled with low whole-rock and clinopyroxene δ26Mg values, high δ66Zn and δ57Fe values, indicating the occurrence of carbonated silicate melts. The transition from orthopyroxenites to (olivine) websterites is marked by the decreasing of their whole-rock δ26Mg, δ57Fe values and Zn/Fe ratios and increasing of their δ66Zn values, along with decreasing of their crystallization temperatures, suggesting that silica-rich melts were gradually transformed into carbonated silicate melts via continuous interaction with carbonated peridotite. Our findings demonstrate that silica-rich melts from the stagnant slab can extract carbon from pre-existing carbonated mantle within the big mantle wedge.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Formation of giant carbonatite rare earth deposits controlled by deep-seated magma chambers</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68785-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68785-7</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 15:36:29 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shuo Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wubin Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hecai Niu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongping He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianxi Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoliang Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weidong Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming-Xing Ling</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xing Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wanzhu Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68785-7</prism:doi><description>Carbonatite-associated rare earth element (REE) deposits are currently the primary source of REE resources. Their formation requires REE enrichment during prolonged magma evolution, achieved by suppressing REE-rich mineral crystallization and promoting REE-enriched brine melt formation. Our experiments on the fractional crystallization of carbonatitic magmas indicate that pressure (emplacement depth) is the primary factor controlling REE enrichment. High-pressure ( &amp;gt;0.3 GPa) promotes early olivine crystallization, depleting silica and suppressing REE-rich apatite formation. Deep emplacement also delays aqueous fluid exsolution, thereby stabilizing brine melts that enhance phosphate dissolution and prevent REE dispersion into apatite. In contrast, low-pressure conditions ( &amp;lt;0.3 GPa) lead to exsolution of REE-poor hydrothermal fluids, dispersing REE into magmatic apatite and preventing the deposition of economically significant REE-carbonates in subsequent hydrothermal stages. Our pressure-dependent model highlights deep emplacement as crucial for passive REE enrichment in residual brine melts, driving large-scale mineralization through precipitation of burbankite and/or bastnäsite. Pressure or emplacement depth exerts crucial control on REE enrichment in carbonatites. Deep emplacement ( &amp;gt; 0.3 GPa) suppresses REE dispersion into apatite, enabling enrichment in residual brine melts and precipitation of economic REE-carbonates.
Published: 2026-02-02T15:36:29+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.666 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shuo Xue; Wubin Yang; Hecai Niu; Hongping He; Jianxi Zhu; Xiaoliang Liang; Weidong Sun; Ming-Xing Ling; Xing Ding; Wanzhu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68785-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68785-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.666 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbonatite-associated rare earth element (REE) deposits are currently the primary source of REE resources. Their formation requires REE enrichment during prolonged magma evolution, achieved by suppressing REE-rich mineral crystallization and promoting REE-enriched brine melt formation. Our experiments on the fractional crystallization of carbonatitic magmas indicate that pressure (emplacement depth) is the primary factor controlling REE enrichment. High-pressure ( &amp;amp;gt;0.3 GPa) promotes early olivine crystallization, depleting silica and suppressing REE-rich apatite formation. Deep emplacement also delays aqueous fluid exsolution, thereby stabilizing brine melts that enhance phosphate dissolution and prevent REE dispersion into apatite. In contrast, low-pressure conditions ( &amp;amp;lt;0.3 GPa) lead to exsolution of REE-poor hydrothermal fluids, dispersing REE into magmatic apatite and preventing the deposition of economically significant REE-carbonates in subsequent hydrothermal stages. Our pressure-dependent model highlights deep emplacement as crucial for passive REE enrichment in residual brine melts, driving large-scale mineralization through precipitation of burbankite and/or bastnäsite. Pressure or emplacement depth exerts crucial control on REE enrichment in carbonatites. Deep emplacement ( &amp;amp;gt; 0.3 GPa) suppresses REE dispersion into apatite, enabling enrichment in residual brine melts and precipitation of economic REE-carbonates.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Reworking of continental crust, deep geological processes and large-scale W-Sn-Au-Cu mineralization in the Nanling-Wuyi metallogenic belts, South China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1771-8</link><guid>10.1007/s11430-025-1771-8</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 05:28:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pei Ni</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoguang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junyi Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wensheng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhe Chi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science China Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s11430-025-1771-8</prism:doi><description>The Nanling-Wuyi regions in South China collectively form a globally significant metallogenic province hosting a group of world-class W-Sn-Au-Cu ore deposits. The mineralization in Nanling and Wuyi regions exhibits typical zonation characteristics: the former is distinguished by extensive multi-episodes of granite emplacement and associated W-Sn mineralization; the latter is characterized by intense Yanshanian volcanic activities along continental margins and associated Au-Cu mineralization. The Nanling region has experienced multiple intensive tecto-magmatic movements, including the Caledonian, Indosinian, and Yanshanian periods. Its predominant W-Sn mineralization occurred during the Yanshanian period, governed by the combined effects of crustal reworking and a high degree of magmatic differentiation. In contrast, the Wuyi metallogenic belt experienced Mesozoic volcanic activities predominantly during the Middle-Late Jurassic, Early Cretaceous, and early Late Cretaceous periods. The Yanshanian Au-Cu mineralization in this belt results from the remobilization of ancient Au-Cu enriched crustal sources triggered by paleo-Pacific plate subduction. The distinct deep geological processes in the Nanling and Wuyi regions have fundamentally shaped their characteristic ore-related igneous rocks and mineralization types.
Published: 2026-01-30T05:28:14+00:00
Venue: Science China Earth Sciences
Score: 0.652 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pei Ni; Guoguang Wang; Junyi Pan; Wensheng Li; Zhe Chi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science China Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1771-8"&gt;10.1007/s11430-025-1771-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.652 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Nanling-Wuyi regions in South China collectively form a globally significant metallogenic province hosting a group of world-class W-Sn-Au-Cu ore deposits. The mineralization in Nanling and Wuyi regions exhibits typical zonation characteristics: the former is distinguished by extensive multi-episodes of granite emplacement and associated W-Sn mineralization; the latter is characterized by intense Yanshanian volcanic activities along continental margins and associated Au-Cu mineralization. The Nanling region has experienced multiple intensive tecto-magmatic movements, including the Caledonian, Indosinian, and Yanshanian periods. Its predominant W-Sn mineralization occurred during the Yanshanian period, governed by the combined effects of crustal reworking and a high degree of magmatic differentiation. In contrast, the Wuyi metallogenic belt experienced Mesozoic volcanic activities predominantly during the Middle-Late Jurassic, Early Cretaceous, and early Late Cretaceous periods. The Yanshanian Au-Cu mineralization in this belt results from the remobilization of ancient Au-Cu enriched crustal sources triggered by paleo-Pacific plate subduction. The distinct deep geological processes in the Nanling and Wuyi regions have fundamentally shaped their characteristic ore-related igneous rocks and mineralization types.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Copper and molybdenum isotope signatures along a vertical section through the Valeriano epithermal-porphyry Cu-Au system, El Indio-Maricunga belt, northern Chile</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00126-025-01414-3</link><guid>10.1007/s00126-025-01414-3</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 00:28:38 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Stephanie Lohmeier</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bernd Lehmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrew Hodgkin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jan Pašava</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lukáš Ackerman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ondřej Šebek</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexandre Andronikov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Albrecht Schneider</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Mineralium Deposita</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00126-025-01414-3</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Valeriano composite epithermal-porphyry Cu‒Au system in the El Indio-Maricunga metallogenic belt, Vicuña segment, consists of a shallow silicic lithocap with low-grade Au‒Ag ± Cu mineralization underlain by a large porphyry-Cu (± Mo, ± Au) deposit. A deep drillhole (VALD-D13-14) allows the systematic evaluation of bulk-rock Cu‒Mo isotope compositions over a vertical extent of ~ 1,900 m through the hydrothermal porphyry-epithermal system. Copper isotope values in the lower 1,000 m of the mineralized potassic and phyllic altered porphyry zone increase slightly upwards in the range of +0.2 to +0.4‰, and scatter in the upper phyllic and advanced argillic zone (δ 65 Cu: ‒3.7‰ to +2.7‰). The near-surface low-Cu leached zone has very negative δ 65 Cu values down to ‒6.5‰ and there are also some distinctly negative excursions in the deep potassic zone with subordinate advanced argillic alteration. Molybdenum isotope values are slightly negative in the potassic porphyry zone (δ 98 Mo: ‒0.3 to ‒0.2‰), but increase over the phyllic zone to positive values of 0.2‒0.3‰, and strongly scatter at the transition to the high-sulfidation epithermal system. The Cu and Mo isotope patterns can be mainly attributed to Rayleigh fractionation between vapor and brine in the magmatic-hydrothermal porphyry system and to redox-controlled isotope shifts during supergene alteration in the epithermal system. Deviations from the general trend in some deep drillcore intercepts relate to short intervals of advanced argillic alteration and corresponding redox fluctuations with Cu enrichment.
Published: 2026-02-03T00:28:38+00:00
Venue: Mineralium Deposita
Score: 0.621 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Stephanie Lohmeier; Bernd Lehmann; Andrew Hodgkin; Jan Pašava; Lukáš Ackerman; Ondřej Šebek; Alexandre Andronikov; Albrecht Schneider&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Mineralium Deposita&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00126-025-01414-3"&gt;10.1007/s00126-025-01414-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.621 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Valeriano composite epithermal-porphyry Cu‒Au system in the El Indio-Maricunga metallogenic belt, Vicuña segment, consists of a shallow silicic lithocap with low-grade Au‒Ag ± Cu mineralization underlain by a large porphyry-Cu (± Mo, ± Au) deposit. A deep drillhole (VALD-D13-14) allows the systematic evaluation of bulk-rock Cu‒Mo isotope compositions over a vertical extent of ~ 1,900 m through the hydrothermal porphyry-epithermal system. Copper isotope values in the lower 1,000 m of the mineralized potassic and phyllic altered porphyry zone increase slightly upwards in the range of +0.2 to +0.4‰, and scatter in the upper phyllic and advanced argillic zone (δ 65 Cu: ‒3.7‰ to +2.7‰). The near-surface low-Cu leached zone has very negative δ 65 Cu values down to ‒6.5‰ and there are also some distinctly negative excursions in the deep potassic zone with subordinate advanced argillic alteration. Molybdenum isotope values are slightly negative in the potassic porphyry zone (δ 98 Mo: ‒0.3 to ‒0.2‰), but increase over the phyllic zone to positive values of 0.2‒0.3‰, and strongly scatter at the transition to the high-sulfidation epithermal system. The Cu and Mo isotope patterns can be mainly attributed to Rayleigh fractionation between vapor and brine in the magmatic-hydrothermal porphyry system and to redox-controlled isotope shifts during supergene alteration in the epithermal system. Deviations from the general trend in some deep drillcore intercepts relate to short intervals of advanced argillic alteration and corresponding redox fluctuations with Cu enrichment.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Extremely light Mo isotope compositions of the lower continental crust caused by fluid leaching</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123267</link><guid>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123267</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 16:44:12 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ying Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao-Long Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanjun Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Chemical Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123267</prism:doi><description>Mantle-crust differentiation and crustal material cycling are fundamental processes in Earth's evolution. Molybdenum (Mo) isotopes provide new constraints due to their fractionation between the upper continental crust and the mantle. However, data on Mo isotope compositions from the lower continental crust, an important intermediary layer, remain scarce, hindering the effective utilization of Mo isotopes in understanding continental crust formation and evolution. This study investigates the Mo isotope compositions of mafic granulite and websterite xenoliths derived from Mesozoic basalts in the western Cathaysia Block to directly constrain the mechanisms underlying Mo isotope variations in the juvenile lower continental crust. Xenoliths with high Mo concentrations show mantle-like δ 98/95 Mo (−0.18 ‰), whereas those with low Mo concentrations display significant variation in δ 98/95 Mo values (−1.94 ‰ to 0.55 ‰). This significant variation cannot be fully explained by mantle heterogeneity, as supported by Sr Nd isotopes with limited variability and low Nb/Zr, (La/Sm) N , and Th/Yb ratios. The lack of covariance between δ 98/95 Mo and differentiation index Mg# argues against magmatic differentiation governing Mo isotopic fractionation. Most samples show a sharp decline in δ 98/95 Mo values with decreasing Mo/Ce ratios, far below mantle values, suggesting that fluid leaching is responsible for the observed Mo isotope fractionation. Based on newly obtained Mo isotope data for these Mesozoic xenoliths, the juvenile lower crust beneath the Cathaysia Block is enriched in extremely light Mo isotopes compared to the mantle. It is proposed that widely distributed fluids in the crust may be an important reservoir for balancing Earth's Mo isotope system. In this context, molybdenum isotope fingerprinting of fluid activities constitutes a significant approach for investigating crustal differentiation.
Published: 2026-01-29T16:44:12+00:00
Venue: Chemical Geology
Score: 0.621 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ying Wei; Xiao-Long Huang; Yanjun Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Chemical Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123267"&gt;10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123267&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.621 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mantle-crust differentiation and crustal material cycling are fundamental processes in Earth&amp;#x27;s evolution. Molybdenum (Mo) isotopes provide new constraints due to their fractionation between the upper continental crust and the mantle. However, data on Mo isotope compositions from the lower continental crust, an important intermediary layer, remain scarce, hindering the effective utilization of Mo isotopes in understanding continental crust formation and evolution. This study investigates the Mo isotope compositions of mafic granulite and websterite xenoliths derived from Mesozoic basalts in the western Cathaysia Block to directly constrain the mechanisms underlying Mo isotope variations in the juvenile lower continental crust. Xenoliths with high Mo concentrations show mantle-like δ 98/95 Mo (−0.18 ‰), whereas those with low Mo concentrations display significant variation in δ 98/95 Mo values (−1.94 ‰ to 0.55 ‰). This significant variation cannot be fully explained by mantle heterogeneity, as supported by Sr Nd isotopes with limited variability and low Nb/Zr, (La/Sm) N , and Th/Yb ratios. The lack of covariance between δ 98/95 Mo and differentiation index Mg# argues against magmatic differentiation governing Mo isotopic fractionation. Most samples show a sharp decline in δ 98/95 Mo values with decreasing Mo/Ce ratios, far below mantle values, suggesting that fluid leaching is responsible for the observed Mo isotope fractionation. Based on newly obtained Mo isotope data for these Mesozoic xenoliths, the juvenile lower crust beneath the Cathaysia Block is enriched in extremely light Mo isotopes compared to the mantle. It is proposed that widely distributed fluids in the crust may be an important reservoir for balancing Earth&amp;#x27;s Mo isotope system. In this context, molybdenum isotope fingerprinting of fluid activities constitutes a significant approach for investigating crustal differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Eccentricity rhythms in the Oligocene-Miocene carbon cycle regulated by weathering and carbonate burial</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx6682</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adx6682</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 18:58:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Fenghao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Enqing Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinlong Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wentao Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhonghui Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lucas J. Lourens</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Tian</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adx6682</prism:doi><description>During the Cenozoic unipolar ice ages, benthic foraminiferal oxygen and carbon isotopes (proxies for bottom-water temperature and ice volume and for the carbon cycle, respectively) exhibited in-phase changes on eccentricity timescales. However, the mechanisms underlying this synchronized relationship remain unclear. Here, we present a high-resolution reconstruction of Miocene benthic foraminiferal boron-to-calcium ratios, revealing that eccentricity-paced fluctuations in deep-sea carbonate ion saturation covaried with oxygen and carbon isotopes, as well as with pelagic carbonate deposition. Integrating model results, we propose that orbital configurations and elevated temperatures during eccentricity maxima intensified monsoon rainfall and chemical weathering, enhancing the transport of dissolved inorganic carbon and alkalinity from land to sea. These processes further redistributed massive carbonate burial from deep-ocean basins to continental shelves, lowering carbonate ion concentration and the carbon isotopic composition of seawater. Our findings underscore the crucial role of the low-latitude hydrological cycle in regulating carbon-cycle dynamics under warm climatic conditions.
Published: 2026-01-30T18:58:16+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.620 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Fenghao Liu; Enqing Huang; Jinlong Du; Wentao Ma; Zhonghui Liu; Lucas J. Lourens; Jun Tian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adx6682"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adx6682&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.620 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Cenozoic unipolar ice ages, benthic foraminiferal oxygen and carbon isotopes (proxies for bottom-water temperature and ice volume and for the carbon cycle, respectively) exhibited in-phase changes on eccentricity timescales. However, the mechanisms underlying this synchronized relationship remain unclear. Here, we present a high-resolution reconstruction of Miocene benthic foraminiferal boron-to-calcium ratios, revealing that eccentricity-paced fluctuations in deep-sea carbonate ion saturation covaried with oxygen and carbon isotopes, as well as with pelagic carbonate deposition. Integrating model results, we propose that orbital configurations and elevated temperatures during eccentricity maxima intensified monsoon rainfall and chemical weathering, enhancing the transport of dissolved inorganic carbon and alkalinity from land to sea. These processes further redistributed massive carbonate burial from deep-ocean basins to continental shelves, lowering carbonate ion concentration and the carbon isotopic composition of seawater. Our findings underscore the crucial role of the low-latitude hydrological cycle in regulating carbon-cycle dynamics under warm climatic conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Large-scale slab dynamics as drivers of seismicity: Modeling earthquakes in the izu-bonin-mariana subduction zones</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119878</link><guid>10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119878</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 14:27:08 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yida Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Neil M. Ribe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhe Jia</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119878</prism:doi><description>Subduction zones host the majority of global earthquakes, ranging from shallow megathrust and outer-rise earthquakes to deep intraplate seismicity. Although it is well-established that subducting slabs supply the primary energy driving most earthquakes, the quantitative relationship between slab dynamics and seismic events remains poorly understood. Here we develop a comprehensive 3D geodynamic model of the Izu-Bonin-Mariana subduction system to quantitatively connect long-term slab dynamics with earthquake activity. Based on an analytical thermal model combined with slab geometry, we find that earthquakes predominantly occur under conditions cooler than ∼ 900 ∘ C, defining a thermal boundary for the seismogenic zone. Within this zone, we identify a notable spatial correlation between the modeled energy dissipation rate and the observed distribution of seismicity, indicating that seismicity is intrinsically driven by long-term tectonic deformation. Furthermore, our comparison of the modeled stress state predictions with observed earthquake focal mechanisms reveals that both shallow megathrust and outer-rise earthquakes, as well as deep earthquakes associated with plate bending at the mantle transition zone, can be explained by slab dynamics. By analyzing the misfit between modeled and observed focal mechanisms, we further constrain slab rheology, finding that shallow earthquakes favor a relatively weak slab (yield stress of 100 – 150MPa), while deep earthquakes prefer a stronger slab (300 - 500MPa) accompanied by a 10 – 100–fold viscosity increase at the 660 km phase transition. Taken together, our results underscore the profound link between earthquake occurrence and the large-scale, long-term dynamics of mantle flow and subduction.
Published: 2026-01-29T14:27:08+00:00
Venue: Earth and Planetary Science Letters
Score: 0.620 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yida Li; Neil M. Ribe; Zhe Jia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Earth and Planetary Science Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119878"&gt;10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119878&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.620 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subduction zones host the majority of global earthquakes, ranging from shallow megathrust and outer-rise earthquakes to deep intraplate seismicity. Although it is well-established that subducting slabs supply the primary energy driving most earthquakes, the quantitative relationship between slab dynamics and seismic events remains poorly understood. Here we develop a comprehensive 3D geodynamic model of the Izu-Bonin-Mariana subduction system to quantitatively connect long-term slab dynamics with earthquake activity. Based on an analytical thermal model combined with slab geometry, we find that earthquakes predominantly occur under conditions cooler than ∼ 900 ∘ C, defining a thermal boundary for the seismogenic zone. Within this zone, we identify a notable spatial correlation between the modeled energy dissipation rate and the observed distribution of seismicity, indicating that seismicity is intrinsically driven by long-term tectonic deformation. Furthermore, our comparison of the modeled stress state predictions with observed earthquake focal mechanisms reveals that both shallow megathrust and outer-rise earthquakes, as well as deep earthquakes associated with plate bending at the mantle transition zone, can be explained by slab dynamics. By analyzing the misfit between modeled and observed focal mechanisms, we further constrain slab rheology, finding that shallow earthquakes favor a relatively weak slab (yield stress of 100 – 150MPa), while deep earthquakes prefer a stronger slab (300 - 500MPa) accompanied by a 10 – 100–fold viscosity increase at the 660 km phase transition. Taken together, our results underscore the profound link between earthquake occurrence and the large-scale, long-term dynamics of mantle flow and subduction.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hydraulic fracturing-induced gold remobilization: Pyrite geochemical and sulfur isotopic insights from the Liuan lode gold deposit, South China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gexplo.2026.107994</link><guid>10.1016/j.gexplo.2026.107994</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 15:42:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zebin Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongjun Shao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bing Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuling Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xingting Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongtao Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lianjie Zhao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geochemical Exploration</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.gexplo.2026.107994</prism:doi><description>The coupled dissolution-reprecipitation (CDR) process is critical for gold remobilization and re-enrichment within global gold mineralization systems, and its driving mechanism warrants further investigation. The Liuan lode gold deposit in the Dayaoshan district (South China) features multiple generations of pyrite, including Py1 (pre-ore stage), Py2 (including Py2c and Py2r) and Py3 (ore stage), and Py4 (post-ore stage). Py2c is As-Cu-Pb-Ag-Au-rich (initial gold enrichment), suggestive of fluid boiling during its formation, corroborated by low δ 34 S values (avg. −3.83‰) and hydrothermal breccias. In contrast, Py2r is depleted in these elements, indicative of non-boiling conditions, further supported by heavier δ 34 S values (avg. −2.53‰). Several pieces of evidence, including sharp reaction fronts and As-Au contents differences between Py2c and Py3, and Py2c remnants and mineral inclusions (chalcopyrite, galena, and native gold) within Py3, indicate the CDR process, during which Au in Py2c was remobilized and reprecipitated as native gold. The CDR process is triggered by oxidation of the mineralizing fluids, consistent with the decreasing δ 34 S values from Py2r to Py3. Combined with higher Co-Ni concentrations in Py3 (similar to Py2c) relative to Py2r, we infer that fluid oxidation is associated with hydraulic fracturing restart. Multiple sulfur isotopes (δ 34 S: −4.92 to 0.45‰; Δ 33 S: −0.05 ± 0.10‰) and low Co-Ni and high Se contents of pyrite suggest a magmatic fluid origin from a possible concealed intrusion. This study underscores magmatic-hydrothermal contributions in forming lode gold deposits in Dayaoshan, and highlights the importance of pressure-driven hydrothermal processes in initial gold precipitation, remobilization, and reprecipitation within gold deposits.
Published: 2026-01-29T15:42:33+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geochemical Exploration
Score: 0.604 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xu Wang; Yu Zhang; Zebin Tang; Yongjun Shao; Bing Xiao; Shuling Song; Xingting Sun; Hongtao Zhao; Lianjie Zhao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geochemical Exploration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gexplo.2026.107994"&gt;10.1016/j.gexplo.2026.107994&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.604 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coupled dissolution-reprecipitation (CDR) process is critical for gold remobilization and re-enrichment within global gold mineralization systems, and its driving mechanism warrants further investigation. The Liuan lode gold deposit in the Dayaoshan district (South China) features multiple generations of pyrite, including Py1 (pre-ore stage), Py2 (including Py2c and Py2r) and Py3 (ore stage), and Py4 (post-ore stage). Py2c is As-Cu-Pb-Ag-Au-rich (initial gold enrichment), suggestive of fluid boiling during its formation, corroborated by low δ 34 S values (avg. −3.83‰) and hydrothermal breccias. In contrast, Py2r is depleted in these elements, indicative of non-boiling conditions, further supported by heavier δ 34 S values (avg. −2.53‰). Several pieces of evidence, including sharp reaction fronts and As-Au contents differences between Py2c and Py3, and Py2c remnants and mineral inclusions (chalcopyrite, galena, and native gold) within Py3, indicate the CDR process, during which Au in Py2c was remobilized and reprecipitated as native gold. The CDR process is triggered by oxidation of the mineralizing fluids, consistent with the decreasing δ 34 S values from Py2r to Py3. Combined with higher Co-Ni concentrations in Py3 (similar to Py2c) relative to Py2r, we infer that fluid oxidation is associated with hydraulic fracturing restart. Multiple sulfur isotopes (δ 34 S: −4.92 to 0.45‰; Δ 33 S: −0.05 ± 0.10‰) and low Co-Ni and high Se contents of pyrite suggest a magmatic fluid origin from a possible concealed intrusion. This study underscores magmatic-hydrothermal contributions in forming lode gold deposits in Dayaoshan, and highlights the importance of pressure-driven hydrothermal processes in initial gold precipitation, remobilization, and reprecipitation within gold deposits.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Prolonged cooling and degassing of Apollo 17 volcanic glasses on the lunar surface</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-69087-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-69087-8</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 06:54:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Peng Ni</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Zhan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-69087-8</prism:doi><description>Abstract Studying lunar pyroclastic volcanism provides key insights into the thermo-chemical evolution of the lunar mantle and the Moon’s volatile budget. Pyroclastic deposits, although volumetrically minor compared to mare basalts, are derived from deeper, more primitive, and volatile-rich mantle sources. Here we synthesize volatile degassing recorded by Apollo 17 sample 74220, one of most studied pyroclastic deposits. By modeling the volatile degassing of olivine-hosted melt inclusions, melt embayments, and glass beads, we show that volatile depletion of these samples cannot be explained solely by degassing during free-flight, as previously proposed. Instead, the data require extended thermal histories, with beads undergoing slow cooling and prolonged degassing on the lunar surface for years, a scenario further supported by thermal modeling. Our findings suggest that pyroclastic deposits remained active volatile sources well beyond eruption, which is potentially important for sustaining a local transient lunar atmosphere and the long-term volatile cycle of the Moon.
Published: 2026-02-03T06:54:45+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.600 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Peng Ni; Yan Zhan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-69087-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-69087-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.600 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Studying lunar pyroclastic volcanism provides key insights into the thermo-chemical evolution of the lunar mantle and the Moon’s volatile budget. Pyroclastic deposits, although volumetrically minor compared to mare basalts, are derived from deeper, more primitive, and volatile-rich mantle sources. Here we synthesize volatile degassing recorded by Apollo 17 sample 74220, one of most studied pyroclastic deposits. By modeling the volatile degassing of olivine-hosted melt inclusions, melt embayments, and glass beads, we show that volatile depletion of these samples cannot be explained solely by degassing during free-flight, as previously proposed. Instead, the data require extended thermal histories, with beads undergoing slow cooling and prolonged degassing on the lunar surface for years, a scenario further supported by thermal modeling. Our findings suggest that pyroclastic deposits remained active volatile sources well beyond eruption, which is potentially important for sustaining a local transient lunar atmosphere and the long-term volatile cycle of the Moon.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Two episodes of ultrahigh-temperature metamorphism within one orogenic cycle</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119887</link><guid>10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119887</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 23:18:00 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jie Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunjing Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuguang Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guochun Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guibin Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Earth and Planetary Science Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119887</prism:doi><description>Ultrahigh-temperature metamorphism (UHTM) is significant for constraining the thermal-mechanical evolution of continental crust, which can periodically occur within one orogenic cycle involving subduction, collision and subsequent extension stages. However, multi-episode UHTM within one orogenic cycle has been rarely reported. Here, we performed a comprehensive investigation of petrography, phase equilibria modelling, and zircon U-Pb dating for felsic and Mg-Fe-Al granulites from the Kunlun-Qaidam Massif in north Qingzang Plateau. Three episodes of metamorphism were inferred, involving two episodes of low pressure (LP)-UHTM intervened by an episode of medium-pressure and high-temperature (MP-HT) metamorphism. The first episode LP-UHTM (I) exhibits peak P–T conditions of 0.5–0.8 GPa/930–1050 °C, occurring at &gt;460 Ma. The second episode MP-HT metamorphism (II) was achieved by compressional cooling from the LP-UHT conditions to MP-HT conditions of &gt;0.9–1.2 GPa/ 410 Ma. Combining our metamorphic studies and other geological data, a three-stage tectonic model is proposed: (a) oceanic slab rollback inducing an arc-backarc extension and the LP-UHTM (I) during the late-stage subduction of the Proto-Tethys Ocean; (b) continental subduction-collision leading to the thickening of hot arc-backarc crust and the MP-HT metamorphism (II) after the closure of the Proto-Tethys Ocean, and (c) post-collisional crustal thinning and mantle upwelling related to lithosphere delamination resulting in the LP-UHTM (III). It is for the first time that we recognize two episodes of LP-UHTM occurring within &lt; 50 Myr in one orogenic cycle.
Published: 2026-01-28T23:18:00+00:00
Venue: Earth and Planetary Science Letters
Score: 0.597 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jie Dong; Chunjing Wei; Shuguang Song; Guochun Zhao; Guibin Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Earth and Planetary Science Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119887"&gt;10.1016/j.epsl.2026.119887&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.597 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultrahigh-temperature metamorphism (UHTM) is significant for constraining the thermal-mechanical evolution of continental crust, which can periodically occur within one orogenic cycle involving subduction, collision and subsequent extension stages. However, multi-episode UHTM within one orogenic cycle has been rarely reported. Here, we performed a comprehensive investigation of petrography, phase equilibria modelling, and zircon U-Pb dating for felsic and Mg-Fe-Al granulites from the Kunlun-Qaidam Massif in north Qingzang Plateau. Three episodes of metamorphism were inferred, involving two episodes of low pressure (LP)-UHTM intervened by an episode of medium-pressure and high-temperature (MP-HT) metamorphism. The first episode LP-UHTM (I) exhibits peak P–T conditions of 0.5–0.8 GPa/930–1050 °C, occurring at &amp;gt;460 Ma. The second episode MP-HT metamorphism (II) was achieved by compressional cooling from the LP-UHT conditions to MP-HT conditions of &amp;gt;0.9–1.2 GPa/ 410 Ma. Combining our metamorphic studies and other geological data, a three-stage tectonic model is proposed: (a) oceanic slab rollback inducing an arc-backarc extension and the LP-UHTM (I) during the late-stage subduction of the Proto-Tethys Ocean; (b) continental subduction-collision leading to the thickening of hot arc-backarc crust and the MP-HT metamorphism (II) after the closure of the Proto-Tethys Ocean, and (c) post-collisional crustal thinning and mantle upwelling related to lithosphere delamination resulting in the LP-UHTM (III). It is for the first time that we recognize two episodes of LP-UHTM occurring within &amp;lt; 50 Myr in one orogenic cycle.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Rhodope Metamorphic Complex as a case for extreme vertical extrusion</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/g53889.1</link><guid>10.1130/g53889.1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:17:46 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Iskander A. Muldashev</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thorsten J. Nagel</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/g53889.1</prism:doi><description>We explore the fate of subducted continental margins using thermomechanical modeling with constant-force boundary conditions. Under certain conditions, large volumes of upper crust can get subducted to mantle depth, detach from the slab, and rise through the upper plate’s lithosphere even against considerable compressive tectonic stress. At the surface, such an event is expressed as a phase of intense horizontal extension and magmatism internal of the oceanic suture zone. The process can create normal-fault-bounded core complexes hundreds of kilometers wide, in which metamorphic continental crust derived from the subducting plate is exposed. Horizontal tectonic stress and the thickness of the downgoing upper crust control the width of complexes, their topographic elevation, and the subduction depth of exposed rocks. We propose that the Rhodope Metamorphic Complex on the Balkan Peninsula represents a prime example for such vertical extrusion internal of a suture zone. Lower tectonic units in this domain exhibit Eocene high-pressure metamorphism and nappe stacking followed by massive magmatism and large-offset normal faulting. Despite more than 100 km of extension in Cenozoic times, the area still has thick crust. Our modeling results support schemes that attribute the lower units of the Rhodope Metamorphic Complex to the subducted Adriatic plate.
Published: 2026-01-28T20:17:46+00:00
Venue: Geology
Score: 0.592 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Iskander A. Muldashev; Thorsten J. Nagel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/g53889.1"&gt;10.1130/g53889.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.592 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explore the fate of subducted continental margins using thermomechanical modeling with constant-force boundary conditions. Under certain conditions, large volumes of upper crust can get subducted to mantle depth, detach from the slab, and rise through the upper plate’s lithosphere even against considerable compressive tectonic stress. At the surface, such an event is expressed as a phase of intense horizontal extension and magmatism internal of the oceanic suture zone. The process can create normal-fault-bounded core complexes hundreds of kilometers wide, in which metamorphic continental crust derived from the subducting plate is exposed. Horizontal tectonic stress and the thickness of the downgoing upper crust control the width of complexes, their topographic elevation, and the subduction depth of exposed rocks. We propose that the Rhodope Metamorphic Complex on the Balkan Peninsula represents a prime example for such vertical extrusion internal of a suture zone. Lower tectonic units in this domain exhibit Eocene high-pressure metamorphism and nappe stacking followed by massive magmatism and large-offset normal faulting. Despite more than 100 km of extension in Cenozoic times, the area still has thick crust. Our modeling results support schemes that attribute the lower units of the Rhodope Metamorphic Complex to the subducted Adriatic plate.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Metal transport by magmatic volatile phases in crustal systems</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/g54065.1</link><guid>10.1130/g54065.1</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 22:20:43 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Austin M. Gion</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fabrice Gaillard</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/g54065.1</prism:doi><description>Magmatic volatile phases (MVPs) are multicomponent fluids that are a transport medium for metals being transferred from deep magmatic sources to sites of ore formation. However, the melt-to-fluid exchange of metals remains elusive because existing empirical simulations primarily address metal transport through the fate of one chemical element. We use a comprehensive thermochemical model to simulate the fractional crystallization of a silicate melt that degasses a multicomponent MVP. We show that the major and trace element abundances in MVPs formed from non-enriched magmatic systems are indistinguishable from MVPs found as fluid inclusions in mineralized and non-mineralized systems. We therefore conclude that ore formation is the consequence of repetitive intrusion-fractionation-degassing cycles common to crustal systems without pre-enriched sources, as opposed to scenarios wherein a particular or complex chemical system is required. Instead, the driving force of ore formation is a long-lived system fueled by an H2O- and Cl-bearing melt. Variations in metal signatures of fluids therefore reflect the pressure-temperature path of melt ascent and the changes in major element composition of the melt.
Published: 2026-02-02T22:20:43+00:00
Venue: Geology
Score: 0.588 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Austin M. Gion; Fabrice Gaillard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/g54065.1"&gt;10.1130/g54065.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.588 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magmatic volatile phases (MVPs) are multicomponent fluids that are a transport medium for metals being transferred from deep magmatic sources to sites of ore formation. However, the melt-to-fluid exchange of metals remains elusive because existing empirical simulations primarily address metal transport through the fate of one chemical element. We use a comprehensive thermochemical model to simulate the fractional crystallization of a silicate melt that degasses a multicomponent MVP. We show that the major and trace element abundances in MVPs formed from non-enriched magmatic systems are indistinguishable from MVPs found as fluid inclusions in mineralized and non-mineralized systems. We therefore conclude that ore formation is the consequence of repetitive intrusion-fractionation-degassing cycles common to crustal systems without pre-enriched sources, as opposed to scenarios wherein a particular or complex chemical system is required. Instead, the driving force of ore formation is a long-lived system fueled by an H2O- and Cl-bearing melt. Variations in metal signatures of fluids therefore reflect the pressure-temperature path of melt ascent and the changes in major element composition of the melt.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Coupled anatexis and extreme differentiation are the keys for producing giant lithium-rich pegmatites</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2517372123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2517372123</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:09:01 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hai-Zhen Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin R. Palmer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiqin Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenbin Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xi-Sheng Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anthony Williams-Jones</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bi-Hai Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian-Guo Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qin Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hefeng Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Da-Sheng Zuo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2517372123</prism:doi><description>Despite the economic importance of lithium, there is considerable disagreement over the processes that concentrate it and other rare metals in pegmatite-type lithium deposits. Two main processes have been invoked, namely extreme differentiation of a peraluminous granitic magma and direct anatexis of a sedimentary protolith. We use geochemical modeling to quantify lithium enrichment via these two processes from a study of the Jiajika lithium pegmatite field, one of the largest of its type in the world. Based on a lithium–silicon–boron–barium (Li-Si-B-Ba) isotope study involving systematic sampling along 4,211-m of core from two deep boreholes and from the regional zonation of pegmatites at outcrops, we propose a three-stage model for the formation of the pegmatite field: i) generation of a rare metal-rich melt by deep anatexis, involving ~5% partial melting of metapelitic rocks in the presence of 10 to 30% metamorphic fluid; ii) gradual enrichment of rare metals along a path of continuous magma differentiation until 75% of the initial melt had crystallized; and iii) a final stage of lithium mineralization during the escape of the water-rich magma due to the overpressures created in response to massive fluid exsolution and the extensional stress in the granite dome structure. The study provides important insights into how lithium-rich pegmatites can be targeted during exploration for pegmatite-hosted resources of lithium.
Published: 2026-02-03T19:09:01+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.586 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hai-Zhen Wei; Martin R. Palmer; Zhiqin Xu; Wenbin Zhu; Xi-Sheng Xu; Anthony Williams-Jones; Bi-Hai Zheng; Jian-Guo Gao; Qin Wang; Jing Ma; Ke Yang; Hefeng Lin; Da-Sheng Zuo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2517372123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2517372123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.586 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the economic importance of lithium, there is considerable disagreement over the processes that concentrate it and other rare metals in pegmatite-type lithium deposits. Two main processes have been invoked, namely extreme differentiation of a peraluminous granitic magma and direct anatexis of a sedimentary protolith. We use geochemical modeling to quantify lithium enrichment via these two processes from a study of the Jiajika lithium pegmatite field, one of the largest of its type in the world. Based on a lithium–silicon–boron–barium (Li-Si-B-Ba) isotope study involving systematic sampling along 4,211-m of core from two deep boreholes and from the regional zonation of pegmatites at outcrops, we propose a three-stage model for the formation of the pegmatite field: i) generation of a rare metal-rich melt by deep anatexis, involving ~5% partial melting of metapelitic rocks in the presence of 10 to 30% metamorphic fluid; ii) gradual enrichment of rare metals along a path of continuous magma differentiation until 75% of the initial melt had crystallized; and iii) a final stage of lithium mineralization during the escape of the water-rich magma due to the overpressures created in response to massive fluid exsolution and the extensional stress in the granite dome structure. The study provides important insights into how lithium-rich pegmatites can be targeted during exploration for pegmatite-hosted resources of lithium.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Reactivation of basement faults by deep fluids during the 2017 Changdao earthquake swarm, Eastern China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03228-1</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03228-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:57:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Peng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Baoshan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhigang Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinglin Lei</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03228-1</prism:doi><description>Ancient basement faults within plate interiors may be reactivated by external forces, generating intraplate seismicity. However, the driving mechanisms remain unclear. The 2017 Changdao earthquake swarm in the Bohai Bay Basin, eastern China, provides an opportunity to investigate such processes. A high-resolution earthquake catalog, constructed using matched filter detection and waveform-based relocation, reveals that the swarm occurred at 7-13 km depth along an X-shaped fault network, with migration following sqrt(t) diffusion (D = 0.08 – 1.2 m² s-1). High b-values and external forcing rate, and substantial isotropic components (13-38%) in the moment tensors indicate fluid involvement. Combined with low VP/VS ratios and proximity to CO2-rich hydrocarbon fields, we propose a fault-valve model where highly compressible fluids episodically breach fault intersections, triggering transient crack opening and swarm migration. This study reveals how deep fluids reactivate ancient basement faults in intraplate regions, and provides new insights for seismic hazard assessment in hydrocarbon-bearing basins. A distinctive migration pattern consistent with fluid pressure diffusion is identified within a high-resolution earthquake catalogue of the 2017 Changdao swarm and suggests a fault-valve mechanism driven by overpressure CO2-rich fluids was responsible.
Published: 2026-01-28T11:57:50+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.586 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Peng Wang; Baoshan Wang; Zhigang Peng; Xinglin Lei&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03228-1"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03228-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.586 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ancient basement faults within plate interiors may be reactivated by external forces, generating intraplate seismicity. However, the driving mechanisms remain unclear. The 2017 Changdao earthquake swarm in the Bohai Bay Basin, eastern China, provides an opportunity to investigate such processes. A high-resolution earthquake catalog, constructed using matched filter detection and waveform-based relocation, reveals that the swarm occurred at 7-13 km depth along an X-shaped fault network, with migration following sqrt(t) diffusion (D = 0.08 – 1.2 m² s-1). High b-values and external forcing rate, and substantial isotropic components (13-38%) in the moment tensors indicate fluid involvement. Combined with low VP/VS ratios and proximity to CO2-rich hydrocarbon fields, we propose a fault-valve model where highly compressible fluids episodically breach fault intersections, triggering transient crack opening and swarm migration. This study reveals how deep fluids reactivate ancient basement faults in intraplate regions, and provides new insights for seismic hazard assessment in hydrocarbon-bearing basins. A distinctive migration pattern consistent with fluid pressure diffusion is identified within a high-resolution earthquake catalogue of the 2017 Changdao swarm and suggests a fault-valve mechanism driven by overpressure CO2-rich fluids was responsible.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mineralization processes for sphalerite in MVT deposits: Insights from the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang ore field, Guizhou, Southwest China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-125</link><guid>10.1144/jgs2025-125</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:01:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Weijun He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Youguo Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sigen Ma</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of the Geological Society</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1144/jgs2025-125</prism:doi><description>Although Mississippi Valley-type (MVT) deposit mineralization processes are well characterized, the associated ore-forming fluids, which are crucial to understanding Pb and Zn mineralization, should be investigated further. With more than 0.7 million tonnes (Mt) of Zn reserves at average grades ranging from 4–8%, the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field comprises representative deposits such as those of Caiyuanhe, Heli, and Qingshuitang. The ore bodies, which exhibit stratiform, vein-like, and lenticular forms, are hosted within the Cambrian Qingxudong Formation dolomite and are spatially associated with the NE-trending Mandong fault. This Zn ore field in Southwest China is a classic example of Zn-rich mineralization. However, the genetic mechanisms and processes responsible for the Zn-rich nature of these MVT Pb‒Zn deposits remain poorly understood. This study aims to characterize Zn mineralization in the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field, Southwest China. The rare earth elements (REE) concentrations in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol2) from the syn-ore stage vary between 5.63 and 32.50 ppm (with an average of 14.07 ppm), whereas in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol3) from post-ore stage, the values range from 45.63 to 95.69 ppm (with an average of 72.03 ppm). The fluid inclusions of Dol2 and Dol3 exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 98–204°C (with an average of 143°C) and 98–195°C (with an average of 132°C), with corresponding salinity ranges of 13.0–29.5 wt% (with an average of 20.9 wt%) and 16.0–25.7 wt% (with an average of 18.9 wt%) NaCl equivalent, respectively. Sphalerite inclusions exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 95–230°C (with a mean of 143°C) and salinities ranging from 13.8–28.9 wt% (with a mean of 23.7 wt%) NaCl. The δ 13 C fluid , δ D fluid , and δ 18 O fluid values of the ore-forming fluids range from -4.4‰ to -3.8‰ (with a mean of -4.1‰), -36.4‰ to -27.8‰ (with a mean of -31.9‰), and 4.9‰ to 5.7‰ (with a mean of 5.3‰), respectively. In this study, an Fe- and Zn-enriched NaCl-H₂O basement brine is identified as the ore-forming fluid responsible for the Zn-rich MVT deposits. During its low- to medium-temperature migration, the fluid was channelled by the Mandong fault and Wangsi anticline structural framework, which provided ideal pathways and traps. During migration, the fluid leached sulfur (reduced from evaporites to H 2 S) from wall rocks and ultimately precipitated within dolomite faults and fractures. The distinct Zn-rich character of the deposits stems from the following two key factors: a primary derivation from the Zn-rich basement of the Yangtze Block and a chemical preference for Zn enrichment, which is driven by the differing fractionation coefficients of Zn- and Pb-chloride complexes in the NaCl–H 2 O system. This study advances the understanding of the genesis of MVT deposits worldwide.
Published: 2026-01-28T11:01:17+00:00
Venue: Journal of the Geological Society
Score: 0.586 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Weijun He; Youguo Li; Sigen Ma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of the Geological Society&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-125"&gt;10.1144/jgs2025-125&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.586 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Mississippi Valley-type (MVT) deposit mineralization processes are well characterized, the associated ore-forming fluids, which are crucial to understanding Pb and Zn mineralization, should be investigated further. With more than 0.7 million tonnes (Mt) of Zn reserves at average grades ranging from 4–8%, the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field comprises representative deposits such as those of Caiyuanhe, Heli, and Qingshuitang. The ore bodies, which exhibit stratiform, vein-like, and lenticular forms, are hosted within the Cambrian Qingxudong Formation dolomite and are spatially associated with the NE-trending Mandong fault. This Zn ore field in Southwest China is a classic example of Zn-rich mineralization. However, the genetic mechanisms and processes responsible for the Zn-rich nature of these MVT Pb‒Zn deposits remain poorly understood. This study aims to characterize Zn mineralization in the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field, Southwest China. The rare earth elements (REE) concentrations in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol2) from the syn-ore stage vary between 5.63 and 32.50 ppm (with an average of 14.07 ppm), whereas in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol3) from post-ore stage, the values range from 45.63 to 95.69 ppm (with an average of 72.03 ppm). The fluid inclusions of Dol2 and Dol3 exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 98–204°C (with an average of 143°C) and 98–195°C (with an average of 132°C), with corresponding salinity ranges of 13.0–29.5 wt% (with an average of 20.9 wt%) and 16.0–25.7 wt% (with an average of 18.9 wt%) NaCl equivalent, respectively. Sphalerite inclusions exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 95–230°C (with a mean of 143°C) and salinities ranging from 13.8–28.9 wt% (with a mean of 23.7 wt%) NaCl. The δ 13 C fluid , δ D fluid , and δ 18 O fluid values of the ore-forming fluids range from -4.4‰ to -3.8‰ (with a mean of -4.1‰), -36.4‰ to -27.8‰ (with a mean of -31.9‰), and 4.9‰ to 5.7‰ (with a mean of 5.3‰), respectively. In this study, an Fe- and Zn-enriched NaCl-H₂O basement brine is identified as the ore-forming fluid responsible for the Zn-rich MVT deposits. During its low- to medium-temperature migration, the fluid was channelled by the Mandong fault and Wangsi anticline structural framework, which provided ideal pathways and traps. During migration, the fluid leached sulfur (reduced from evaporites to H 2 S) from wall rocks and ultimately precipitated within dolomite faults and fractures. The distinct Zn-rich character of the deposits stems from the following two key factors: a primary derivation from the Zn-rich basement of the Yangtze Block and a chemical preference for Zn enrichment, which is driven by the differing fractionation coefficients of Zn- and Pb-chloride complexes in the NaCl–H 2 O system. This study advances the understanding of the genesis of MVT deposits worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Physicochemical controls on ancient carbon assimilation into ecosystem biomass in shallow-water hydrothermal systems</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03254-z</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03254-z</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 04:46:18 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Joely Marie Maak</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marcus Elvert</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hendrik Grotheer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu-Shih Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gesine Mollenhauer</dc:creator><dc:creator>In-Tian Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Solveig I. Bühring</dc:creator><dc:creator>Enno Schefuß</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03254-z</prism:doi><description>Abstract Hydrothermal vents release substantial amounts of ancient carbon into the ocean, primarily as carbon dioxide, yet the extent to which this carbon is integrated into marine food webs remains poorly constrained. Here, we present a combination of bulk radiocarbon and stable carbon isotope measurements of particulate organic carbon from water column filters with compound-specific hydrogen and radiocarbon isotope analyses of fatty acids from surface sediments to trace carbon assimilation across benthic and pelagic realms in a low pH, shallow-water hydrothermal system off Taiwan. Isotope correlations indicate that vent-derived carbon dioxide constitutes a substantial fraction of the local microbial and faunal biomass through chemoautotrophic pathways (up to ~30%). Farther from the vents, hydrothermal carbon remains detectable and is incorporated into photoautotrophic biomass in the overlying water column. Notably, ancient carbon content in the standing stock of particulate organic carbon was higher at the lower temperature (“White”) vent, even though fluid and sulfide emissions – and thus potential energy availability – were substantially greater at the higher temperature (“Yellow”) vent. These findings show that physicochemical conditions, including pH and temperature, rather than fluid chemistry alone, control carbon assimilation patterns and ultimately limit the retention of vent-derived carbon in this shallow-water system.
Published: 2026-02-02T04:46:18+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.579 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Joely Marie Maak; Marcus Elvert; Hendrik Grotheer; Yu-Shih Lin; Gesine Mollenhauer; In-Tian Lin; Solveig I. Bühring; Enno Schefuß&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03254-z"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03254-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.579 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Hydrothermal vents release substantial amounts of ancient carbon into the ocean, primarily as carbon dioxide, yet the extent to which this carbon is integrated into marine food webs remains poorly constrained. Here, we present a combination of bulk radiocarbon and stable carbon isotope measurements of particulate organic carbon from water column filters with compound-specific hydrogen and radiocarbon isotope analyses of fatty acids from surface sediments to trace carbon assimilation across benthic and pelagic realms in a low pH, shallow-water hydrothermal system off Taiwan. Isotope correlations indicate that vent-derived carbon dioxide constitutes a substantial fraction of the local microbial and faunal biomass through chemoautotrophic pathways (up to ~30%). Farther from the vents, hydrothermal carbon remains detectable and is incorporated into photoautotrophic biomass in the overlying water column. Notably, ancient carbon content in the standing stock of particulate organic carbon was higher at the lower temperature (“White”) vent, even though fluid and sulfide emissions – and thus potential energy availability – were substantially greater at the higher temperature (“Yellow”) vent. These findings show that physicochemical conditions, including pH and temperature, rather than fluid chemistry alone, control carbon assimilation patterns and ultimately limit the retention of vent-derived carbon in this shallow-water system.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Author Correction: Evidence for oxygen-conserving diamond formation in redox-buffered subducted oceanic crust sampled as eclogite</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-69139-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-69139-z</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 10:32:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Sonja Aulbach</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Stachel</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-69139-z</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-29567-z , published online 8 April 2022
Published: 2026-02-02T10:32:23+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.577 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sonja Aulbach; Thomas Stachel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-69139-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-69139-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.577 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-29567-z , published online 8 April 2022&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seismic and mineralogical evidence for an iron-rich mega–ultralow-velocity zone beneath Hawai’i</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz1962</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adz1962</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 18:59:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Doyeon Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jung-Hun Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vasilije V. Dobrosavljevic</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vedran Lekić</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adz1962</prism:doi><description>Mantle plumes beneath major oceanic hot spots appear to be rooted in unusually large structures near the core-mantle boundary, which have markedly reduced seismic wave speeds. The origin of these large ultralow-velocity zones (ULVZs), referred to as mega-ULVZs, remains uncertain partly because of lack of constraints on the relative reduction in shear versus compressional wave speeds ( R S/P ). This ratio can give clues into the compositional makeup of the mega-ULVZs. Through joint seismic analysis of core-diffracted P and S waves beneath Hawai’i, we constrain the R S/P of its mega-ULVZ to 1 to 1.3. Mineralogical modeling reveals that iron enrichment via solid iron-rich magnesiowüstite [(Mg,Fe)O] matches this seismic constraint, independent of modeled ULVZ thickness. Enrichment of metallic iron-rich magnesiowüstite likely enhances the thermal conductivity of mega-ULVZs and provides a mechanism to drive localized plume upwelling. Higher reported R S/P values for smaller ULVZs near subduction zones may therefore indicate different processes at play controlling ULVZ formation across the diverse core-mantle boundary landscape.
Published: 2026-01-28T18:59:52+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.577 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Doyeon Kim; Jung-Hun Song; Vasilije V. Dobrosavljevic; Vedran Lekić&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz1962"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adz1962&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.577 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mantle plumes beneath major oceanic hot spots appear to be rooted in unusually large structures near the core-mantle boundary, which have markedly reduced seismic wave speeds. The origin of these large ultralow-velocity zones (ULVZs), referred to as mega-ULVZs, remains uncertain partly because of lack of constraints on the relative reduction in shear versus compressional wave speeds ( R S/P ). This ratio can give clues into the compositional makeup of the mega-ULVZs. Through joint seismic analysis of core-diffracted P and S waves beneath Hawai’i, we constrain the R S/P of its mega-ULVZ to 1 to 1.3. Mineralogical modeling reveals that iron enrichment via solid iron-rich magnesiowüstite [(Mg,Fe)O] matches this seismic constraint, independent of modeled ULVZ thickness. Enrichment of metallic iron-rich magnesiowüstite likely enhances the thermal conductivity of mega-ULVZs and provides a mechanism to drive localized plume upwelling. Higher reported R S/P values for smaller ULVZs near subduction zones may therefore indicate different processes at play controlling ULVZ formation across the diverse core-mantle boundary landscape.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ultradeep drilling beyond 10 km revealing new insights into Earth systems and resources</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03246-z</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03246-z</guid><pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 13:56:54 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Guangyou Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haiping Huang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03246-z</prism:doi><description>Ultradeep drilling beyond nine to ten kilometers has progressed from an engineering challenge to a powerful approach for investigating deep Earth processes and subsurface resources. Early continental drilling showed that the deep crust is not cold or impermeable, but contains fluids, active heat flow, and ongoing chemical reactions. This review presents an integrated synthesis of scientific results from drilling that exceeds ten kilometers, with emphasis on recent Chinese programs. These wells document methane-rich fluids, high pressures, and high temperatures in sedimentary and crystalline rocks, indicating that hydrocarbon systems, deep fluids, and permeability persist far deeper than traditionally assumed. Integrating observations from cores, formation fluids, stress measurements, and geochemical analyses, we show that revised geothermal gradients, fault-controlled fluid pathways, and fluid–rock reactions such as serpentinization, carbonation, and hydrocarbon cracking sustain permeability at extreme depths. Ultradeep drilling thus provides insights into Earth system dynamics, deep energy resources, carbon storage, and mineral systems. Hydrocarbons can persist and migrate far deeper than previously assumed and may coexist with natural hydrogen, geothermal fluids, and metal-rich brines, according to a synthesis of geochemical and petrophysical drilling data beyond 10 km from China’s recent programs.
Published: 2026-02-03T13:56:54+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.576 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Guangyou Zhu; Haiping Huang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03246-z"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03246-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.576 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultradeep drilling beyond nine to ten kilometers has progressed from an engineering challenge to a powerful approach for investigating deep Earth processes and subsurface resources. Early continental drilling showed that the deep crust is not cold or impermeable, but contains fluids, active heat flow, and ongoing chemical reactions. This review presents an integrated synthesis of scientific results from drilling that exceeds ten kilometers, with emphasis on recent Chinese programs. These wells document methane-rich fluids, high pressures, and high temperatures in sedimentary and crystalline rocks, indicating that hydrocarbon systems, deep fluids, and permeability persist far deeper than traditionally assumed. Integrating observations from cores, formation fluids, stress measurements, and geochemical analyses, we show that revised geothermal gradients, fault-controlled fluid pathways, and fluid–rock reactions such as serpentinization, carbonation, and hydrocarbon cracking sustain permeability at extreme depths. Ultradeep drilling thus provides insights into Earth system dynamics, deep energy resources, carbon storage, and mineral systems. Hydrocarbons can persist and migrate far deeper than previously assumed and may coexist with natural hydrogen, geothermal fluids, and metal-rich brines, according to a synthesis of geochemical and petrophysical drilling data beyond 10 km from China’s recent programs.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Petrogenesis of mid-Neoproterozoic low-δ
                    &lt;sup&gt;18&lt;/sup&gt;
                    O and high Ba-Sr granitoids in the western margin of the South China Block</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-191</link><guid>10.1144/jgs2025-191</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 08:59:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Suheng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengqi Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peng Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Minghui Yin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Youliang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of the Geological Society</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1144/jgs2025-191</prism:doi><description>Middle Neoproterozoic granitoids from the western margin of the Yangtze Block provide critical insights into crust-mantle interaction and crustal growth processes of the South China Block during Rodinia supercontinental cycles. Zircon U-Pb dating reveals that the Datian diorite and granite were emplaced contemporaneously at ca. 760–770 Ma. The Datian diorites exhibit variable SiO 2 (56.60–67.03%), high Mg # (49.32–55.18), medium Na 2 O+K 2 O (5.02–6.46), A/CNK (1.02–1.16) shows aluminum, and high Cr and Ni concentrations, while the granites show high SiO 2 (70.91–80.73%) and low MgO (0.11–0.67%), Na 2 O+K 2 O (4.72–8.52) shows a subalkaline series, A/CNK (0.86–1.22) indicates metaluminous to peraluminous. Both the diorite and granite are enriched in LILEs but depleted in HFSEs, resembling that of typical arc affinities. The diorites display moderate positive ε Hf (t) (+2.3 to +6.6) and mantle-like δ 18 O (4.95–6.30 ‰), while the granites exhibit similar ε Hf (t) compositions (+1.83 to +7.15) but low- δ 18 O (0.59–5.90‰) values. More importantly, the diorites display high Ba-Sr (Ba + Sr = 898 – 1720 ppm) signatures and characterized by amphibole-rich lithologies. These geochemical and isotopic signatures suggest that the parental magmas of the diorites were most likely generated by partial melting of the mantle wedge metasomatized by the subducted oceanic slab during the early stage, and subsequently the high Ba-Sr melts differentiate to generate the Datian diorite in a continental arc setting. The low- δ ¹⁸O granites were formed through partial melting of juvenile lower gabbroic crust that had been interpointed by high-temperature hydrothermal alteration. The high Ba-Sr granitoids share geochemical affinity with Archean sanukitoids, forming via amphibole-dominated fractional crystallization of fluid-metasomatized mantle. The development of mid-Neoproterozoic continental arcs along the margin of the Yangtze Block suggests that South China occupied a peripheral location in Rodinia.
Published: 2026-01-29T08:59:16+00:00
Venue: Journal of the Geological Society
Score: 0.575 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Suheng Zhang; Zhengqi Xu; Peng Wu; Minghui Yin; Hao Song; Youliang Chen; Wei Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of the Geological Society&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-191"&gt;10.1144/jgs2025-191&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.575 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Middle Neoproterozoic granitoids from the western margin of the Yangtze Block provide critical insights into crust-mantle interaction and crustal growth processes of the South China Block during Rodinia supercontinental cycles. Zircon U-Pb dating reveals that the Datian diorite and granite were emplaced contemporaneously at ca. 760–770 Ma. The Datian diorites exhibit variable SiO 2 (56.60–67.03%), high Mg # (49.32–55.18), medium Na 2 O+K 2 O (5.02–6.46), A/CNK (1.02–1.16) shows aluminum, and high Cr and Ni concentrations, while the granites show high SiO 2 (70.91–80.73%) and low MgO (0.11–0.67%), Na 2 O+K 2 O (4.72–8.52) shows a subalkaline series, A/CNK (0.86–1.22) indicates metaluminous to peraluminous. Both the diorite and granite are enriched in LILEs but depleted in HFSEs, resembling that of typical arc affinities. The diorites display moderate positive ε Hf (t) (+2.3 to +6.6) and mantle-like δ 18 O (4.95–6.30 ‰), while the granites exhibit similar ε Hf (t) compositions (+1.83 to +7.15) but low- δ 18 O (0.59–5.90‰) values. More importantly, the diorites display high Ba-Sr (Ba + Sr = 898 – 1720 ppm) signatures and characterized by amphibole-rich lithologies. These geochemical and isotopic signatures suggest that the parental magmas of the diorites were most likely generated by partial melting of the mantle wedge metasomatized by the subducted oceanic slab during the early stage, and subsequently the high Ba-Sr melts differentiate to generate the Datian diorite in a continental arc setting. The low- δ ¹⁸O granites were formed through partial melting of juvenile lower gabbroic crust that had been interpointed by high-temperature hydrothermal alteration. The high Ba-Sr granitoids share geochemical affinity with Archean sanukitoids, forming via amphibole-dominated fractional crystallization of fluid-metasomatized mantle. The development of mid-Neoproterozoic continental arcs along the margin of the Yangtze Block suggests that South China occupied a peripheral location in Rodinia.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Establishment and development of mantle geochemistry</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1820-6</link><guid>10.1007/s11430-025-1820-6</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 09:32:25 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lihui Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoyu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian Zhao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science China Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s11430-025-1820-6</prism:doi><description>Mantle geochemistry, a field that emerged in the mid-1970s, utilizes geochemical approaches to investigate the chemical composition and structure as well as the evolution and dynamics of Earth’s mantle. Since its establishment, this field has become a key part of solid Earth Science and Planetary Science, demonstrating great vitality. The development of its theoretical framework began with the observation of mantle heterogeneity revealed by the radiogenic isotopic compositions of ocean island basalts (OIBs) and mid-ocean ridge basalts (MORBs), which in turn gave rise to the classic “crustal recycling” model. Based on this, a suite of globally representative mantle end-member components, namely DMM (Depleted MORB Mantle), EMI (Enriched Mantle I), EMII (Enriched Mantle II), HIMU (High μ, μ=238U/204Pb) and PREMA (prevalent mantle), was identified, thereby establishing a comprehensive framework to characterize the geochemical structure and geodynamic system of the mantle. Over the past five decades, mantle geochemistry has advanced with new analytical techniques and theoretical development, greatly broadening its scope. It is now a key field within the Earth System Sciences, crucial for developing models of deep material cycling and surface environmental responses. Aiming to review the development of mantle geochemistry, this paper analyzes eight seminal studies focused on radiogenic isotopes, revisiting the establishment and evolution of mantle geochemistry, exploring the scientific vision of pioneers and highlighting the key topics that define this discipline.
Published: 2026-01-29T09:32:25+00:00
Venue: Science China Earth Sciences
Score: 0.573 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lihui Chen; Xiaoyu Zhang; Jian Zhao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science China Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1820-6"&gt;10.1007/s11430-025-1820-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.573 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mantle geochemistry, a field that emerged in the mid-1970s, utilizes geochemical approaches to investigate the chemical composition and structure as well as the evolution and dynamics of Earth’s mantle. Since its establishment, this field has become a key part of solid Earth Science and Planetary Science, demonstrating great vitality. The development of its theoretical framework began with the observation of mantle heterogeneity revealed by the radiogenic isotopic compositions of ocean island basalts (OIBs) and mid-ocean ridge basalts (MORBs), which in turn gave rise to the classic “crustal recycling” model. Based on this, a suite of globally representative mantle end-member components, namely DMM (Depleted MORB Mantle), EMI (Enriched Mantle I), EMII (Enriched Mantle II), HIMU (High μ, μ=238U/204Pb) and PREMA (prevalent mantle), was identified, thereby establishing a comprehensive framework to characterize the geochemical structure and geodynamic system of the mantle. Over the past five decades, mantle geochemistry has advanced with new analytical techniques and theoretical development, greatly broadening its scope. It is now a key field within the Earth System Sciences, crucial for developing models of deep material cycling and surface environmental responses. Aiming to review the development of mantle geochemistry, this paper analyzes eight seminal studies focused on radiogenic isotopes, revisiting the establishment and evolution of mantle geochemistry, exploring the scientific vision of pioneers and highlighting the key topics that define this discipline.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magmatic evolution of the Karakoram Batholith (∼160–62 Ma), Trans-Himalaya, NW India: Geochemical insights for arc dynamics and crustal growth</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106989</link><guid>10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106989</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 17:10:08 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Irfan M. Bhat</dc:creator><dc:creator>H. Chauhan</dc:creator><dc:creator>T. Ahmad</dc:creator><dc:creator>T. Tanaka</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Asian Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106989</prism:doi><description>The Karakoram Terrane (KT), a continental block along the southern margin of the Asian Plate, originated within the peri -Gondwanan Cimmerian assemblage. It rifted from the Gondwana during the Permian, opened the Neo-Tethys Ocean, and accreted to southern Asia by the Early Jurassic. To constrain its tectono-magmatic evolution, we present whole-rock geochemical data from the Karakoram Batholith (KB), a major granitoid complex of the Trans-Himalaya, NW India. The KB is dominated by porphyritic granites containing abundant diorite enclaves, reflecting magma mingling between coeval mafic and felsic melts. Geochemically, KB granites and diorites exhibit calc-alkaline metaluminous characteristics typical of I-type granitoids, analogous to subduction-zone settings. KB granites have whole-rock ε Nd (t = 110 Ma) values from −6.9 to −8.8 with Nd depleted mantle model ages (T DM ) from 1650 to 1857 Ma. Similarly, KB diorites have whole-rock ε Nd (t = 110 Ma) values from −4.5 to −6.3 with T DM from 1800 to 1953 Ma. These results are analogous to those of the Middle Cretaceous KB diorites (−8.2 to −7.3, and 1380 to 1650 Ma; respectively). These features indicate that during the Jurassic-Cretaceous, northward subduction of the Neo-Tethys oceanic plate beneath the southern margin of the KT established an Andean-type tectonic setting. This emplaced extensive KB magmatism derived from mixed sources, including the mantle wedge and upper crustal rocks of the KT.
Published: 2026-01-30T17:10:08+00:00
Venue: Journal of Asian Earth Sciences
Score: 0.567 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Irfan M. Bhat; H. Chauhan; T. Ahmad; T. Tanaka&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Asian Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106989"&gt;10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106989&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.567 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Karakoram Terrane (KT), a continental block along the southern margin of the Asian Plate, originated within the peri -Gondwanan Cimmerian assemblage. It rifted from the Gondwana during the Permian, opened the Neo-Tethys Ocean, and accreted to southern Asia by the Early Jurassic. To constrain its tectono-magmatic evolution, we present whole-rock geochemical data from the Karakoram Batholith (KB), a major granitoid complex of the Trans-Himalaya, NW India. The KB is dominated by porphyritic granites containing abundant diorite enclaves, reflecting magma mingling between coeval mafic and felsic melts. Geochemically, KB granites and diorites exhibit calc-alkaline metaluminous characteristics typical of I-type granitoids, analogous to subduction-zone settings. KB granites have whole-rock ε Nd (t = 110 Ma) values from −6.9 to −8.8 with Nd depleted mantle model ages (T DM ) from 1650 to 1857 Ma. Similarly, KB diorites have whole-rock ε Nd (t = 110 Ma) values from −4.5 to −6.3 with T DM from 1800 to 1953 Ma. These results are analogous to those of the Middle Cretaceous KB diorites (−8.2 to −7.3, and 1380 to 1650 Ma; respectively). These features indicate that during the Jurassic-Cretaceous, northward subduction of the Neo-Tethys oceanic plate beneath the southern margin of the KT established an Andean-type tectonic setting. This emplaced extensive KB magmatism derived from mixed sources, including the mantle wedge and upper crustal rocks of the KT.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Lithium concentrations and isotopic compositions of chondrules − Part I: Type I and type II chondrule systematics</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.041</link><guid>10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.041</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 17:03:10 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Julia Neukampf</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yves Marrocchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Johan Villeneuve</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mathieu Roskosz</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.041</prism:doi><description>We report high-precision lithium (Li) abundances and isotopic compositions of olivine crystals from type I chondrules in carbonaceous chondrites (Murchison, NWA 852, Renazzo) and type II chondrules in ordinary chondrites (NWA 11752, NWA 12462, NWA 12581, NWA 13501). Olivine crystals in type I chondrules exhibit large Li isotopic fractionations both within and between grains, with δ 7 Li values ranging from −46.6‰ to + 9.9‰ and Li concentrations of 3.8–9.0 ppm. Olivine grains in type II chondrules, including Mg-rich relict cores, show δ 7 Li values from −38.0‰ to + 8.4‰ (Li = 0.6–5.6 ppm), while their Fe-rich overgrowths exhibit lower variability, with δ 7 Li values between −30.6‰ and + 4.7‰ (Li = 0.6–11.9 ppm). Our data indicate that the observed variations are not attributable to low-temperature aqueous alteration or dry thermal metamorphism, fractional crystallisation, or simple degassing of the chondrule melt. Instead, the Li isotopic signatures are best explained by kinetic fractionation during open-system gas–melt exchange with a volatile-rich vapour, enriching the chondrule melts in Li. Such open-system processes produced larger isotopic fractionations than expected during closed-system crystallisation. These findings suggest that some type II chondrules may have originated from type I chondrules through reprocessing in an open-system environment, providing new insights into the complex physicochemical evolution of early solar system solids.
Published: 2026-01-30T17:03:10+00:00
Venue: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta
Score: 0.566 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Julia Neukampf; Yves Marrocchi; Johan Villeneuve; Mathieu Roskosz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.041"&gt;10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.041&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.566 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We report high-precision lithium (Li) abundances and isotopic compositions of olivine crystals from type I chondrules in carbonaceous chondrites (Murchison, NWA 852, Renazzo) and type II chondrules in ordinary chondrites (NWA 11752, NWA 12462, NWA 12581, NWA 13501). Olivine crystals in type I chondrules exhibit large Li isotopic fractionations both within and between grains, with δ 7 Li values ranging from −46.6‰ to + 9.9‰ and Li concentrations of 3.8–9.0 ppm. Olivine grains in type II chondrules, including Mg-rich relict cores, show δ 7 Li values from −38.0‰ to + 8.4‰ (Li = 0.6–5.6 ppm), while their Fe-rich overgrowths exhibit lower variability, with δ 7 Li values between −30.6‰ and + 4.7‰ (Li = 0.6–11.9 ppm). Our data indicate that the observed variations are not attributable to low-temperature aqueous alteration or dry thermal metamorphism, fractional crystallisation, or simple degassing of the chondrule melt. Instead, the Li isotopic signatures are best explained by kinetic fractionation during open-system gas–melt exchange with a volatile-rich vapour, enriching the chondrule melts in Li. Such open-system processes produced larger isotopic fractionations than expected during closed-system crystallisation. These findings suggest that some type II chondrules may have originated from type I chondrules through reprocessing in an open-system environment, providing new insights into the complex physicochemical evolution of early solar system solids.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Geochemical constraints on the evolution and tectonic setting of United Arab Emirates Ophiolitic Serpentinites</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106990</link><guid>10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106990</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Feb 2026 15:15:39 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Mabrouk Sami</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hamed Gamaleldien</dc:creator><dc:creator>Theodoros Ntaflos</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chun-Feng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ioan V. Sanislav</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xun Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vandi Dlama Kamaunji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bahaa M. Amin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Douaa Fathy</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mostafa R. Abukhadra</dc:creator><dc:creator>Khaled Abdelfadil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suhail S. Alhejji</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Asian Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106990</prism:doi><description>Serpentinites in fore-arc settings provide critical constraints on mantle depletion, redox evolution, and slab–mantle fluid transfer during subduction initiation. In the northern Semail Ophiolite of the United Arab Emirates, serpentinites of the Jabal Mundassah–Malaqet (JMM) are studied using mineral chemistry, whole-rock geochemitry, and platinum-group element (PGEs) compositions to constrain protolith characteristics, melting history, and tectono-magmatic evolution. The rocks comprise massive and foliated serpentinites dominated by intergrown lizardite and antigorite with relict Cr-spinel and altered olivine. The JMM serpentinites are characterized by high MgO (34.9–39.2 wt.%), extremely low Al 2 O 3 (0.21–0.92 wt.%) and TiO 2 (0.01–0.03 wt.%), elevated Ni (up to 2462 ppm) and Cr (up to 3143 ppm), and very low high-field-strength element (HFSE) and Th–U contents. These features indicate a highly refractory dunite–harzburgite protolith formed by extensive melt extraction. This interpretation is reinforced by Cr-spinel compositions (Cr# = 0.42–0.48; Mg# = 0.58–0.61) and low total PGE abundances (ΣPGE ≈ 15–35 ppb), which are diagnostic of a strongly depleted, sulfide-exhausted mantle residue. Pronounced depletion in HFSE coupled with diagnostic Nb–Th systematics definitively fingerprints a supra-subduction zone (SSZ) fore-arc tectonic setting. PGE systematics (ΣPGE ≈ 8–26 ppb; modest Pt–Pd enrichment over Os–Ir–Ru; low Pd/Ir=1.18-1.61) record moderate partial melting followed by selective mobilization of PPGEs during serpentinization, preserving a dominantly magmatic signature with a limited metasomatic overprint. We propose the JMM serpentinites originated as a highly depleted mantle residue during intra-oceanic subduction initiation. It was subsequently serpentinized by slab-derived fluids under fore-arc conditions before being tectonically emplaced onto the Arabian margin during Late Cretaceous ophiolite obduction. Relative to the main Semail mantle section, the JMM captures an earlier, less-evolved snapshot of fore-arc development during Late Cretaceous obduction, refining models for Neo-Tethyan subduction initiation and ophiolite assembly.
Published: 2026-02-01T15:15:39+00:00
Venue: Journal of Asian Earth Sciences
Score: 0.565 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mabrouk Sami; Hamed Gamaleldien; Theodoros Ntaflos; Chun-Feng Li; Ioan V. Sanislav; Xun Zhao; Vandi Dlama Kamaunji; Bahaa M. Amin; Douaa Fathy; Mostafa R. Abukhadra; Khaled Abdelfadil; Suhail S. Alhejji&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Asian Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106990"&gt;10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106990&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.565 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Serpentinites in fore-arc settings provide critical constraints on mantle depletion, redox evolution, and slab–mantle fluid transfer during subduction initiation. In the northern Semail Ophiolite of the United Arab Emirates, serpentinites of the Jabal Mundassah–Malaqet (JMM) are studied using mineral chemistry, whole-rock geochemitry, and platinum-group element (PGEs) compositions to constrain protolith characteristics, melting history, and tectono-magmatic evolution. The rocks comprise massive and foliated serpentinites dominated by intergrown lizardite and antigorite with relict Cr-spinel and altered olivine. The JMM serpentinites are characterized by high MgO (34.9–39.2 wt.%), extremely low Al 2 O 3 (0.21–0.92 wt.%) and TiO 2 (0.01–0.03 wt.%), elevated Ni (up to 2462 ppm) and Cr (up to 3143 ppm), and very low high-field-strength element (HFSE) and Th–U contents. These features indicate a highly refractory dunite–harzburgite protolith formed by extensive melt extraction. This interpretation is reinforced by Cr-spinel compositions (Cr# = 0.42–0.48; Mg# = 0.58–0.61) and low total PGE abundances (ΣPGE ≈ 15–35 ppb), which are diagnostic of a strongly depleted, sulfide-exhausted mantle residue. Pronounced depletion in HFSE coupled with diagnostic Nb–Th systematics definitively fingerprints a supra-subduction zone (SSZ) fore-arc tectonic setting. PGE systematics (ΣPGE ≈ 8–26 ppb; modest Pt–Pd enrichment over Os–Ir–Ru; low Pd/Ir=1.18-1.61) record moderate partial melting followed by selective mobilization of PPGEs during serpentinization, preserving a dominantly magmatic signature with a limited metasomatic overprint. We propose the JMM serpentinites originated as a highly depleted mantle residue during intra-oceanic subduction initiation. It was subsequently serpentinized by slab-derived fluids under fore-arc conditions before being tectonically emplaced onto the Arabian margin during Late Cretaceous ophiolite obduction. Relative to the main Semail mantle section, the JMM captures an earlier, less-evolved snapshot of fore-arc development during Late Cretaceous obduction, refining models for Neo-Tethyan subduction initiation and ophiolite assembly.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Trace Elements and Sulfur Isotopes of Sulfides at the Leon Sediment‐Hosted Gold Deposit, Ratatotok District, North Sulawesi, Indonesia: Constraints on the Genesis of Ore Formation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1111/rge.70028</link><guid>10.1111/rge.70028</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 04:05:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Muhammad Arba Azzaman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ryohei Takahashi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pearlyn Manalo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrea Agangi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manuel Nopeia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hinako Sato</dc:creator><dc:creator>Arifudin Idrus</dc:creator><dc:creator>Doly R. Simbolon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Renaldi Suhendra</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Resource Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1111/rge.70028</prism:doi><description>ABSTRACT The Leon gold deposit in the Ratatotok district, North Sulawesi, Indonesia, is hosted by the Middle to Late Miocene Ratatotok Limestone Formation overlying Early to Middle Miocene volcanic rocks. This study aims to elucidate the mode of occurrence of ores, and the conditions and genesis of ore formation of the deposit, based on morphological characteristics, trace elements, and sulfur isotope compositions of sulfide minerals. Four stages of sulfide mineralization associated with sedimentary and hydrothermal processes were identified. Stage 1 is characterized by disseminated framboidal pyrite (pyrite 1; a number after mineral name hereafter indicates its mineralization stage) of sedimentary origin. Stages 2–4 record hydrothermal overprinting, with successive formation of euhedral to subhedral pyrite 2 and marcasite 2, euhedral to anhedral pyrite 3 and arsenopyrite 3, and anhedral pyrite 4. Pyrite 1, pyrite 2, and marcasite 2 have lower Au and As contents, + ) in the sulfides. Gold and As were incorporated into pyrite as coupled partitioning. Temperature and sulfur fugacity (in atm) during the mineralization of arsenopyrite 3 were ~303°C–399°C and log f S 2 = −10.6 to −6.6. δ 34 S CDT values of hydrothermal pyrite in stages 2–4 vary from −3.1‰ to +1.2‰, indicating a predominant magmatic source for S. The Leon deposit is a sediment‐hosted gold deposit with probably a distal intrusion‐centered setting.
Published: 2026-02-02T04:05:14+00:00
Venue: Resource Geology
Score: 0.562 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Muhammad Arba Azzaman; Ryohei Takahashi; Pearlyn Manalo; Andrea Agangi; Manuel Nopeia; Hinako Sato; Arifudin Idrus; Doly R. Simbolon; Renaldi Suhendra&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Resource Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/rge.70028"&gt;10.1111/rge.70028&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.562 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ABSTRACT The Leon gold deposit in the Ratatotok district, North Sulawesi, Indonesia, is hosted by the Middle to Late Miocene Ratatotok Limestone Formation overlying Early to Middle Miocene volcanic rocks. This study aims to elucidate the mode of occurrence of ores, and the conditions and genesis of ore formation of the deposit, based on morphological characteristics, trace elements, and sulfur isotope compositions of sulfide minerals. Four stages of sulfide mineralization associated with sedimentary and hydrothermal processes were identified. Stage 1 is characterized by disseminated framboidal pyrite (pyrite 1; a number after mineral name hereafter indicates its mineralization stage) of sedimentary origin. Stages 2–4 record hydrothermal overprinting, with successive formation of euhedral to subhedral pyrite 2 and marcasite 2, euhedral to anhedral pyrite 3 and arsenopyrite 3, and anhedral pyrite 4. Pyrite 1, pyrite 2, and marcasite 2 have lower Au and As contents, + ) in the sulfides. Gold and As were incorporated into pyrite as coupled partitioning. Temperature and sulfur fugacity (in atm) during the mineralization of arsenopyrite 3 were ~303°C–399°C and log f S 2 = −10.6 to −6.6. δ 34 S CDT values of hydrothermal pyrite in stages 2–4 vary from −3.1‰ to +1.2‰, indicating a predominant magmatic source for S. The Leon deposit is a sediment‐hosted gold deposit with probably a distal intrusion‐centered setting.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Multi-mineral control on Fe isotopic variations during crustal anatexis: Implications for heterogeneous Fe isotopic composition in granitic systems</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123272</link><guid>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123272</guid><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2026 16:20:42 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zheng Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shengyao Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaocong Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yinbiao Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongyong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuanzhi Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lintao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xingzhou Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Chemical Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123272</prism:doi><description>Iron (Fe) isotopes provide a powerful tracer of crustal anatexis, yet their application is complicated by isotopic heterogeneity arising from multi-mineral processes during melting and melt evolution. To address this issue, we present an integrated Fe isotope dataset for whole-rocks and key minerals (e.g., biotite and ilmenite) from a continuous granitic gneiss-migmatite-pegmatite sequence in the North Qaidam ultrahigh-pressure belt. Petrology, whole-rock major, trace element and Nd isotope indicate that the migmatite and pegmatite originated from fluid-absent muscovite-present melting in the granitic gneiss, possibly via the following reaction: Ms. + Pl + Qtz → Kfs + Sill + Bt + Melt. Resulting diatexites and leucosomes show elevated δ 56 Fe (0.13–0.16‰; 0.15–0.24‰) relative to the protolith (0.09–0.11‰) and melanosomes (0.04–0.09‰). After evaluating the effects of weathering/alteration, diffusion, and fluid exsolution, multi-mineral interactions are inferred to be the primary driver of Fe fractionation during crustal anatexis: (1) The retention of ilmenite (δ 56 Fe = −0.16 ± 0.01‰) in the residue resulted in significant Fe isotope fractionation between melanosomes and leucosomes. (2) Peritectic biotite in diatexites exhibits higher δ 56 Fe values (0.18 ± 0.03‰) than residual biotite (0.10 ± 0.02‰) and its entrainment elevated the 56 Fe values in the diatexites during melt migration. (3) Pegmatites display the highest δ 56 Fe (0.22–0.26‰), largely reflecting feldspar accumulation. These results demonstrate that ilmenite retention, peritectic biotite entrainment, and feldspar accumulation collectively generate substantial Fe isotopic heterogeneity in anatectic granites. Fe isotopes thus serve as a sensitive tracer for constraining multi-mineral interactions during crustal anatexis, with broader implications for understanding crustal melting and granite genesis.
Published: 2026-01-30T16:20:42+00:00
Venue: Chemical Geology
Score: 0.562 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zheng Sun; Shengyao Yu; Xiaocong Jiang; Yinbiao Peng; Dongyong Li; Chuanzhi Li; Lintao Wang; Xingzhou Jiang; Qi Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Chemical Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123272"&gt;10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123272&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.562 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iron (Fe) isotopes provide a powerful tracer of crustal anatexis, yet their application is complicated by isotopic heterogeneity arising from multi-mineral processes during melting and melt evolution. To address this issue, we present an integrated Fe isotope dataset for whole-rocks and key minerals (e.g., biotite and ilmenite) from a continuous granitic gneiss-migmatite-pegmatite sequence in the North Qaidam ultrahigh-pressure belt. Petrology, whole-rock major, trace element and Nd isotope indicate that the migmatite and pegmatite originated from fluid-absent muscovite-present melting in the granitic gneiss, possibly via the following reaction: Ms. + Pl + Qtz → Kfs + Sill + Bt + Melt. Resulting diatexites and leucosomes show elevated δ 56 Fe (0.13–0.16‰; 0.15–0.24‰) relative to the protolith (0.09–0.11‰) and melanosomes (0.04–0.09‰). After evaluating the effects of weathering/alteration, diffusion, and fluid exsolution, multi-mineral interactions are inferred to be the primary driver of Fe fractionation during crustal anatexis: (1) The retention of ilmenite (δ 56 Fe = −0.16 ± 0.01‰) in the residue resulted in significant Fe isotope fractionation between melanosomes and leucosomes. (2) Peritectic biotite in diatexites exhibits higher δ 56 Fe values (0.18 ± 0.03‰) than residual biotite (0.10 ± 0.02‰) and its entrainment elevated the 56 Fe values in the diatexites during melt migration. (3) Pegmatites display the highest δ 56 Fe (0.22–0.26‰), largely reflecting feldspar accumulation. These results demonstrate that ilmenite retention, peritectic biotite entrainment, and feldspar accumulation collectively generate substantial Fe isotopic heterogeneity in anatectic granites. Fe isotopes thus serve as a sensitive tracer for constraining multi-mineral interactions during crustal anatexis, with broader implications for understanding crustal melting and granite genesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Melt production and transport beneath the slow-spreading Mariana arc−back-arc system</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/g53706.1</link><guid>10.1130/g53706.1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 20:16:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tae-shin Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sung-Joon Chang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/g53706.1</prism:doi><description>Back-arc basin basalts are broadly similar in composition to mid-ocean ridge basalts, but also incorporate arc-like geochemical signatures. The processes governing melt transport from the arc to the back-arc spreading center remain enigmatic, particularly beneath slow-spreading systems with limited melt volumes, where imaging of small-scale structures has been challenging. Here, we use multimode Rayleigh-wave tomography, enhanced by increased raypath coverage through both two- and three-station interferometry, to resolve S-wave velocity structure down to ∼100 km depth beneath the central Mariana subduction zone. Our model reveals a triangle-like low-velocity anomaly at 15−30 km depth beneath the Mariana trough and an elliptical low-velocity anomaly at 50−90 km depth beneath the Mariana arc, both consistent with melt equilibration depths from thermobarometry. Additionally, a cylindrical low-velocity anomaly extends from the base of the triangle-like low-velocity anomaly to ∼80 km depth and appears weakly connected to the anomaly beneath the arc. We interpret this feature as diapiric upwelling that links melt sources beneath the arc and back-arc.
Published: 2026-01-28T20:16:52+00:00
Venue: Geology
Score: 0.561 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tae-shin Kim; Sung-Joon Chang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/g53706.1"&gt;10.1130/g53706.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.561 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back-arc basin basalts are broadly similar in composition to mid-ocean ridge basalts, but also incorporate arc-like geochemical signatures. The processes governing melt transport from the arc to the back-arc spreading center remain enigmatic, particularly beneath slow-spreading systems with limited melt volumes, where imaging of small-scale structures has been challenging. Here, we use multimode Rayleigh-wave tomography, enhanced by increased raypath coverage through both two- and three-station interferometry, to resolve S-wave velocity structure down to ∼100 km depth beneath the central Mariana subduction zone. Our model reveals a triangle-like low-velocity anomaly at 15−30 km depth beneath the Mariana trough and an elliptical low-velocity anomaly at 50−90 km depth beneath the Mariana arc, both consistent with melt equilibration depths from thermobarometry. Additionally, a cylindrical low-velocity anomaly extends from the base of the triangle-like low-velocity anomaly to ∼80 km depth and appears weakly connected to the anomaly beneath the arc. We interpret this feature as diapiric upwelling that links melt sources beneath the arc and back-arc.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Boron isotopes of tourmaline and muscovite record melt formation and fluid-magma interactions in high-silica granitic rocks</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123284</link><guid>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123284</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 16:26:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shuaiqi Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guibin Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu Xiong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuzhen Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Chemical Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123284</prism:doi><description>The petrogenesis of high-silica granites is crucial for understanding the evolution of granitic melts and the formation of rare metal mineralization. However, the processes occurring from melt formation to evolution following crustal anatexis, as well as their contributions to magma compositions, remain unclear. This study characterizes the chemical composition and B isotope systematics of tourmaline and muscovite, along with whole-rock geochemistry in high-silica granitic rocks from the central Himalaya. We use these data to constrain the melt formation and subsequent fluid-magma interactions in high-silica granites. The leucosomes exhibit high CaO, Sr, Sr/Y, and Eu/Eu* values but low Rb and Rb/Sr contents, characteristic of hydration melting. Muscovite in the leucosomes shows a significant B isotope range (δ 11 B = −20.6‰ to −5.8‰), with δ 11 B values displaying negative correlations with B, Rb, and Cs contents, and positive correlations with Rb/Cs ratios. These patterns reflect increasing muscovite breakdown during prograde hydration melting. The leucogranites were classified into two groups, including tourmaline and two-mica leucogranites. Compared to the two-mica leucogranites, the tourmaline leucogranites are characterized by higher Rb, Rb/Sr, but lower CaO, Sr/Y, Eu/Eu*, and muscovite δ 11 B values. These geochemical differences primarily reflect distinct melting reactions: tourmaline leucogranites result from muscovite dehydration melting, whereas two-mica leucogranites form through hydration melting. In tourmaline leucogranites, tourmaline exhibits δ 11 B ranging from −18.2‰ to −13.5‰, with increasing δ 11 B values and Nb, Ta, and rare earth element (REE) contents from core to rim, indicative of fluid-magma interactions. Magmatic fluid metasomatism also explains the muscovite B isotopic zoning from both leucogranite types, with rims showing elevated δ 11 B, Rb, Cs, and B values alongside notably decreased Nb/Ta ratios. Geochemical modeling suggests that fluid–magma interaction with fluid/magma ratios of 0.2–0.6 could produce the observed B isotopic zoning. Therefore, in-situ tourmaline and muscovite B systematic studies reveal the role of magmatic fluids in the generation of the Himalayan leucogranites. Furthermore, the leucogranites exhibit higher whole-rock and muscovite rare-metal (Li, Nb, Ta, Rb, and Cs) contents than the leucosomes. The rare metals increased, accompanied by the sharply decreased Nb/Ta ratios in the muscovite rims. This evidence supports that the magmatic fluid metasomatism represents a key mechanism for elevating rare metal contents in high-silica granites.
Published: 2026-02-02T16:26:36+00:00
Venue: Chemical Geology
Score: 0.561 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shuaiqi Liu; Guibin Zhang; Qi Jin; Lu Xiong; Shuzhen Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Chemical Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123284"&gt;10.1016/j.chemgeo.2026.123284&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.561 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The petrogenesis of high-silica granites is crucial for understanding the evolution of granitic melts and the formation of rare metal mineralization. However, the processes occurring from melt formation to evolution following crustal anatexis, as well as their contributions to magma compositions, remain unclear. This study characterizes the chemical composition and B isotope systematics of tourmaline and muscovite, along with whole-rock geochemistry in high-silica granitic rocks from the central Himalaya. We use these data to constrain the melt formation and subsequent fluid-magma interactions in high-silica granites. The leucosomes exhibit high CaO, Sr, Sr/Y, and Eu/Eu* values but low Rb and Rb/Sr contents, characteristic of hydration melting. Muscovite in the leucosomes shows a significant B isotope range (δ 11 B = −20.6‰ to −5.8‰), with δ 11 B values displaying negative correlations with B, Rb, and Cs contents, and positive correlations with Rb/Cs ratios. These patterns reflect increasing muscovite breakdown during prograde hydration melting. The leucogranites were classified into two groups, including tourmaline and two-mica leucogranites. Compared to the two-mica leucogranites, the tourmaline leucogranites are characterized by higher Rb, Rb/Sr, but lower CaO, Sr/Y, Eu/Eu*, and muscovite δ 11 B values. These geochemical differences primarily reflect distinct melting reactions: tourmaline leucogranites result from muscovite dehydration melting, whereas two-mica leucogranites form through hydration melting. In tourmaline leucogranites, tourmaline exhibits δ 11 B ranging from −18.2‰ to −13.5‰, with increasing δ 11 B values and Nb, Ta, and rare earth element (REE) contents from core to rim, indicative of fluid-magma interactions. Magmatic fluid metasomatism also explains the muscovite B isotopic zoning from both leucogranite types, with rims showing elevated δ 11 B, Rb, Cs, and B values alongside notably decreased Nb/Ta ratios. Geochemical modeling suggests that fluid–magma interaction with fluid/magma ratios of 0.2–0.6 could produce the observed B isotopic zoning. Therefore, in-situ tourmaline and muscovite B systematic studies reveal the role of magmatic fluids in the generation of the Himalayan leucogranites. Furthermore, the leucogranites exhibit higher whole-rock and muscovite rare-metal (Li, Nb, Ta, Rb, and Cs) contents than the leucosomes. The rare metals increased, accompanied by the sharply decreased Nb/Ta ratios in the muscovite rims. This evidence supports that the magmatic fluid metasomatism represents a key mechanism for elevating rare metal contents in high-silica granites.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Coupled Basin‐Mountain Data Record the Permian‐Triassic Tectonic Transition Along the Eastern Margin of Eurasia</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031395</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb031395</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 08:43:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ning‐Chen Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian‐Bo Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhong‐Jie Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Simon A. Wilde</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen‐Jiao Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhuo Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ri‐Hui Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gong‐Yu Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong‐Yan Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb031395</prism:doi><description>Abstract The eastern margin of Eurasia records complex tectonic events from its interaction with the Paleo‐Asian, Mongol‐Okhotsk, and Paleo‐Pacific Ocean plates during the late Paleozoic to early Mesozoic. However, the subduction histories remain controversial. We employed detrital zircon U‐Pb geochronology and trace element analyses to investigate the provenance of strata of this age within the Jiamusi Massif of NE China. To mitigate age bias from variations in zircon fertility, we compiled zirconium concentrations from 338 granitoid samples across the massif, grouped into four categories: Neoproterozoic (996–722 Ma), early Paleozoic (538–446 Ma), late Paleozoic‐early Mesozoic (338–209 Ma), and Cretaceous (112–92 Ma). Applying the zircon fertility factors (ZFFs) revealed no difference between the early Paleozoic and late Paleozoic‐early Mesozoic suites, which we combined, resulting in values of 1.58, 1.45, and 1.0, respectively. After correcting detrital zircon age spectra using these ZFFs, a sediment provenance shift was evident from active magmatic arcs along the eastern margin of the Jiamusi Massif during the early Permian, to collisional orogenesis between the Jiamusi and Songliao massifs in the Late Triassic along the western margin. Integration with regional tectonic data defines a transition in geodynamics from subduction of the Mongol‐Okhotsk Ocean in the early Permian to combined subduction and collision related to the Paleo‐Pacific domain in the Late Triassic. This study improves the accuracy of interpreting provenance evolution through multi‐dimensional provenance analysis using ZFF correction procedures and offers a reproducible methodology for refining tectonic reconstructions of accretionary orogens and other tectonically complex regions worldwide.
Published: 2026-02-02T08:43:49+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.559 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ning‐Chen Sun; Jian‐Bo Zhou; Zhong‐Jie Xu; Simon A. Wilde; Wen‐Jiao Xiao; Zhuo Chen; Ri‐Hui Cheng; Gong‐Yu Li; Hong‐Yan Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031395"&gt;10.1029/2025jb031395&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.559 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The eastern margin of Eurasia records complex tectonic events from its interaction with the Paleo‐Asian, Mongol‐Okhotsk, and Paleo‐Pacific Ocean plates during the late Paleozoic to early Mesozoic. However, the subduction histories remain controversial. We employed detrital zircon U‐Pb geochronology and trace element analyses to investigate the provenance of strata of this age within the Jiamusi Massif of NE China. To mitigate age bias from variations in zircon fertility, we compiled zirconium concentrations from 338 granitoid samples across the massif, grouped into four categories: Neoproterozoic (996–722 Ma), early Paleozoic (538–446 Ma), late Paleozoic‐early Mesozoic (338–209 Ma), and Cretaceous (112–92 Ma). Applying the zircon fertility factors (ZFFs) revealed no difference between the early Paleozoic and late Paleozoic‐early Mesozoic suites, which we combined, resulting in values of 1.58, 1.45, and 1.0, respectively. After correcting detrital zircon age spectra using these ZFFs, a sediment provenance shift was evident from active magmatic arcs along the eastern margin of the Jiamusi Massif during the early Permian, to collisional orogenesis between the Jiamusi and Songliao massifs in the Late Triassic along the western margin. Integration with regional tectonic data defines a transition in geodynamics from subduction of the Mongol‐Okhotsk Ocean in the early Permian to combined subduction and collision related to the Paleo‐Pacific domain in the Late Triassic. This study improves the accuracy of interpreting provenance evolution through multi‐dimensional provenance analysis using ZFF correction procedures and offers a reproducible methodology for refining tectonic reconstructions of accretionary orogens and other tectonically complex regions worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Long duration of Permian mafic intrusions in the northern Tarim Basin (northwestern China) and implications for the geodynamic evolution of the Tarim large igneous province</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38032.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38032.1</guid><pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2026 20:15:43 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lu Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhuang-Fu Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yong-Zhong Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu-Lin Shen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38032.1</prism:doi><description>The mafic intrusions represent one of the key factors contributing to an improved understanding of the characteristics of the Tarim large igneous province (LIP) of northwestern China and the geodynamic processes. The Awati-Manjar transition zone in the northern Tarim Basin contains extensive mafic intrusions, predominantly composed of diabases, making it a critical region for strengthening our understanding of the evolution and dynamics of the Tarim LIP. In this paper, we conducted an integrated analysis of the newly identified diabase intrusions in the Awati-Manjar transition zone of the northern Tarim Basin, including seismic and drilling data interpretation, petrographic observations, U-Pb isotopic dating, and whole-rock elemental and Sr-Nd isotopic analyses. Seismic and drilling data reveal two distinct occurrence models for the diabase intrusions: sill-shaped and saucer-shaped. Apatite U-Pb dating indicates that the diabases range in age from ca. 308 Ma to 266 Ma, with two distinguishable emplacement episodes identified within analytical uncertainty of 308−299 Ma and 286−266 Ma. The diabases from the earlier episode are sparsely distributed across the study area, whereas those from the later episode are widespread and constitute the majority of the diabase intrusions in the region. Geochemically, the diabases belong to an alkaline, sodium-rich, and high-Ti series. They exhibit consistent chondrite-normalized rare earth element and primitive mantle−normalized trace element patterns, marked by pronounced enrichment in light rare earth elements and highly incompatible elements, respectively. Notably, no Eu anomaly is observed, while distinct positive anomalies are present at Ba and Pb. Whole-rock Sr-Nd isotopic analyses reveal relatively depleted signatures, with (87Sr/86Sr)i ratios ranging from 0.7049 to 0.7074 and εNd(t) values from +0.60 to +2.75. Both elemental and isotopic data indicate that the diabases are compositionally analogous to oceanic-island basalt, implying a genetic link to a mantle plume. That is, they were likely formed through partial melting of a mantle plume source, followed by variable degrees of crustal assimilation and fractional crystallization. More significantly, our newly acquired geological data reveal that the mafic intrusions within the Tarim LIP actually exhibit a longer emplacement duration (spanning the entire lifespan of the Tarim LIP) and a broader spatial distribution (extending beyond the craton margins into its interior) than previously considered. To account for these observed characteristics, a new integrated crust-mantle interaction model has been developed.
Published: 2026-02-02T20:15:43+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.559 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lu Lu; Hao Liu; Zhuang-Fu Li; Yong-Zhong Xu; Yu-Lin Shen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38032.1"&gt;10.1130/b38032.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.559 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mafic intrusions represent one of the key factors contributing to an improved understanding of the characteristics of the Tarim large igneous province (LIP) of northwestern China and the geodynamic processes. The Awati-Manjar transition zone in the northern Tarim Basin contains extensive mafic intrusions, predominantly composed of diabases, making it a critical region for strengthening our understanding of the evolution and dynamics of the Tarim LIP. In this paper, we conducted an integrated analysis of the newly identified diabase intrusions in the Awati-Manjar transition zone of the northern Tarim Basin, including seismic and drilling data interpretation, petrographic observations, U-Pb isotopic dating, and whole-rock elemental and Sr-Nd isotopic analyses. Seismic and drilling data reveal two distinct occurrence models for the diabase intrusions: sill-shaped and saucer-shaped. Apatite U-Pb dating indicates that the diabases range in age from ca. 308 Ma to 266 Ma, with two distinguishable emplacement episodes identified within analytical uncertainty of 308−299 Ma and 286−266 Ma. The diabases from the earlier episode are sparsely distributed across the study area, whereas those from the later episode are widespread and constitute the majority of the diabase intrusions in the region. Geochemically, the diabases belong to an alkaline, sodium-rich, and high-Ti series. They exhibit consistent chondrite-normalized rare earth element and primitive mantle−normalized trace element patterns, marked by pronounced enrichment in light rare earth elements and highly incompatible elements, respectively. Notably, no Eu anomaly is observed, while distinct positive anomalies are present at Ba and Pb. Whole-rock Sr-Nd isotopic analyses reveal relatively depleted signatures, with (87Sr/86Sr)i ratios ranging from 0.7049 to 0.7074 and εNd(t) values from +0.60 to +2.75. Both elemental and isotopic data indicate that the diabases are compositionally analogous to oceanic-island basalt, implying a genetic link to a mantle plume. That is, they were likely formed through partial melting of a mantle plume source, followed by variable degrees of crustal assimilation and fractional crystallization. More significantly, our newly acquired geological data reveal that the mafic intrusions within the Tarim LIP actually exhibit a longer emplacement duration (spanning the entire lifespan of the Tarim LIP) and a broader spatial distribution (extending beyond the craton margins into its interior) than previously considered. To account for these observed characteristics, a new integrated crust-mantle interaction model has been developed.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>