<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 23:51:36 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>The potential for bridgmanite megacrysts to drive magma ocean segregation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10063-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-10063-5</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:02:29 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jie Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junwei Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yidi Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jina Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haiyang Niu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lars Stixrude</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-10063-5</prism:doi><description>Earth’s early mantle probably existed as a deep, vigorously convecting magma ocean, and its solidification is considered central to the long-term chemical and dynamical evolution of the planet. Yet a notable uncertainty is the grain size of bridgmanite—the dominant lower-mantle phase—whose nucleation behaviour at extreme pressure has remained experimentally inaccessible. Here we show, using a combination of cutting-edge techniques, including large-scale molecular dynamics simulations consisting of up to 1 million atoms driven by machine learning potentials (MLPs), seeding and enhanced sampling, that crystal–melt interfacial energies of MgSiO3 bridgmanite increase substantially with pressure, surpassing those of silicate–liquid systems at ambient pressure by a factor of up to ten (refs. 1–3). In a deep basal magma ocean (BMO), this amplified interfacial energy, combined with the potential sluggish cooling, may permit the formation of unusually large bridgmanite crystals, up to centimetre-to-metre-scale sizes. Such potentially large crystals could drive efficient fractional crystallization and cause substantial chemical differentiation and mantle compaction. If operative, this mechanism would provide a new physical pathway linking lower-mantle material properties to early Earth stratification and it motivates future geodynamic models that explicitly incorporate supercooling, compositional convection and elemental partitioning. Our findings thus offer a plausible hypothesis connecting microscopic nucleation processes with macroscopic planetary structure, refining present views of how the Earth’s interior acquired its initial compositional architecture. Large-scale molecular dynamics simulations show that the crystal–melt interfacial energies of MgSiO3 bridgmanite increase substantially with pressure, potentially forming unusually large bridgmanite crystals and suggesting a new physical mechanism driving magma ocean segregation.
Published: 2026-01-21T16:02:29+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.646 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jie Deng; Junwei Hu; Yidi Shi; Jina Lee; Haiyang Niu; Lars Stixrude&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10063-5"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-10063-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.646 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earth’s early mantle probably existed as a deep, vigorously convecting magma ocean, and its solidification is considered central to the long-term chemical and dynamical evolution of the planet. Yet a notable uncertainty is the grain size of bridgmanite—the dominant lower-mantle phase—whose nucleation behaviour at extreme pressure has remained experimentally inaccessible. Here we show, using a combination of cutting-edge techniques, including large-scale molecular dynamics simulations consisting of up to 1 million atoms driven by machine learning potentials (MLPs), seeding and enhanced sampling, that crystal–melt interfacial energies of MgSiO3 bridgmanite increase substantially with pressure, surpassing those of silicate–liquid systems at ambient pressure by a factor of up to ten (refs. 1–3). In a deep basal magma ocean (BMO), this amplified interfacial energy, combined with the potential sluggish cooling, may permit the formation of unusually large bridgmanite crystals, up to centimetre-to-metre-scale sizes. Such potentially large crystals could drive efficient fractional crystallization and cause substantial chemical differentiation and mantle compaction. If operative, this mechanism would provide a new physical pathway linking lower-mantle material properties to early Earth stratification and it motivates future geodynamic models that explicitly incorporate supercooling, compositional convection and elemental partitioning. Our findings thus offer a plausible hypothesis connecting microscopic nucleation processes with macroscopic planetary structure, refining present views of how the Earth’s interior acquired its initial compositional architecture. Large-scale molecular dynamics simulations show that the crystal–melt interfacial energies of MgSiO3 bridgmanite increase substantially with pressure, potentially forming unusually large bridgmanite crystals and suggesting a new physical mechanism driving magma ocean segregation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Electrical Conductivity of Carbonatite Melts to 20 GPa: Constraints on Partial Melting Atop the 410‐km Discontinuity and in the Lower Mantle Transition Zone</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb033390</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb033390</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 07:53:22 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bin Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jintao Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takashi Yoshino</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb033390</prism:doi><description>Abstract Deep‐origin carbonatite melts are considered to be the products of partial‐melting of the oceanic crust in the subduction zones. In this study, we conducted electrical conductivity (EC) measurements on two samples, the composition of which resemble the partial‐melting products atop the 410‐km discontinuity and in the lower part of the transition zone. The EC of carbonatite melts was investigated using impedance spectroscopy combined with a multi‐anvil press up to 20 GPa. Pressure has a great effect on the EC of the carbonatite melts. While the EC dropped overall by 0.6 log unit from 3 to 20 GPa for varying compositions, the pressure effect becomes weaker above 10 GPa. The Hashin‐Shtrikman mixing model indicates that melt fraction of 0–0.3 vol% is necessary to account for the EC atop the 410‐km discontinuity beneath NE China, north Philippine Sea, north Pacific, and Australian craton. However, this value soars to 1–4.5 vol% for the lower part of the transition zone in the same regions, and further increases to 3.7–7.3 vol% for cold subduction regions if the slab surface temperature is 300 K lower. The difference in the needed melt fraction at different depths implies that the magnitude of partial melting is much larger in the lower part of the mantle transition zone, and it is thus likely to be the main barrier to the recycled carbonates towards the deep interior.
Published: 2026-01-20T07:53:22+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.630 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bin Zhao; Jintao Zhu; Qi Chen; Takashi Yoshino&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb033390"&gt;10.1029/2025jb033390&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.630 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Deep‐origin carbonatite melts are considered to be the products of partial‐melting of the oceanic crust in the subduction zones. In this study, we conducted electrical conductivity (EC) measurements on two samples, the composition of which resemble the partial‐melting products atop the 410‐km discontinuity and in the lower part of the transition zone. The EC of carbonatite melts was investigated using impedance spectroscopy combined with a multi‐anvil press up to 20 GPa. Pressure has a great effect on the EC of the carbonatite melts. While the EC dropped overall by 0.6 log unit from 3 to 20 GPa for varying compositions, the pressure effect becomes weaker above 10 GPa. The Hashin‐Shtrikman mixing model indicates that melt fraction of 0–0.3 vol% is necessary to account for the EC atop the 410‐km discontinuity beneath NE China, north Philippine Sea, north Pacific, and Australian craton. However, this value soars to 1–4.5 vol% for the lower part of the transition zone in the same regions, and further increases to 3.7–7.3 vol% for cold subduction regions if the slab surface temperature is 300 K lower. The difference in the needed melt fraction at different depths implies that the magnitude of partial melting is much larger in the lower part of the mantle transition zone, and it is thus likely to be the main barrier to the recycled carbonates towards the deep interior.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seamount subduction and its role in triggering magmatic flare-ups: Evidence from the Late Devonian Northern Yili Arc</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38166.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38166.1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 19:37:47 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hao Xing</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junling Pei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaobo Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guangxian Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinfeng Wen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiatian Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Songjian Lin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38166.1</prism:doi><description>Magmatic flare-ups are widely recognized as pivotal features of continental arc magmatism, yet their driving mechanisms remain poorly understood. In this study, we present new radiometric ages and geochemical data for normal calc-alkaline, high-magnesian, and Nb-enriched arc magmatic rocks from the Northern Yili Arc (Western Tianshan, China), which coincide with the Late Devonian magmatic flare-up in the region. The normal arc magmatic rocks likely originated from partial melting of a slab fluid-metasomatized mantle wedge, possibly accompanied by fractional crystallization and crustal assimilation processes. In contrast, the high-magnesian andesites (HMAs) and Nb-enriched basalts (NEBs) were derived from sediment melt and slab melt-metasomatized mantle sources, respectively. The systematic decoupling of Nd-Hf isotopes in contemporaneous mafic-intermediate lavas further indicates mantle source heterogeneity. The clustered eruption of HMAs and NEBs, alongside enriched continental signatures in their mantle sources, implies intensified slab-mantle interactions. We attribute this to enhanced interaction efficiency driven by a unique geodynamic process. We propose that the most plausible mechanism for the Late Devonian−Early Carboniferous magmatic fluctuations involves seamount/oceanic plateau subduction followed by slab retreat or rollback. The Late Devonian seamount subduction scenario provides new insights into the geodynamic evolution of the North Tianshan Ocean, the distribution of Au-Cu deposits, and the polarity of subduction in ancient oceanic plates within the Yili microcontinent.
Published: 2026-01-21T19:37:47+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.618 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hao Xing; Junling Pei; Xiaobo Zhao; Guangxian Liu; Jinfeng Wen; Xiatian Zhang; Songjian Lin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38166.1"&gt;10.1130/b38166.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.618 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magmatic flare-ups are widely recognized as pivotal features of continental arc magmatism, yet their driving mechanisms remain poorly understood. In this study, we present new radiometric ages and geochemical data for normal calc-alkaline, high-magnesian, and Nb-enriched arc magmatic rocks from the Northern Yili Arc (Western Tianshan, China), which coincide with the Late Devonian magmatic flare-up in the region. The normal arc magmatic rocks likely originated from partial melting of a slab fluid-metasomatized mantle wedge, possibly accompanied by fractional crystallization and crustal assimilation processes. In contrast, the high-magnesian andesites (HMAs) and Nb-enriched basalts (NEBs) were derived from sediment melt and slab melt-metasomatized mantle sources, respectively. The systematic decoupling of Nd-Hf isotopes in contemporaneous mafic-intermediate lavas further indicates mantle source heterogeneity. The clustered eruption of HMAs and NEBs, alongside enriched continental signatures in their mantle sources, implies intensified slab-mantle interactions. We attribute this to enhanced interaction efficiency driven by a unique geodynamic process. We propose that the most plausible mechanism for the Late Devonian−Early Carboniferous magmatic fluctuations involves seamount/oceanic plateau subduction followed by slab retreat or rollback. The Late Devonian seamount subduction scenario provides new insights into the geodynamic evolution of the North Tianshan Ocean, the distribution of Au-Cu deposits, and the polarity of subduction in ancient oceanic plates within the Yili microcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Core–envelope miscibility in sub-Neptunes and super-Earths</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09970-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09970-4</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:02:49 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Travis Gilmore</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lars Stixrude</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09970-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract Sub-Neptunes and super-Earths, the most abundant types of planet in the galaxy, are unlike anything in the Solar System, with radii between those of Earth and Neptune 1,2 . Fundamental questions remain regarding their structure and origin. Although super-Earths have a rocky composition 3 , sub-Neptunes form a distinct population at larger radii and are thought to consist of a rocky core overlain by a hydrogen-rich envelope 4,5 . At the extreme conditions of the core–envelope interface (exceeding several gigapascals and several thousand kelvin 4,6 ), reaction between core and envelope seems possible, but the nature and extent of these reactions are unknown. Here we use first-principles molecular dynamics driven by density functional theory to show that silicate and hydrogen are completely miscible over a wide range of plausible core–envelope pressure–temperature conditions. We find the origin of miscibility in extensive chemical reaction between hydrogen and silicate, producing silane, SiO and water species, which may be observable with ongoing or future missions. Core–envelope miscibility profoundly affects the evolution of sub-Neptunes and super-Earths, by dissolving a large fraction of the hydrogen of the planet in the core and driving exchange of hydrogen between core and envelope as the planet evolves.
Published: 2026-01-21T16:02:49+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.613 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Travis Gilmore; Lars Stixrude&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09970-4"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09970-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.613 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Sub-Neptunes and super-Earths, the most abundant types of planet in the galaxy, are unlike anything in the Solar System, with radii between those of Earth and Neptune 1,2 . Fundamental questions remain regarding their structure and origin. Although super-Earths have a rocky composition 3 , sub-Neptunes form a distinct population at larger radii and are thought to consist of a rocky core overlain by a hydrogen-rich envelope 4,5 . At the extreme conditions of the core–envelope interface (exceeding several gigapascals and several thousand kelvin 4,6 ), reaction between core and envelope seems possible, but the nature and extent of these reactions are unknown. Here we use first-principles molecular dynamics driven by density functional theory to show that silicate and hydrogen are completely miscible over a wide range of plausible core–envelope pressure–temperature conditions. We find the origin of miscibility in extensive chemical reaction between hydrogen and silicate, producing silane, SiO and water species, which may be observable with ongoing or future missions. Core–envelope miscibility profoundly affects the evolution of sub-Neptunes and super-Earths, by dissolving a large fraction of the hydrogen of the planet in the core and driving exchange of hydrogen between core and envelope as the planet evolves.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Presence of primordial Mg can explain the seismic low-velocity layer in the Earth’s outermost outer core</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68572-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68572-4</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 14:37:57 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhicheng Jing</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68572-4</prism:doi><description>The composition of Earth’s Fe-rich liquid outer core has long been debated. Available models incorporating light elements, such as Si, O, C, S, and H, cannot explain the seismically low velocity layer in the uppermost outer core (E′ layer). Here we employ first-principles molecular dynamics simulations to determine the density and sound velocity ($${V}_{P}$$) of Fe-Mg liquids under outer core conditions, which were unknown previously. Results show that the presence of Mg slightly decreases the $${V}_{P}$$ of liquid Fe, in contrast to the enhancing effects of other light elements. Our modeling suggests that 0.5-1.79 wt% Mg is required to match seismically observed core densities and velocities. Such amount of Mg could have entered the outermost outer core following the Moon-forming giant impact, thereby providing a viable explanation for the formation of the E′ layer and contributing to the slight Mg depletion in the bulk silicate Earth relative to chondritic meteorites. Simulations show that primordial Mg deposited to the core through the Moon-forming giant impact can decrease the sound velocity of Fe-rich liquids, providing a viable explanation for the low seismic velocity in the Earth’s outermost outer core.
Published: 2026-01-20T14:37:57+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.612 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tao Liu; Zhicheng Jing&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68572-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68572-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.612 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The composition of Earth’s Fe-rich liquid outer core has long been debated. Available models incorporating light elements, such as Si, O, C, S, and H, cannot explain the seismically low velocity layer in the uppermost outer core (E′ layer). Here we employ first-principles molecular dynamics simulations to determine the density and sound velocity ($${V}_{P}$$) of Fe-Mg liquids under outer core conditions, which were unknown previously. Results show that the presence of Mg slightly decreases the $${V}_{P}$$ of liquid Fe, in contrast to the enhancing effects of other light elements. Our modeling suggests that 0.5-1.79 wt% Mg is required to match seismically observed core densities and velocities. Such amount of Mg could have entered the outermost outer core following the Moon-forming giant impact, thereby providing a viable explanation for the formation of the E′ layer and contributing to the slight Mg depletion in the bulk silicate Earth relative to chondritic meteorites. Simulations show that primordial Mg deposited to the core through the Moon-forming giant impact can decrease the sound velocity of Fe-rich liquids, providing a viable explanation for the low seismic velocity in the Earth’s outermost outer core.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Zinc isotopes record lunar magmatic outgassing and surface processes in different Chang’e-5 samples</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03215-6</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03215-6</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:36:59 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ziwei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haolan Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingnan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Frédéric Moynier</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ji Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huimin Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fang Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liping Qin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03215-6</prism:doi><description>The Moon is depleted in moderately volatile elements compared with Earth, likely due to high-temperature processes during its formation. How this depletion evolved and the role of later surface processes remain unclear. Here we report high-precision zinc isotope measurements of basalt fragments and soils collected by the Chang’e-5 (CE-5) mission from a ~ 2-billion-year-old volcanic region. The basalts have zinc isotope values similar to those of Apollo mare basalts, consistent with global volatile loss during the Moon-forming impact. In contrast, soils show lighter zinc isotope signatures than Apollo soils and no variation with depth, suggesting little effect from space weathering. Instead, the data indicate that low-temperature volcanic outgassing deposited isotopically light zinc on the surface. These results show that young lunar soils can retain evidence of late-stage volcanic degassing, distinct from the intense volatile loss that shaped the early Moon. Zinc isotope data from Chang’e-5 lunar basalt samples records early impact driven volatile depletion, whereas soil samples primarily record&amp;nbsp;late-stage volcanic degassing, with only limited space-weathering modification.
Published: 2026-01-21T11:36:59+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.603 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ziwei Wang; Haolan Tang; Yingnan Zhang; Frédéric Moynier; Ji Shen; Huimin Yu; Fang Huang; Liping Qin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03215-6"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03215-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.603 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Moon is depleted in moderately volatile elements compared with Earth, likely due to high-temperature processes during its formation. How this depletion evolved and the role of later surface processes remain unclear. Here we report high-precision zinc isotope measurements of basalt fragments and soils collected by the Chang’e-5 (CE-5) mission from a ~ 2-billion-year-old volcanic region. The basalts have zinc isotope values similar to those of Apollo mare basalts, consistent with global volatile loss during the Moon-forming impact. In contrast, soils show lighter zinc isotope signatures than Apollo soils and no variation with depth, suggesting little effect from space weathering. Instead, the data indicate that low-temperature volcanic outgassing deposited isotopically light zinc on the surface. These results show that young lunar soils can retain evidence of late-stage volcanic degassing, distinct from the intense volatile loss that shaped the early Moon. Zinc isotope data from Chang’e-5 lunar basalt samples records early impact driven volatile depletion, whereas soil samples primarily record&amp;amp;nbsp;late-stage volcanic degassing, with only limited space-weathering modification.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Morphology-modified contributions of electronic transitions to the optical response of plasmonic nanoporous gold metamaterial</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68506-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68506-0</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:48:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tlek Tapani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonas M. Pettersson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nils Henriksson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Carla M. Brunner</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ann Céline Zimmermann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Erik Zäll</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nils V. Hauff</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lakshmi Das</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anastasiia Sapunova</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gianluca Balestra</dc:creator><dc:creator>Massimo Cuscunà</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aitor De Andrés</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tommaso Giovannini</dc:creator><dc:creator>Denis Garoli</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicolò Maccaferri</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68506-0</prism:doi><description>Abstract Nanoporous metals have emerged as promising functional architectures with tunable optical and electronic properties, high surface areas, and applicability in sensing, catalysis, and biomedicine. While their linear optical behavior and morphological properties have been extensively studied, the electronic properties, and in particular how they are affected by morphology, remain not fully understood. Here we combine experimental and theoretical studies of electronic excitation and relaxation in a nanoporous gold metamaterial. Optical pump–probe experiments show slower electron relaxation dynamics compared to the continuous film, consistent with a higher transient electronic temperature and stronger smearing of the Fermi–Dirac distribution, well reproduced by an extended two-temperature model. Furthermore, cathodoluminescence measurements reveal broadband localized plasmon resonances, and atomistic simulations disentangle intra- and interband effects, demonstrating that nanoscale porosity fundamentally reshapes the electronic response. These findings support nanoporosity as a key design parameter for controlling steady-state and ultrafast optical behavior in plasmonic materials.
Published: 2026-01-20T11:48:50+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.596 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tlek Tapani; Jonas M. Pettersson; Nils Henriksson; Carla M. Brunner; Ann Céline Zimmermann; Erik Zäll; Nils V. Hauff; Lakshmi Das; Anastasiia Sapunova; Gianluca Balestra; Massimo Cuscunà; Aitor De Andrés; Tommaso Giovannini; Denis Garoli; Nicolò Maccaferri&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68506-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68506-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.596 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Nanoporous metals have emerged as promising functional architectures with tunable optical and electronic properties, high surface areas, and applicability in sensing, catalysis, and biomedicine. While their linear optical behavior and morphological properties have been extensively studied, the electronic properties, and in particular how they are affected by morphology, remain not fully understood. Here we combine experimental and theoretical studies of electronic excitation and relaxation in a nanoporous gold metamaterial. Optical pump–probe experiments show slower electron relaxation dynamics compared to the continuous film, consistent with a higher transient electronic temperature and stronger smearing of the Fermi–Dirac distribution, well reproduced by an extended two-temperature model. Furthermore, cathodoluminescence measurements reveal broadband localized plasmon resonances, and atomistic simulations disentangle intra- and interband effects, demonstrating that nanoscale porosity fundamentally reshapes the electronic response. These findings support nanoporosity as a key design parameter for controlling steady-state and ultrafast optical behavior in plasmonic materials.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Oxidative uptake of Ce by oceanic ferromanganese crusts and implications for paleoredox estimates using Ce isotopes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03196-6</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03196-6</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 15:54:08 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Alain Manceau</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianlin Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrea Giacomelli</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marius Retegan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrea Koschinsky</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephan N. Steinmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Olivier Mathon</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03196-6</prism:doi><description>The oxidative enrichment and isotopic fractionation of cerium (Ce) in contact with vernadite (δ-MnO2) serve as a proxy for past redox conditions in both terrestrial and marine environments. However, the molecular processes that govern the scavenging of Ce from the dissolved 3+ to the insoluble 4+ oxidation states remain obscure. Adsorption experiments on synthetic δ-MnO2 suggest that aqueous Ce(III) precipitates as ceric hydroxide (Ce(OH)4), an unknown mineral. Here, the atomic-scale structure of Ce in natural vernadite from ferromanganese crusts collected across the Pacific, Atlantic, and Indian Oceans was examined using advanced high-energy-resolution extended X-ray absorption fine structure spectroscopy. The findings provide direct evidence for the uptake of Ce as mononuclear Ce(IV) complexes at the layer-edge sites (DES complex) and Mn(IV) vacancy sites of vernadite. Density functional theory-based Gibbs free-energy calculations indicate that hydrolysis of the DES complex promotes the oxidation of Ce(III) to Ce(IV). Quantum mechanical calculations predict that the equilibrium 136Ce/140Ce isotope fractionation factor between Ce(III) dissolved in seawater and the Ce(IV) complexes can reach 1.2-1.3 ‰ at 25 °C, indicating that the 136Ce/140Ce ratio has high potential as a new paleoredox proxy. Seawater cerium (III) forms mononuclear complexes in vernadite from global ferromanganese crusts and is oxidized to cerium (IV) during hydrolysis, as shown by atomic-scale analysis and quantum calculations. This leads to strong Ce isotope fractionation.
Published: 2026-01-20T15:54:08+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.583 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Alain Manceau; Jianlin Liao; Yan Li; Andrea Giacomelli; Marius Retegan; Andrea Koschinsky; Stephan N. Steinmann; Olivier Mathon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03196-6"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03196-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.583 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The oxidative enrichment and isotopic fractionation of cerium (Ce) in contact with vernadite (δ-MnO2) serve as a proxy for past redox conditions in both terrestrial and marine environments. However, the molecular processes that govern the scavenging of Ce from the dissolved 3+ to the insoluble 4+ oxidation states remain obscure. Adsorption experiments on synthetic δ-MnO2 suggest that aqueous Ce(III) precipitates as ceric hydroxide (Ce(OH)4), an unknown mineral. Here, the atomic-scale structure of Ce in natural vernadite from ferromanganese crusts collected across the Pacific, Atlantic, and Indian Oceans was examined using advanced high-energy-resolution extended X-ray absorption fine structure spectroscopy. The findings provide direct evidence for the uptake of Ce as mononuclear Ce(IV) complexes at the layer-edge sites (DES complex) and Mn(IV) vacancy sites of vernadite. Density functional theory-based Gibbs free-energy calculations indicate that hydrolysis of the DES complex promotes the oxidation of Ce(III) to Ce(IV). Quantum mechanical calculations predict that the equilibrium 136Ce/140Ce isotope fractionation factor between Ce(III) dissolved in seawater and the Ce(IV) complexes can reach 1.2-1.3 ‰ at 25 °C, indicating that the 136Ce/140Ce ratio has high potential as a new paleoredox proxy. Seawater cerium (III) forms mononuclear complexes in vernadite from global ferromanganese crusts and is oxidized to cerium (IV) during hydrolysis, as shown by atomic-scale analysis and quantum calculations. This leads to strong Ce isotope fractionation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Cooling‐Induced Rheological Weakening Along the Nascent Plate Interface—A Mechanism for Catastrophic Subduction Initiation?</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032212</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032212</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 12:27:03 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Alissa J. Kotowski</dc:creator><dc:creator>Caroline E. Seyler</dc:creator><dc:creator>James D. Kirkpatrick</dc:creator><dc:creator>Douwe J. J. van Hinsbergen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032212</prism:doi><description>Abstract Subduction initiation often begins with slow, forced convergence, switches “on” catastrophically as the slab collapses into the mantle, and then evolves to steady‐state, self‐sustained sinking that drives global plate movements. Numerical models suggest that the collapse phase implies sudden weakening of the plate interface. However, geological records of subduction infancy preserved as metamorphosed oceanic crust accreted beneath ophiolites (i.e., metamorphic soles) present a paradox. During the pre‐collapse period that may last 2–15 million years, the nascent plate interface is hot, whereas during collapse, shear zone temperatures plummet, which typically strengthens rocks. So, how could cooling cause weakening? Here, we show microstructures of metamorphic sole rocks from Mont Albert (Québec, Canada) that demonstrate that upon cooling, metamorphic mineralogy became more heterogeneous, average grain size decreased, and deformation mechanisms shifted from dislocation‐accommodated to fluid‐assisted and grain size sensitive, which culminated in drastic rheological weakening. Quartz piezometry indicates that flow stress increased with cooling, but flow laws indicate that the colder rocks exhibited lower viscosity and therefore could localize strain. Interface viscosity initially rose with cooling, but upon reaching a threshold where major metamorphic minerals changed, dropped from &gt;10 18 to 17 Pa‐s. Cooling‐induced mineral‐mechanical changes thus drove rheological weakening, and provide a general mechanism explaining slab collapse and the transition to self‐sustaining subduction. This implies that strain localization is inherent to modern metamorphosed oceanic lithosphere and does not require a “stress drop.” The next step to understanding subduction initiation is identifying causes of high temperatures and incipient cooling during the pre‐collapse phase.
Published: 2026-01-21T12:27:03+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.579 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Alissa J. Kotowski; Caroline E. Seyler; James D. Kirkpatrick; Douwe J. J. van Hinsbergen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032212"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032212&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.579 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Subduction initiation often begins with slow, forced convergence, switches “on” catastrophically as the slab collapses into the mantle, and then evolves to steady‐state, self‐sustained sinking that drives global plate movements. Numerical models suggest that the collapse phase implies sudden weakening of the plate interface. However, geological records of subduction infancy preserved as metamorphosed oceanic crust accreted beneath ophiolites (i.e., metamorphic soles) present a paradox. During the pre‐collapse period that may last 2–15 million years, the nascent plate interface is hot, whereas during collapse, shear zone temperatures plummet, which typically strengthens rocks. So, how could cooling cause weakening? Here, we show microstructures of metamorphic sole rocks from Mont Albert (Québec, Canada) that demonstrate that upon cooling, metamorphic mineralogy became more heterogeneous, average grain size decreased, and deformation mechanisms shifted from dislocation‐accommodated to fluid‐assisted and grain size sensitive, which culminated in drastic rheological weakening. Quartz piezometry indicates that flow stress increased with cooling, but flow laws indicate that the colder rocks exhibited lower viscosity and therefore could localize strain. Interface viscosity initially rose with cooling, but upon reaching a threshold where major metamorphic minerals changed, dropped from &amp;gt;10 18 to 17 Pa‐s. Cooling‐induced mineral‐mechanical changes thus drove rheological weakening, and provide a general mechanism explaining slab collapse and the transition to self‐sustaining subduction. This implies that strain localization is inherent to modern metamorphosed oceanic lithosphere and does not require a “stress drop.” The next step to understanding subduction initiation is identifying causes of high temperatures and incipient cooling during the pre‐collapse phase.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Constraints on the impactor flux to the Earth–Moon system from oxygen isotopes of the lunar regolith</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2531796123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2531796123</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 18:59:25 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Anthony M. Gargano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Justin I. Simon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Erick Cano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Karen Ziegler</dc:creator><dc:creator>Charles K. Shearer</dc:creator><dc:creator>James M. D. Day</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zachary Sharp</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2531796123</prism:doi><description>The impactor flux record to Earth has largely been erased by active tectonics, weathering, and continual reworking of the crust. Instead, a record of highly siderophile elements (HSE: Re, Os, Ir, Ru, Rh, Pt, Pd, and Au) in lunar impactites has been used as a proxy for the type of impactor material added to the Earth–Moon system. Quantifying impactor mass and flux with the HSE can potentially be complicated by numerous secondary processes, however, including silicate–metal segregation and multiple impact heritage. In contrast, because oxygen has an invariant geochemical affinity, triple oxygen isotope compositions have the potential to offer a robust long-term record of impactor fluxes in complex mixtures such as regolith. Here, we use high-precision triple oxygen isotopes to deconvolve the influences of meteorite addition and silicate vaporization and identify a ubiquitous impactor contaminant comprised of partially evaporated CM or ureilite-like material representing at least 1 wt% of the lunar regolith. Water delivered to Earth by meteorite material over 4 billion years therefore is only a fraction of an ocean’s worth of water but is a significant contributor to the ice reservoir of the lunar cold traps.
Published: 2026-01-20T18:59:25+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.568 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Anthony M. Gargano; Justin I. Simon; Erick Cano; Karen Ziegler; Charles K. Shearer; James M. D. Day; Zachary Sharp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2531796123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2531796123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.568 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impactor flux record to Earth has largely been erased by active tectonics, weathering, and continual reworking of the crust. Instead, a record of highly siderophile elements (HSE: Re, Os, Ir, Ru, Rh, Pt, Pd, and Au) in lunar impactites has been used as a proxy for the type of impactor material added to the Earth–Moon system. Quantifying impactor mass and flux with the HSE can potentially be complicated by numerous secondary processes, however, including silicate–metal segregation and multiple impact heritage. In contrast, because oxygen has an invariant geochemical affinity, triple oxygen isotope compositions have the potential to offer a robust long-term record of impactor fluxes in complex mixtures such as regolith. Here, we use high-precision triple oxygen isotopes to deconvolve the influences of meteorite addition and silicate vaporization and identify a ubiquitous impactor contaminant comprised of partially evaporated CM or ureilite-like material representing at least 1 wt% of the lunar regolith. Water delivered to Earth by meteorite material over 4 billion years therefore is only a fraction of an ocean’s worth of water but is a significant contributor to the ice reservoir of the lunar cold traps.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Calbuco and Osorno volcanoes (Chile) tap into mantle sources that only differ by their water content</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02282-w</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02282-w</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:10:59 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jacqueline Vander Auwera</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tonin Bechon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Salvatrice Montalbano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bernard Charlier</dc:creator><dc:creator>Olivier Bolle</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pierre Schiano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicolas Cluzel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jean-Luc Devidal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luisa Ottolini</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luis E. Lara</dc:creator><dc:creator>Olivier Namur</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas van Gerve</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02282-w</prism:doi><description>The Osorno and Calbuco stratovolcanoes are situated just 27&amp;nbsp;km apart along the volcanic arc front of the Central Southern Volcanic Zone (Chile), yet they exhibit significantly different characteristics. Notably, Calbuco intermediate to andesitic lavas contain amphibole, which is absent in Osorno, and has a much higher explosivity (up to VEI = 4 to 5). Their olivine-hosted melt inclusions (MI) display similar major elements differentiation trends. Incompatible trace element ratios overlap in both volcanoes and therefore do not correlate with the H2O and Cl contents. Indeed, MIs data and petrological hygrometers indicate higher volatiles content at Calbuco (~ 3 wt% @ 51.3 wt% SiO2, 951–3232 ppm) compared to Osorno (~ 1 wt% @ 50.5 wt% SiO2, 521–1091 ppm). Because the Cpx-only geobarometers and geophysical data both place the Osorno and Calbuco main magma reservoirs at the same depth, their differing volatile contents are interpreted as inherited from the mantle melts. Their calculated primary magmas result from similar to identical partial melting fractions of mantle sources that differ only in their H2O content. The mantle source beneath Calbuco partially melted at a lower temperature, possibly because of the slightly more trench ward position of the volcano, which projects vertically into a cooler part of the mantle wedge “nose”. The lack of correlation between incompatible elements and H2O content is interpreted as resulting from evidence for a decoupling between H2O, transported mainly in a solute-poor fluid, and incompatible elements, which are delivered by melts derived from the subducting oceanic lithosphere. The variability of the mantle wedge H2O concentration and the uncorrelated content of slab tracers and H2O have also been observed at a global scale.
Published: 2026-01-20T03:10:59+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.561 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jacqueline Vander Auwera; Tonin Bechon; Salvatrice Montalbano; Bernard Charlier; Olivier Bolle; Pierre Schiano; Nicolas Cluzel; Jean-Luc Devidal; Luisa Ottolini; Luis E. Lara; Olivier Namur; Thomas van Gerve&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02282-w"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02282-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.561 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Osorno and Calbuco stratovolcanoes are situated just 27&amp;amp;nbsp;km apart along the volcanic arc front of the Central Southern Volcanic Zone (Chile), yet they exhibit significantly different characteristics. Notably, Calbuco intermediate to andesitic lavas contain amphibole, which is absent in Osorno, and has a much higher explosivity (up to VEI = 4 to 5). Their olivine-hosted melt inclusions (MI) display similar major elements differentiation trends. Incompatible trace element ratios overlap in both volcanoes and therefore do not correlate with the H2O and Cl contents. Indeed, MIs data and petrological hygrometers indicate higher volatiles content at Calbuco (~ 3 wt% @ 51.3 wt% SiO2, 951–3232 ppm) compared to Osorno (~ 1 wt% @ 50.5 wt% SiO2, 521–1091 ppm). Because the Cpx-only geobarometers and geophysical data both place the Osorno and Calbuco main magma reservoirs at the same depth, their differing volatile contents are interpreted as inherited from the mantle melts. Their calculated primary magmas result from similar to identical partial melting fractions of mantle sources that differ only in their H2O content. The mantle source beneath Calbuco partially melted at a lower temperature, possibly because of the slightly more trench ward position of the volcano, which projects vertically into a cooler part of the mantle wedge “nose”. The lack of correlation between incompatible elements and H2O content is interpreted as resulting from evidence for a decoupling between H2O, transported mainly in a solute-poor fluid, and incompatible elements, which are delivered by melts derived from the subducting oceanic lithosphere. The variability of the mantle wedge H2O concentration and the uncorrelated content of slab tracers and H2O have also been observed at a global scale.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Observation of strong spin-orbit couplings in plasmonic spin-twistronics topological lattices</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68629-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68629-4</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 15:34:59 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Peng Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinxin Gou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weiyu Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haijun Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhihan Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yijie Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaocong Yuan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68629-4</prism:doi><description>Twistronics is based on the control of the relative twist angle between the two layers of two-dimensional (2D) material in a moiré superlattice. Manipulating the twist angle enables controlling a variety of nontrivial properties, making twistronics a platform revolutionizing electronics and material sciences. Here, we introduce spin-twistronics, which brings the principles of twistronics to topological spin photonics. The moiré superlattice is realized by stacking two spin lattices on a single surface plasmonic polariton (SPP) platform. Each 2D SPP wave supports the construction of topological lattices formed by photonic spins with specific topology governed by rotational and translational symmetries and intense spin-orbit couplings. We theoretically and experimentally demonstrate that a twisted bilayer of photonic spin lattices can produce moiré spin superlattices at specific angles. Modulating these periodically by the total angular momentum shows the emergence of spin quasiparticle topologies, such as real skyrmion lattices and meron clusters, multiple fractal patterns and slow-light control, properties that cannot be achieved in conventional plasmonic systems. Spin-twistronics creates multiple degrees of freedom to tune nontrivial nanophotonic properties for advances in on-chip information devices, optical manipulation, and chiral light-matter interactions. Twistronics is commonly applied to a twisted bilayer of two-dimensional materials. Here, authors introduce the concepts of twistronics to the superposition of two spin lattices generated from surface plasmon polaritons on a single surface. The system is periodically modulated by its total angular momentum.
Published: 2026-01-21T15:34:59+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.558 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Peng Shi; Xinxin Gou; Qiang Zhang; Weiyu Wei; Haijun Wu; Zhihan Zhu; Yijie Shen; Xiaocong Yuan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68629-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68629-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.558 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twistronics is based on the control of the relative twist angle between the two layers of two-dimensional (2D) material in a moiré superlattice. Manipulating the twist angle enables controlling a variety of nontrivial properties, making twistronics a platform revolutionizing electronics and material sciences. Here, we introduce spin-twistronics, which brings the principles of twistronics to topological spin photonics. The moiré superlattice is realized by stacking two spin lattices on a single surface plasmonic polariton (SPP) platform. Each 2D SPP wave supports the construction of topological lattices formed by photonic spins with specific topology governed by rotational and translational symmetries and intense spin-orbit couplings. We theoretically and experimentally demonstrate that a twisted bilayer of photonic spin lattices can produce moiré spin superlattices at specific angles. Modulating these periodically by the total angular momentum shows the emergence of spin quasiparticle topologies, such as real skyrmion lattices and meron clusters, multiple fractal patterns and slow-light control, properties that cannot be achieved in conventional plasmonic systems. Spin-twistronics creates multiple degrees of freedom to tune nontrivial nanophotonic properties for advances in on-chip information devices, optical manipulation, and chiral light-matter interactions. Twistronics is commonly applied to a twisted bilayer of two-dimensional materials. Here, authors introduce the concepts of twistronics to the superposition of two spin lattices generated from surface plasmon polaritons on a single surface. The system is periodically modulated by its total angular momentum.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Permeability Enhancement by Slow Faulting Under High Pore Fluid Pressure</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119145</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119145</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 06:59:59 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tommaso Mandolini</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zachary Zega</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mark Rivers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenlu Zhu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119145</prism:doi><description>Abstract The morphology of fault zones formed by slow faulting is markedly different from that of brittle faulting. In this study, we quantify the three‐dimensional (3D) pore distribution and permeability structures of two rock samples that have been deformed to failure by slow and brittle faulting, respectively. Our results show that the permeability structure of fault zones varies greatly depending on the faulting mechanism. Fault cores formed by slow faulting exhibit much higher porosity and permeability compared to the surrounding damage zone and wall rocks, unlike those formed through brittle faulting. Since slow slip events associated with high pore fluid pressures are common in active tectonic regions, we propose that slow slip events can serve as a mechanism to maintain the permeable pathways beneath the seismogenic zone, facilitating the movement of mantle‐derived fluids from deep reservoirs toward the surface.
Published: 2026-01-21T06:59:59+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.558 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tommaso Mandolini; Zachary Zega; Mark Rivers; Wenlu Zhu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119145"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119145&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.558 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The morphology of fault zones formed by slow faulting is markedly different from that of brittle faulting. In this study, we quantify the three‐dimensional (3D) pore distribution and permeability structures of two rock samples that have been deformed to failure by slow and brittle faulting, respectively. Our results show that the permeability structure of fault zones varies greatly depending on the faulting mechanism. Fault cores formed by slow faulting exhibit much higher porosity and permeability compared to the surrounding damage zone and wall rocks, unlike those formed through brittle faulting. Since slow slip events associated with high pore fluid pressures are common in active tectonic regions, we propose that slow slip events can serve as a mechanism to maintain the permeable pathways beneath the seismogenic zone, facilitating the movement of mantle‐derived fluids from deep reservoirs toward the surface.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Dynamic redox–promoted iron and nutrient cycling drove graptolite evolution across the Ordovician-Silurian transition</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea1423</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aea1423</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 19:00:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhen Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Caineng Zou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaqiang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aiguo Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weiliang Kong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yijun Xiong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul B. Wignall</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zaicong Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiangkun Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Simon W. Poulton</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aea1423</prism:doi><description>Graptolites were abundant and cosmopolitan zooplankton in Early Paleozoic oceans, but a prominent change in species occurred across the Late Ordovician mass extinction. We use ocean redox, iron isotope (δ 56 Fe), and phosphorus phase partitioning records from shelf and deep-ocean settings to evaluate the drivers behind this major reshaping of the pelagic marine ecosystem. A marked decrease in mesopelagic graptolites coincided with a stepwise negative δ 56 Fe shift on the shelf, driven by partial seawater Fe drawdown resulting from episodic intensification of mid-depth euxinia. Subsequently, a positive δ 56 Fe shift in both deep-ocean and shelf sediments reflects extensive seawater Fe removal during the development of more widespread euxinia. This led to enhanced sedimentary phosphorus recycling from sediments, which ultimately fueled the radiation of epipelagic graptolites. Thus, wide-scale changes in Fe cycling, linking the global oceanic redox state to phosphorus cycling, were ultimately responsible for the initial demise and subsequent radiation of select graptolite species.
Published: 2026-01-21T19:00:26+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.555 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhen Qiu; Caineng Zou; Jiaqiang Zhang; Aiguo Dong; Weiliang Kong; Yijun Xiong; Paul B. Wignall; Ming Li; Zaicong Wang; Xiangkun Zhu; Simon W. Poulton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea1423"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aea1423&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.555 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graptolites were abundant and cosmopolitan zooplankton in Early Paleozoic oceans, but a prominent change in species occurred across the Late Ordovician mass extinction. We use ocean redox, iron isotope (δ 56 Fe), and phosphorus phase partitioning records from shelf and deep-ocean settings to evaluate the drivers behind this major reshaping of the pelagic marine ecosystem. A marked decrease in mesopelagic graptolites coincided with a stepwise negative δ 56 Fe shift on the shelf, driven by partial seawater Fe drawdown resulting from episodic intensification of mid-depth euxinia. Subsequently, a positive δ 56 Fe shift in both deep-ocean and shelf sediments reflects extensive seawater Fe removal during the development of more widespread euxinia. This led to enhanced sedimentary phosphorus recycling from sediments, which ultimately fueled the radiation of epipelagic graptolites. Thus, wide-scale changes in Fe cycling, linking the global oceanic redox state to phosphorus cycling, were ultimately responsible for the initial demise and subsequent radiation of select graptolite species.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Operando nuclear magnetic resonance decodes alkali-tuned proton-electron relay boosting CO2-to-formate conversion</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68604-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68604-z</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 03:33:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yingli Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongchun Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gaocheng Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hang Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haifeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xue-Lu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ye-Feng Yao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68604-z</prism:doi><description>The proton-coupled electron transfer (PCET) kinetics plays a critical role in governing the CO2-to-formate conversion efficiency during CO2 eletroreduction reaction. While alkali metal cations are known to influence the reaction pathway, elucidating how trace doping modifies the catalytic sites remains a key challenge. Here we show that incorporating Li into bismuth oxycarbonate (BOC-Li) induces structural modifications that optimize the PCET process at bismuth-active sites, thereby boosting CO2-to-formate conversion. By employing dual-isotope (2H/13C) operando nuclear magnetic resonance&amp;nbsp;(NMR) to track the formation of 1H13COO−/2H13COO−, combined with kinetic isotope effect, Tafel analysis and in situ attenuated total reflection surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy, we observe a more efficient proton-electron transfer pathway. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations suggest that Li doping is associated with enhanced activity of Bi sites, potentially strengthening H2O/CO2 adsorption and reducing the O–H activation energy. Collectively, this work highlights alkali doping as a promising strategy for structurally engineering catalytic sites to improve PCET kinetics. Understanding how alkali doping promotes CO2 electroreduction is challenging, as tracking proton transfer is difficult. Here, the authors report operando nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy reveals Li doping promotes a proton–electron relay from water, thereby boosting CO2-to-formate conversion.
Published: 2026-01-20T03:33:52+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.555 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yingli Shi; Ying Liu; Hongchun Dong; Gaocheng Fu; Hang Zhou; Haifeng Wang; Xue-Lu Wang; Ye-Feng Yao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68604-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68604-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.555 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proton-coupled electron transfer (PCET) kinetics plays a critical role in governing the CO2-to-formate conversion efficiency during CO2 eletroreduction reaction. While alkali metal cations are known to influence the reaction pathway, elucidating how trace doping modifies the catalytic sites remains a key challenge. Here we show that incorporating Li into bismuth oxycarbonate (BOC-Li) induces structural modifications that optimize the PCET process at bismuth-active sites, thereby boosting CO2-to-formate conversion. By employing dual-isotope (2H/13C) operando nuclear magnetic resonance&amp;amp;nbsp;(NMR) to track the formation of 1H13COO−/2H13COO−, combined with kinetic isotope effect, Tafel analysis and in situ attenuated total reflection surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy, we observe a more efficient proton-electron transfer pathway. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations suggest that Li doping is associated with enhanced activity of Bi sites, potentially strengthening H2O/CO2 adsorption and reducing the O–H activation energy. Collectively, this work highlights alkali doping as a promising strategy for structurally engineering catalytic sites to improve PCET kinetics. Understanding how alkali doping promotes CO2 electroreduction is challenging, as tracking proton transfer is difficult. Here, the authors report operando nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy reveals Li doping promotes a proton–electron relay from water, thereby boosting CO2-to-formate conversion.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Chainmail-inspired conformable and switchable microwave metamaterial absorber</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68694-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68694-9</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 16:05:51 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Ruiyang Tan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jintang Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ping Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68694-9</prism:doi><description>The rigidity of conventional microwave absorbers impedes their reliable integration with complex curved surfaces and deformable components. However, these capabilities remain indispensable for electromagnetic stealth and miniaturized electromagnetic compatibility (EMC) applications that rely on advanced conformal wave-manipulation. To overcome these challenges, we present a chainmail-inspired conformal and switchable microwave metamaterial absorber, conveniently fabricated via 3D printing. The structure exhibits a broadband effective absorption bandwidth (EAB) from 6.2 to 17.6 GHz, while its interlocking topological design enables curvature adaptation without deformation of the absorbing parts. After conformal shaping, the average absorptivity decreases by only 0.049, demonstrating markedly enhanced robustness compared with conventional designs. Furthermore, we integrate the microwave absorber with elastic bands to achieve reversible switching between expanded and contracted states, extending the minimum operating frequency. The optimally configured design achieves a cumulative bandwidth (union of the EABs achieved at 24 cm and 27 cm configurations) from 4.6 to 18 GHz, circumventing the Rozanov limit through dynamic switching. This work provides a practical strategy for realizing switchable ultra-wideband conformal microwave absorbers in diverse electromagnetic applications. Authors present a chainmail-inspired microwave absorber, fabricated via 3D printing, that adapts to complex surfaces with minimal performance degradation. It allows dynamic frequency tuning through structural reconfiguration, providing a combined absorption bandwidth from 4.6 to 18 GHz across different configurations.
Published: 2026-01-20T16:05:51+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.553 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Ruiyang Tan; Jintang Zhou; Ping Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68694-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68694-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.553 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rigidity of conventional microwave absorbers impedes their reliable integration with complex curved surfaces and deformable components. However, these capabilities remain indispensable for electromagnetic stealth and miniaturized electromagnetic compatibility (EMC) applications that rely on advanced conformal wave-manipulation. To overcome these challenges, we present a chainmail-inspired conformal and switchable microwave metamaterial absorber, conveniently fabricated via 3D printing. The structure exhibits a broadband effective absorption bandwidth (EAB) from 6.2 to 17.6 GHz, while its interlocking topological design enables curvature adaptation without deformation of the absorbing parts. After conformal shaping, the average absorptivity decreases by only 0.049, demonstrating markedly enhanced robustness compared with conventional designs. Furthermore, we integrate the microwave absorber with elastic bands to achieve reversible switching between expanded and contracted states, extending the minimum operating frequency. The optimally configured design achieves a cumulative bandwidth (union of the EABs achieved at 24 cm and 27 cm configurations) from 4.6 to 18 GHz, circumventing the Rozanov limit through dynamic switching. This work provides a practical strategy for realizing switchable ultra-wideband conformal microwave absorbers in diverse electromagnetic applications. Authors present a chainmail-inspired microwave absorber, fabricated via 3D printing, that adapts to complex surfaces with minimal performance degradation. It allows dynamic frequency tuning through structural reconfiguration, providing a combined absorption bandwidth from 4.6 to 18 GHz across different configurations.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The contribution of increased global soil salinity to changes in inorganic carbon</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2522643123</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2522643123</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 18:45:37 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiaofang Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xian Xue</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2522643123</prism:doi><description>Soil salinization poses a serious environmental challenge, but the impact of global salinity on SIC (Soil Inorganic Carbon) remains unclear. Using 94,515 samples from 0 to 200 cm depth, combined with subregional classification (such as soil type, land use, climate, geomorphology, and soil texture) which helps address spatial heterogeneity, we obtain relatively accurate global distribution data for EC (Electrical Conductivity) and SIC. EC of 0 to 40 cm layer positively influences SIC in most taxonomic subregions, which may be due to the inorganic CO 2 absorption influenced by pH and salinity. EC of 80 to 100 cm layer sometimes negatively influences SIC due to the increase of soil depth. When EC is below 4 dS/m, EC often positively influences SIC. When EC increases by 2 to 4 dS/m, the mean global SIC in 0 to 20, 20 to 40, and 80 to 100 cm layers increases from 66.15, 78.75, and 117.39 to 174.47 to 190.38, 132.76 to 154.98, and 149.14 to 161.37 g/kg, respectively. The increase is relatively high but similar overall, which deserves high attention. These findings elucidate the dynamics of carbon–salt coupling in the soil–atmosphere–water system, offering pivotal scientific insights for carbon-neutrality strategies.
Published: 2026-01-21T18:45:37+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.539 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiaofang Jiang; Xian Xue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2522643123"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2522643123&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.539 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soil salinization poses a serious environmental challenge, but the impact of global salinity on SIC (Soil Inorganic Carbon) remains unclear. Using 94,515 samples from 0 to 200 cm depth, combined with subregional classification (such as soil type, land use, climate, geomorphology, and soil texture) which helps address spatial heterogeneity, we obtain relatively accurate global distribution data for EC (Electrical Conductivity) and SIC. EC of 0 to 40 cm layer positively influences SIC in most taxonomic subregions, which may be due to the inorganic CO 2 absorption influenced by pH and salinity. EC of 80 to 100 cm layer sometimes negatively influences SIC due to the increase of soil depth. When EC is below 4 dS/m, EC often positively influences SIC. When EC increases by 2 to 4 dS/m, the mean global SIC in 0 to 20, 20 to 40, and 80 to 100 cm layers increases from 66.15, 78.75, and 117.39 to 174.47 to 190.38, 132.76 to 154.98, and 149.14 to 161.37 g/kg, respectively. The increase is relatively high but similar overall, which deserves high attention. These findings elucidate the dynamics of carbon–salt coupling in the soil–atmosphere–water system, offering pivotal scientific insights for carbon-neutrality strategies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Protracted cooling in a long-lived Orosirian orogen: insights from major and trace element diffusion modeling in metamorphic garnet</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02290-w</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02290-w</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 02:10:29 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jia-Hui Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thorsten A. Markmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hugo Dominguez</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinghui Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qian W. L. Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liangliang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guochun Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pierre Lanari</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02290-w</prism:doi><description>Constraining the cooling timescales/rates of metamorphic rocks of orogens is critical for understanding their tectonic settings and geodynamic mechanisms, especially their links to plate tectonics and the formation of the continental lithosphere. The Orosirian period (2.1–1.8 Ga) is characterized by widespread orogenesis and is potentially linked to the onset of global plate tectonics, yet the metamorphic cooling histories of Orosirian orogens remain underexplored. This study applies a dual-constraint diffusion modeling approach, integrating both major (Fe, Mn, Mg, Ca) and trace elements (HREE + Y) in garnet. This is based on multi-mineral microprobe and laser ablation mapping to two metamorphic rocks from the Wutai–Fuping crustal section of the Trans-North China Orogen (TNCO). Sample 20FP09, collected from the Wanzi Supracrustal Rocks, records a two-stage retrograde P–T path: an isothermal decompression (ITD) from the M2 peak (725&amp;nbsp;° C/0.9 GPa) to M3 decompression (725&amp;nbsp;° C/0.6 GPa), followed by isobaric cooling (IBC) to M4 (550&amp;nbsp;° C/0.4 GPa). Sample L17, from the Shizui Subgroup, preserves a single cooling segment from the M2T peak (680&amp;nbsp;° C/0.6 GPa) to M3 (550&amp;nbsp;° C/0.4 GPa). Diffusion modeling using multiple experimental datasets of diffusion coefficients yields an ITD duration of 1–4 Myr and an IBC duration of 11–31 Myr for sample 20FP09, and a single 35–50 Myr cooling interval for sample L17. Together, these results indicate a protracted cooling duration of 13–50 Myr, corresponding to a cooling rate of 2–13&amp;nbsp;° C/Myr for the TNCO. Such rates are significantly slower than those of Phanerozoic orogens (&amp;gt; 100&amp;nbsp;° C/Myr). This implies that Orosirian orogenesis may have involved in prolonged thermal relaxation within a hot, weak Paleoproterozoic lithosphere, likely influenced by higher mantle temperatures and orogenic thermal structures. This study also demonstrates the importance of large datasets containing high spatial element maps for obtaining robust constraints on metamorphic timescales; and offers a first-order empirical estimate of Sc diffusivity in garnet, which remains experimentally unconstrained.
Published: 2026-01-20T02:10:29+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.537 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jia-Hui Liu; Thorsten A. Markmann; Hugo Dominguez; Jinghui Guo; Qian W. L. Zhang; Liangliang Zhang; Guochun Zhao; Pierre Lanari&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02290-w"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02290-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.537 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Constraining the cooling timescales/rates of metamorphic rocks of orogens is critical for understanding their tectonic settings and geodynamic mechanisms, especially their links to plate tectonics and the formation of the continental lithosphere. The Orosirian period (2.1–1.8 Ga) is characterized by widespread orogenesis and is potentially linked to the onset of global plate tectonics, yet the metamorphic cooling histories of Orosirian orogens remain underexplored. This study applies a dual-constraint diffusion modeling approach, integrating both major (Fe, Mn, Mg, Ca) and trace elements (HREE + Y) in garnet. This is based on multi-mineral microprobe and laser ablation mapping to two metamorphic rocks from the Wutai–Fuping crustal section of the Trans-North China Orogen (TNCO). Sample 20FP09, collected from the Wanzi Supracrustal Rocks, records a two-stage retrograde P–T path: an isothermal decompression (ITD) from the M2 peak (725&amp;amp;nbsp;° C/0.9 GPa) to M3 decompression (725&amp;amp;nbsp;° C/0.6 GPa), followed by isobaric cooling (IBC) to M4 (550&amp;amp;nbsp;° C/0.4 GPa). Sample L17, from the Shizui Subgroup, preserves a single cooling segment from the M2T peak (680&amp;amp;nbsp;° C/0.6 GPa) to M3 (550&amp;amp;nbsp;° C/0.4 GPa). Diffusion modeling using multiple experimental datasets of diffusion coefficients yields an ITD duration of 1–4 Myr and an IBC duration of 11–31 Myr for sample 20FP09, and a single 35–50 Myr cooling interval for sample L17. Together, these results indicate a protracted cooling duration of 13–50 Myr, corresponding to a cooling rate of 2–13&amp;amp;nbsp;° C/Myr for the TNCO. Such rates are significantly slower than those of Phanerozoic orogens (&amp;amp;gt; 100&amp;amp;nbsp;° C/Myr). This implies that Orosirian orogenesis may have involved in prolonged thermal relaxation within a hot, weak Paleoproterozoic lithosphere, likely influenced by higher mantle temperatures and orogenic thermal structures. This study also demonstrates the importance of large datasets containing high spatial element maps for obtaining robust constraints on metamorphic timescales; and offers a first-order empirical estimate of Sc diffusivity in garnet, which remains experimentally unconstrained.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>De-coherent parallel laser processing of ultradense nanopores for high-density, large-area 3D optical phase encoding</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67828-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67828-9</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 13:40:34 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhendi Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiacheng Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lijing Zhong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yueqiang Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianrong Qiu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67828-9</prism:doi><description>Single-beam femtosecond laser pulses can surpass the diffraction limit of conventional focusing systems, enabling deep sub-waveguide single-spot modifications via nonlinear absorption at the focus. However, extending this capability to multi-beam parallel processing has been fundamentally limited by the diffraction limit (~λ/2). Herein, we experimentally and theoretically clarify that this limitation stems from spatial coherence and temporal sequence interference, inducing laser-matter interaction crosstalk, non-uniform modifications, and sparse duty-cycle structures. To address this, we propose a de-coherent parallel direct laser writing (Dc-PDLW) strategy, utilizing a patterned single pulse together with a de-coherent holographic algorithm (SSP-BM) to ensure multi-foci polarization orthogonality and eliminate spatial coherence. This method achieves single-shot fabrication of ultra-dense nanopore arrays, with 300 nm (~λ/4) resolution in crystals. We further demonstrate centimeter-scale 3D Pancharatnam–Berry phase plates and voluminous cipher sequences, realizing high-density 3D phase and polarization coding. The authors present a decoherent parallel direct laser writing (Dc-PDLW) strategy that combines a patterned single pulse with a de-coherent hologram algorithm to achieve 300 nm (~λ/4) resolution in crystal, enabling centimeter-scale 3D phase plates and dense 3D phase coding.
Published: 2026-01-20T13:40:34+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.535 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhendi Jiang; Jiacheng Hu; Lijing Zhong; Yueqiang Zhu; Jie Zhang; Wei Zhao; Jianrong Qiu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67828-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67828-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.535 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single-beam femtosecond laser pulses can surpass the diffraction limit of conventional focusing systems, enabling deep sub-waveguide single-spot modifications via nonlinear absorption at the focus. However, extending this capability to multi-beam parallel processing has been fundamentally limited by the diffraction limit (~λ/2). Herein, we experimentally and theoretically clarify that this limitation stems from spatial coherence and temporal sequence interference, inducing laser-matter interaction crosstalk, non-uniform modifications, and sparse duty-cycle structures. To address this, we propose a de-coherent parallel direct laser writing (Dc-PDLW) strategy, utilizing a patterned single pulse together with a de-coherent holographic algorithm (SSP-BM) to ensure multi-foci polarization orthogonality and eliminate spatial coherence. This method achieves single-shot fabrication of ultra-dense nanopore arrays, with 300 nm (~λ/4) resolution in crystals. We further demonstrate centimeter-scale 3D Pancharatnam–Berry phase plates and voluminous cipher sequences, realizing high-density 3D phase and polarization coding. The authors present a decoherent parallel direct laser writing (Dc-PDLW) strategy that combines a patterned single pulse with a de-coherent hologram algorithm to achieve 300 nm (~λ/4) resolution in crystal, enabling centimeter-scale 3D phase plates and dense 3D phase coding.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Extreme barocaloric effect at dissolution</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10013-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-10013-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:02:32 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yifang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhe Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haoyu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wanwu Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoyan Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiayu Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ziqi Guan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shogo Kawaguchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaoxu Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaqing Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Su</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yiming Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Runjian Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yifan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yating Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanxu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianchao Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinlong Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peng Tong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suxin Qian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kuo Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhidong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bing Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-10013-1</prism:doi><description>Refrigeration is indispensable to modern society1, yet the dominant vapour-compression systems rely on environmentally harmful fluorocarbon refrigerants with high global warming potential2–4. Solid-state caloric refrigeration offers a low-carbon alternative5–7, but its practical deployment has been hindered by limited cooling capacity and the inefficient indirect heat transfer that requires secondary fluids. Here we report an extreme barocaloric effect in NH4SCN aqueous solutions enabled by pressure-tuned dissolution and precipitation. This mechanism delivers an exceptionally large cooling capacity and markedly enhanced cooling efficiency. We obtain an in situ temperature drop of 26.8 K in the solution at room temperature, surpassing all known caloric materials. A Carnot-like cycle is designed to deliver 67 J g−1 cooling capacity per cycle with a second-law efficiency of 77%, benefiting from the extremely large temperature drops and direct heat transfer due to the self-circulating aqueous solution. Beyond the phase-transition scenario, this dissolution-based approach that combines the merits of current leading technologies emerges as a promising sustainable refrigeration solution. An extreme barocaloric effect in NH4SCN aqueous solutions is enabled by pressure-induced dissolution and precipitation, but without using a separate heat-transfer liquid.
Published: 2026-01-21T16:02:32+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.535 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kun Zhang; Yifang Liu; Ying Gao; Zhe Zhang; Haoyu Wang; Wanwu Li; Xiaoyan Fan; Jiayu Ding; Ziqi Guan; Shogo Kawaguchi; Zhaoxu Du; Jiaqing Zhang; Lei Su; Yiming Li; Runjian Jiang; Yifan Li; Yating Jia; Yanxu Wang; Jianchao Lin; Jinlong Zhu; Peng Tong; Suxin Qian; Kuo Li; Zhidong Zhang; Bing Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10013-1"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-10013-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.535 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refrigeration is indispensable to modern society1, yet the dominant vapour-compression systems rely on environmentally harmful fluorocarbon refrigerants with high global warming potential2–4. Solid-state caloric refrigeration offers a low-carbon alternative5–7, but its practical deployment has been hindered by limited cooling capacity and the inefficient indirect heat transfer that requires secondary fluids. Here we report an extreme barocaloric effect in NH4SCN aqueous solutions enabled by pressure-tuned dissolution and precipitation. This mechanism delivers an exceptionally large cooling capacity and markedly enhanced cooling efficiency. We obtain an in situ temperature drop of 26.8 K in the solution at room temperature, surpassing all known caloric materials. A Carnot-like cycle is designed to deliver 67 J g−1 cooling capacity per cycle with a second-law efficiency of 77%, benefiting from the extremely large temperature drops and direct heat transfer due to the self-circulating aqueous solution. Beyond the phase-transition scenario, this dissolution-based approach that combines the merits of current leading technologies emerges as a promising sustainable refrigeration solution. An extreme barocaloric effect in NH4SCN aqueous solutions is enabled by pressure-induced dissolution and precipitation, but without using a separate heat-transfer liquid.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Interfacial water regulation on Ru single atoms doped Co3O4 toward efficient electrochemical hydrogenation of quinoxaline</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68740-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68740-6</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 01:46:38 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Linghu Meng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tian-yi Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jilong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengjin Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fengyan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qing Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tong-hui Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongwen Tan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68740-6</prism:doi><description>Electrochemical hydrogenation of quinoxaline presents a promising alternative to traditional methods, yet is suffering from low current density and Faradaic efficiency due to the hampered hydrogenation process. Herein, we develop a cocatalytic system of Ru single atoms doped Co3O4 nanosheet (RuSA/ns-Co3O4) to optimize the interfacial H2O behavior by tuning the Ru single atoms concentration for accelerating the electrochemical hydrogenation of quinoxaline, which enables remarkable Faradaic efficiency of 82% toward 1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquinoxaline at high current density of 200 mA cm-2. Detailed experimental and theoretical studies reveal that Ru single atoms trigger interfacial charge redistribution, inducing an asymmetric local electric field that reconstructs interfacial H2O molecules into an H-down configuration. This reorientation remodels the hydrogen-bonded water network, shortens the distance between hydrogen atoms and the Co3O4 surface, regulates K•H2O availability, and enhances H2O dissociation to supply H*. Consequently, the membrane electrode assembly electrolyser exhibits a long-term stability of &amp;gt;100 h at 200 mA cm-2. Our findings highlight the prospect of interfacial water microenvironment for electrochemical hydrogenation of unsaturated N-heterocyclic compounds, with promising applications for the electrosynthesis of other valuable chemicals. Electrochemical hydrogenation of quinoxaline is a promising alternative to traditional methods but is limited by low current density and Faradaic efficiency. Here, the authors report a Ru&amp;nbsp;single&amp;nbsp;atoms doped Co3O4 nanosheet catalyst that regulates interfacial water to achieve excellent performance.
Published: 2026-01-21T01:46:38+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.532 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Linghu Meng; Tian-yi Dai; Jilong Li; Chengjin Dong; Fengyan Wang; Ming Peng; Qing Jiang; Tong-hui Wang; Yongwen Tan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68740-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68740-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.532 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrochemical hydrogenation of quinoxaline presents a promising alternative to traditional methods, yet is suffering from low current density and Faradaic efficiency due to the hampered hydrogenation process. Herein, we develop a cocatalytic system of Ru single atoms doped Co3O4 nanosheet (RuSA/ns-Co3O4) to optimize the interfacial H2O behavior by tuning the Ru single atoms concentration for accelerating the electrochemical hydrogenation of quinoxaline, which enables remarkable Faradaic efficiency of 82% toward 1,2,3,4-tetrahydroquinoxaline at high current density of 200 mA cm-2. Detailed experimental and theoretical studies reveal that Ru single atoms trigger interfacial charge redistribution, inducing an asymmetric local electric field that reconstructs interfacial H2O molecules into an H-down configuration. This reorientation remodels the hydrogen-bonded water network, shortens the distance between hydrogen atoms and the Co3O4 surface, regulates K•H2O availability, and enhances H2O dissociation to supply H*. Consequently, the membrane electrode assembly electrolyser exhibits a long-term stability of &amp;amp;gt;100 h at 200 mA cm-2. Our findings highlight the prospect of interfacial water microenvironment for electrochemical hydrogenation of unsaturated N-heterocyclic compounds, with promising applications for the electrosynthesis of other valuable chemicals. Electrochemical hydrogenation of quinoxaline is a promising alternative to traditional methods but is limited by low current density and Faradaic efficiency. Here, the authors report a Ru&amp;amp;nbsp;single&amp;amp;nbsp;atoms doped Co3O4 nanosheet catalyst that regulates interfacial water to achieve excellent performance.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Accretion bursts crystallize silicates in a planet-forming disk</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09939-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09939-3</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:02:35 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jeong-Eun Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chul-Hwan Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jaeyeong Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Seokho Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Young-Jun Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Seonjae Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Giseon Baek</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joel D. Green</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gregory J. Herczeg</dc:creator><dc:creator>Doug Johnstone</dc:creator><dc:creator>Klaus M. Pontoppidan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuri Aikawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yao-Lun Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Logan Francis</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mihwa Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hyerin Jang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09939-3</prism:doi><description>Crystalline silicates form at high temperatures (&amp;gt;900 K) (refs. 1,2). Their presence in comets3–6 suggests that high-temperature dust processing occurred in the early Solar System and was subsequently transported outwards to comet-forming regions. However, direct evidence for this crystallization and redistribution in Sun-like protostars has remained unknown. By comparing James Webb Space Telescope mid-infrared spectra of the periodically bursting protostar EC 53 (ref. 7), we detect crystalline silicate (forsterite and enstatite) emission features that appear only during the burst. The emergence of these features indicates active crystal formation by thermal annealing in the hot inner disk during the accretion burst. We also detect a nested outflow—a collimated atomic jet enclosed by slower molecular outflows, consistent with magnetohydrodynamic wind models8. This configuration provides a mechanism for the outward transport of freshly crystallized silicates9. To our knowledge,&amp;nbsp;our results provide the first direct observational evidence of in situ silicate crystallization during episodic accretion bursts in a very young star still embedded in its dense envelope. Although we do not directly detect grains transported to the outer disk, the observed trends are consistent with outward redistribution, indicating that both dust processing and transport occur during the earliest and most dynamic stages of star formation. The detection of forsterite and enstatite emissions in EC 53 during accretion bursts marks one of the first pieces of&amp;nbsp;direct evidence of in situ silicate crystallization in young stars.
Published: 2026-01-21T16:02:35+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.532 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jeong-Eun Lee; Chul-Hwan Kim; Jaeyeong Kim; Seokho Lee; Young-Jun Kim; Seonjae Lee; Giseon Baek; Joel D. Green; Gregory J. Herczeg; Doug Johnstone; Klaus M. Pontoppidan; Yuri Aikawa; Yao-Lun Yang; Logan Francis; Mihwa Jin; Hyerin Jang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09939-3"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09939-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.532 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crystalline silicates form at high temperatures (&amp;amp;gt;900 K) (refs. 1,2). Their presence in comets3–6 suggests that high-temperature dust processing occurred in the early Solar System and was subsequently transported outwards to comet-forming regions. However, direct evidence for this crystallization and redistribution in Sun-like protostars has remained unknown. By comparing James Webb Space Telescope mid-infrared spectra of the periodically bursting protostar EC 53 (ref. 7), we detect crystalline silicate (forsterite and enstatite) emission features that appear only during the burst. The emergence of these features indicates active crystal formation by thermal annealing in the hot inner disk during the accretion burst. We also detect a nested outflow—a collimated atomic jet enclosed by slower molecular outflows, consistent with magnetohydrodynamic wind models8. This configuration provides a mechanism for the outward transport of freshly crystallized silicates9. To our knowledge,&amp;amp;nbsp;our results provide the first direct observational evidence of in situ silicate crystallization during episodic accretion bursts in a very young star still embedded in its dense envelope. Although we do not directly detect grains transported to the outer disk, the observed trends are consistent with outward redistribution, indicating that both dust processing and transport occur during the earliest and most dynamic stages of star formation. The detection of forsterite and enstatite emissions in EC 53 during accretion bursts marks one of the first pieces of&amp;amp;nbsp;direct evidence of in situ silicate crystallization in young stars.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Electrochemical C–N coupling via adsorption modulation: selective synthesis of amines from biomass-derived 5-hydroxymethylfurfural</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68734-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68734-4</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 11:37:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Dingbo Lai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zi-Ang Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaolin Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chaoxi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junqing Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tuo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi-Jian Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinlong Gong</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68734-4</prism:doi><description>The electrochemical C–N coupling of biomass-derived 5-hydroxymethylfurfural (HMF) with methylamine offers a promising sustainable route to value-added amines. However, achieving high selectivity remains challenging due to competing side reactions, including C = O hydrogenation and C–C dimerization. This paper describes tailoring the surface structure of Ag catalysts to modulate HMF adsorption and intermediate hydrogenation behavior and thus&amp;nbsp;enhancing C–N coupling selectivity. Ag nanoparticles, predominantly exposing the (111) facet, exhibit higher selectivity compared with Ag nanocubes mainly enclosed by (100) planes. The Ag(111) facet favors the C–N coupling pathway by regulating both adsorption geometry and hydrogenation ability. In-situ Raman spectroscopy and density functional theory (DFT) calculations reveal that an η1(C)-aldehyde adsorption configuration, dominant on Ag(111), enhances carbonyl electrophilicity and facilitates C = O polarization, promoting nucleophilic attack by methylamine. In contrast, the η2(C,O)–aldehyde configuration, more common on Ag (100), stabilizes the C = O bond, limiting its reactivity. Moreover, Ag(111) shows enhanced imine hydrogenation activity, further improving amine selectivity. This study highlights the significance of facet-dependent adsorption modulation in steering reaction pathways and advancing sustainable electrochemical synthesis. Electrochemical C–N coupling of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural with methylamine offers a sustainable route to produce value-added amines. Here, the authors present a facet-controlled Ag catalyst that tunes the substrate adsorption geometry and hydrogenation propensity for promoted selectivity.
Published: 2026-01-21T11:37:14+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.527 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Dingbo Lai; Jia Yu; Zi-Ang Ma; Xiaolin Ye; Chaoxi Wang; Junqing Zhang; Tuo Wang; Zhi-Jian Zhao; Peng Zhang; Jinlong Gong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68734-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68734-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.527 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The electrochemical C–N coupling of biomass-derived 5-hydroxymethylfurfural (HMF) with methylamine offers a promising sustainable route to value-added amines. However, achieving high selectivity remains challenging due to competing side reactions, including C = O hydrogenation and C–C dimerization. This paper describes tailoring the surface structure of Ag catalysts to modulate HMF adsorption and intermediate hydrogenation behavior and thus&amp;amp;nbsp;enhancing C–N coupling selectivity. Ag nanoparticles, predominantly exposing the (111) facet, exhibit higher selectivity compared with Ag nanocubes mainly enclosed by (100) planes. The Ag(111) facet favors the C–N coupling pathway by regulating both adsorption geometry and hydrogenation ability. In-situ Raman spectroscopy and density functional theory (DFT) calculations reveal that an η1(C)-aldehyde adsorption configuration, dominant on Ag(111), enhances carbonyl electrophilicity and facilitates C = O polarization, promoting nucleophilic attack by methylamine. In contrast, the η2(C,O)–aldehyde configuration, more common on Ag (100), stabilizes the C = O bond, limiting its reactivity. Moreover, Ag(111) shows enhanced imine hydrogenation activity, further improving amine selectivity. This study highlights the significance of facet-dependent adsorption modulation in steering reaction pathways and advancing sustainable electrochemical synthesis. Electrochemical C–N coupling of 5-hydroxymethylfurfural with methylamine offers a sustainable route to produce value-added amines. Here, the authors present a facet-controlled Ag catalyst that tunes the substrate adsorption geometry and hydrogenation propensity for promoted selectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Flexible light-emitting diodes with EQE approaching 26.4% from horizontal dipole-oriented metal nanoclusters</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67737-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67737-x</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 10:02:42 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhenyu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingguo Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guizhong Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenwu Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengyu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tianqi Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenyu Ji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fujun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhennan Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xue Bai</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67737-x</prism:doi><description>Metal nanoclusters, as unique metallic molecules comprising a few to hundreds of metal atoms and stabilized by organic monolayer ligands, have recently emerged as a novel class of chromophores and hold great promise for flexible light-emitting diodes. However, the fabrication of flexible metal nanoclusters-based light-emitting diodes is still hindered by low photoluminescence quantum yields, suboptimal solution processability, and consequently compromised emitter-film quality with random dipole orientations. This work addresses these limitations through strategic molecular engineering by employing 1, 3-di(9H-carbazol-9-yl)benzene as a π-conjugated mediator. This approach enables supramolecular assembly to achieve π-π coupling-mediated horizontal dipole alignment in nanocluster solid films, allowing an external quantum efficiency of up to 26.4% in flexible light-emitting diodes with a maximum brightness of 41,365 cd m−2, and retaining more than 94% of initial efficiency after 2000 bending cycles at 3 mm curvature radius. Metal nanoclusters are promising for flexible light-emitting diodes but face efficiency and stability challenges. Here, the authors employ a π-conjugated mediator to align dipole alignment, yielding devices with 26.4% external quantum efficiency and 94% efficiency retention after 2000 bending cycles.
Published: 2026-01-21T10:02:42+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.527 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhenyu Wang; Yingguo Yang; Guizhong Luo; Wenwu Xu; Chengyu Liu; Tianqi Yang; Wenyu Ji; Fujun Zhang; Min Lu; Yu Zhang; Zhennan Wu; Xue Bai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67737-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67737-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.527 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metal nanoclusters, as unique metallic molecules comprising a few to hundreds of metal atoms and stabilized by organic monolayer ligands, have recently emerged as a novel class of chromophores and hold great promise for flexible light-emitting diodes. However, the fabrication of flexible metal nanoclusters-based light-emitting diodes is still hindered by low photoluminescence quantum yields, suboptimal solution processability, and consequently compromised emitter-film quality with random dipole orientations. This work addresses these limitations through strategic molecular engineering by employing 1, 3-di(9H-carbazol-9-yl)benzene as a π-conjugated mediator. This approach enables supramolecular assembly to achieve π-π coupling-mediated horizontal dipole alignment in nanocluster solid films, allowing an external quantum efficiency of up to 26.4% in flexible light-emitting diodes with a maximum brightness of 41,365 cd m−2, and retaining more than 94% of initial efficiency after 2000 bending cycles at 3 mm curvature radius. Metal nanoclusters are promising for flexible light-emitting diodes but face efficiency and stability challenges. Here, the authors employ a π-conjugated mediator to align dipole alignment, yielding devices with 26.4% external quantum efficiency and 94% efficiency retention after 2000 bending cycles.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Age and Composition of the Voyager Seamounts: Evidence for a Long‐Lived Marquesas Mantle Source</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gc012650</link><guid>10.1029/2025gc012650</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 14:01:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Andrea Balbas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hannah Paradis</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kevin Konrad</dc:creator><dc:creator>Valerie A. Finlayson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael Bizimis</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stephanie Anderson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher Kelley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicole A. Raineault</dc:creator><dc:creator>Beth N. Orcutt</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gc012650</prism:doi><description>Abstract We present new observations on the dynamics and locations of deep mantle reservoirs derived from the ages and compositions of Voyager Seamount Chain lava flows. The previously unexplored Voyager Seamount Chain trends NW–SE between the Mid‐Pacific Mountains and the Northwestern Hawaiian Ridge. Volcanic samples were recovered from the chain during the Ocean Exploration Trust expedition NA134. The lava flows are alkalic to highly alkalic in composition. Ages ranged from 81 to 86 Ma ( n = 8), with the oldest ages in the NW and an age‐progression toward the SE. The Voyager age‐progression continues southward through the Northern Line Islands region until at least 69 Ma. Mantle flowlines using absolute plate motion models indicate that the Voyagers were emplaced near the modern Marquesas Hotspot location approximately 86–69 Ma. The Sr‐Nd‐Pb‐Hf isotope systematics show the influence of an EMII component and overlap the compositions of Pliocene volcanism from the Marquesas Islands, consistent with the plate motion age model. These data imply a long‐lived plume as the source of the Voyager seamounts and the Marquesas. However, the lack of a clear and continuous seamount chain between the 86–69 Ma Voyager Seamount Chain and the 6–0 Ma Marquesas Islands implies that the mantle plume displays variable buoyancy flux over time. The surface expression of this mantle reservoir experienced a potential hiatus of up to ∼60 m.y. These new data indicate that the mantle beneath the Marquesas Islands region has been discontinuously producing age‐progressive, EMII‐like hotspot volcanism since at least the Late Cretaceous.
Published: 2026-01-21T14:01:26+00:00
Venue: Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems
Score: 0.526 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Andrea Balbas; Hannah Paradis; Kevin Konrad; Valerie A. Finlayson; Michael Bizimis; Stephanie Anderson; Christopher Kelley; Nicole A. Raineault; Beth N. Orcutt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gc012650"&gt;10.1029/2025gc012650&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.526 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract We present new observations on the dynamics and locations of deep mantle reservoirs derived from the ages and compositions of Voyager Seamount Chain lava flows. The previously unexplored Voyager Seamount Chain trends NW–SE between the Mid‐Pacific Mountains and the Northwestern Hawaiian Ridge. Volcanic samples were recovered from the chain during the Ocean Exploration Trust expedition NA134. The lava flows are alkalic to highly alkalic in composition. Ages ranged from 81 to 86 Ma ( n = 8), with the oldest ages in the NW and an age‐progression toward the SE. The Voyager age‐progression continues southward through the Northern Line Islands region until at least 69 Ma. Mantle flowlines using absolute plate motion models indicate that the Voyagers were emplaced near the modern Marquesas Hotspot location approximately 86–69 Ma. The Sr‐Nd‐Pb‐Hf isotope systematics show the influence of an EMII component and overlap the compositions of Pliocene volcanism from the Marquesas Islands, consistent with the plate motion age model. These data imply a long‐lived plume as the source of the Voyager seamounts and the Marquesas. However, the lack of a clear and continuous seamount chain between the 86–69 Ma Voyager Seamount Chain and the 6–0 Ma Marquesas Islands implies that the mantle plume displays variable buoyancy flux over time. The surface expression of this mantle reservoir experienced a potential hiatus of up to ∼60 m.y. These new data indicate that the mantle beneath the Marquesas Islands region has been discontinuously producing age‐progressive, EMII‐like hotspot volcanism since at least the Late Cretaceous.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Relatively warm deep-water formation persisted in the Last Glacial Maximum</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10012-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-10012-2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 16:02:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jack H. Wharton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emilia Kozikowska</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lloyd D. Keigwin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas M. Marchitto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mark A. Maslin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin Ziegler</dc:creator><dc:creator>David J. R. Thornalley</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-10012-2</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Last Glacial Maximum (19–23 thousand years ago) was characterized by low greenhouse gas concentrations and continental ice sheets that covered large parts of North America and Europe 1 . Glacial climate was therefore very different, with colder global mean temperatures and an increased Equator-to-pole temperature gradient, probably resulting in stronger westerlies 2 . However, the state of the deep North Atlantic Ocean under these glacial climate forcings remains uncertain 3–6 , particularly owing to the rarity of deep-ocean temperature and salinity constraints. Here we show that the temperature of the glacial deep (&gt;1.5 km) Northwest Atlantic was approximately 0–2 °C (only 1.8 ± 0.5 °C (2 s.e.) colder than today), and, after accounting for the whole-ocean change, seawater δ 18 O was 0.3 ± 0.1‰ (2 s.e.) higher and can be traced back to the surface subtropics via the subpolar Northeast Atlantic and Nordic Seas. Together, our hydrographic data reveal the thermal and isotopic structure of the deep Northwest Atlantic and suggest sustained production of relatively warm and probably salty North Atlantic Deep Water during the Last Glacial Maximum. Furthermore, our results provide updated constraints for benchmarking Earth system models used to project future climate change.
Published: 2026-01-21T16:02:50+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.523 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jack H. Wharton; Emilia Kozikowska; Lloyd D. Keigwin; Thomas M. Marchitto; Mark A. Maslin; Martin Ziegler; David J. R. Thornalley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-10012-2"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-10012-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.523 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Last Glacial Maximum (19–23 thousand years ago) was characterized by low greenhouse gas concentrations and continental ice sheets that covered large parts of North America and Europe 1 . Glacial climate was therefore very different, with colder global mean temperatures and an increased Equator-to-pole temperature gradient, probably resulting in stronger westerlies 2 . However, the state of the deep North Atlantic Ocean under these glacial climate forcings remains uncertain 3–6 , particularly owing to the rarity of deep-ocean temperature and salinity constraints. Here we show that the temperature of the glacial deep (&amp;gt;1.5 km) Northwest Atlantic was approximately 0–2 °C (only 1.8 ± 0.5 °C (2 s.e.) colder than today), and, after accounting for the whole-ocean change, seawater δ 18 O was 0.3 ± 0.1‰ (2 s.e.) higher and can be traced back to the surface subtropics via the subpolar Northeast Atlantic and Nordic Seas. Together, our hydrographic data reveal the thermal and isotopic structure of the deep Northwest Atlantic and suggest sustained production of relatively warm and probably salty North Atlantic Deep Water during the Last Glacial Maximum. Furthermore, our results provide updated constraints for benchmarking Earth system models used to project future climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Silicic magma reservoir anisotropy persists through protracted crystallization and low strain rates</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03214-7</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03214-7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:05:03 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Wenkai Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brandon Schmandt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Justin Wilgus</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fan-Chi Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ross Maguire</dc:creator><dc:creator>Julien Chaput</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03214-7</prism:doi><description>Magma reservoir organization is hidden from view but important to systematic understanding of active volcanoes and intrusive igneous rocks. Seismic anisotropy in active silicic reservoirs suggests horizontally elongated melt sheets or sills, but it remains unclear if shallow silicic reservoirs in low strain rate settings without recent recharge maintain similar organization. Here we present new 3-D seismic tomography of the upper crustal reservoir beneath the tectonically quiescent Valles Caldera using dense nodal arrays. Results reveal &amp;gt;15% radial anisotropy consistent with up to 17-24% melt in horizontally elongated volumes interspersed with melt-poor layers, despite net crystallization since about 0.5 Ma and little contemporary strain. Structural similarity of Valles Caldera to more dynamic modern systems indicates that intrinsic reservoir processes like iterative magma injection, crystal settling, and melt compaction organize long-lived horizontally-layered structure, largely independent of tectonic setting and recharge rate. A partially molten sill-complex structure is found within the slowly crystallizing and tectonically quiet magma reservoir beneath Valles Caldera using anisotropic Rayleigh and Love wave tomography.
Published: 2026-01-21T13:05:03+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.520 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Wenkai Song; Brandon Schmandt; Justin Wilgus; Fan-Chi Lin; Ross Maguire; Julien Chaput&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03214-7"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03214-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.520 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magma reservoir organization is hidden from view but important to systematic understanding of active volcanoes and intrusive igneous rocks. Seismic anisotropy in active silicic reservoirs suggests horizontally elongated melt sheets or sills, but it remains unclear if shallow silicic reservoirs in low strain rate settings without recent recharge maintain similar organization. Here we present new 3-D seismic tomography of the upper crustal reservoir beneath the tectonically quiescent Valles Caldera using dense nodal arrays. Results reveal &amp;amp;gt;15% radial anisotropy consistent with up to 17-24% melt in horizontally elongated volumes interspersed with melt-poor layers, despite net crystallization since about 0.5 Ma and little contemporary strain. Structural similarity of Valles Caldera to more dynamic modern systems indicates that intrinsic reservoir processes like iterative magma injection, crystal settling, and melt compaction organize long-lived horizontally-layered structure, largely independent of tectonic setting and recharge rate. A partially molten sill-complex structure is found within the slowly crystallizing and tectonically quiet magma reservoir beneath Valles Caldera using anisotropic Rayleigh and Love wave tomography.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Quantum Hall effect at 0.002 T in graphene</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68695-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68695-8</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 17:14:54 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Alexander S. Mayorov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ping Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaokai Yue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Biao Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianhong He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Di Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fuzhuo Lian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Siqi Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiabei Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zihao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qian Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kenji Watanabe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takashi Taniguchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Renjun Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rui Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Baigeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kostya S. Novoselov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Geliang Yu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68695-8</prism:doi><description>Graphene enables precise carrier-density control via gating, making it an ideal platform for studying electronic interactions. However, sample inhomogeneities often limit access to the low-density regimes where these interactions dominate. Enhancing carrier mobility is therefore crucial for exploring fundamental properties and developing device applications. Here, we demonstrate a significant reduction in external inhomogeneity using a double-layer graphene architecture separated by an ultra-thin hexagonal boron nitride layer. Mutual screening between the layers reduces scattering from random Coulomb potentials, resulting in a quantum mobility exceeding $$1{0}^{7}{{m{c}}}{{{m{m}}}}^{2}{{{m{V}}}}^{-1}{{{m{s}}}}^{-1}$$. Shubnikov–de Haas oscillations emerge at magnetic fields below 1 mT, while integer quantum Hall features are observed at 0.002 T. Furthermore, we identify a fractional quantum Hall plateau at a filling factor of $${v}_{{{m{tot}}}}=-10/3$$ at 2 T. These results demonstrate the platform’s suitability for investigating strongly correlated electronic phases in graphene-based heterostructures. Enhancing the carrier mobility of graphene can enable the investigation of its fundamental properties and promote device applications. Here, the authors report the fabrication of double-layer graphene devices with a quantum mobility up to 107 cm2V−1s−1 and integer quantum Hall features at magnetic fields as low as 0.002 T.
Published: 2026-01-21T17:14:54+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.520 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Alexander S. Mayorov; Ping Wang; Xiaokai Yue; Biao Wu; Jianhong He; Di Zhang; Fuzhuo Lian; Siqi Jiang; Jiabei Huang; Zihao Wang; Qian Guo; Kenji Watanabe; Takashi Taniguchi; Renjun Du; Rui Wang; Baigeng Wang; Lei Wang; Kostya S. Novoselov; Geliang Yu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68695-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68695-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.520 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graphene enables precise carrier-density control via gating, making it an ideal platform for studying electronic interactions. However, sample inhomogeneities often limit access to the low-density regimes where these interactions dominate. Enhancing carrier mobility is therefore crucial for exploring fundamental properties and developing device applications. Here, we demonstrate a significant reduction in external inhomogeneity using a double-layer graphene architecture separated by an ultra-thin hexagonal boron nitride layer. Mutual screening between the layers reduces scattering from random Coulomb potentials, resulting in a quantum mobility exceeding $$1{0}^{7}{{m{c}}}{{{m{m}}}}^{2}{{{m{V}}}}^{-1}{{{m{s}}}}^{-1}$$. Shubnikov–de Haas oscillations emerge at magnetic fields below 1 mT, while integer quantum Hall features are observed at 0.002 T. Furthermore, we identify a fractional quantum Hall plateau at a filling factor of $${v}_{{{m{tot}}}}=-10/3$$ at 2 T. These results demonstrate the platform’s suitability for investigating strongly correlated electronic phases in graphene-based heterostructures. Enhancing the carrier mobility of graphene can enable the investigation of its fundamental properties and promote device applications. Here, the authors report the fabrication of double-layer graphene devices with a quantum mobility up to 107 cm2V−1s−1 and integer quantum Hall features at magnetic fields as low as 0.002 T.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Photovoltaic nanoassembly of nanowire arrays sensitized with colloidal nanocrystals for near-infrared retina photostimulation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea7001</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aea7001</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 19:00:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tarik S. Kaya</dc:creator><dc:creator>Humeyra N. Kaleli</dc:creator><dc:creator>Antoine Chaffiol</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrea Corna</dc:creator><dc:creator>Corentin Joffrois</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ridvan Balamur</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ugur B. Caliskan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Asim Onal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cigdem Pehlivan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eren Tekinay</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alp Yilmaz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Roya Mohajeri</dc:creator><dc:creator>Arif E. Cetin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Günther Zeck</dc:creator><dc:creator>Serge Picaud</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sedat Nizamoglu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aea7001</prism:doi><description>Nanowires have served as a transformative platform for advanced neural and tissue interfaces. While their photovoltaic properties hold exceptional promise for neural modulation, existing photostimulation approaches predominantly rely on visible light–activated photoelectrochemical mechanisms. Here, we present a solution-processed photovoltaic nanoassembly comprising a ZnO nanowire array sensitized with AgBiS 2 nanocrystals that enables efficient near-infrared (NIR) neural stimulation through capacitive photocurrents. By optimizing nanowire morphology and nanocrystal interdigitation, the platform achieves high charge injection densities (tens of microcoulombs per square centimeter) at low NIR intensities (
Published: 2026-01-21T19:00:26+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.516 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tarik S. Kaya; Humeyra N. Kaleli; Antoine Chaffiol; Andrea Corna; Corentin Joffrois; Ridvan Balamur; Ugur B. Caliskan; Asim Onal; Cigdem Pehlivan; Eren Tekinay; Alp Yilmaz; Roya Mohajeri; Arif E. Cetin; Günther Zeck; Serge Picaud; Sedat Nizamoglu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea7001"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aea7001&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.516 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nanowires have served as a transformative platform for advanced neural and tissue interfaces. While their photovoltaic properties hold exceptional promise for neural modulation, existing photostimulation approaches predominantly rely on visible light–activated photoelectrochemical mechanisms. Here, we present a solution-processed photovoltaic nanoassembly comprising a ZnO nanowire array sensitized with AgBiS 2 nanocrystals that enables efficient near-infrared (NIR) neural stimulation through capacitive photocurrents. By optimizing nanowire morphology and nanocrystal interdigitation, the platform achieves high charge injection densities (tens of microcoulombs per square centimeter) at low NIR intensities (&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Wafer-scale high-κ HfO2 dielectric films with sub-5-Å equivalent oxide thickness for 2D MoS2 transistors</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68584-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68584-0</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jan 2026 11:06:03 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Songge Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hua Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiuzhen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenyang Cui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuchao Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hailing Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuopei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongfeng Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liangfeng Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liqi Bai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Su Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cheng Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luojun Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongxia Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lede Xian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoming Tao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang Chai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Na Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guangyu Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68584-0</prism:doi><description>High-κ gate dielectrics are indispensable in modern transistor technology and play a pivotal role in efficient capacitive gating and suppression of leakage currents. However, the realization of industry-compatible high-κ gate dielectrics at a sub-5-Å equivalent oxide thickness (EOT) remains challenging. Here we report the realization of 1.3-nm thick hafnium oxide (HfO2) dielectrics via an industry-compatible multiple oxidation atomic layer deposition process at 200 °C. A low EOT down to 2.5 Å is demonstrated for 1.3-nm thick HfO2 dielectrics on metal gates with a low leakage current of 10−6 A/cm2 and a robust breakdown electric field of ~22.3 MV/cm. Remarkably, such low EOT high-κ/metal gates can be directly implanted into emerging two-dimensional (2D) transistors and low-power logic circuits on 8-inch wafer scale to showcase their potentials. The as-fabricated molybdenum disulfide (MoS2) transistors exhibit a large on-state current density of 260 µA/µm at source-drain bias of 0.5 V, a high on/off ratio of 108, an average subthreshold slope (SS) of 75 mV/dec, and small capacitance equivalent thickness (CET) values of 0.34 nm for gate-first transistors and 0.50 nm for gate-last transistors. Our ultra-scaled dielectrics hold significant promise for advanced semiconductor fabrication processes towards the angstrom era. The integration of high-κ dielectrics with low equivalent oxide thickness (EOT) is crucial for the development of 2D transistors. Here, the authors report the low-temperature fabrication of wafer-scale HfO2 dielectric films with sub-5-Å EOT and their application for the realization of high-performance 2D MoS2 transistors and circuits.
Published: 2026-01-20T11:06:03+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.516 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Songge Zhang; Tao Zhang; Hua Yu; Tong Li; Xiuzhen Li; Chenyang Cui; Yuchao Zhou; Hailing Guo; Shuopei Wang; Dongfeng Zheng; Liangfeng Huang; Liqi Bai; Su Liu; Cheng Shen; Wei Yang; Luojun Du; Dongxia Shi; Lede Xian; Xiaoming Tao; Yang Chai; Na Li; Guangyu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68584-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68584-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.516 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-κ gate dielectrics are indispensable in modern transistor technology and play a pivotal role in efficient capacitive gating and suppression of leakage currents. However, the realization of industry-compatible high-κ gate dielectrics at a sub-5-Å equivalent oxide thickness (EOT) remains challenging. Here we report the realization of 1.3-nm thick hafnium oxide (HfO2) dielectrics via an industry-compatible multiple oxidation atomic layer deposition process at 200 °C. A low EOT down to 2.5 Å is demonstrated for 1.3-nm thick HfO2 dielectrics on metal gates with a low leakage current of 10−6 A/cm2 and a robust breakdown electric field of ~22.3 MV/cm. Remarkably, such low EOT high-κ/metal gates can be directly implanted into emerging two-dimensional (2D) transistors and low-power logic circuits on 8-inch wafer scale to showcase their potentials. The as-fabricated molybdenum disulfide (MoS2) transistors exhibit a large on-state current density of 260 µA/µm at source-drain bias of 0.5 V, a high on/off ratio of 108, an average subthreshold slope (SS) of 75 mV/dec, and small capacitance equivalent thickness (CET) values of 0.34 nm for gate-first transistors and 0.50 nm for gate-last transistors. Our ultra-scaled dielectrics hold significant promise for advanced semiconductor fabrication processes towards the angstrom era. The integration of high-κ dielectrics with low equivalent oxide thickness (EOT) is crucial for the development of 2D transistors. Here, the authors report the low-temperature fabrication of wafer-scale HfO2 dielectric films with sub-5-Å EOT and their application for the realization of high-performance 2D MoS2 transistors and circuits.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>