<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 23:33:10 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Unveiling the metallogenic continuum of an Archean craton</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68507-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68507-z</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:54:47 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Matthew Demmer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Isra Ezad</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marco Fiorentini</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68507-z</prism:doi><description>The synchronous formation between 2675–2655 Ma of hydrothermal gold mineralisation in the Kalgoorlie and Kurnalpi Terranes and of magmatic sulfide mineralisation enriched in nickel, copper and platinum-group elements in the South West Terrane of the Archean Yilgarn Craton of Western Australia offers key insights into first-order controls on the genesis of mineral systems. Here we show that hydrothermal and magmatic deposits formed on opposite sides of this craton share four key features: timing, enrichment in incompatible chalcophile elements, positive Δ³³S sulfur isotope signatures, and links to hydrous, metasomatised lithospheric mantle. These commonalities challenge conventional models that treat such mineralised systems as unrelated. Instead, they point to a shared origin: a fertile lithospheric mantle reservoir enriched by crustal recycling, which was subsequently tapped to generate magmas and fluids anomalously endowed in volatiles and metals that migrated through the overlying lithosphere, punctually triggering ore formation. These findings support a unified mineral system model in which mantle processes exert a first-order control over metal endowment of Archean cratons. Conventional models treat hydrothermal gold and magmatic sulfide systems as unrelated. Here, the authors show that coeval deposits share isotopic and metal signatures, implying a common origin from a hydrous, fertile lithospheric mantle that has been modified by crustal recycling.
Published: 2026-01-16T17:54:47+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.711 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Matthew Demmer; Isra Ezad; Marco Fiorentini&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68507-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68507-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.711 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The synchronous formation between 2675–2655 Ma of hydrothermal gold mineralisation in the Kalgoorlie and Kurnalpi Terranes and of magmatic sulfide mineralisation enriched in nickel, copper and platinum-group elements in the South West Terrane of the Archean Yilgarn Craton of Western Australia offers key insights into first-order controls on the genesis of mineral systems. Here we show that hydrothermal and magmatic deposits formed on opposite sides of this craton share four key features: timing, enrichment in incompatible chalcophile elements, positive Δ³³S sulfur isotope signatures, and links to hydrous, metasomatised lithospheric mantle. These commonalities challenge conventional models that treat such mineralised systems as unrelated. Instead, they point to a shared origin: a fertile lithospheric mantle reservoir enriched by crustal recycling, which was subsequently tapped to generate magmas and fluids anomalously endowed in volatiles and metals that migrated through the overlying lithosphere, punctually triggering ore formation. These findings support a unified mineral system model in which mantle processes exert a first-order control over metal endowment of Archean cratons. Conventional models treat hydrothermal gold and magmatic sulfide systems as unrelated. Here, the authors show that coeval deposits share isotopic and metal signatures, implying a common origin from a hydrous, fertile lithospheric mantle that has been modified by crustal recycling.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Trace Element and Isotopic Evolution of the Lunar Interior During Magma Ocean Solidification, Cumulate Overturn, and Subsequent Melting: Insights Into Lunar Melt Sources</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2024je008865</link><guid>10.1029/2024je008865</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 02:21:04 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>J. L. Scholpp</dc:creator><dc:creator>N. Dygert</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2024je008865</prism:doi><description>Abstract The solidification of a lunar magma ocean (LMO) after a giant impact event formed the Moon's gravitationally unstable juvenile mantle. Hybridization of the lunar mantle during the overturn of late‐crystallized Fe‐ and Ti‐rich ilmenite‐bearing cumulates (IBC) in the lunar interior is required to explain the variable TiO 2 and Rare Earth Element (REE) abundances of lunar basalts and picritic melts. We model chemical fractionation during LMO solidification, mantle hybridization, and partial melting of hybridized and unhybridized cumulates to evaluate the formation of lunar picritic glasses. Solidification models indicate that &gt;65% of the plagioclase formed during LMO solidification must be removed by flotation to explain negative Eu anomalies exhibited by lunar picritic glasses. Melting models demonstrate that unhybridized cumulates could produce low‐Ti picritic glasses but not Ti enriched glasses. Post‐hybridization melting models demonstrate that hybridized garnet‐free sources can generate elemental ratios of most Ti enriched picritic glasses. The heavy rare earth element depleted compositions of some orange picritic glasses require a ∼0.25–5% garnet component in the downwelling IBC or hybridized sources. If the LMO extends to the core‐mantle boundary, cumulate overturn is likely required for garnet to form in the lunar mantle. Isotopic models indicate that the Nd and Hf trends of lunar basalt sources reflect primary lunar differentiation processes coupled with post differentiation hybridization. The combined elemental and isotopic characteristics of Ti enriched picritic glasses and basalts are strong evidence of cumulate overturn during early lunar differentiation.
Published: 2026-01-17T02:21:04+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets
Score: 0.569 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; J. L. Scholpp; N. Dygert&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2024je008865"&gt;10.1029/2024je008865&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.569 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The solidification of a lunar magma ocean (LMO) after a giant impact event formed the Moon&amp;#x27;s gravitationally unstable juvenile mantle. Hybridization of the lunar mantle during the overturn of late‐crystallized Fe‐ and Ti‐rich ilmenite‐bearing cumulates (IBC) in the lunar interior is required to explain the variable TiO 2 and Rare Earth Element (REE) abundances of lunar basalts and picritic melts. We model chemical fractionation during LMO solidification, mantle hybridization, and partial melting of hybridized and unhybridized cumulates to evaluate the formation of lunar picritic glasses. Solidification models indicate that &amp;gt;65% of the plagioclase formed during LMO solidification must be removed by flotation to explain negative Eu anomalies exhibited by lunar picritic glasses. Melting models demonstrate that unhybridized cumulates could produce low‐Ti picritic glasses but not Ti enriched glasses. Post‐hybridization melting models demonstrate that hybridized garnet‐free sources can generate elemental ratios of most Ti enriched picritic glasses. The heavy rare earth element depleted compositions of some orange picritic glasses require a ∼0.25–5% garnet component in the downwelling IBC or hybridized sources. If the LMO extends to the core‐mantle boundary, cumulate overturn is likely required for garnet to form in the lunar mantle. Isotopic models indicate that the Nd and Hf trends of lunar basalt sources reflect primary lunar differentiation processes coupled with post differentiation hybridization. The combined elemental and isotopic characteristics of Ti enriched picritic glasses and basalts are strong evidence of cumulate overturn during early lunar differentiation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Spin-state engineering of single titanium adsorbates on ultrathin magnesium oxide</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68314-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68314-6</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 11:17:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Soo-hyon Phark</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong Thi Bui</dc:creator><dc:creator>We-hyo Seo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yaowu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Valeria Sheina</dc:creator><dc:creator>Curie Lee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christoph Wolf</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andreas J. Heinrich</dc:creator><dc:creator>Roberto Robles</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicolás Lorente</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68314-6</prism:doi><description>Single atomic adsorbates on ultrathin insulating films provide a promising route towards building bottom-up quantum architectures based on atomically identical yet individually addressable spin qubits on solid surfaces. A key challenge in engineering quantum-coherent spin nanostructures lies in understanding and controlling the spin state of individual adsorbates. In this work, we investigate single titanium (Ti) atoms adsorbed on MgO/Ag(100) surfaces using a combined scanning tunneling microscopy and electron spin resonance. Our measurements reveal two distinct spin states, S&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;1/2 and S&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;1, depending on the local adsorption site and the thickness of the MgO film. Density functional theory calculations suggest a Ti+ configuration for the Ti adsorbates with approximately 3 electrons in the 4s and 3d valence shells. Using multi-orbital magnetic multiplet calculations the site dependence of the spin can be rationalized as a charge redistribution between spin-polarizing and depolarizing orbitals. These findings underscore the potential of surface-supported single atoms as spin qubits with tunable spin and charge states, enabling atom-by-atom control in the realization of a versatile quantum platform on surfaces. The study shows that the spin state of a single titanium atom on an insulating surface can be reversibly switched by its local environment, without chemical changes (no hydrogenation), using advanced microscopy, spectroscopy, and theory.
Published: 2026-01-16T11:17:26+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.567 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Soo-hyon Phark; Hong Thi Bui; We-hyo Seo; Yaowu Liu; Valeria Sheina; Curie Lee; Christoph Wolf; Andreas J. Heinrich; Roberto Robles; Nicolás Lorente&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68314-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68314-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.567 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single atomic adsorbates on ultrathin insulating films provide a promising route towards building bottom-up quantum architectures based on atomically identical yet individually addressable spin qubits on solid surfaces. A key challenge in engineering quantum-coherent spin nanostructures lies in understanding and controlling the spin state of individual adsorbates. In this work, we investigate single titanium (Ti) atoms adsorbed on MgO/Ag(100) surfaces using a combined scanning tunneling microscopy and electron spin resonance. Our measurements reveal two distinct spin states, S&amp;amp;nbsp;=&amp;amp;nbsp;1/2 and S&amp;amp;nbsp;=&amp;amp;nbsp;1, depending on the local adsorption site and the thickness of the MgO film. Density functional theory calculations suggest a Ti+ configuration for the Ti adsorbates with approximately 3 electrons in the 4s and 3d valence shells. Using multi-orbital magnetic multiplet calculations the site dependence of the spin can be rationalized as a charge redistribution between spin-polarizing and depolarizing orbitals. These findings underscore the potential of surface-supported single atoms as spin qubits with tunable spin and charge states, enabling atom-by-atom control in the realization of a versatile quantum platform on surfaces. The study shows that the spin state of a single titanium atom on an insulating surface can be reversibly switched by its local environment, without chemical changes (no hydrogenation), using advanced microscopy, spectroscopy, and theory.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Deciphering stress perturbations throughout the 2025 Mw 7.1 Dingri, Southern Xizang Earthquake</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68128-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68128-y</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 07:24:30 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhangfeng Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenglong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongyu Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Han Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingzhe Lyu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingfeng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luca Dal Zilio</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinjian Shan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shengji Wei</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68128-y</prism:doi><description>The 2025 moment magnitude (Mw) 7.1 Dingri earthquake in Southern Xizang, China, caused severe devastation and exhibited a complex stress evolution. Its northward unilateral rupture along the twisted, west-dipping graben edge generated ~2 MPa of dynamic stress, triggering blind coseismic slip on an east-dipping fault. Coseismic stress perturbations activated over 50 previously unmapped fault segments, mostly with aseismic slip, while also inducing an early viscoelastic response in the weak middle-to-lower crustal layer below ~20 km depth. Here we explain these behaviours by deciphering the stress perturbations through earthquake cycle observations and models. A major implication is that tracking stress evolution throughout an earthquake provides critical insights into earthquake mechanics. Earthquake-cycle observations reveal that the 2025 Mw 7.1 Dingri earthquake featured complex rupture, widespread triggered a/seismic slip, and early viscoelastic relaxation, highlighting how stress transfer through the cycle shapes fault behaviour.
Published: 2026-01-16T07:24:30+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.558 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhangfeng Ma; Chenglong Li; Hongyu Zeng; Han Chen; Mingzhe Lyu; Yingfeng Zhang; Luca Dal Zilio; Xinjian Shan; Shengji Wei&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68128-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68128-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.558 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2025 moment magnitude (Mw) 7.1 Dingri earthquake in Southern Xizang, China, caused severe devastation and exhibited a complex stress evolution. Its northward unilateral rupture along the twisted, west-dipping graben edge generated ~2 MPa of dynamic stress, triggering blind coseismic slip on an east-dipping fault. Coseismic stress perturbations activated over 50 previously unmapped fault segments, mostly with aseismic slip, while also inducing an early viscoelastic response in the weak middle-to-lower crustal layer below ~20 km depth. Here we explain these behaviours by deciphering the stress perturbations through earthquake cycle observations and models. A major implication is that tracking stress evolution throughout an earthquake provides critical insights into earthquake mechanics. Earthquake-cycle observations reveal that the 2025 Mw 7.1 Dingri earthquake featured complex rupture, widespread triggered a/seismic slip, and early viscoelastic relaxation, highlighting how stress transfer through the cycle shapes fault behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Spatiotemporally ordered topological transformation in layered double hydroxides enables synergistic mineralization of AsIII/Cd2+</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68326-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68326-2</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 12:56:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Meiqi Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huanxu Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoqing Cao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Si-Min Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenying Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xianggui Kong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingfei Shao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xue Duan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68326-2</prism:doi><description>The co-contamination of arsenite (AsIII) and cadmium (Cd2+) poses a significant challenge in environmental remediation due to their divergent chemical speciation and transformation pathways. Here, a redox-active layered double oxide (MgMn-LDO) is designed, and achieves adsorption capacities of 821.7 mg g‒1 for AsIII and 1895.6 mg g‒1 for Cd2+ in their coexisting system, presenting a state-of-the-art performance. Unexpectedly, the co-adsorption system not only enhances individual adsorption capacities but also accelerates the adsorption rate by 181‒fold compared to single-component systems. The LDO undergoes a four-stage spatiotemporally ordered topological transformation, which effectively decouples the oxidation of AsIII from the adsorption of Cd2+ and reverses the conventional competitive sequence. This stepwise mechanism ensures preferential oxidation of AsIII to AsV, followed by the alteration of Cd2+ adsorption pathway to isomorphous substitution, expanding diffusion pathways and accelerating As immobilization. Large-scale experiments demonstrate this material’s potential in synergistic remediation As/Cd in mining wastewater and contaminated soils. Here authors prepare a defect-rich Mg–Mn layered double hydroxide, which via a spatiotemporally ordered topotactic transformation, achieving synergistic comineralisation of AsIII and Cd2+.
Published: 2026-01-16T12:56:21+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.535 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Meiqi Zheng; Huanxu Du; Xiaoqing Cao; Si-Min Xu; Wei Chen; Wenying Shi; Xianggui Kong; Mingfei Shao; Xue Duan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68326-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68326-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.535 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The co-contamination of arsenite (AsIII) and cadmium (Cd2+) poses a significant challenge in environmental remediation due to their divergent chemical speciation and transformation pathways. Here, a redox-active layered double oxide (MgMn-LDO) is designed, and achieves adsorption capacities of 821.7 mg g‒1 for AsIII and 1895.6 mg g‒1 for Cd2+ in their coexisting system, presenting a state-of-the-art performance. Unexpectedly, the co-adsorption system not only enhances individual adsorption capacities but also accelerates the adsorption rate by 181‒fold compared to single-component systems. The LDO undergoes a four-stage spatiotemporally ordered topological transformation, which effectively decouples the oxidation of AsIII from the adsorption of Cd2+ and reverses the conventional competitive sequence. This stepwise mechanism ensures preferential oxidation of AsIII to AsV, followed by the alteration of Cd2+ adsorption pathway to isomorphous substitution, expanding diffusion pathways and accelerating As immobilization. Large-scale experiments demonstrate this material’s potential in synergistic remediation As/Cd in mining wastewater and contaminated soils. Here authors prepare a defect-rich Mg–Mn layered double hydroxide, which via a spatiotemporally ordered topotactic transformation, achieving synergistic comineralisation of AsIII and Cd2+.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Twist-stacked black phosphorus for wide-spectral chiral photodetection</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68531-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68531-z</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 15:45:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hao Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liheng An</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaolong Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoqiang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jintao Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuran Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuzhe Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruihua He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xingzhan Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiang-Long Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cheng-Wei Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weibo Gao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68531-z</prism:doi><description>On-chip integrable circularly polarized light (CPL) detectors hold significant potential for applications in optical communications, bioimaging, quantum information, and intelligent sensing, enabling chip-scale chiral light detection and information processing. However, current developments in materials and structural designs struggle to achieve wide-spectral detection capability while maintaining high circular polarization discrimination. This limitation significantly constrains the practical applicability of such detectors in complex environments and object detection scenarios. Herein, we propose a CPL detector based on a twist-stacked black phosphorus (b-p) system. By utilizing twisted b-p as an artificially constructed unit with chiral response and designing a symmetry-stacked sandwich structure in space, we achieve bipolar circular polarization detection and imaging across a wide wavelength range (from visible light to mid-infrared), with peak responsivity reaching 0.1 A/W. This design demonstrates both theoretically and experimentally the feasibility of utilizing a twist-stacked b-p system for wide-spectral CPL detection. This advancement offers valuable insights for addressing the bottlenecks in chip-integrated CPL detection technology. On-chip circularly polarized light (CPL) detectors are relevant for various applications, but current approaches have shown a trade-off between wide spectral detection range, high discrimination ratio and high polarization sensitivity. Here, the authors report broadband high-performance CPL detectors based on twisted black phosphorus structures.
Published: 2026-01-17T15:45:26+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.534 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hao Jiang; Liheng An; Xiaolong Chen; Guoqiang Xu; Yan Zhang; Jintao Fu; Xuran Dai; Yuzhe Yang; Ruihua He; Xingzhan Wei; Xiang-Long Yu; Cheng-Wei Qiu; Weibo Gao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68531-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68531-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.534 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On-chip integrable circularly polarized light (CPL) detectors hold significant potential for applications in optical communications, bioimaging, quantum information, and intelligent sensing, enabling chip-scale chiral light detection and information processing. However, current developments in materials and structural designs struggle to achieve wide-spectral detection capability while maintaining high circular polarization discrimination. This limitation significantly constrains the practical applicability of such detectors in complex environments and object detection scenarios. Herein, we propose a CPL detector based on a twist-stacked black phosphorus (b-p) system. By utilizing twisted b-p as an artificially constructed unit with chiral response and designing a symmetry-stacked sandwich structure in space, we achieve bipolar circular polarization detection and imaging across a wide wavelength range (from visible light to mid-infrared), with peak responsivity reaching 0.1 A/W. This design demonstrates both theoretically and experimentally the feasibility of utilizing a twist-stacked b-p system for wide-spectral CPL detection. This advancement offers valuable insights for addressing the bottlenecks in chip-integrated CPL detection technology. On-chip circularly polarized light (CPL) detectors are relevant for various applications, but current approaches have shown a trade-off between wide spectral detection range, high discrimination ratio and high polarization sensitivity. Here, the authors report broadband high-performance CPL detectors based on twisted black phosphorus structures.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seismological Characterization of Northern Hikurangi Margin Slow Slip Regions Associated With Normal Faults, Seamounts, and Seeps</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032916</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032916</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 09:40:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Amy Woodward</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ian D. Bastow</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rebecca Bell</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laura Wallace</dc:creator><dc:creator>Katrina Jacobs</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stuart Henrys</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bill Fry</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas A. J. Merry</dc:creator><dc:creator>Victoria Lane</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laurene Ville</dc:creator><dc:creator>Phoebe Houldsworth‐Bianek</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luke Broadley</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032916</prism:doi><description>Abstract At the northern Hikurangi margin, Aotearoa New Zealand, slow slip events (SSEs) recur every 6–24 months to 30 km depth. Although shallow SSEs (0–10 km) are well‐studied offshore, the deeper portion (10–30 km) remains poorly understood, limiting insight into SSE initiation. Here we investigate this deeper region and examine relationships between newly resolved SSEs and seismicity. Using time‐dependent inversions, we resolve two small SSEs ( 6.2 and 6.4), including one that extends from 15 to 30 km depth. Using data from a dense onshore seismograph network deployed directly above this deeper portion from December 2017 to October 2018, we construct a catalog of 3,071 high‐quality earthquakes with hypocentral uncertainties 5 km, located using a 3‐D velocity model and a new 1‐D model. Earthquake magnitudes range from −0.84 to 4.40, with a completeness magnitude of 1.7 and a b‐value of 1.06. Focal mechanisms reveal numerous normal‐faulting earthquakes, including some within the slab mantle. Vertically‐aligned seismicity and normal‐faulting earthquakes outline pathways linking the slab mantle to surface seeps of mantle‐derived fluids. We infer that normal faults form due to slab bending and localized uplift of subducting seamounts, which roughen the plate interface, damage the upper plate, and promote fluid migration. Landward of 100 km from the trench, both surface seeps and normal‐faulting mechanisms cease, coinciding with the downdip limit of shallow SSEs. Together, these results suggest that the Hikurangi margin's rough subducting plate interface exerts strong control on forearc dewatering and SSE genesis.
Published: 2026-01-17T09:40:31+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.534 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Amy Woodward; Ian D. Bastow; Rebecca Bell; Laura Wallace; Katrina Jacobs; Stuart Henrys; Bill Fry; Thomas A. J. Merry; Victoria Lane; Laurene Ville; Phoebe Houldsworth‐Bianek; Luke Broadley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032916"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032916&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.534 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract At the northern Hikurangi margin, Aotearoa New Zealand, slow slip events (SSEs) recur every 6–24 months to 30 km depth. Although shallow SSEs (0–10 km) are well‐studied offshore, the deeper portion (10–30 km) remains poorly understood, limiting insight into SSE initiation. Here we investigate this deeper region and examine relationships between newly resolved SSEs and seismicity. Using time‐dependent inversions, we resolve two small SSEs ( 6.2 and 6.4), including one that extends from 15 to 30 km depth. Using data from a dense onshore seismograph network deployed directly above this deeper portion from December 2017 to October 2018, we construct a catalog of 3,071 high‐quality earthquakes with hypocentral uncertainties 5 km, located using a 3‐D velocity model and a new 1‐D model. Earthquake magnitudes range from −0.84 to 4.40, with a completeness magnitude of 1.7 and a b‐value of 1.06. Focal mechanisms reveal numerous normal‐faulting earthquakes, including some within the slab mantle. Vertically‐aligned seismicity and normal‐faulting earthquakes outline pathways linking the slab mantle to surface seeps of mantle‐derived fluids. We infer that normal faults form due to slab bending and localized uplift of subducting seamounts, which roughen the plate interface, damage the upper plate, and promote fluid migration. Landward of 100 km from the trench, both surface seeps and normal‐faulting mechanisms cease, coinciding with the downdip limit of shallow SSEs. Together, these results suggest that the Hikurangi margin&amp;#x27;s rough subducting plate interface exerts strong control on forearc dewatering and SSE genesis.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Real-time visualization of sub-particle reaction anisotropy via rotary-encoded scattering microscopy</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67721-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67721-5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 06:36:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jun-Hao Wan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gang Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chen Qian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng-Yang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xian-Wei Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67721-5</prism:doi><description>Understanding nanoscale chemical transformations within liquid environments is essential for advancing catalysis, material synthesis, and nanotechnology. However, existing optical imaging techniques face significant challenges in resolve sub-particle-level dynamics due to intrinsic limitations in spatial resolution and sensitivity. Here, we introduce an optical imaging technique, Rotary-Encoded Scattering Microscopy (RESM), that achieves real-time, label-free visualization of sub-particle chemical transformations with high sensitivity and resolution. By dynamically engineering the point spread function (PSF) to encode sub-particle structural changes into distinctive scattering patterns, RESM enables direct tracking of chemical reactions at the sub-particle level. Using RESM, we elucidate concentration-dependent oxidation mechanisms during the oxidation of silver nanospheres (Ag NSs) in aqueous environments. At high Cl- concentrations, anisotropic oxidation via AgCl precipitation emerges as a distinct liquid-phase pathway, marking a clear transition from the isotropic oxidation observed at lower concentrations and indicating that Cl- controls pathway selection while Fe3+ sets the overall rate. We further demonstrate the versatility of RESM by capturing anisotropic intercalation kinetics of Prussian blue nanoparticles, uncovering sub-particle heterogeneity even in highly symmetric materials. By enabling direct visualization of previously hidden sub-particle reaction pathways, RESM establishes a broadly applicable platform for high-sensitivity chemical imaging, bridging structural characterization and functional performance at the nanoscale. This study reports an optical imaging approach that encodes structural information into scattering patterns, enabling real-time visualization of sub-particle reaction dynamics in liquid environments.
Published: 2026-01-16T06:36:14+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.530 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jun-Hao Wan; Gang Wu; Chen Qian; Zheng-Yang Wang; Xian-Wei Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67721-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67721-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.530 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding nanoscale chemical transformations within liquid environments is essential for advancing catalysis, material synthesis, and nanotechnology. However, existing optical imaging techniques face significant challenges in resolve sub-particle-level dynamics due to intrinsic limitations in spatial resolution and sensitivity. Here, we introduce an optical imaging technique, Rotary-Encoded Scattering Microscopy (RESM), that achieves real-time, label-free visualization of sub-particle chemical transformations with high sensitivity and resolution. By dynamically engineering the point spread function (PSF) to encode sub-particle structural changes into distinctive scattering patterns, RESM enables direct tracking of chemical reactions at the sub-particle level. Using RESM, we elucidate concentration-dependent oxidation mechanisms during the oxidation of silver nanospheres (Ag NSs) in aqueous environments. At high Cl- concentrations, anisotropic oxidation via AgCl precipitation emerges as a distinct liquid-phase pathway, marking a clear transition from the isotropic oxidation observed at lower concentrations and indicating that Cl- controls pathway selection while Fe3+ sets the overall rate. We further demonstrate the versatility of RESM by capturing anisotropic intercalation kinetics of Prussian blue nanoparticles, uncovering sub-particle heterogeneity even in highly symmetric materials. By enabling direct visualization of previously hidden sub-particle reaction pathways, RESM establishes a broadly applicable platform for high-sensitivity chemical imaging, bridging structural characterization and functional performance at the nanoscale. This study reports an optical imaging approach that encodes structural information into scattering patterns, enabling real-time visualization of sub-particle reaction dynamics in liquid environments.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Permeability Architecture at the Base of the Seismogenic Zone: Experimental Studies on Cataclasite‐ and Pseudotachylyte‐Bearing Mylonitic Rocks Along the Red River Fault, China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031958</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb031958</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 09:38:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Debao Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qingbao Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianye Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinyu Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb031958</prism:doi><description>Abstract Fluid transport properties at the base of the seismogenic zone exert a critical control on fault strength, slip behavior, and fluid circulation. However, quantitative constraints on permeability in deep fault rocks remain limited. We present new laboratory measurements of permeability, porosity, and specific storage on cataclasite‐ and pseudotachylyte‐bearing mylonitic rocks along the Red River Fault (RRF), China. Experiments conducted at effective pressures up to 165 MPa reveal systematically low permeabilities, with mylonitized cataclasites and pseudotachylyte‐bearing rocks exhibiting the lowest values (10 −22 –10 −21 m 2 ), while mylonites display relatively higher permeabilities, up to 10 −19 m 2 . A key finding is the pronounced permeability anisotropy, where permeability parallel to foliation is up to two orders of magnitude greater than perpendicular values. This anisotropy reflects the microstructural alignment of phyllosilicate minerals and cavitation bands, which provides interconnected flow pathways along foliation while impeding cross‐foliation transport. The hydraulic architecture of the RRF at the base of the seismogenic zone is thus characterized by overall low permeabilities with fluid flow facilitated along mylonitic foliation. Such fabric‐controlled anisotropy persists even under mid‐crustal pressure conditions, indicating that fault zones at the base of seismogenic depths can retain directional fluid pathways despite overall low permeabilities. Our results provide critical constraints on the hydraulic architecture of the RRF and offer broader insights into the role of anisotropy in controlling fluid flow and deformation at the base of the seismogenic zone.
Published: 2026-01-17T09:38:27+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.530 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Debao Liang; Qingbao Duan; Jianye Chen; Jinyu Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031958"&gt;10.1029/2025jb031958&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.530 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Fluid transport properties at the base of the seismogenic zone exert a critical control on fault strength, slip behavior, and fluid circulation. However, quantitative constraints on permeability in deep fault rocks remain limited. We present new laboratory measurements of permeability, porosity, and specific storage on cataclasite‐ and pseudotachylyte‐bearing mylonitic rocks along the Red River Fault (RRF), China. Experiments conducted at effective pressures up to 165 MPa reveal systematically low permeabilities, with mylonitized cataclasites and pseudotachylyte‐bearing rocks exhibiting the lowest values (10 −22 –10 −21 m 2 ), while mylonites display relatively higher permeabilities, up to 10 −19 m 2 . A key finding is the pronounced permeability anisotropy, where permeability parallel to foliation is up to two orders of magnitude greater than perpendicular values. This anisotropy reflects the microstructural alignment of phyllosilicate minerals and cavitation bands, which provides interconnected flow pathways along foliation while impeding cross‐foliation transport. The hydraulic architecture of the RRF at the base of the seismogenic zone is thus characterized by overall low permeabilities with fluid flow facilitated along mylonitic foliation. Such fabric‐controlled anisotropy persists even under mid‐crustal pressure conditions, indicating that fault zones at the base of seismogenic depths can retain directional fluid pathways despite overall low permeabilities. Our results provide critical constraints on the hydraulic architecture of the RRF and offer broader insights into the role of anisotropy in controlling fluid flow and deformation at the base of the seismogenic zone.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Quantum boomerang effect of light</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68293-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68293-8</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 08:17:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiangrui Hou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaoxin Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fangyu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shiyao Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaoju Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68293-8</prism:doi><description>The quantum boomerang effect is a counterintuitive phenomenon in which a wave packet launched with finite momentum in a disordered medium returns to its origin. However, up to now, the experimental exploration of this boomerang effect remains largely unexplored. Here, we report the observation of this effect with light in an on-chip, one-dimensional (1D) disordered waveguide lattice. After benchmarking the system through Anderson localization, we launch a kinetic light beam into the system and track its center of mass (COM): it first moves away from its starting point, arrives at a maximum-valued point, reverses its direction, and returns to its original position over time, revealing the real-space observation of the photonic quantum boomerang effect. We also show two methods to accelerate and control the return: a symmetric gradient loss and time-varying coupling control to effectively increase the return velocity. Both strategies are realized experimentally and captured by our model. These results establish a controllable photonic platform for boomerang physics and open an avenue for future study in nonlinear and many-photon regimes. Light launched into a disordered photonic chip first drifts, then unexpectedly reverses and returns to its point of origin. This work presents the first real-space observation of this quantum boomerang effect and demonstrates how engineered loss and time-varying couplings can accelerate the return dynamics.
Published: 2026-01-16T08:17:44+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.512 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiangrui Hou; Zhaoxin Wu; Fangyu Wang; Shiyao Zhu; Bo Yan; Zhaoju Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68293-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68293-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.512 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quantum boomerang effect is a counterintuitive phenomenon in which a wave packet launched with finite momentum in a disordered medium returns to its origin. However, up to now, the experimental exploration of this boomerang effect remains largely unexplored. Here, we report the observation of this effect with light in an on-chip, one-dimensional (1D) disordered waveguide lattice. After benchmarking the system through Anderson localization, we launch a kinetic light beam into the system and track its center of mass (COM): it first moves away from its starting point, arrives at a maximum-valued point, reverses its direction, and returns to its original position over time, revealing the real-space observation of the photonic quantum boomerang effect. We also show two methods to accelerate and control the return: a symmetric gradient loss and time-varying coupling control to effectively increase the return velocity. Both strategies are realized experimentally and captured by our model. These results establish a controllable photonic platform for boomerang physics and open an avenue for future study in nonlinear and many-photon regimes. Light launched into a disordered photonic chip first drifts, then unexpectedly reverses and returns to its point of origin. This work presents the first real-space observation of this quantum boomerang effect and demonstrates how engineered loss and time-varying couplings can accelerate the return dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Multilayer oxide protection layer with multiple tunnelling paths for efficient and durable Si-based photocathode</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68665-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68665-0</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 15:46:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yang Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zijie Cheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanhong Lyu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinbo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nataliya Tsud</dc:creator><dc:creator>Viacheslav Kalinovych</dc:creator><dc:creator>Roland De Marco</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongmin He</dc:creator><dc:creator>San Ping Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianyun Zheng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68665-0</prism:doi><description>Constructing a low-resistance oxide protection layer is challenging but highly beneficial for realizing a practical photoelectrochemical device. The thickness of oxide layer strongly influences its behaviors of carrier transport and corrosion resistance, generally leading to a trade-off between efficiency and durability. Different from the previous methods, here we propose and demonstrate a universal approach to decouple the trade-off of oxide layer by multiple carrier-tunnelling paths. This approach with oxide/metal architecture ((O/M)n, n is the number of nano-scale repeating unit) enables low-resistance carrier transport as required for high efficiency, while allowing the layer to be sufficiently thick, which reinforces durability. This approach can be applied to various oxide-based layers, such as (TiO2/Fe)n, (CeO2/Fe)n and (TiO2/Pd)n. In addition, a good correlation between carrier dynamics and oxide/metal architecture is established by employing systematic photoelectrochemical-electrical measurements and simulation models. Here we show important contributions for further developing the practical photoelectrodes in photoelectrochemical devices and controlling the carrier transport behaviors in complex multilayer structure. A universal approach to construct low-resistance oxide layer by multiple tunnelling paths is proposed for efficient and durable Si-based photocathode. This approach can speed up the pace of development of practical photoelectrochemical devices.
Published: 2026-01-17T15:46:27+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.509 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yang Zhou; Zijie Cheng; Yanhong Lyu; Jinbo Wang; Nataliya Tsud; Viacheslav Kalinovych; Roland De Marco; Xiao Luo; Yongmin He; San Ping Jiang; Jianyun Zheng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68665-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68665-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.509 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Constructing a low-resistance oxide protection layer is challenging but highly beneficial for realizing a practical photoelectrochemical device. The thickness of oxide layer strongly influences its behaviors of carrier transport and corrosion resistance, generally leading to a trade-off between efficiency and durability. Different from the previous methods, here we propose and demonstrate a universal approach to decouple the trade-off of oxide layer by multiple carrier-tunnelling paths. This approach with oxide/metal architecture ((O/M)n, n is the number of nano-scale repeating unit) enables low-resistance carrier transport as required for high efficiency, while allowing the layer to be sufficiently thick, which reinforces durability. This approach can be applied to various oxide-based layers, such as (TiO2/Fe)n, (CeO2/Fe)n and (TiO2/Pd)n. In addition, a good correlation between carrier dynamics and oxide/metal architecture is established by employing systematic photoelectrochemical-electrical measurements and simulation models. Here we show important contributions for further developing the practical photoelectrodes in photoelectrochemical devices and controlling the carrier transport behaviors in complex multilayer structure. A universal approach to construct low-resistance oxide layer by multiple tunnelling paths is proposed for efficient and durable Si-based photocathode. This approach can speed up the pace of development of practical photoelectrochemical devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Spectroelectrochemical insight into copper cobalt catalysts for CO2 and nitrite co-electroreduction to urea</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68481-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68481-6</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 09:45:24 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Putri Ramadhany</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thành Trần-Phú</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jodie A. Yuwono</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rosalie K. Hocking</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhipeng Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuan Minh Chau Ta</dc:creator><dc:creator>Priyank Kumar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Denny Gunawan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bernt Johannessen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Antonio Tricoli</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexandr N. Simonov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rose Amal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rahman Daiyan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68481-6</prism:doi><description>Electrochemical CO2 and nitrite co-reduction provides a sustainable urea synthesis route but remains limited by low selectivity and an undecided C–N coupling mechanism. Here, we report co-sputtered bimetallic Cu–Co catalysts that facilitate urea formation via a tandem relay mechanism. The optimal Cu:Co ratio of 1:1 achieves a urea yield rate of 61 ± 6 mmol h⁻1gcat⁻1 at –1.2 V vs. RHE under neutral pH, emphasizing the importance of proton balance in sustaining proton-coupled electron transfer. In situ synchrotron-based infrared and Raman spectroscopy monitor the dynamic evolution of *CO, *NH2, and C‒N intermediates. In situ X-ray absorption spectroscopy indicates the structural stability of metallic Cu and Co active sites. Density functional theory calculations suggest that *COOH + *NH2 coupling initiates urea pathway, with *NH2CO formation as the potential-determining step. This study integrates rational catalyst design and in situ spectroelectrochemical analysis to advance understanding of electrochemical C–N coupling for urea synthesis. Electrochemical conversion of CO2 and nitrite offers a green route to produce urea. Here, the authors report co-sputtered copper cobalt catalysts enable efficient C–N coupling through a tandem mechanism, yielding 61 mmol h⁻1gcat⁻1 urea at –1.2 V vs. RHE.
Published: 2026-01-17T09:45:24+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.508 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Putri Ramadhany; Thành Trần-Phú; Jodie A. Yuwono; Rosalie K. Hocking; Zhipeng Ma; Xuan Minh Chau Ta; Priyank Kumar; Denny Gunawan; Bernt Johannessen; Antonio Tricoli; Alexandr N. Simonov; Rose Amal; Rahman Daiyan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68481-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68481-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.508 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrochemical CO2 and nitrite co-reduction provides a sustainable urea synthesis route but remains limited by low selectivity and an undecided C–N coupling mechanism. Here, we report co-sputtered bimetallic Cu–Co catalysts that facilitate urea formation via a tandem relay mechanism. The optimal Cu:Co ratio of 1:1 achieves a urea yield rate of 61 ± 6 mmol h⁻1gcat⁻1 at –1.2 V vs. RHE under neutral pH, emphasizing the importance of proton balance in sustaining proton-coupled electron transfer. In situ synchrotron-based infrared and Raman spectroscopy monitor the dynamic evolution of *CO, *NH2, and C‒N intermediates. In situ X-ray absorption spectroscopy indicates the structural stability of metallic Cu and Co active sites. Density functional theory calculations suggest that *COOH + *NH2 coupling initiates urea pathway, with *NH2CO formation as the potential-determining step. This study integrates rational catalyst design and in situ spectroelectrochemical analysis to advance understanding of electrochemical C–N coupling for urea synthesis. Electrochemical conversion of CO2 and nitrite offers a green route to produce urea. Here, the authors report co-sputtered copper cobalt catalysts enable efficient C–N coupling through a tandem mechanism, yielding 61 mmol h⁻1gcat⁻1 urea at –1.2 V vs. RHE.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Manipulating metal growth in hollow ionic-electronic conductor for anode-free lithium metal batteries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adt2630</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adt2630</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:59:06 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lianqiang Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaotian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zihang Xi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yawen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yujie Ning</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qing Zhao</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adt2630</prism:doi><description>Anode-free lithium metal batteries (AFLMBs) demonstrate promising high energy density yet suffer from irregular Li deposition, parasitic reactions, and severe volume expansion. The current anode modulation strategies such as tailored solid electrolyte interphase (SEI) and lithiophilic host architectures can hardly simultaneously resolve all above issues, especially at high-capacity Li deposition. Here, we design a Li-rich, hollow ionic-electronic conductor (HIEC) interlayer, which integrates metallic Li encapsulation and interfacial protection, thus guiding highly reversible thick Li deposition (5 milliampere-hours per square centimeter). In addition, the built-in electron-deficient domains in the HIEC facilitate the formation of the hierarchical SEI and further mitigate active Li corrosion. These synergistic effects of the interlayer enable stable cycling in batteries under both anode-less and anode-free configurations, attaining &gt;99% coulombic efficiency under industrial-level cathode loading and lean electrolyte conditions. This study highlights the significance of interlayers in integrating the SEI and host functions and provides a viable and scalable solution for energy-dense batteries.
Published: 2026-01-16T18:59:06+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.507 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lianqiang Peng; Xiaotian Wang; Xu Liu; Zihang Xi; Yawen Li; Jie Zhang; Yujie Ning; Qing Zhao&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adt2630"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adt2630&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.507 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anode-free lithium metal batteries (AFLMBs) demonstrate promising high energy density yet suffer from irregular Li deposition, parasitic reactions, and severe volume expansion. The current anode modulation strategies such as tailored solid electrolyte interphase (SEI) and lithiophilic host architectures can hardly simultaneously resolve all above issues, especially at high-capacity Li deposition. Here, we design a Li-rich, hollow ionic-electronic conductor (HIEC) interlayer, which integrates metallic Li encapsulation and interfacial protection, thus guiding highly reversible thick Li deposition (5 milliampere-hours per square centimeter). In addition, the built-in electron-deficient domains in the HIEC facilitate the formation of the hierarchical SEI and further mitigate active Li corrosion. These synergistic effects of the interlayer enable stable cycling in batteries under both anode-less and anode-free configurations, attaining &amp;gt;99% coulombic efficiency under industrial-level cathode loading and lean electrolyte conditions. This study highlights the significance of interlayers in integrating the SEI and host functions and provides a viable and scalable solution for energy-dense batteries.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mapping pan-Arctic riverine particulate organic carbon from space (1985 to 2022)</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady6314</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.ady6314</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:59:06 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xianghan Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liqiao Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongwei Fang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Desmond E. Walling</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jaia Syvitski</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Deren Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunmiao Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lian Feng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.ady6314</prism:doi><description>Carbon release from high-latitude regions is intensifying, with profound consequences for the Arctic carbon cycle. Here, we provide a comprehensive analysis of changes in fluvial particulate organic carbon (POC) concentrations ( C POC ) and fluxes ( F POC ) during ice-free seasons of pan-Arctic rivers from 1985 to 2022 on the basis of satellite observations. Across 578,000 kilometers of river length, 18% of the total length experienced a significant increase in C POC , which exceeds the 11% that exhibited declines, resulting in a net rise. Most increases occurred after 2005, contributing to a 12.6% (0.49 teragrams per year) increase in total F POC to the Arctic Ocean between 1985 to 2005 and 2006 to 2022. Regional contrasts highlight distinct possible drivers: increased precipitation in the North American Arctic and atmospheric warming in the Eurasian Arctic. Deepening of the permafrost active layer is also significantly correlated with C POC increases. These findings highlight climate-driven fluvial POC export as a key contributor to the Arctic carbon budget and provide a high-resolution, satellite-based dataset that can inform carbon cycle models and data assimilation efforts.
Published: 2026-01-16T18:59:06+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.507 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xianghan Sun; Liqiao Tian; Hongwei Fang; Desmond E. Walling; Jaia Syvitski; Lei Huang; Deren Li; Chunmiao Zheng; Lian Feng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady6314"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.ady6314&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.507 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbon release from high-latitude regions is intensifying, with profound consequences for the Arctic carbon cycle. Here, we provide a comprehensive analysis of changes in fluvial particulate organic carbon (POC) concentrations ( C POC ) and fluxes ( F POC ) during ice-free seasons of pan-Arctic rivers from 1985 to 2022 on the basis of satellite observations. Across 578,000 kilometers of river length, 18% of the total length experienced a significant increase in C POC , which exceeds the 11% that exhibited declines, resulting in a net rise. Most increases occurred after 2005, contributing to a 12.6% (0.49 teragrams per year) increase in total F POC to the Arctic Ocean between 1985 to 2005 and 2006 to 2022. Regional contrasts highlight distinct possible drivers: increased precipitation in the North American Arctic and atmospheric warming in the Eurasian Arctic. Deepening of the permafrost active layer is also significantly correlated with C POC increases. These findings highlight climate-driven fluvial POC export as a key contributor to the Arctic carbon budget and provide a high-resolution, satellite-based dataset that can inform carbon cycle models and data assimilation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Valence-free open nanoparticle superlattices</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68316-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68316-4</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 13:44:24 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Binay P. Nayak</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenjie Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Prapti Kakkar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Honghu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zinnia Mallick</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shan Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dmytro Nykypanchuk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Surya K. Mallapragada</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alex Travesset</dc:creator><dc:creator>David Vaknin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68316-4</prism:doi><description>A cornerstone of advanced materials design is establishing a framework for assembling nanoparticle superstructures with tailored symmetries. A longstanding challenge has been assembling diamond-like superstructures for photonic devices. Traditionally, such open superstructures require functionalized nanoparticles with directional or anisotropic interactions, reminiscent of valence bonding in a diamond. Here, we present a robust strategy for assembling valence-free nanoparticles into a broad array of cubic superstructures. By grafting nanoparticles with oppositely charged, end-functionalized water-soluble polymers of adjustable molecular weight, we gain control over electrostatic interactions and conformational constraints. This unified approach yields lattices analogous to rock salt, CsCl, zinc-blende, diamond, and the rare simple cubic phase, with tunable lattice constants. Theoretical models and simulations elucidate the underlying interactions, providing a framework for engineering valence-free nanoparticle superlattices. Tuning surface charge and polymer length enables PEG-grafted nanoparticles to assemble into cubic superlattices resembling ZnS, NaCl, CsCl, simple cubic and diamond, offering a programmable route to valence-free crystals.
Published: 2026-01-17T13:44:24+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.502 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Binay P. Nayak; Wenjie Wang; Prapti Kakkar; Honghu Zhang; Zinnia Mallick; Shan Zhou; Dmytro Nykypanchuk; Surya K. Mallapragada; Alex Travesset; David Vaknin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68316-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68316-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.502 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cornerstone of advanced materials design is establishing a framework for assembling nanoparticle superstructures with tailored symmetries. A longstanding challenge has been assembling diamond-like superstructures for photonic devices. Traditionally, such open superstructures require functionalized nanoparticles with directional or anisotropic interactions, reminiscent of valence bonding in a diamond. Here, we present a robust strategy for assembling valence-free nanoparticles into a broad array of cubic superstructures. By grafting nanoparticles with oppositely charged, end-functionalized water-soluble polymers of adjustable molecular weight, we gain control over electrostatic interactions and conformational constraints. This unified approach yields lattices analogous to rock salt, CsCl, zinc-blende, diamond, and the rare simple cubic phase, with tunable lattice constants. Theoretical models and simulations elucidate the underlying interactions, providing a framework for engineering valence-free nanoparticle superlattices. Tuning surface charge and polymer length enables PEG-grafted nanoparticles to assemble into cubic superlattices resembling ZnS, NaCl, CsCl, simple cubic and diamond, offering a programmable route to valence-free crystals.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Giant unusual anisotropic magnetoresistance enabled by hole-electron resonance in van der Waals heterostructures</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68438-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68438-9</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 07:24:29 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qian Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuxin Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chang Niu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hainan Mao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ya Zhai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiyan Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yong Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Xia</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68438-9</prism:doi><description>The hole-electron resonance in two-dimensional WTe2 dynamically screens the built-in electric field, disrupting the scattering equilibrium constraints of conventional electron transport. Here, we propose utilizing the hole-electron resonance to achieve Coulomb force-unconstrained spin angular momentum transfer across the WTe2/Fe3GaTe2 interface, offering a novel platform for exploring unconventional spin transport phenomena. A clear signature of this mechanism is the observation of an unusual anisotropic magnetoresistance of 289%, which far exceeds conventional spin Hall magnetoresistance and cannot be explained by standard spin absorption or scattering models. Its angular profile deviates from the simple cosine-squared form but realigns after accounting for magnetization and field orientation, reflecting the interplay between hole-electron resonance and magnetization dynamics. Furthermore, chiral transverse transport with distinct symmetry transitions emerges within the hole-active temperature regime, originating from interfacial symmetry breaking and the inhomogeneous spin-orbital coupling. These findings highlight the essential roles of both electrons and holes in spin transport. Hole–electron resonance in WTe2 unlocks Coulomb-unconstrained spin transfer across WTe2/Fe3GaTe2, producing a giant 289% unusual anisotropic magnetoresistance and chiral transverse transport beyond conventional spin-transport models.
Published: 2026-01-16T07:24:29+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.502 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qian Chen; Yuxin Tian; Lei Wang; Chang Niu; Wei Jiang; Hainan Mao; Ya Zhai; Zhiyan Jia; Yong Jiang; Ke Xia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68438-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68438-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.502 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hole-electron resonance in two-dimensional WTe2 dynamically screens the built-in electric field, disrupting the scattering equilibrium constraints of conventional electron transport. Here, we propose utilizing the hole-electron resonance to achieve Coulomb force-unconstrained spin angular momentum transfer across the WTe2/Fe3GaTe2 interface, offering a novel platform for exploring unconventional spin transport phenomena. A clear signature of this mechanism is the observation of an unusual anisotropic magnetoresistance of 289%, which far exceeds conventional spin Hall magnetoresistance and cannot be explained by standard spin absorption or scattering models. Its angular profile deviates from the simple cosine-squared form but realigns after accounting for magnetization and field orientation, reflecting the interplay between hole-electron resonance and magnetization dynamics. Furthermore, chiral transverse transport with distinct symmetry transitions emerges within the hole-active temperature regime, originating from interfacial symmetry breaking and the inhomogeneous spin-orbital coupling. These findings highlight the essential roles of both electrons and holes in spin transport. Hole–electron resonance in WTe2 unlocks Coulomb-unconstrained spin transfer across WTe2/Fe3GaTe2, producing a giant 289% unusual anisotropic magnetoresistance and chiral transverse transport beyond conventional spin-transport models.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Exciton-polariton photodiodes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68312-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68312-8</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 08:06:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qixiao Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Adam D. Alfieri</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengjia Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anping Ge</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haonan Ge</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liaoxin Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Runzhang Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Deep Jariwala</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinshui Miao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weida Hu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68312-8</prism:doi><description>Photodiodes are central to high-speed communication, sensing and light-harvesting devices. While silicon and other inorganic semiconductor-based photodiodes have been widely integrated into commercial technologies, photodiodes from excitonic semiconductors continue to maintain high interest in research. Excitonic semiconductors are superior in terms of absorption as compared to silicon and III-V semiconductors, but have always suffered from poor charge transport and narrow band absorption due to the short diffusion lengths and resonant nature of the excitons, respectively. Here, we attempt to solve both these central issues in excitonic photodiode devices via use of polariton physics and demonstrating photodiodes in the strong light-matter coupling regime. By using a conductive tin-doped indium oxide transparent top electrode that also serves as an anti-reflective coating combined with self-trapping and hybridization of light in inorganic excitonic semiconductor WS2, we demonstrate photodiodes with broadband absorption and internal quantum efficiency values approaching unity near the zero-detuning condition. Furthermore, it is demonstrated that the response speed of photodiodes is enhanced under strong coupling. Our work presents a promising approach to explore the physics and applications of photodiodes based on excitonic semiconductors. While excitonic semiconductors offer appealing optical properties, their application for competitive optoelectronic devices has remained limited. Here, the authors report the realization of broadband exciton-polariton photodiodes based on a layered excitonic semiconductor, WS2, contacted by tin-doped indium oxide in an open optical cavity design, showing ~MHz bandwidth at room temperature.
Published: 2026-01-17T08:06:27+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.501 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qixiao Zhao; Adam D. Alfieri; Mengjia Xia; Anping Ge; Haonan Ge; Liaoxin Sun; Runzhang Xie; Fang Wang; Deep Jariwala; Jinshui Miao; Weida Hu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68312-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68312-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.501 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photodiodes are central to high-speed communication, sensing and light-harvesting devices. While silicon and other inorganic semiconductor-based photodiodes have been widely integrated into commercial technologies, photodiodes from excitonic semiconductors continue to maintain high interest in research. Excitonic semiconductors are superior in terms of absorption as compared to silicon and III-V semiconductors, but have always suffered from poor charge transport and narrow band absorption due to the short diffusion lengths and resonant nature of the excitons, respectively. Here, we attempt to solve both these central issues in excitonic photodiode devices via use of polariton physics and demonstrating photodiodes in the strong light-matter coupling regime. By using a conductive tin-doped indium oxide transparent top electrode that also serves as an anti-reflective coating combined with self-trapping and hybridization of light in inorganic excitonic semiconductor WS2, we demonstrate photodiodes with broadband absorption and internal quantum efficiency values approaching unity near the zero-detuning condition. Furthermore, it is demonstrated that the response speed of photodiodes is enhanced under strong coupling. Our work presents a promising approach to explore the physics and applications of photodiodes based on excitonic semiconductors. While excitonic semiconductors offer appealing optical properties, their application for competitive optoelectronic devices has remained limited. Here, the authors report the realization of broadband exciton-polariton photodiodes based on a layered excitonic semiconductor, WS2, contacted by tin-doped indium oxide in an open optical cavity design, showing ~MHz bandwidth at room temperature.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Perovskite nanocrystals-in-glass hierarchical structures enable stable continuous-wave random lasers</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz8460</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adz8460</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 18:59:06 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xinkuo Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenduan Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linhan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhu Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhou Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuanzheng Yue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianrong Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dezhi Tan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adz8460</prism:doi><description>Encapsulating perovskite nanocrystals (PNCs) in glass enables enhanced stability of PNCs and numerous applications such as random lasers. However, preparing PNCs and tuning their properties in glass is energy consuming because of high processing temperature and long processing time, and continuous-wave (CW) random lasers have not been achieved. Here, we report modulation of the structure, photoluminescence, and lasing properties of PNCs in glass at temperatures well below the glass transition temperature with a short processing period. We generate tunable PNCs in glass via nanophase separation and ion exchange in the perovskite domains. PNCs-in-glass hierarchical structures are created by controlling nanophase separation and crystallization of PNCs. Substantially increased scattering in the hierarchical structures enables stable CW single-mode random lasing with an ultralow threshold of 52.6 milliwatts per square centimeter. We achieve flexible CW random lasers by incorporating hierarchical structures into the polydimethylsiloxane film. The random lasers are used in speckle-free laser imaging and dynamic holographic displays.
Published: 2026-01-16T18:59:06+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.498 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xinkuo Li; Chenduan Chen; Ke Sun; Linhan Li; Zhu Xiao; Zhou Li; Yuanzheng Yue; Jianrong Qiu; Dezhi Tan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz8460"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adz8460&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.498 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encapsulating perovskite nanocrystals (PNCs) in glass enables enhanced stability of PNCs and numerous applications such as random lasers. However, preparing PNCs and tuning their properties in glass is energy consuming because of high processing temperature and long processing time, and continuous-wave (CW) random lasers have not been achieved. Here, we report modulation of the structure, photoluminescence, and lasing properties of PNCs in glass at temperatures well below the glass transition temperature with a short processing period. We generate tunable PNCs in glass via nanophase separation and ion exchange in the perovskite domains. PNCs-in-glass hierarchical structures are created by controlling nanophase separation and crystallization of PNCs. Substantially increased scattering in the hierarchical structures enables stable CW single-mode random lasing with an ultralow threshold of 52.6 milliwatts per square centimeter. We achieve flexible CW random lasers by incorporating hierarchical structures into the polydimethylsiloxane film. The random lasers are used in speckle-free laser imaging and dynamic holographic displays.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Publisher Correction: Tree methane exchange in a changing world</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43017-026-00762-6</link><guid>10.1038/s43017-026-00762-6</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:10:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Vincent Gauci</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Reviews Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43017-026-00762-6</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Nature Reviews Earth &amp; Environment https://doi.org/10.1038/s43017-025-00692-9 , published online 19 June 2025.
Published: 2026-01-16T13:10:23+00:00
Venue: Nature Reviews Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.497 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Vincent Gauci&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Reviews Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43017-026-00762-6"&gt;10.1038/s43017-026-00762-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.497 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Nature Reviews Earth &amp;amp; Environment https://doi.org/10.1038/s43017-025-00692-9 , published online 19 June 2025.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Atomic-scale mechanism unlocks thermal-stable high-κ performance in HfO2 via coherent interfaces</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68496-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68496-z</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:18:29 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yihao Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongzheng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaochun Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuxiao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fei Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuxian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pengfei Nan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Binghui Ge</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shujun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haohai Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huaijin Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68496-z</prism:doi><description>Complementary-metal-oxide-semiconductor-compatible HfO2-based high-κ dielectrics are pivotal for next-generation electronics in the post-Moore’s Law era. However, establishing coherent interfaces via morphotropic phase boundaries across the tetragonal and orthorhombic (ferroelectric or antiferroelectric) phases—a key strategy for enhancing dielectric properties—remains challenging due to unclear atomic-scale mechanisms and inherent thermal instability, which compromises long-term stability and reliability. To address this, we leverage metallurgical quenching principles to stabilize tetragonal/orthorhombic-antiferroelectric morphotropic phase boundaries in HfO2-based (Lu:Hf0.6Zr0.4O2) bulk crystals. Through precise composition tuning and growth optimization, we stabilize these metastable morphotropic phase boundaries at the tetragonal/orthorhombic-antiferroelectric interface at room temperature, achieving a comparable κ-value (57) to actively studied tetragonal/orthorhombic-ferroelectric counterparts. Microstructural characterization reveals how tensile strain within the t-phase drives dielectric enhancement through softening of the low-frequency Eu phonon mode. Critically, the tetragonal/orthorhombic-antiferroelectric morphotropic phase boundary demonstrates a ~58% reduction in κ variation rate over 30–200 °C relative to tetragonal/orthorhombic-ferroelectric counterparts, signifying superior thermal stability. Our study establishes a generalizable design paradigm for developing high-κ dielectrics in fluorite-structured materials, advancing next-generation complementary-metal-oxide-semiconductor-compatible-integrated functional devices for data storage, energy harvesting, sensing, and integrated photonics. Developing hafnium dioxide-based high-κ dielectrics via morphotropic phase boundaries remains challenging. This study proposes a thermal-stable high-κ strategy via coherent interface design and elucidates the atomic-scale enhancement mechanism.
Published: 2026-01-16T16:18:29+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.493 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yihao Shen; Hongzheng Wang; Xiaochun Ma; Yuxiao Liu; Fei Liang; Shuxian Wang; Pengfei Nan; Binghui Ge; Shujun Zhang; Haohai Yu; Huaijin Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68496-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68496-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.493 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complementary-metal-oxide-semiconductor-compatible HfO2-based high-κ dielectrics are pivotal for next-generation electronics in the post-Moore’s Law era. However, establishing coherent interfaces via morphotropic phase boundaries across the tetragonal and orthorhombic (ferroelectric or antiferroelectric) phases—a key strategy for enhancing dielectric properties—remains challenging due to unclear atomic-scale mechanisms and inherent thermal instability, which compromises long-term stability and reliability. To address this, we leverage metallurgical quenching principles to stabilize tetragonal/orthorhombic-antiferroelectric morphotropic phase boundaries in HfO2-based (Lu:Hf0.6Zr0.4O2) bulk crystals. Through precise composition tuning and growth optimization, we stabilize these metastable morphotropic phase boundaries at the tetragonal/orthorhombic-antiferroelectric interface at room temperature, achieving a comparable κ-value (57) to actively studied tetragonal/orthorhombic-ferroelectric counterparts. Microstructural characterization reveals how tensile strain within the t-phase drives dielectric enhancement through softening of the low-frequency Eu phonon mode. Critically, the tetragonal/orthorhombic-antiferroelectric morphotropic phase boundary demonstrates a ~58% reduction in κ variation rate over 30–200 °C relative to tetragonal/orthorhombic-ferroelectric counterparts, signifying superior thermal stability. Our study establishes a generalizable design paradigm for developing high-κ dielectrics in fluorite-structured materials, advancing next-generation complementary-metal-oxide-semiconductor-compatible-integrated functional devices for data storage, energy harvesting, sensing, and integrated photonics. Developing hafnium dioxide-based high-κ dielectrics via morphotropic phase boundaries remains challenging. This study proposes a thermal-stable high-κ strategy via coherent interface design and elucidates the atomic-scale enhancement mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Breaking the oxo-wall for Co(IV)-oxo species and their nanoconfined catalytic performance within Ce-Co lamellar membrane</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68471-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68471-8</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 16:45:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Mengtao Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongyi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lintao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Can Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenghua Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68471-8</prism:doi><description>Co(IV) = O-mediated Fenton-like processes show great potential for water remediation but are fundamentally limited by the “oxo-wall” effect, which imposes prohibitive activation energies for Co(IV) = O bond formation and stabilization. Herein, by unifying thermodynamic analysis with the “oxo-wall” constraint mechanism, we establish the comprehensive theoretical framework for Co(IV) = O-dominated non-radical Fenton-like oxidation pathways. We design a Ce-Co tetra-(4-carboxyphenyl) porphyrin framework (Ce-Co TCPP), where Ce(IV)-based oxide linkers induce long-range electronic modulation, enhancing electronic delocalization at Co–N4 sites. This significantly reduces electron occupancy in Co–O antibonding orbitals, thereby effectively circumventing “oxo-wall” constraints. Combined experimental and computational analyses confirm that Co(IV) = O species dominate in the Ce-Co TCPP/peroxymonosulfate (PMS) system, where synergistic electron transfer and proton transfer processes significantly lower activation barriers. Practically, the lamellar Ce-Co TCPP membrane/PMS system achieves desirable water permeability (126.97 L·m−2·h−1·bar−1 (LMHB)), high pollutant degradation efficiency (0.0717 ms−1), robust anti-interference capability, and long-term operational stability (95 h), which can be attributed to the shortened mass transport pathways and the approximately 1000-fold enrichment of Co(IV) = O complexes within membrane nanoconfined channels. This work offers an innovative strategy for sustainable Co(IV) = O-mediated advanced oxidation processes in water treatment. Authors overcome the “oxo-wall” effect of Co(IV) = O complexes, offering the lamellar Ce-Co tetra-(4-carboxyphenyl) porphyrin framework membrane for sustainable Co(IV) = O-mediated advanced oxidation processes in water treatment.
Published: 2026-01-16T16:45:27+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.488 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mengtao Tian; Hongyi Zhang; Yi Liu; Lintao Li; Can Yu; Zhen Chen; Zhenghua Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68471-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68471-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.488 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Co(IV) = O-mediated Fenton-like processes show great potential for water remediation but are fundamentally limited by the “oxo-wall” effect, which imposes prohibitive activation energies for Co(IV) = O bond formation and stabilization. Herein, by unifying thermodynamic analysis with the “oxo-wall” constraint mechanism, we establish the comprehensive theoretical framework for Co(IV) = O-dominated non-radical Fenton-like oxidation pathways. We design a Ce-Co tetra-(4-carboxyphenyl) porphyrin framework (Ce-Co TCPP), where Ce(IV)-based oxide linkers induce long-range electronic modulation, enhancing electronic delocalization at Co–N4 sites. This significantly reduces electron occupancy in Co–O antibonding orbitals, thereby effectively circumventing “oxo-wall” constraints. Combined experimental and computational analyses confirm that Co(IV) = O species dominate in the Ce-Co TCPP/peroxymonosulfate (PMS) system, where synergistic electron transfer and proton transfer processes significantly lower activation barriers. Practically, the lamellar Ce-Co TCPP membrane/PMS system achieves desirable water permeability (126.97 L·m−2·h−1·bar−1 (LMHB)), high pollutant degradation efficiency (0.0717 ms−1), robust anti-interference capability, and long-term operational stability (95 h), which can be attributed to the shortened mass transport pathways and the approximately 1000-fold enrichment of Co(IV) = O complexes within membrane nanoconfined channels. This work offers an innovative strategy for sustainable Co(IV) = O-mediated advanced oxidation processes in water treatment. Authors overcome the “oxo-wall” effect of Co(IV) = O complexes, offering the lamellar Ce-Co tetra-(4-carboxyphenyl) porphyrin framework membrane for sustainable Co(IV) = O-mediated advanced oxidation processes in water treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Efficient solution-processed light-emitting diodes based on organic-inorganic hybrid antimony halides</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68597-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68597-9</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 02:35:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhuangzhuang Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weihong Chu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiming Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qicong Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinzhen Ji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuailing Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingmin Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiuyong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengyao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongyang Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenghao Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Niannian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongwen Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanbing Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linyuan Lian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mochen Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xu Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jibin Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Di Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinjian Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chongxin Shan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianpu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhifeng Shi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68597-9</prism:doi><description>Organic-inorganic hybrid antimony halides are emerging emitters for solution-processed light-emitting diodes. However, achieving high-efficiency electroluminescence remains challenging resulting from the non-radiative recombination within emitters and inferior charge transport within device. Here, we develop an organic cation engineering to design a carbazole-functionalized triphenyl(9-ethyl-9H-carbazol-3-yl) phosphonium (TPPEtCz+), which enables a (TPPEtCz)2Sb2Br8 film with good luminescence and achieves an improved charge transport within device. The TPPEtCz+ facilitates strong hydrogen bonding with the [Sb2Br8]2− species and dichloromethane solvent, resulting in a more complete crystal restructuring, thus improving the quality of films. Moreover, non-covalent π–π interactions between carbazole moieties of (TPPEtCz)2Sb2Br8 and benzimidazole moieties of electron-transport TPBi modify the interfacial contact that promotes electron transport and injection. Consequently, our light-emitting diodes reach a peak external quantum efficiency of 19.4% and half-lifetime of 10,190 min at 100 cd m−2. These discoveries provide critical insights into the cation design of hybrid devices that are promising for practical applications. Ma et al. report an organic cation engineering strategy to improve the luminescent properties and charge transport in organic-inorganic antimony halide films, enabling red LEDs with efficiency up to 19.4% and half-lifetime of 10,190 min. Large-area (12.15 cm2) LEDs show efficiency of 14.2%.
Published: 2026-01-17T02:35:19+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.488 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhuangzhuang Ma; Weihong Chu; Qiming Peng; Qicong Zhou; Xinzhen Ji; Shuailing Lin; Jingmin Wang; Xiuyong Li; Meng Wang; Mengyao Zhang; Dongyang Zhu; Zhenghao Xia; Niannian Wang; Dongwen Yang; Ying Liu; Yanbing Han; Linyuan Lian; Mochen Jia; Xu Chen; Jibin Zhang; Di Wu; Xinjian Li; Chongxin Shan; Jianpu Wang; Zhifeng Shi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68597-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68597-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.488 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organic-inorganic hybrid antimony halides are emerging emitters for solution-processed light-emitting diodes. However, achieving high-efficiency electroluminescence remains challenging resulting from the non-radiative recombination within emitters and inferior charge transport within device. Here, we develop an organic cation engineering to design a carbazole-functionalized triphenyl(9-ethyl-9H-carbazol-3-yl) phosphonium (TPPEtCz+), which enables a (TPPEtCz)2Sb2Br8 film with good luminescence and achieves an improved charge transport within device. The TPPEtCz+ facilitates strong hydrogen bonding with the [Sb2Br8]2− species and dichloromethane solvent, resulting in a more complete crystal restructuring, thus improving the quality of films. Moreover, non-covalent π–π interactions between carbazole moieties of (TPPEtCz)2Sb2Br8 and benzimidazole moieties of electron-transport TPBi modify the interfacial contact that promotes electron transport and injection. Consequently, our light-emitting diodes reach a peak external quantum efficiency of 19.4% and half-lifetime of 10,190 min at 100 cd m−2. These discoveries provide critical insights into the cation design of hybrid devices that are promising for practical applications. Ma et al. report an organic cation engineering strategy to improve the luminescent properties and charge transport in organic-inorganic antimony halide films, enabling red LEDs with efficiency up to 19.4% and half-lifetime of 10,190 min. Large-area (12.15 cm2) LEDs show efficiency of 14.2%.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Multiple hydrogen bonding enables large-area doped phosphorescent glasses with robust stability and high-temperature afterglow</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68590-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68590-2</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:54:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chuanli Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuezhen Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lutong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenbo Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunxiang Lei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miaochang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huayue Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaobo Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongpeng Yan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68590-2</prism:doi><description>Molecular room-temperature phosphorescence (RTP) materials with compact and ordered structures organized by intermolecular interactions have proven to be a newly-emerged strategy for high-performance luminescence. However, typical crystalline materials exhibit intrinsic brittleness and compromised optical transparency due to their highly ordered packing, thereby restricting their applicability in diverse functional systems. Herein, a universal non-conjugated molecule (1,2,3,4-butane tetracarboxylic acid) with abundant hydrogen-bonding positions is introduced as a host matrix for supramolecular glasses (SGs) through a convenient evaporation-induced self-assembly procedure. A series of SGs doped with aromatic anhydride derivatives is fabricated, exhibiting highly efficient ultralong phosphorescence with afterglow up to 40 s and quantum yields of 56.8%. Experimental and computational studies show that the multiple hydrogen bonds synergistically facilitate glass formation by stabilizing disordered structures while establishing a rigid molecular matrix, which effectively suppressed non-radiative decay of triplet excitons. The doped SGs demonstrate largely enhanced phosphorescent performance, including high temperature afterglow up to 200 oC and robust tolerance in various extreme environments compared with crystal counterparts. Particularly, a large-scale fabrication (25 cm × 25 cm) and shaping capability that is unattainable by traditional crystals. This work thus offers significant potential of these SGs for advanced displays and anti-counterfeiting applications. Materials with room temperature phosphorescence have a range of potential applications, but when crystalline can be brittle and optically non-transparent. Here, the authors report the development of supramolecular glasses by evaporation-induced assembly, with high-temperature afterglow properties.
Published: 2026-01-17T17:54:55+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.487 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chuanli Chen; Yuezhen Yang; Lutong Zhang; Wenbo Dai; Yunxiang Lei; Miaochang Liu; Huayue Wu; Xiaobo Huang; Dongpeng Yan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68590-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68590-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.487 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molecular room-temperature phosphorescence (RTP) materials with compact and ordered structures organized by intermolecular interactions have proven to be a newly-emerged strategy for high-performance luminescence. However, typical crystalline materials exhibit intrinsic brittleness and compromised optical transparency due to their highly ordered packing, thereby restricting their applicability in diverse functional systems. Herein, a universal non-conjugated molecule (1,2,3,4-butane tetracarboxylic acid) with abundant hydrogen-bonding positions is introduced as a host matrix for supramolecular glasses (SGs) through a convenient evaporation-induced self-assembly procedure. A series of SGs doped with aromatic anhydride derivatives is fabricated, exhibiting highly efficient ultralong phosphorescence with afterglow up to 40 s and quantum yields of 56.8%. Experimental and computational studies show that the multiple hydrogen bonds synergistically facilitate glass formation by stabilizing disordered structures while establishing a rigid molecular matrix, which effectively suppressed non-radiative decay of triplet excitons. The doped SGs demonstrate largely enhanced phosphorescent performance, including high temperature afterglow up to 200 oC and robust tolerance in various extreme environments compared with crystal counterparts. Particularly, a large-scale fabrication (25 cm × 25 cm) and shaping capability that is unattainable by traditional crystals. This work thus offers significant potential of these SGs for advanced displays and anti-counterfeiting applications. Materials with room temperature phosphorescence have a range of potential applications, but when crystalline can be brittle and optically non-transparent. Here, the authors report the development of supramolecular glasses by evaporation-induced assembly, with high-temperature afterglow properties.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Publisher Correction: Terahertz field effect in a two-dimensional semiconductor</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68521-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68521-1</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:01:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tomoki Hiraoka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sandra Nestler</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wentao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Simon Rossel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hassan A. Hafez</dc:creator><dc:creator>Savio Fabretti</dc:creator><dc:creator>Heike Schlörb</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andy Thomas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dmitry Turchinovich</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68521-1</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-60588-6 , published online 05 June 2025
Published: 2026-01-17T18:01:52+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.487 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tomoki Hiraoka; Sandra Nestler; Wentao Zhang; Simon Rossel; Hassan A. Hafez; Savio Fabretti; Heike Schlörb; Andy Thomas; Dmitry Turchinovich&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68521-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68521-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.487 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Nature Communications https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-60588-6 , published online 05 June 2025&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Distinct magneto-optical response of Frenkel and Wannier excitons in CrSBr</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68482-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68482-5</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 14:04:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Maciej Śmiertka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michał Rygała</dc:creator><dc:creator>Katarzyna Posmyk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paulina Peksa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mateusz Dyksik</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dimitar Pashov</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kseniia Mosina</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zdeněk Sofer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mark van Schilfgaarde</dc:creator><dc:creator>Florian Dirnberger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michał Baranowski</dc:creator><dc:creator>Swagata Acharya</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paulina Plochocka</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68482-5</prism:doi><description>Abstract Excitons in recently discovered two-dimensional magnetic semiconductors have emerged as a promising vehicle for optoelectronic and spin-photonic applications. To exploit novel possibilities magnetic degrees of freedom offer, insight into the interplay of magnetism, lattice and optical excitations becomes essential. We consider Chromium Sulphur Bromide, which has two kinds of excitons, X B at 1.8 eV and X A at 1.38 eV. Here we show, through a combination of many body perturbation theory and experiment, that X B is an order of magnitude more sensitive to magnetic and lattice perturbations than X A . We trace the difference to the latter being localised (Frenkel-like), while the former is delocalised (Wannier-Mott-like) – a coexistence rarely seen in two-dimensional materials. This finding is supported by the strong temperature and magnetic field (up to 85 Tesla) dependent shifts in optical response for X B (much smaller for X A ), and we show it is related to X B ’s tendency for delocalisation (in-plane and out-of-plane) and enhanced coupling with A g phonon modes.
Published: 2026-01-17T14:04:21+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.486 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Maciej Śmiertka; Michał Rygała; Katarzyna Posmyk; Paulina Peksa; Mateusz Dyksik; Dimitar Pashov; Kseniia Mosina; Zdeněk Sofer; Mark van Schilfgaarde; Florian Dirnberger; Michał Baranowski; Swagata Acharya; Paulina Plochocka&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68482-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68482-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.486 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Excitons in recently discovered two-dimensional magnetic semiconductors have emerged as a promising vehicle for optoelectronic and spin-photonic applications. To exploit novel possibilities magnetic degrees of freedom offer, insight into the interplay of magnetism, lattice and optical excitations becomes essential. We consider Chromium Sulphur Bromide, which has two kinds of excitons, X B at 1.8 eV and X A at 1.38 eV. Here we show, through a combination of many body perturbation theory and experiment, that X B is an order of magnitude more sensitive to magnetic and lattice perturbations than X A . We trace the difference to the latter being localised (Frenkel-like), while the former is delocalised (Wannier-Mott-like) – a coexistence rarely seen in two-dimensional materials. This finding is supported by the strong temperature and magnetic field (up to 85 Tesla) dependent shifts in optical response for X B (much smaller for X A ), and we show it is related to X B ’s tendency for delocalisation (in-plane and out-of-plane) and enhanced coupling with A g phonon modes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Contrasting evolution of the Arabian Sea and Pacific Ocean oxygen minimum zones during the Miocene</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03112-4</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03112-4</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 10:02:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Anya V. Hess</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alexandra Auderset</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yair Rosenthal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel M. Sigman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alfredo Martínez-García</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03112-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract Ocean oxygen minimum zones have expanded since the mid-20 th century, yet their future remains uncertain. Previous studies show that the eastern tropical North Pacific was well oxygenated during the warm Miocene Climatic Optimum (17.0–14.8 Ma), suggesting better oxygenation under climatic warming. To explore whether this response was global, we reconstruct Miocene oxygenation in the second largest oxygen minimum zone, the Arabian Sea. Trace elements and nitrogen isotopes in planktonic foraminifera show that the Arabian Sea was also better oxygenated during the Miocene Climatic Optimum than today. However, deoxygenation history and establishment of a true oxygen deficient zone following the Miocene cooling lagged in the Arabian Sea, indicating the important role of regional oceanographic processes like proto-monsoon or Tethys outflow. Our study supports future projections of deoxygenation reversals in both oxygen minimum zones, but with more complexity in the Arabian Sea due to competing changes in monsoonal upwelling and influx from marginal seas.
Published: 2026-01-16T10:02:50+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.486 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Anya V. Hess; Alexandra Auderset; Yair Rosenthal; Daniel M. Sigman; Alfredo Martínez-García&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03112-4"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03112-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.486 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Ocean oxygen minimum zones have expanded since the mid-20 th century, yet their future remains uncertain. Previous studies show that the eastern tropical North Pacific was well oxygenated during the warm Miocene Climatic Optimum (17.0–14.8 Ma), suggesting better oxygenation under climatic warming. To explore whether this response was global, we reconstruct Miocene oxygenation in the second largest oxygen minimum zone, the Arabian Sea. Trace elements and nitrogen isotopes in planktonic foraminifera show that the Arabian Sea was also better oxygenated during the Miocene Climatic Optimum than today. However, deoxygenation history and establishment of a true oxygen deficient zone following the Miocene cooling lagged in the Arabian Sea, indicating the important role of regional oceanographic processes like proto-monsoon or Tethys outflow. Our study supports future projections of deoxygenation reversals in both oxygen minimum zones, but with more complexity in the Arabian Sea due to competing changes in monsoonal upwelling and influx from marginal seas.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seismological Evidence of Multiple Crustal Magma Reservoirs Beneath Mt. Wrangell in Southcentral Alaska</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117016</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl117016</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 03:45:11 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qili Andy Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haiying Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sahria Nayon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zane Michael Cleghorn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cong Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl117016</prism:doi><description>Abstract Recent studies have challenged the classical view of magma chambers as ephemeral, melt‐rich bodies confined to shallow depths beneath arc volcanoes at subduction zones. Instead, increasing evidence supports the existence of long‐lived, vertically extensive magmatic systems with persistent partial melts within the crust. Nevertheless, the depth and extent of crustal magma reservoirs remain poorly constrained. We use 549 P ‐wave receiver function events at station AV.WACK and 223 at AV.WAZA to image the crustal structure beneath Mt. Wrangell in southcentral Alaska. We identify a prominent low‐velocity layer in the lower crust, approximately 4–9 km thick and 40 km wide, and a narrower low‐velocity layer at shallower depths. These observations suggest a large lower‐crustal magma chamber containing 9%–33% melt and a localized shallow reservoir with ∼10% melt, supporting the existence of a long‐lived, multi‐layered magmatic system. Our findings provide critical constraints for evaluating and monitoring volcanic hazards in this region.
Published: 2026-01-17T03:45:11+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.484 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qili Andy Dai; Haiying Gao; Sahria Nayon; Zane Michael Cleghorn; Cong Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117016"&gt;10.1029/2025gl117016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.484 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Recent studies have challenged the classical view of magma chambers as ephemeral, melt‐rich bodies confined to shallow depths beneath arc volcanoes at subduction zones. Instead, increasing evidence supports the existence of long‐lived, vertically extensive magmatic systems with persistent partial melts within the crust. Nevertheless, the depth and extent of crustal magma reservoirs remain poorly constrained. We use 549 P ‐wave receiver function events at station AV.WACK and 223 at AV.WAZA to image the crustal structure beneath Mt. Wrangell in southcentral Alaska. We identify a prominent low‐velocity layer in the lower crust, approximately 4–9 km thick and 40 km wide, and a narrower low‐velocity layer at shallower depths. These observations suggest a large lower‐crustal magma chamber containing 9%–33% melt and a localized shallow reservoir with ∼10% melt, supporting the existence of a long‐lived, multi‐layered magmatic system. Our findings provide critical constraints for evaluating and monitoring volcanic hazards in this region.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Study on thermal hydraulic characters of corrugated plate dryer based on DPM coupled ELFM method</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jandt.2026.01.002</link><guid>10.1016/j.jandt.2026.01.002</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 17:15:35 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shunhao Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengyao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ru Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruifeng Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sichao Tan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>International Journal of Advanced Nuclear Reactor Design and Technology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.jandt.2026.01.002</prism:doi><description>To improve the structures and characteristics of the steam generator corrugated plate dryer and increase the steam-liquid separation efficiency, the discrete phase model (DPM) coupled with the Eulerian liquid film model (ELFM) is employed to calculate the flow field of a corrugated plate dryer, and the flow field characteristics of the double-hooked corrugated plate are analyzed. The motion of liquid droplets and the separation of liquid film in the corrugated plate are numerically simulated and investigated by the DPM coupled with the ELFM and combined with three critical values. The applicability of the model is verified by comparing the numerically calculated and experimental values in the cold-state. And the separation performance of other different types of corrugated plates is compared, which lays an important technical foundation for the selection and structural optimization of corrugated plates in engineering practice.
Published: 2026-01-16T17:15:35+00:00
Venue: International Journal of Advanced Nuclear Reactor Design and Technology
Score: 0.481 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shunhao Xu; Bo Wang; Mengyao Wang; Ru Li; Ruifeng Tian; Sichao Tan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; International Journal of Advanced Nuclear Reactor Design and Technology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jandt.2026.01.002"&gt;10.1016/j.jandt.2026.01.002&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.481 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve the structures and characteristics of the steam generator corrugated plate dryer and increase the steam-liquid separation efficiency, the discrete phase model (DPM) coupled with the Eulerian liquid film model (ELFM) is employed to calculate the flow field of a corrugated plate dryer, and the flow field characteristics of the double-hooked corrugated plate are analyzed. The motion of liquid droplets and the separation of liquid film in the corrugated plate are numerically simulated and investigated by the DPM coupled with the ELFM and combined with three critical values. The applicability of the model is verified by comparing the numerically calculated and experimental values in the cold-state. And the separation performance of other different types of corrugated plates is compared, which lays an important technical foundation for the selection and structural optimization of corrugated plates in engineering practice.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Crustal Structure Across the Okavango Rift, Botswana: The SEISORZ Wide‐Angle Seismic Experiment</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032322</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032322</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 18:10:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>J. Pablo Canales</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lucky Moffat</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kebabonye Laletsang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel Lizarralde</dc:creator><dc:creator>Steven Harder</dc:creator><dc:creator>Galen Kaip</dc:creator><dc:creator>Estella A. Atekwana</dc:creator><dc:creator>Motsoptse P. Modisi</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032322</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Okavango Rift Zone (ORZ) is an incipient continental rift in Botswana at the terminus of the Southwestern Branch of the East African Rift System. The lack of syn‐rift magmatism and tectonic processes overprinting pre‐rift structures provide an opportunity to investigate incipient‐stage rift processes and the role of pre‐existing structures in rift initiation and strain localization. We present SEISORZ, a ∼450‐km‐long wide‐angle seismic transect across the ORZ and neighboring tectonic terranes. A 2.5‐D V P tomographic inversion reveals crustal thinning within a ∼130‐km‐wide section of the Damara Belt hosting the ORZ where Moho depth is 38.7 ± 3.4 km, shallower than in other Damara Belt terranes (46.3 ± 1.4 km) and the Kalahari Craton (45.6 ± 2.0 km). Mantle V P is consistent with ultramafic lithologies without evidence for metasomatism, partial melt, or elevated temperatures. Crustal V P is variable but consistent with geological information and with lower‐crustal mafic lithologies. However, beneath the rifting region, the model shows low crustal velocities (Δ V P = −0.26 ± 0.05 km/s) that we interpret as damage from rift‐related faulting and deformation, and to a lesser extent elevated temperatures possibly from excess radiogenic heat production. Upper crustal heterogeneity correlates with known and newly detected intra‐rift faults, suggesting that pre‐existing structures promoted strain localization and establishment of the rift border fault system. Collectively, all these factors point to a rheologically weak section in the Ghanzi‐Chobe zone which is more susceptible to deformation in response to far‐field stresses than neighboring terranes, explaining why incipient rifting is localizing there and not across any other of the terranes that compose the Damara Belt.
Published: 2026-01-17T18:10:58+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.480 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; J. Pablo Canales; Lucky Moffat; Kebabonye Laletsang; Daniel Lizarralde; Steven Harder; Galen Kaip; Estella A. Atekwana; Motsoptse P. Modisi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032322"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032322&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.480 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Okavango Rift Zone (ORZ) is an incipient continental rift in Botswana at the terminus of the Southwestern Branch of the East African Rift System. The lack of syn‐rift magmatism and tectonic processes overprinting pre‐rift structures provide an opportunity to investigate incipient‐stage rift processes and the role of pre‐existing structures in rift initiation and strain localization. We present SEISORZ, a ∼450‐km‐long wide‐angle seismic transect across the ORZ and neighboring tectonic terranes. A 2.5‐D V P tomographic inversion reveals crustal thinning within a ∼130‐km‐wide section of the Damara Belt hosting the ORZ where Moho depth is 38.7 ± 3.4 km, shallower than in other Damara Belt terranes (46.3 ± 1.4 km) and the Kalahari Craton (45.6 ± 2.0 km). Mantle V P is consistent with ultramafic lithologies without evidence for metasomatism, partial melt, or elevated temperatures. Crustal V P is variable but consistent with geological information and with lower‐crustal mafic lithologies. However, beneath the rifting region, the model shows low crustal velocities (Δ V P = −0.26 ± 0.05 km/s) that we interpret as damage from rift‐related faulting and deformation, and to a lesser extent elevated temperatures possibly from excess radiogenic heat production. Upper crustal heterogeneity correlates with known and newly detected intra‐rift faults, suggesting that pre‐existing structures promoted strain localization and establishment of the rift border fault system. Collectively, all these factors point to a rheologically weak section in the Ghanzi‐Chobe zone which is more susceptible to deformation in response to far‐field stresses than neighboring terranes, explaining why incipient rifting is localizing there and not across any other of the terranes that compose the Damara Belt.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Membrane-free CO2 hydrogenation electrolyzer for salt precipitation management in acidic electrochemical CO2 reduction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68600-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68600-3</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jan 2026 17:43:51 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yumin Da</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lei Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenlong Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rui Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haotian Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongqiang Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ganwen Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chonglai Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenrui Ji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tong Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhe Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68600-3</prism:doi><description>Electrochemical CO2 reduction (ECR) in acidic electrolytes minimizes CO2 loss and carbonate formation issues, allowing for high CO2 utilization efficiency and showing good potential for practical CO2 upgrading applications. However, in the membrane-based electrolyzer, the proton transfer efficiency across the membrane from the anolyte to the catholyte is crucial for the stability of the catholyte pH in acidic ECR, especially at high current density and during long-term electrolysis. Here, we investigate the effects of proton transfer efficiency and salt precipitation in different acidic ECR electrolyzer and propose a membrane-free CO2 hydrogenation electrolyzer, which couple CO2 reduction and hydrogen oxidation. This electrolyzer design effectively maintains a stable electrolyte pH during long-term electrolysis, and simultaneously achieves high Faradaic efficiency for HCOOH production, high single-pass carbon utilization efficiency, and a lower cell voltage. At a current density of 100 mA cm−2, the system requires only 1.7 V to achieve a 90% HCOOH Faradaic efficiency and demonstrates stable operation for 208 hours. Acidic electrochemical CO2 reduction promises efficient carbon use, but maintaining stable acidity at high current remains a major challenge. Here, the authors demonstrate a membrane-free CO2 hydrogenation electrolyzer that stabilizes pH and enables efficient and stable formic acid production.
Published: 2026-01-17T17:43:51+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.480 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yumin Da; Lei Fan; Wenlong Wang; Rui Jiang; Haotian Lu; Hongqiang Jin; Ganwen Chen; Chonglai Jiang; Chenrui Ji; Xiang Chen; Tong Zhu; Zhe Wu; Wei Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68600-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68600-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.480 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrochemical CO2 reduction (ECR) in acidic electrolytes minimizes CO2 loss and carbonate formation issues, allowing for high CO2 utilization efficiency and showing good potential for practical CO2 upgrading applications. However, in the membrane-based electrolyzer, the proton transfer efficiency across the membrane from the anolyte to the catholyte is crucial for the stability of the catholyte pH in acidic ECR, especially at high current density and during long-term electrolysis. Here, we investigate the effects of proton transfer efficiency and salt precipitation in different acidic ECR electrolyzer and propose a membrane-free CO2 hydrogenation electrolyzer, which couple CO2 reduction and hydrogen oxidation. This electrolyzer design effectively maintains a stable electrolyte pH during long-term electrolysis, and simultaneously achieves high Faradaic efficiency for HCOOH production, high single-pass carbon utilization efficiency, and a lower cell voltage. At a current density of 100 mA cm−2, the system requires only 1.7 V to achieve a 90% HCOOH Faradaic efficiency and demonstrates stable operation for 208 hours. Acidic electrochemical CO2 reduction promises efficient carbon use, but maintaining stable acidity at high current remains a major challenge. Here, the authors demonstrate a membrane-free CO2 hydrogenation electrolyzer that stabilizes pH and enables efficient and stable formic acid production.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>