<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 23:45:14 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Giant near-field nonlinear electrophotonic effects in an angstrom-scale plasmonic junction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68823-4</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68823-4</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 16:16:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shota Takahashi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Atsunori Sakurai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tatsuto Mochizuki</dc:creator><dc:creator>Toshiki Sugimoto</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68823-4</prism:doi><description>Abstract Plasmons facilitate a strong confinement and enhancement of near-field light, offering exciting opportunities to enhance nonlinear optical responses at the nanoscale. However, despite significant advancements, the electrically tunable range of the nonlinear optical responses at nanometer-scale plasmonic structures remains limited to a few percents per volt. Here, we transcend the limitation of the nanometer regime by expanding the concept of electrophotonics into angstrom-scale platform, enabling high-performance modulation of near-field nonlinear optical responses inaccessible in prior architectures. We demonstrate ~2000% enhancement in second-harmonic generation (SHG) within 1 V of voltage application by utilizing an angstrom-scale plasmonic gap between a metallic tip and a flat metal substrate in a scanning tunneling microscope. Extending this near-field SHG scheme to sum-frequency generation that is accompanied by large frequency upconversion, we also found that such giant electrical modulation of plasmon-enhanced nonlinear optical phenomena is effective over mid-infrared to visible broad wavelength range. Our results and concepts lay the foundation for developing near-field-based angstrom-scale nonlinear electrophotonics with significant modulation depth at low driving voltage.
Published: 2026-01-24T16:16:44+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.593 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shota Takahashi; Atsunori Sakurai; Tatsuto Mochizuki; Toshiki Sugimoto&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68823-4"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68823-4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.593 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Plasmons facilitate a strong confinement and enhancement of near-field light, offering exciting opportunities to enhance nonlinear optical responses at the nanoscale. However, despite significant advancements, the electrically tunable range of the nonlinear optical responses at nanometer-scale plasmonic structures remains limited to a few percents per volt. Here, we transcend the limitation of the nanometer regime by expanding the concept of electrophotonics into angstrom-scale platform, enabling high-performance modulation of near-field nonlinear optical responses inaccessible in prior architectures. We demonstrate ~2000% enhancement in second-harmonic generation (SHG) within 1 V of voltage application by utilizing an angstrom-scale plasmonic gap between a metallic tip and a flat metal substrate in a scanning tunneling microscope. Extending this near-field SHG scheme to sum-frequency generation that is accompanied by large frequency upconversion, we also found that such giant electrical modulation of plasmon-enhanced nonlinear optical phenomena is effective over mid-infrared to visible broad wavelength range. Our results and concepts lay the foundation for developing near-field-based angstrom-scale nonlinear electrophotonics with significant modulation depth at low driving voltage.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mo Isotopic Records Imply Persistent Ocean Oxygenation in the Deep Southwest Pacific During the Early Cenozoic Warming Period</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119743</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119743</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 03:18:47 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiaowen Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaole Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weidong Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuchen Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yufei Hao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sifan Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Le Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Huang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119743</prism:doi><description>Abstract During the early Cenozoic greenhouse period, counterintuitive contractions in tropical Pacific oxygen‐deficient zones have been linked to enhanced deep‐ocean ventilation, yet direct geological evidence remains limited. Here we present molybdenum (Mo) isotopic records from International Ocean Discovery Program Site U1509. Raman spectroscopy shows that Mn and Fe occur mainly as MnO 2 and Fe–Mn oxides. The δ 98 / 95 Mo values show a sustained negative shift from ∼1‰ to −2‰ between ∼59.5 and 50.5 Ma, and this trend is best explained by strengthened Mo adsorption onto Mn and Fe bearing oxides at the sediment–water interface. This mechanism provides a direct basis for interpreting the Mo isotope depletion, indicating prolonged bottom‐water oxygenation within early Cenozoic greenhouse conditions. At ∼50.5 Ma, a sharp decline in silicate εNd values and coeval rises in Ti, Zr, and Sc enrichment factors indicate intensified continental weathering that supplied isotopically light Mo. These results provide new constraints on early Cenozoic redox evolution.
Published: 2026-01-25T03:18:47+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.575 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiaowen Liu; Xiaole Sun; Yi Huang; Weidong Sun; Yuchen Li; Yufei Hao; Sifan Wu; Le Li; Jing Huang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119743"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119743&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.575 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract During the early Cenozoic greenhouse period, counterintuitive contractions in tropical Pacific oxygen‐deficient zones have been linked to enhanced deep‐ocean ventilation, yet direct geological evidence remains limited. Here we present molybdenum (Mo) isotopic records from International Ocean Discovery Program Site U1509. Raman spectroscopy shows that Mn and Fe occur mainly as MnO 2 and Fe–Mn oxides. The δ 98 / 95 Mo values show a sustained negative shift from ∼1‰ to −2‰ between ∼59.5 and 50.5 Ma, and this trend is best explained by strengthened Mo adsorption onto Mn and Fe bearing oxides at the sediment–water interface. This mechanism provides a direct basis for interpreting the Mo isotope depletion, indicating prolonged bottom‐water oxygenation within early Cenozoic greenhouse conditions. At ∼50.5 Ma, a sharp decline in silicate εNd values and coeval rises in Ti, Zr, and Sc enrichment factors indicate intensified continental weathering that supplied isotopically light Mo. These results provide new constraints on early Cenozoic redox evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The H2O component of sheared mantle peridotites from the Kaapvaal craton: evidence for hydrous deformation with implications for the stability of cratons</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02295-5</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02295-5</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 06:00:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Catharina Heckel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anthony C. Withers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alan B. Woodland</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sally A. Gibson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Ludwig</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02295-5</prism:doi><description>Abstract Sheared peridotite xenoliths entrained by kimberlites provide snapshots of metasomatism and deformation within the cratonic mantle. Here, we present H 2 O concentrations of nominally anhydrous minerals (olivine, orthopyroxene and clinopyroxene) in 18 low-, moderate- and high-T sheared peridotites from the Kimberley and northern Lesotho kimberlite cluster (Kaapvaal craton). H 2 O contents range from 2 O concentrations indicate that ortho- and clinopyroxene cores preserve an older metasomatic/deformation event in the lithospheric mantle while olivine cores record the youngest metasomatic event. The latter must have happened immediately prior to xenolith entrainment and transport to the surface. Calculated H 2 O contents for the metasomatic agents range from 1 to 3 wt% H 2 O. We speculate that highly-reactive hydrous (proto-)kimberlitic melts caused oxidizing metasomatism that triggered deformation prior potentially enhanced craton destabilization as well as the local resorption of diamonds.
Published: 2026-01-24T06:00:15+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.559 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Catharina Heckel; Anthony C. Withers; Alan B. Woodland; Sally A. Gibson; Thomas Ludwig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02295-5"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02295-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.559 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Sheared peridotite xenoliths entrained by kimberlites provide snapshots of metasomatism and deformation within the cratonic mantle. Here, we present H 2 O concentrations of nominally anhydrous minerals (olivine, orthopyroxene and clinopyroxene) in 18 low-, moderate- and high-T sheared peridotites from the Kimberley and northern Lesotho kimberlite cluster (Kaapvaal craton). H 2 O contents range from 2 O concentrations indicate that ortho- and clinopyroxene cores preserve an older metasomatic/deformation event in the lithospheric mantle while olivine cores record the youngest metasomatic event. The latter must have happened immediately prior to xenolith entrainment and transport to the surface. Calculated H 2 O contents for the metasomatic agents range from 1 to 3 wt% H 2 O. We speculate that highly-reactive hydrous (proto-)kimberlitic melts caused oxidizing metasomatism that triggered deformation prior potentially enhanced craton destabilization as well as the local resorption of diamonds.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Research on the Characterization of CO
                    &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
                    Mineralization Rate and Its Impact on the Physical and Mechanical Properties of Basalt</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032957</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032957</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:51:02 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Y. Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>J. Bi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Y. Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>C. L. Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>W. Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Y. F. Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. X. Shen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032957</prism:doi><description>Abstract Basalt mineralization storage is widely recognized as a secure, permanent method for large‐scale CO 2 sequestration. At present, the majority of research endeavors are centered around the investigation of reaction mechanisms and microscopic properties. However, research on standard basalt rock samples (before/after storage) and the quantification of CO 2 consumption during reactions remains limited. This study explored CO 2 ‐water‐rock interactions, focusing on how mineral carbonation alters rock physical/mechanical properties and how to characterize CO 2 consumption rate. Experiments were conducted using a self‐designed rock reactor on standard cylindrical basalt samples (from Wenchang, Hainan) under 12 MPa and 70°C for 0, 10, 20, 30, and 60 d. A theoretical CO 2 consumption calculation method (based on pressure drop, accounting for gas‐liquid‐solid three‐phase systems) was proposed. Validated against actual consumption data (from water and rock weigh changes in the reactor), it showed an average absolute deviation (AAD) 2 consumption data were fitted with a double exponential function to derive the reaction rate curve, which peaked initially, then decreased continuously, and finally flattened. Changes in uniaxial compressive strength, tensile strength, Poisson's ratio, elastic modulus, porosity, T 2 and mineral composition were observed at different reaction times. Though siderite and calcite precipitated on sample surfaces, rock dissolution dominated—increasing porosity, reducing mechanical properties and leaving yellowish‐brown precipitates (more pronounced with longer reactions). These findings support safety evaluation of basalt reservoirs.
Published: 2026-01-24T10:51:02+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.559 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Y. Pan; J. Bi; Y. Zhao; C. L. Wang; W. Zhang; Y. F. Zhang; M. X. Shen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032957"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032957&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.559 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Basalt mineralization storage is widely recognized as a secure, permanent method for large‐scale CO 2 sequestration. At present, the majority of research endeavors are centered around the investigation of reaction mechanisms and microscopic properties. However, research on standard basalt rock samples (before/after storage) and the quantification of CO 2 consumption during reactions remains limited. This study explored CO 2 ‐water‐rock interactions, focusing on how mineral carbonation alters rock physical/mechanical properties and how to characterize CO 2 consumption rate. Experiments were conducted using a self‐designed rock reactor on standard cylindrical basalt samples (from Wenchang, Hainan) under 12 MPa and 70°C for 0, 10, 20, 30, and 60 d. A theoretical CO 2 consumption calculation method (based on pressure drop, accounting for gas‐liquid‐solid three‐phase systems) was proposed. Validated against actual consumption data (from water and rock weigh changes in the reactor), it showed an average absolute deviation (AAD) 2 consumption data were fitted with a double exponential function to derive the reaction rate curve, which peaked initially, then decreased continuously, and finally flattened. Changes in uniaxial compressive strength, tensile strength, Poisson&amp;#x27;s ratio, elastic modulus, porosity, T 2 and mineral composition were observed at different reaction times. Though siderite and calcite precipitated on sample surfaces, rock dissolution dominated—increasing porosity, reducing mechanical properties and leaving yellowish‐brown precipitates (more pronounced with longer reactions). These findings support safety evaluation of basalt reservoirs.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mid‐Proterozoic Transient Oxygenation Events Linked to Enhanced Continental Chemical Weathering: Evidence From Carbonate Lithium Isotopes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119617</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119617</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 05:44:40 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lei Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoying Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Philip A. E. Pogge von Strandmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiqiang Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiangli Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yilin Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Lei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qianling Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Limin Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Longfei Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Baozeng Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinqiang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dongjie Tang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119617</prism:doi><description>Abstract Potential drivers disrupting mid‐Proterozoic (∼1.8–0.8 Ga) environmental stasis remain poorly constrained. Here we examined carbonate Li isotopes from the ∼1.44 Ga Tieling Formation, North China, to evaluate the effects of continental chemical weathering on coeval oxygenation. Our results identify two negative excursions in seawater δ 7 Li values, suggesting enhanced continental chemical weathering. Applying a dynamic box model, we demonstrate that 2.5‐fold increase in riverine Li influx coupled with decrease in riverine δ 7 Li by 6‰ can generate the observed data pattern. Intermittently enhanced continental chemical weathering could have delivered elevated nutrients to the ocean, stimulating primary productivity and thus organic carbon burial, favoring the ∼1.44 Ga oxygenation event.
Published: 2026-01-25T05:44:40+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.542 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lei Xu; Xiaoying Shi; Philip A. E. Pogge von Strandmann; Xiqiang Zhou; Xiangli Wang; Yilin Xiao; Jing Lei; Qianling Zhou; Limin Zhou; Longfei Sun; Baozeng Xie; Xinqiang Wang; Dongjie Tang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119617"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119617&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.542 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Potential drivers disrupting mid‐Proterozoic (∼1.8–0.8 Ga) environmental stasis remain poorly constrained. Here we examined carbonate Li isotopes from the ∼1.44 Ga Tieling Formation, North China, to evaluate the effects of continental chemical weathering on coeval oxygenation. Our results identify two negative excursions in seawater δ 7 Li values, suggesting enhanced continental chemical weathering. Applying a dynamic box model, we demonstrate that 2.5‐fold increase in riverine Li influx coupled with decrease in riverine δ 7 Li by 6‰ can generate the observed data pattern. Intermittently enhanced continental chemical weathering could have delivered elevated nutrients to the ocean, stimulating primary productivity and thus organic carbon burial, favoring the ∼1.44 Ga oxygenation event.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Curvature programmed inkjet printing enables adaptive deposition for Gaussian sintering lasers</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68613-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68613-y</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:15:28 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiangyu Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengsen Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianqin Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhi Tao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu Qiu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68613-y</prism:doi><description>The inherent Gaussian intensity distribution of laser beams causes critical issues such as ablation, spattering, and porosity during laser sintering and melting. Although modulating the intensity distribution by a beam shaper can alleviate these problems, it suffers from high cost, limited durability, and significant energy loss. To address these challenges, we propose a thickness-matching strategy that aligns film geometry with the laser intensity profile. Mathematical analysis provides the optimal thickness distribution, while inkjet printing with computable parameters enables curved circuits with ideal profiles. The curved profile strategy demonstrates enhanced performance in both semiconducting and metallic circuits. For indium tin oxide (ITO) conductive glass, up to a 3.8-fold improvement in conductance and a 5.1% increase in transmittance are achieved compared with planar circuits, while for copper (Cu) conformal circuits, the electrical conductivity is improved by 160% compared with planar circuits. This work establishes a practical additive manufacturing route for high-performance conformal circuits. To address non-uniform sintering caused by Gaussian laser beams, the authors use adaptive inkjet printing to form curved circuits that match the light profile, thereby enhancing the electrical and optical performance of metal and semiconductor films.
Published: 2026-01-24T15:15:28+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.531 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiangyu Chen; Mengsen Zhang; Jianqin Zhu; Zhi Tao; Lu Qiu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68613-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68613-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.531 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inherent Gaussian intensity distribution of laser beams causes critical issues such as ablation, spattering, and porosity during laser sintering and melting. Although modulating the intensity distribution by a beam shaper can alleviate these problems, it suffers from high cost, limited durability, and significant energy loss. To address these challenges, we propose a thickness-matching strategy that aligns film geometry with the laser intensity profile. Mathematical analysis provides the optimal thickness distribution, while inkjet printing with computable parameters enables curved circuits with ideal profiles. The curved profile strategy demonstrates enhanced performance in both semiconducting and metallic circuits. For indium tin oxide (ITO) conductive glass, up to a 3.8-fold improvement in conductance and a 5.1% increase in transmittance are achieved compared with planar circuits, while for copper (Cu) conformal circuits, the electrical conductivity is improved by 160% compared with planar circuits. This work establishes a practical additive manufacturing route for high-performance conformal circuits. To address non-uniform sintering caused by Gaussian laser beams, the authors use adaptive inkjet printing to form curved circuits that match the light profile, thereby enhancing the electrical and optical performance of metal and semiconductor films.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Publisher Correction: Tsunamigenic earthquake at the Sunda trench promoted by aseismic slip after a previous megathrust event</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03133-z</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03133-z</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 04:06:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qiang Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eric Lindsey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lujia Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linlin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peizhen Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian Lin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03133-z</prism:doi><description>Correction to: Communications Earth &amp; Environment https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02873-2 , published online 11 November 2025
Published: 2026-01-24T04:06:36+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.488 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qiang Qiu; Eric Lindsey; Lujia Feng; Linlin Li; Peizhen Zhang; Jian Lin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03133-z"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03133-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.488 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Correction to: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02873-2 , published online 11 November 2025&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Supershear Transitions and Bilateral Asymmetric Rupture of the 2025 Sagaing (Myanmar) Earthquake Revealed by Geodetic and Seismic Observations</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119653</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119653</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 06:00:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhenjiang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jyr‐Ching Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenhong Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuang Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chen Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiatong Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuesong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianbing Peng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119653</prism:doi><description>Abstract The Sagaing Fault (SF) accommodates major plate motion in Myanmar, yet large earthquakes along it have rarely been captured by modern geodetic and seismic observations. The 2025 Sagaing earthquake generated an exceptionally long rupture (∼535 km), offering a rare opportunity to investigate rupture dynamics along continental transform fault. We integrate complementary high‐resolution imaging geodesy, teleseismic and strong‐motion waveforms, back‐projection, and finite‐fault inversion to investigate rupture extent, process, and slip evolution. Our results reveal a marked bilateral asymmetry in both rupture extent and speed: it propagated ∼85 km northward at sub‐shear speeds and ∼450 km southward predominantly at supershear speeds (∼6 km/s), punctuated by short sub‐shear segments. We propose that structural barrier and stress shadows limited the extent, whereas the SF's bimaterial interface and local stress‐drop heterogeneity jointly may potentially drive the asymmetric, intermittent supershear behavior. These findings provide new insight into mechanisms controlling complex rupture on continental strike‐slip faults.
Published: 2026-01-25T06:00:45+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.480 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhenjiang Liu; Jyr‐Ching Hu; Zhenhong Li; Chuang Song; Yi Chen; Chen Yu; Jiatong Wang; Xuesong Zhang; Jianbing Peng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119653"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119653&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.480 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The Sagaing Fault (SF) accommodates major plate motion in Myanmar, yet large earthquakes along it have rarely been captured by modern geodetic and seismic observations. The 2025 Sagaing earthquake generated an exceptionally long rupture (∼535 km), offering a rare opportunity to investigate rupture dynamics along continental transform fault. We integrate complementary high‐resolution imaging geodesy, teleseismic and strong‐motion waveforms, back‐projection, and finite‐fault inversion to investigate rupture extent, process, and slip evolution. Our results reveal a marked bilateral asymmetry in both rupture extent and speed: it propagated ∼85 km northward at sub‐shear speeds and ∼450 km southward predominantly at supershear speeds (∼6 km/s), punctuated by short sub‐shear segments. We propose that structural barrier and stress shadows limited the extent, whereas the SF&amp;#x27;s bimaterial interface and local stress‐drop heterogeneity jointly may potentially drive the asymmetric, intermittent supershear behavior. These findings provide new insight into mechanisms controlling complex rupture on continental strike‐slip faults.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Connecting the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation to the Southern Ocean Following the Closure of Equatorial Seaways During the Cenozoic</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119115</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119115</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 06:26:20 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Erwan Pineau</dc:creator><dc:creator>Camille Lique</dc:creator><dc:creator>David Ferreira</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thierry Huck</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jean‐Baptiste Ladant</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emma Fabre</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeanne Millot‐Weil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yannick Donnadieu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119115</prism:doi><description>Abstract Global ocean circulation regulates climate and has undergone significant changes over the Cenozoic. Today, the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) is driven by North Atlantic Deep Water (NADW) formation and Southern Ocean upwelling. By contrast, during the middle Eocene to early Oligocene (48–28 Ma), a restricted Drake Passage was limiting the northern Ekman transport, while a circum‐equatorial current sustained by trade winds promoted low‐latitude upwelling. Our set of simulations with the IPSL‐CM5A2 model reveals that this paleogeographic setting favored proto‐NADW upwelling at low latitudes, confining the AMOC to the Northern Hemisphere. Consequently, the role of southern westerly winds was limited, and the northward heat transport was weaker than in the modern ocean.
Published: 2026-01-25T06:26:20+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.478 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Erwan Pineau; Camille Lique; David Ferreira; Thierry Huck; Jean‐Baptiste Ladant; Emma Fabre; Jeanne Millot‐Weil; Yannick Donnadieu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119115"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119115&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.478 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Global ocean circulation regulates climate and has undergone significant changes over the Cenozoic. Today, the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) is driven by North Atlantic Deep Water (NADW) formation and Southern Ocean upwelling. By contrast, during the middle Eocene to early Oligocene (48–28 Ma), a restricted Drake Passage was limiting the northern Ekman transport, while a circum‐equatorial current sustained by trade winds promoted low‐latitude upwelling. Our set of simulations with the IPSL‐CM5A2 model reveals that this paleogeographic setting favored proto‐NADW upwelling at low latitudes, confining the AMOC to the Northern Hemisphere. Consequently, the role of southern westerly winds was limited, and the northward heat transport was weaker than in the modern ocean.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Craters and Lunar Lua (Pits/Skylights) in Mare Tranquillitatis and Marius Hills Reveal Variations in Protolith Properties</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009427</link><guid>10.1029/2025je009427</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 09:50:18 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>E. S. Costello</dc:creator><dc:creator>C. L. Acohido</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. A. Chertok</dc:creator><dc:creator>C. M. Ferrari‐Wong</dc:creator><dc:creator>C. L. Slagle</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Ito</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025je009427</prism:doi><description>Abstract We investigated the regolith parent rock (“protolith”) properties of Mare Tranquillitatis and Marius Hills on the Moon, utilizing lunar pit craters (“lua”) to contextualize observations of rock abundance and crater degradation. We discovered a significant difference in underlying materials: the region around the Tranquillitatis lua is characterized by a competent, dense, solidified basalt, whereas the region around the Marius Hills lua exhibits a more friable protolith, indicative of porous or vesicular volcanic deposits. These distinct protoliths directly influence rock evolution, with the Marius Hills region demonstrating higher initial rock excavation but also more rapid degradation of rocky ejecta and interiors, while the Mare Tranquillitatis region produces larger, more persistent blocks that resist fragmentation for longer periods. Consequently, the competent protolith of Mare Tranquillitatis makes its lua an ideal candidate for future lunar exploration missions, offering superior geotechnical integrity for potential subsurface habitats and enhanced protection from surface radiation and impact bombardment.
Published: 2026-01-24T09:50:18+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets
Score: 0.478 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; E. S. Costello; C. L. Acohido; M. A. Chertok; C. M. Ferrari‐Wong; C. L. Slagle; A. Ito&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009427"&gt;10.1029/2025je009427&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.478 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract We investigated the regolith parent rock (“protolith”) properties of Mare Tranquillitatis and Marius Hills on the Moon, utilizing lunar pit craters (“lua”) to contextualize observations of rock abundance and crater degradation. We discovered a significant difference in underlying materials: the region around the Tranquillitatis lua is characterized by a competent, dense, solidified basalt, whereas the region around the Marius Hills lua exhibits a more friable protolith, indicative of porous or vesicular volcanic deposits. These distinct protoliths directly influence rock evolution, with the Marius Hills region demonstrating higher initial rock excavation but also more rapid degradation of rocky ejecta and interiors, while the Mare Tranquillitatis region produces larger, more persistent blocks that resist fragmentation for longer periods. Consequently, the competent protolith of Mare Tranquillitatis makes its lua an ideal candidate for future lunar exploration missions, offering superior geotechnical integrity for potential subsurface habitats and enhanced protection from surface radiation and impact bombardment.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Residence time of Hunga stratospheric water vapour perturbation quantified at 9 years</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03216-5</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03216-5</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 16:34:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xin Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Quanliang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wuhu Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Saffron Heddell</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sandip S. Dhomse</dc:creator><dc:creator>Graham Mann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hugh C. Pumphrey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luis Millán</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michelle L. Santee</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martyn P. Chipperfield</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03216-5</prism:doi><description>Abstract The January 2022 eruption of the Hunga volcano (20 ∘ S) injected 150 Tg of water vapour into the middle atmosphere, leading to an increase in the stratospheric water burden of 10%, unprecedented in the observational record. In the first two years post eruption the stratospheric burden hardly changed, leaving the residence time of volcanically injected water vapour, a key control on its climate impact, uncertain. Here, using satellite observations, we show a substantial decline from 2024 to early 2025, the largest drop since the eruption. Comparison with 3-D numerical model simulations shows that the long-term removal of the Hunga water has now entered a new phase, with stratosphere-troposphere exchange playing an increasingly important role, exceeding Antarctic dehydration in 2024. We estimate that the additional stratospheric water vapour is now decaying steadily with an e-folding time of 3 years and will reach the observed pre-Hunga range of variability around 2030.
Published: 2026-01-24T16:34:45+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.471 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xin Zhou; Quanliang Chen; Wuhu Feng; Saffron Heddell; Sandip S. Dhomse; Graham Mann; Hugh C. Pumphrey; Luis Millán; Michelle L. Santee; Martyn P. Chipperfield&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03216-5"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03216-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.471 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The January 2022 eruption of the Hunga volcano (20 ∘ S) injected 150 Tg of water vapour into the middle atmosphere, leading to an increase in the stratospheric water burden of 10%, unprecedented in the observational record. In the first two years post eruption the stratospheric burden hardly changed, leaving the residence time of volcanically injected water vapour, a key control on its climate impact, uncertain. Here, using satellite observations, we show a substantial decline from 2024 to early 2025, the largest drop since the eruption. Comparison with 3-D numerical model simulations shows that the long-term removal of the Hunga water has now entered a new phase, with stratosphere-troposphere exchange playing an increasingly important role, exceeding Antarctic dehydration in 2024. We estimate that the additional stratospheric water vapour is now decaying steadily with an e-folding time of 3 years and will reach the observed pre-Hunga range of variability around 2030.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>An open decoupled cell design achieving electricity generation and amplification through waste-to-energy conversion</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68550-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68550-w</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 04:36:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhiyang Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng-Yi Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bosi Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiahe Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiqiang Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhexuan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiachang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiongwei Zhong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Boran Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guangmin Zhou</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68550-w</prism:doi><description>Conventional closed batteries are constrained by the electrical energy efficiency of 100%, inevitably leading to the reduction of electricity storage. In contrast, open decoupled batteries offer the possibility to break this limitation, but remain unexplored. Here, we develop a highly efficient and sustainable open decoupled battery through a three-electrodynamic-potential (3E) design, simultaneously realizing waste-to-energy conversion, power generation and energy storage. For decoupled electrodes, we engineer high discharge voltage (ED) incorporating zinc oxidation and oxygen reduction reactions, and low charge voltage (EC) involving zinc-ion reduction and hydrazine (waste) oxidation reactions. Furthermore, we introduce reverse electrodialysis potential (ERED) by decoupling electrolytes. Consequently, the assembled battery demonstrates stability for 1000 cycles at the fast-charging current density of 300 mA cm−2. Moreover, a scaled 20-Ah-capacity battery was performed achieving a high electrical energy efficiency of 375% at 10 mA cm−2. Techno-economic analyses reveal that storing one megawatt-hour of electricity using the open decoupled battery can reduce the cost and carbon emissions of power generation by over 80% compared to conventional batteries. This work establishes a foundation for designing electricity-amplified batteries with economic and environmental benefits. Conventional closed batteries are constrained by the electrical energy efficiency of 100%. Here, authors develop an open decoupled battery with an efficiency of 375% at 10 mA cm−2 through a three electrodynamic-potential design, realizing waste-to-energy conversion and electricity amplification.
Published: 2026-01-24T04:36:50+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.469 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhiyang Zheng; Feng-Yi Zheng; Bosi Huang; Jiahe Xu; Zhiqiang Xiao; Zhexuan Liu; Jiachang Liu; Xiongwei Zhong; Boran Wang; Guangmin Zhou&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68550-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68550-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.469 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventional closed batteries are constrained by the electrical energy efficiency of 100%, inevitably leading to the reduction of electricity storage. In contrast, open decoupled batteries offer the possibility to break this limitation, but remain unexplored. Here, we develop a highly efficient and sustainable open decoupled battery through a three-electrodynamic-potential (3E) design, simultaneously realizing waste-to-energy conversion, power generation and energy storage. For decoupled electrodes, we engineer high discharge voltage (ED) incorporating zinc oxidation and oxygen reduction reactions, and low charge voltage (EC) involving zinc-ion reduction and hydrazine (waste) oxidation reactions. Furthermore, we introduce reverse electrodialysis potential (ERED) by decoupling electrolytes. Consequently, the assembled battery demonstrates stability for 1000 cycles at the fast-charging current density of 300 mA cm−2. Moreover, a scaled 20-Ah-capacity battery was performed achieving a high electrical energy efficiency of 375% at 10 mA cm−2. Techno-economic analyses reveal that storing one megawatt-hour of electricity using the open decoupled battery can reduce the cost and carbon emissions of power generation by over 80% compared to conventional batteries. This work establishes a foundation for designing electricity-amplified batteries with economic and environmental benefits. Conventional closed batteries are constrained by the electrical energy efficiency of 100%. Here, authors develop an open decoupled battery with an efficiency of 375% at 10 mA cm−2 through a three electrodynamic-potential design, realizing waste-to-energy conversion and electricity amplification.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Entanglement-inspired frequency-agile rangefinding</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68589-9</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68589-9</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 12:14:37 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Weijie Nie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peide Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alex McMillan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alex S. Clark</dc:creator><dc:creator>John G. Rarity</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68589-9</prism:doi><description>Abstract Entanglement, a key feature of quantum mechanics, is recognized for its non-classical correlations which have been shown to provide significant noise resistance in single-photon rangefinding and communications. Drawing inspiration from the advantage given by energy-time entanglement, we developed an energy-time correlated source based on a classical laser that preserves the substantial noise reduction typical of quantum illumination while surpassing the quantum brightness limitation by over six orders of magnitude, making it highly suitable for practical remote sensing applications. A frequency-agile pseudo-random source is realized through fiber chromatic dispersion and pulse carving using an electro-optic intensity modulator. Operating at a faint transmission power of 48 μ W, the distance between two buildings 154.8182 m apart can be measured with a precision better than 0.1 mm, under varying solar background levels and weather conditions with an integration time of only 100 ms. These trials verified the predicted noise reduction of this system, demonstrating advantages over quantum illumination-based rangefinding and highlighting its potential for practical remote sensing applications.
Published: 2026-01-24T12:14:37+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.461 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Weijie Nie; Peide Zhang; Alex McMillan; Alex S. Clark; John G. Rarity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68589-9"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68589-9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.461 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Entanglement, a key feature of quantum mechanics, is recognized for its non-classical correlations which have been shown to provide significant noise resistance in single-photon rangefinding and communications. Drawing inspiration from the advantage given by energy-time entanglement, we developed an energy-time correlated source based on a classical laser that preserves the substantial noise reduction typical of quantum illumination while surpassing the quantum brightness limitation by over six orders of magnitude, making it highly suitable for practical remote sensing applications. A frequency-agile pseudo-random source is realized through fiber chromatic dispersion and pulse carving using an electro-optic intensity modulator. Operating at a faint transmission power of 48 μ W, the distance between two buildings 154.8182 m apart can be measured with a precision better than 0.1 mm, under varying solar background levels and weather conditions with an integration time of only 100 ms. These trials verified the predicted noise reduction of this system, demonstrating advantages over quantum illumination-based rangefinding and highlighting its potential for practical remote sensing applications.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Spatial Patterns of Organic Sulfur and Its Limited Association With Bacterial Communities in the Bohai and Yellow Seas</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc023819</link><guid>10.1029/2025jc023819</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 07:19:56 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Changjie Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Quanrui Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shujing Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nianzhi Jiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Tang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jc023819</prism:doi><description>Abstract While the importance of organic sulfur for marine bacteria is widely recognized, how it relates to bacterial community composition, particularly in coastal environments, remains poorly understood. In this study, we quantified dissolved organic sulfur (DOS) and particulate organic sulfur (POS) in the Bohai and Yellow Seas. DOS ranged from 1.7 to 6.8 μM in surface waters and 0.9–5.4 μM in bottom waters, while POS ranged from 0.3 to 1.7 μM in surface waters and 0.2–1.6 μM in bottom waters. In the Bohai Sea, particulate and dissolved C:S ratios averaged 57 ± 38 and 41.4 ± 7.5, respectively, with minimum sulfur inventories of 0.039 ± 0.025 (POS) and 0.300 ± 0.058 Tg S (DOS). In contrast, the Yellow Sea had a lower particulate C:S ratio (25 ± 17) but a comparable dissolved ratio (46.5 ± 12.5), alongside minimum inventories of 1.14 ± 0.69 (POS) and 1.91 ± 0.52 Tg S (DOS). In contrast to previously reported data from the open ocean, the Bohai and Yellow Seas are characterized by distinctly higher organic sulfur concentrations and lower molar C:S ratios. Bacterial communities differed significantly between surface and bottom waters in terms of diversity and network complexity. However, path analysis showed no significant association of organic sulfur with bacterial community composition in either layer. These findings suggest that despite high total organic sulfur concentrations in these coastal waters, its low concentration of bioavailable fractions and taxon‐specific utilization may explain its limited association with bacterial community.
Published: 2026-01-24T07:19:56+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans
Score: 0.459 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Changjie Dong; Quanrui Chen; Shujing Liu; Nianzhi Jiao; Kai Tang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc023819"&gt;10.1029/2025jc023819&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.459 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract While the importance of organic sulfur for marine bacteria is widely recognized, how it relates to bacterial community composition, particularly in coastal environments, remains poorly understood. In this study, we quantified dissolved organic sulfur (DOS) and particulate organic sulfur (POS) in the Bohai and Yellow Seas. DOS ranged from 1.7 to 6.8 μM in surface waters and 0.9–5.4 μM in bottom waters, while POS ranged from 0.3 to 1.7 μM in surface waters and 0.2–1.6 μM in bottom waters. In the Bohai Sea, particulate and dissolved C:S ratios averaged 57 ± 38 and 41.4 ± 7.5, respectively, with minimum sulfur inventories of 0.039 ± 0.025 (POS) and 0.300 ± 0.058 Tg S (DOS). In contrast, the Yellow Sea had a lower particulate C:S ratio (25 ± 17) but a comparable dissolved ratio (46.5 ± 12.5), alongside minimum inventories of 1.14 ± 0.69 (POS) and 1.91 ± 0.52 Tg S (DOS). In contrast to previously reported data from the open ocean, the Bohai and Yellow Seas are characterized by distinctly higher organic sulfur concentrations and lower molar C:S ratios. Bacterial communities differed significantly between surface and bottom waters in terms of diversity and network complexity. However, path analysis showed no significant association of organic sulfur with bacterial community composition in either layer. These findings suggest that despite high total organic sulfur concentrations in these coastal waters, its low concentration of bioavailable fractions and taxon‐specific utilization may explain its limited association with bacterial community.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Frozen Ground Induces Seawater Retreat in Coastal Unconfined Aquifers</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117947</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl117947</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 05:41:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiayang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yue Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Pu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junjie Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pei Xin</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl117947</prism:doi><description>Abstract While seawater intrusion (SWI) in coastal aquifers has been extensively investigated, most studies focused on unfrozen conditions. In many cold regions, frozen ground is common, yet its impact on SWI remains poorly understood. Here, we demonstrate that the formation of frozen ground alters salinity distribution in coastal unconfined aquifers, based on laboratory experiments and numerical simulations. Under steady‐state conditions with subzero ground temperature, frozen ground creates a confined flow path between itself and the saltwater wedge. This configuration accelerates terrestrial groundwater flow and induces a pronounced seaward retreat of the saltwater wedge. Moreover, lower ground surface and groundwater temperatures enhance this effect by promoting frozen ground formation. These findings have important implications for understanding salinity dynamics in coastal cold‐region aquifers with varying frozen ground.
Published: 2026-01-25T05:41:14+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.451 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiayang Yu; Yue Li; Li Pu; Junjie Wu; Pei Xin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl117947"&gt;10.1029/2025gl117947&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.451 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract While seawater intrusion (SWI) in coastal aquifers has been extensively investigated, most studies focused on unfrozen conditions. In many cold regions, frozen ground is common, yet its impact on SWI remains poorly understood. Here, we demonstrate that the formation of frozen ground alters salinity distribution in coastal unconfined aquifers, based on laboratory experiments and numerical simulations. Under steady‐state conditions with subzero ground temperature, frozen ground creates a confined flow path between itself and the saltwater wedge. This configuration accelerates terrestrial groundwater flow and induces a pronounced seaward retreat of the saltwater wedge. Moreover, lower ground surface and groundwater temperatures enhance this effect by promoting frozen ground formation. These findings have important implications for understanding salinity dynamics in coastal cold‐region aquifers with varying frozen ground.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Bernoulli’s principle-mediated Cl2 electrosynthesis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66643-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66643-6</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:24:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhihao Nie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoliang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingjing Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Markus Antonietti</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sheng Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66643-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract Existing technologies for chlorine (Cl 2 ) synthesis are generally suffered from low productivity or high production cost. Guided by Bernoulli’s principle, here we report an efficient yet cost-effective electrochemical system for Cl 2 electrosynthesis, which is composed of anodic chlorine evolution reaction (CER) connected to gas chamber by triple-phase gas diffusion layer. The key is to modulate gas diffusion layer by Bernoulli’s principle, wherein the pressure difference at triple-phase boundary drives oriented Cl 2 migration directly into gas chamber, thus preventing the crossover of anodic/cathodic products. By further joining with a pH-tolerant catalyst, a standalone prototype device is built for high-rate Cl 2 production, operating at the Faradaic efficiencies of 96.3% ~ 87.6% in the current density range of 0.1 ~ 1.14 A cm −2 , having superior Cl 2 synthesis performance. Further technical-economic evaluations of our synthetic scheme demonstrate reduced Cl 2 production cost, saving 6.75% (1.17 million dollar per year) as comparison to conventional chlor-alkali design. We expect these findings offer broader opportunities to develop industrially production processes for other chemical commodities.
Published: 2026-01-24T14:24:15+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.450 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhihao Nie; Guoliang Xu; Jingjing Duan; Markus Antonietti; Sheng Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66643-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66643-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.450 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Existing technologies for chlorine (Cl 2 ) synthesis are generally suffered from low productivity or high production cost. Guided by Bernoulli’s principle, here we report an efficient yet cost-effective electrochemical system for Cl 2 electrosynthesis, which is composed of anodic chlorine evolution reaction (CER) connected to gas chamber by triple-phase gas diffusion layer. The key is to modulate gas diffusion layer by Bernoulli’s principle, wherein the pressure difference at triple-phase boundary drives oriented Cl 2 migration directly into gas chamber, thus preventing the crossover of anodic/cathodic products. By further joining with a pH-tolerant catalyst, a standalone prototype device is built for high-rate Cl 2 production, operating at the Faradaic efficiencies of 96.3% ~ 87.6% in the current density range of 0.1 ~ 1.14 A cm −2 , having superior Cl 2 synthesis performance. Further technical-economic evaluations of our synthetic scheme demonstrate reduced Cl 2 production cost, saving 6.75% (1.17 million dollar per year) as comparison to conventional chlor-alkali design. We expect these findings offer broader opportunities to develop industrially production processes for other chemical commodities.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hydration Features on Vesta's Surface Seen by the Dawn Visible and Infrared Spectrometer (VIR) Data</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009209</link><guid>10.1029/2025je009209</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:15:03 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shuai Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025je009209</prism:doi><description>Abstract Understanding the sources of hydration on Vesta's surface provides insights into water origins in the inner solar system. We estimated the hydration content across Vesta's surface using new calibrated Dawn VIR data. High content of hydration (up to 1,000 ppm) was observed in previously identified carbonaceous chondrite (CC)‐rich regions. CC‐poor areas consistently showed around 100 ppm of solar wind‐induced hydration with no latitudinal dependence, likely due to Vesta's low surface temperatures and high axial tilt. Despite receiving less solar wind flux, Vesta's low‐latitude surfaces exhibit higher hydration content than the Moon's, attributed to better hydration retention at lower temperatures (e.g., ∼80°) where the maximum daytime temperatures are less than ∼280 K, the Moon can effectively retain around four to five times hydration as that on Vesta, which is in great accordance with the greater solar wind fluence received by the Moon at its heliocentric distance. Our study suggested that the formation of water by solar wind implantation is ubiquitous on airless bodies in the solar system and that the retention of solar wind water is dominantly controlled by surface temperatures of these bodies.
Published: 2026-01-24T10:15:03+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets
Score: 0.449 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shuai Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Planets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025je009209"&gt;10.1029/2025je009209&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.449 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Understanding the sources of hydration on Vesta&amp;#x27;s surface provides insights into water origins in the inner solar system. We estimated the hydration content across Vesta&amp;#x27;s surface using new calibrated Dawn VIR data. High content of hydration (up to 1,000 ppm) was observed in previously identified carbonaceous chondrite (CC)‐rich regions. CC‐poor areas consistently showed around 100 ppm of solar wind‐induced hydration with no latitudinal dependence, likely due to Vesta&amp;#x27;s low surface temperatures and high axial tilt. Despite receiving less solar wind flux, Vesta&amp;#x27;s low‐latitude surfaces exhibit higher hydration content than the Moon&amp;#x27;s, attributed to better hydration retention at lower temperatures (e.g., ∼80°) where the maximum daytime temperatures are less than ∼280 K, the Moon can effectively retain around four to five times hydration as that on Vesta, which is in great accordance with the greater solar wind fluence received by the Moon at its heliocentric distance. Our study suggested that the formation of water by solar wind implantation is ubiquitous on airless bodies in the solar system and that the retention of solar wind water is dominantly controlled by surface temperatures of these bodies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Printing technologies for monitoring crop health</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68778-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68778-6</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:47:34 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>David Panáček</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vojtěch Kupka</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin-Alex Nalepa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ivan Dědek</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruslan Álvarez-Diduk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Selin Olenik</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jose Flauzino</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jan Zdražil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Petr Jakubec</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lukáš Zdražil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lukáš Spíchal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Keval K. Sonigara</dc:creator><dc:creator>Radek Zbořil</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin Pumera</dc:creator><dc:creator>Arben Merkoçi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joseph Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nuria De Diego</dc:creator><dc:creator>Firat Güder</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michal Otyepka</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68778-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract Agricultural production requires low-cost sensors capable of delivering reliable, high-resolution data across large areas. Rising food demand, limited arable land, and severe soil degradation have accelerated the adoption of precision agriculture, which relies on real-time monitoring of soil, plant, and environmental conditions. Central to this shift is the development of scalable sensor technologies enabled by advances in materials science. Printing techniques, including inkjet, screen, aerosol jet, 3D printing, and direct laser writing, offer versatile routes to fabricate flexible, large-area, and plant-integrated sensors. This Review surveys recent progress in printable low-dimensional materials for agricultural sensing, examines their physicochemical properties in relation to sensor performance, and discusses key challenges and future opportunities requiring interdisciplinary integration.
Published: 2026-01-24T15:47:34+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.447 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; David Panáček; Vojtěch Kupka; Martin-Alex Nalepa; Ivan Dědek; Ruslan Álvarez-Diduk; Selin Olenik; Jose Flauzino; Jan Zdražil; Petr Jakubec; Lukáš Zdražil; Lukáš Spíchal; Keval K. Sonigara; Radek Zbořil; Martin Pumera; Arben Merkoçi; Joseph Wang; Nuria De Diego; Firat Güder; Michal Otyepka&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68778-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68778-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.447 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Agricultural production requires low-cost sensors capable of delivering reliable, high-resolution data across large areas. Rising food demand, limited arable land, and severe soil degradation have accelerated the adoption of precision agriculture, which relies on real-time monitoring of soil, plant, and environmental conditions. Central to this shift is the development of scalable sensor technologies enabled by advances in materials science. Printing techniques, including inkjet, screen, aerosol jet, 3D printing, and direct laser writing, offer versatile routes to fabricate flexible, large-area, and plant-integrated sensors. This Review surveys recent progress in printable low-dimensional materials for agricultural sensing, examines their physicochemical properties in relation to sensor performance, and discusses key challenges and future opportunities requiring interdisciplinary integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A Decadal Survey of the Near‐Surface Seismic Velocity Response to Hydrological Variations in Utah, United States</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2024jb030689</link><guid>10.1029/2024jb030689</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:46:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kuan‐Fu Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marine Denolle</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fan‐Chi Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tonie van Dam</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2024jb030689</prism:doi><description>Abstract Ongoing climate change is leading to an increase in prolonged droughts and severe weather events, which are particularly pronounced in semi‐arid regions, such as the western United States. These extremes could have lasting social and environmental impacts. Continuous monitoring of near‐surface hydrological processes and groundwater resources provides helpful information for effective water resource management. The seismological signature of groundwater fluctuations is clear in the temporal variations in seismic velocities, dv/v. To this end, developing a proxy for groundwater level using dv/v represents an opportunity, but further understanding of the relation between dv/v and subsurface hydrology is required. In this study, we apply single‐station cross‐component correlation analysis to 28 broadband seismic stations in Utah between January 2006 and March 2023 and analyze the dv/v in the 2–4 Hz frequency band. To explain dv/v, we linearly superimpose thermoelastic stresses, soil moisture estimated from remote sensing data products, and a long‐term deep water table pore pressure. We find that the relative contributions of each depend on the location. Still, adding a long‐term water table decline, which is not systematically observed in soil moisture, better fits our data. We conclude that soil moisture alone does not explain the variations in total water storage when subsurface moisture is decoupled from the deep‐water table. We also conclude that dv/v can be used as a proxy for water storage.
Published: 2026-01-24T10:46:14+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.447 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kuan‐Fu Feng; Marine Denolle; Fan‐Chi Lin; Tonie van Dam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2024jb030689"&gt;10.1029/2024jb030689&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.447 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Ongoing climate change is leading to an increase in prolonged droughts and severe weather events, which are particularly pronounced in semi‐arid regions, such as the western United States. These extremes could have lasting social and environmental impacts. Continuous monitoring of near‐surface hydrological processes and groundwater resources provides helpful information for effective water resource management. The seismological signature of groundwater fluctuations is clear in the temporal variations in seismic velocities, dv/v. To this end, developing a proxy for groundwater level using dv/v represents an opportunity, but further understanding of the relation between dv/v and subsurface hydrology is required. In this study, we apply single‐station cross‐component correlation analysis to 28 broadband seismic stations in Utah between January 2006 and March 2023 and analyze the dv/v in the 2–4 Hz frequency band. To explain dv/v, we linearly superimpose thermoelastic stresses, soil moisture estimated from remote sensing data products, and a long‐term deep water table pore pressure. We find that the relative contributions of each depend on the location. Still, adding a long‐term water table decline, which is not systematically observed in soil moisture, better fits our data. We conclude that soil moisture alone does not explain the variations in total water storage when subsurface moisture is decoupled from the deep‐water table. We also conclude that dv/v can be used as a proxy for water storage.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Flow‐Dependent Inertial Permeability Defines Crossover Between Darcy and Forchheimer Flow Regimes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120616</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl120616</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 02:54:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kuldeep Singh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Negin Sharifabad</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl120616</prism:doi><description>Abstract We present mechanistic evidence that the Forchheimer inertial permeability coefficient () is flow‐dependent in the weak‐to‐intermediate inertia crossover regime, governed by pore‐scale eddy growth‐to‐confinement dynamics. In contrast to classical theory, attains steady‐state () asymptotically in the dominant inertial regime, marking the validity of Forchheimer law. This highlights a hydrodynamic gap between Darcy and Forchheimer regimes, which is addressed using a physics‐based Eddy‐Growth Dynamics–Inertial Permeability (EG‐DIP) model. The EG‐DIP model contributes to ongoing discussions on inertial permeability by providing a framework to determine , integrate it into Forchheimer law, and suggest a physical basis for estimating . This supports predictive modeling of flow across regimes and identifies as the characteristic medium‐specific property for reliable correlation with porosity, permeability, and grain size. By unifying inertial flow theory through eddy growth dynamics, the EG‐DIP model has direct implications for injection‐induced seismicity, CO 2 storage security, and geothermal energy recovery.
Published: 2026-01-25T02:54:45+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.445 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kuldeep Singh; Negin Sharifabad&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl120616"&gt;10.1029/2025gl120616&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.445 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract We present mechanistic evidence that the Forchheimer inertial permeability coefficient () is flow‐dependent in the weak‐to‐intermediate inertia crossover regime, governed by pore‐scale eddy growth‐to‐confinement dynamics. In contrast to classical theory, attains steady‐state () asymptotically in the dominant inertial regime, marking the validity of Forchheimer law. This highlights a hydrodynamic gap between Darcy and Forchheimer regimes, which is addressed using a physics‐based Eddy‐Growth Dynamics–Inertial Permeability (EG‐DIP) model. The EG‐DIP model contributes to ongoing discussions on inertial permeability by providing a framework to determine , integrate it into Forchheimer law, and suggest a physical basis for estimating . This supports predictive modeling of flow across regimes and identifies as the characteristic medium‐specific property for reliable correlation with porosity, permeability, and grain size. By unifying inertial flow theory through eddy growth dynamics, the EG‐DIP model has direct implications for injection‐induced seismicity, CO 2 storage security, and geothermal energy recovery.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Duration of super-emitting oil and gas methane sources</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68804-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68804-7</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 16:16:45 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Daniel H. Cusworth</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel M. Bon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel J. Varon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alana K. Ayasse</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gregory P. Asner</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joseph Heckler</dc:creator><dc:creator>Evan D. Sherwin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sebastien C. Biraud</dc:creator><dc:creator>Riley M. Duren</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68804-7</prism:doi><description>The duration of super-emitting events (&amp;gt;100 kg h-1) in oil and gas basins remains insufficiently understood but is key for reporting programs and mitigation strategies. Carbon Mapper conducted aerial surveys from April 30 to May 17, 2024, over the New Mexico Permian Basin, covering 276,000 wells, 1100 compressor stations, 175 gas processing plants, and 27,000 km of pipeline. We find over 500 super-emitting sources with 300 of these sources observed repeatedly across multiple days. We quantify total super emissions by integrating individual events with observationally constrained event durations (5.98 −14.7 Gg CH4) and compare to total emissions derived from basin average snapshots (12.7 ± 0.92 Gg CH4). This gap between emission estimates is reconciled through assumptions on missed detections, characteristic event duration, detection frequency, and diurnal variability. Emission events generally lasted for at least 2 hours, and a small subset of sources (18 total), persistently emitted throughout the entire campaign, representing a near-term opportunity for mitigation. When compared to regional flux estimates derived from independent observations, we estimate super-emitters to contribute approximately 50% (37-73%) towards total emissions. Frequent wide-area monitoring is crucial for capturing rare super-emitter events that, together with other emission sources, drive basin-level variability and emission intensity. Aerial surveys over the Permian Basin found 500+ major methane leaks, many recurring. A few sites leaked continuously and offer quick mitigation wins. These super-emitters may produce ~50% of regional emissions, underscoring the need for frequent monitoring.
Published: 2026-01-24T16:16:45+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.440 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Daniel H. Cusworth; Daniel M. Bon; Daniel J. Varon; Alana K. Ayasse; Gregory P. Asner; Joseph Heckler; Evan D. Sherwin; Sebastien C. Biraud; Riley M. Duren&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68804-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68804-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.440 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duration of super-emitting events (&amp;amp;gt;100 kg h-1) in oil and gas basins remains insufficiently understood but is key for reporting programs and mitigation strategies. Carbon Mapper conducted aerial surveys from April 30 to May 17, 2024, over the New Mexico Permian Basin, covering 276,000 wells, 1100 compressor stations, 175 gas processing plants, and 27,000 km of pipeline. We find over 500 super-emitting sources with 300 of these sources observed repeatedly across multiple days. We quantify total super emissions by integrating individual events with observationally constrained event durations (5.98 −14.7 Gg CH4) and compare to total emissions derived from basin average snapshots (12.7 ± 0.92 Gg CH4). This gap between emission estimates is reconciled through assumptions on missed detections, characteristic event duration, detection frequency, and diurnal variability. Emission events generally lasted for at least 2 hours, and a small subset of sources (18 total), persistently emitted throughout the entire campaign, representing a near-term opportunity for mitigation. When compared to regional flux estimates derived from independent observations, we estimate super-emitters to contribute approximately 50% (37-73%) towards total emissions. Frequent wide-area monitoring is crucial for capturing rare super-emitter events that, together with other emission sources, drive basin-level variability and emission intensity. Aerial surveys over the Permian Basin found 500+ major methane leaks, many recurring. A few sites leaked continuously and offer quick mitigation wins. These super-emitters may produce ~50% of regional emissions, underscoring the need for frequent monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Permafrost and wildfire carbon emissions indicate need for additional action to keep Paris Agreement temperature goals within reach</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03189-5</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-026-03189-5</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 07:04:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Christina Schädel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Gasser</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brendan M. Rogers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rachael Treharne</dc:creator><dc:creator>Merritt R. Turetsky</dc:creator><dc:creator>Trevor Smith</dc:creator><dc:creator>Erin MacDonald</dc:creator><dc:creator>Susan M. Natali</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-026-03189-5</prism:doi><description>Rapid Arctic warming is thawing carbon-rich permafrost, releasing greenhouse gases that accelerate climate change. Despite the importance of this feedback, permafrost-enabled global-scale models simulate only gradual, top-down thickening of the seasonally-thawed soil. This ignores abrupt permafrost thaw and intensifying fire regimes that combust soil carbon and further accelerate thaw. Here, we expand a compact Earth system model (OSCAR v3.0) enabling initial estimates of the impacts of abrupt thaw and wildfire, together with gradual thaw, on remaining carbon budgets consistent with the temperature goals of the Paris Agreement. Our model suggests that including permafrost thaw and fire-related carbon emissions reduces the remaining allowable carbon budgets from 2025 onward by 25 % ± 12 % for avoiding 1.5 °C and 17 % ± 7 % for avoiding 2.0 °C, relative to simulations without these processes. Accounting for these additional emissions is critical for setting emissions reduction targets aligned with the Paris Agreement. Including permafrost and wildfire carbon emissions reduces the remaining allowable carbon budget for keeping the global average temperature increase below 1.5 degrees by 25%, according to Earth system model simulations.
Published: 2026-01-24T07:04:17+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.435 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Christina Schädel; Thomas Gasser; Brendan M. Rogers; Rachael Treharne; Merritt R. Turetsky; Trevor Smith; Erin MacDonald; Susan M. Natali&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-026-03189-5"&gt;10.1038/s43247-026-03189-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.435 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rapid Arctic warming is thawing carbon-rich permafrost, releasing greenhouse gases that accelerate climate change. Despite the importance of this feedback, permafrost-enabled global-scale models simulate only gradual, top-down thickening of the seasonally-thawed soil. This ignores abrupt permafrost thaw and intensifying fire regimes that combust soil carbon and further accelerate thaw. Here, we expand a compact Earth system model (OSCAR v3.0) enabling initial estimates of the impacts of abrupt thaw and wildfire, together with gradual thaw, on remaining carbon budgets consistent with the temperature goals of the Paris Agreement. Our model suggests that including permafrost thaw and fire-related carbon emissions reduces the remaining allowable carbon budgets from 2025 onward by 25 % ± 12 % for avoiding 1.5 °C and 17 % ± 7 % for avoiding 2.0 °C, relative to simulations without these processes. Accounting for these additional emissions is critical for setting emissions reduction targets aligned with the Paris Agreement. Including permafrost and wildfire carbon emissions reduces the remaining allowable carbon budget for keeping the global average temperature increase below 1.5 degrees by 25%, according to Earth system model simulations.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Bradyzoite subtypes rule the crossroads of Toxoplasma development</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68489-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68489-y</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:24:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Arzu Ulu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sandeep Srivastava</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nala Kachour</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brandon H. Le</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael W. White</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emma H. Wilson</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68489-y</prism:doi><description>Abstract Toxoplasmosis is a major risk to chronically infected individuals, especially those who become immunocompromised. Although one-third of the globe is infected with Toxoplasma , no treatments prevent or eliminate cysts in part due to limited understanding of bradyzoite biology. The cyst is central to Toxoplasmosis, as transition from bradyzoites to tachyzoites drive pathology. In this study, we aim to understand the biology of bradyzoites prior to recrudescence and the developmental pathways they initiate. Here, we discover ME49EW cysts from infected mice harbor multiple bradyzoite subtypes with distinct fates. Purified subtypes exhibit defined developmental pathways in animals and in primary astrocytes. Single-bradyzoite RNA-sequencing reveals five major subtypes within cysts. We further show that a crucial subtype in chronically infected mice is absent from a widely used in vitro model of bradyzoite development. Altogether, this work establishes new foundational principles of Toxoplasma cyst development and reactivation that operate during the intermediate life cycle of Toxoplasma .
Published: 2026-01-24T14:24:15+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.434 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Arzu Ulu; Sandeep Srivastava; Nala Kachour; Brandon H. Le; Michael W. White; Emma H. Wilson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68489-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68489-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.434 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Toxoplasmosis is a major risk to chronically infected individuals, especially those who become immunocompromised. Although one-third of the globe is infected with Toxoplasma , no treatments prevent or eliminate cysts in part due to limited understanding of bradyzoite biology. The cyst is central to Toxoplasmosis, as transition from bradyzoites to tachyzoites drive pathology. In this study, we aim to understand the biology of bradyzoites prior to recrudescence and the developmental pathways they initiate. Here, we discover ME49EW cysts from infected mice harbor multiple bradyzoite subtypes with distinct fates. Purified subtypes exhibit defined developmental pathways in animals and in primary astrocytes. Single-bradyzoite RNA-sequencing reveals five major subtypes within cysts. We further show that a crucial subtype in chronically infected mice is absent from a widely used in vitro model of bradyzoite development. Altogether, this work establishes new foundational principles of Toxoplasma cyst development and reactivation that operate during the intermediate life cycle of Toxoplasma .&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Click-based determination of accumulation of molecules in Escherichia coli</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68717-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68717-5</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 15:47:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>George M. Ongwae</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zichen Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shasha Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mahendra D. Chordia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rachita Dash</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuchen He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mohammad Sharifian Gh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brianna E. Dalesandro</dc:creator><dc:creator>Taijie Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Karl Barry Sharpless</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiajia Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>M. Sloan Siegrist</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wonpil Im</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marcos M. Pires</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68717-5</prism:doi><description>Abstract Gram-negative bacterial pathogens pose a significant challenge in drug development because their outer membranes hinder the permeation of small molecules. The lack of widely adoptable methods for measuring the cytosolic accumulation of compounds in bacterial cells further hinders drug discovery efforts. To address this challenge, we report the development of the Chloroalkane Azide Membrane Permeability (CHAMP) assay, which we designed specifically to assess molecule accumulation in the cytosol of Gram-negative bacteria. The CHAMP analysis utilizes bioorthogonal epitopes anchored within HaloTag-expressing bacteria and measures the cytosolic arrival of azide-bearing test molecules through strain-promoted azide–alkyne cycloaddition. This workflow enables robust and rapid accumulation measurements of thousands of azide-tagged small molecules. Our approach consistently produces comprehensive accumulation profiles that surpass the scale of previous measurements in Escherichia coli ( E. coli ). We validated the CHAMP assay across various chemical and biological contexts, including hyperporinated cells, membrane-permeabilized cells, and E. coli strains with impaired TolC function, a key component of the efflux pump. The CHAMP platform provides a simple, high-throughput, and accessible method that enables the analysis of over 1000 molecules within hours. This technique addresses a critical gap in antimicrobial research and has the potential to accelerate the development of effective agents against Gram-negative pathogens.
Published: 2026-01-24T15:47:33+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.434 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; George M. Ongwae; Zichen Liu; Shasha Feng; Mahendra D. Chordia; Rachita Dash; Yuchen He; Mohammad Sharifian Gh; Brianna E. Dalesandro; Taijie Guo; Karl Barry Sharpless; Jiajia Dong; M. Sloan Siegrist; Wonpil Im; Marcos M. Pires&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68717-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68717-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.434 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Gram-negative bacterial pathogens pose a significant challenge in drug development because their outer membranes hinder the permeation of small molecules. The lack of widely adoptable methods for measuring the cytosolic accumulation of compounds in bacterial cells further hinders drug discovery efforts. To address this challenge, we report the development of the Chloroalkane Azide Membrane Permeability (CHAMP) assay, which we designed specifically to assess molecule accumulation in the cytosol of Gram-negative bacteria. The CHAMP analysis utilizes bioorthogonal epitopes anchored within HaloTag-expressing bacteria and measures the cytosolic arrival of azide-bearing test molecules through strain-promoted azide–alkyne cycloaddition. This workflow enables robust and rapid accumulation measurements of thousands of azide-tagged small molecules. Our approach consistently produces comprehensive accumulation profiles that surpass the scale of previous measurements in Escherichia coli ( E. coli ). We validated the CHAMP assay across various chemical and biological contexts, including hyperporinated cells, membrane-permeabilized cells, and E. coli strains with impaired TolC function, a key component of the efflux pump. The CHAMP platform provides a simple, high-throughput, and accessible method that enables the analysis of over 1000 molecules within hours. This technique addresses a critical gap in antimicrobial research and has the potential to accelerate the development of effective agents against Gram-negative pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Atroposelective interrupted CuAAC reaction using cyclic diaryliodoniums</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68574-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68574-2</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:02:02 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yuanyuan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shan Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Longhui Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenhua Gu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68574-2</prism:doi><description>Copper-catalyzed azide–alkyne cycloaddition (CuAAC) is a pivotal strategy for joining two fragments, including bioactive moieties under mild conditions. In recent years, “interrupted” CuAAC reaction has emerged by intercepting copper triazolide intermediates, thereby significantly broadening the scope of these transformations. However, asymmetric transformations based on the interruption of copper triazolide intermediates have remained elusive. In this work, we present an efficient and mild approach that intercepts a copper triazolide intermediate with a cyclic diaryliodonium reagent, enabling a three-component coupling of the cyclic diaryliodonium species, an alkyne, and an azide under atroposelective control. This method constitutes an asymmetric interrupted CuAAC reaction and furnishes a diverse array of structurally unique atropisomeric biaryl triazoles. Mechanistic investigations reveal an unusual secondary kinetic isotope effect for the terminal alkyne, while in situ calorimetry–based reaction progress kinetic analysis identifies the individual reaction orders of each substrate: formal 0.4th-order for cyclic diaryliodonium and first-order for both the alkyne and the azide. The overall rate is governed by copper-mediated cyclometallation of the alkyne and azide, as well as the oxidative addition of the copper triazolide intermediate to the cyclic diaryliodonium reagent. Interrupting the copper-catalysed azide–alkyne cycloaddition has emerged as a strategy to broaden the scope of these transformations. Here, the autuors intercepts a copper triazolide intermediate with a cyclic diaryliodonium reagent, enabling a three-component coupling of the cyclic diaryliodonium species, an alkyne, and an azide under atroposelective control.
Published: 2026-01-24T10:02:02+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.433 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yuanyuan Li; Shan Yang; Longhui Duan; Zhenhua Gu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68574-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68574-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.433 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copper-catalyzed azide–alkyne cycloaddition (CuAAC) is a pivotal strategy for joining two fragments, including bioactive moieties under mild conditions. In recent years, “interrupted” CuAAC reaction has emerged by intercepting copper triazolide intermediates, thereby significantly broadening the scope of these transformations. However, asymmetric transformations based on the interruption of copper triazolide intermediates have remained elusive. In this work, we present an efficient and mild approach that intercepts a copper triazolide intermediate with a cyclic diaryliodonium reagent, enabling a three-component coupling of the cyclic diaryliodonium species, an alkyne, and an azide under atroposelective control. This method constitutes an asymmetric interrupted CuAAC reaction and furnishes a diverse array of structurally unique atropisomeric biaryl triazoles. Mechanistic investigations reveal an unusual secondary kinetic isotope effect for the terminal alkyne, while in situ calorimetry–based reaction progress kinetic analysis identifies the individual reaction orders of each substrate: formal 0.4th-order for cyclic diaryliodonium and first-order for both the alkyne and the azide. The overall rate is governed by copper-mediated cyclometallation of the alkyne and azide, as well as the oxidative addition of the copper triazolide intermediate to the cyclic diaryliodonium reagent. Interrupting the copper-catalysed azide–alkyne cycloaddition has emerged as a strategy to broaden the scope of these transformations. Here, the autuors intercepts a copper triazolide intermediate with a cyclic diaryliodonium reagent, enabling a three-component coupling of the cyclic diaryliodonium species, an alkyne, and an azide under atroposelective control.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>CRISPR-Cas9 trans-cleavage is hindered by a flanked R-loop, an elongated spacer, and an inactive HNH domain</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68789-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68789-3</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 03:24:04 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Roser Montagud-Martínez</dc:creator><dc:creator>Raúl Ruiz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sara Baldanta</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rubén Delicado-Mateo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guillermo Rodrigo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68789-3</prism:doi><description>Cas9 can process poly(T) single-stranded DNA molecules upon activation in an RNA-guided manner. Here, we uncover key determinants underlying this function. First, we show that unflanked R-loops in the RNA 5′ side favor trans-cleavage activity, which occur when targeting short double-stranded DNA molecules. Second, we show that elongated guide RNA spacers beyond the canonical 20 bases, even by a few bases, severely impair this collateral activity. Third, although trans-cleavage is mediated by the RuvC domain, we show that a catalytically active HNH domain contributes to an efficient process. Analysis of structural models provides tentative mechanistic insights. Together, these findings illustrate that fine modulation of Cas9 function can be achieved. Prokaryotic Class 2 CRISPR-Cas nucleases like Cas9 exhibit collateral cleavage activity. Here, the authors show that this activity is supported by unflanked R-loops in the RNA 5′ side, spacers of canonical length of 20 nt, and through its HNH and RuvC domains.
Published: 2026-01-24T03:24:04+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.432 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Roser Montagud-Martínez; Raúl Ruiz; Sara Baldanta; Rubén Delicado-Mateo; Guillermo Rodrigo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68789-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68789-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.432 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cas9 can process poly(T) single-stranded DNA molecules upon activation in an RNA-guided manner. Here, we uncover key determinants underlying this function. First, we show that unflanked R-loops in the RNA 5′ side favor trans-cleavage activity, which occur when targeting short double-stranded DNA molecules. Second, we show that elongated guide RNA spacers beyond the canonical 20 bases, even by a few bases, severely impair this collateral activity. Third, although trans-cleavage is mediated by the RuvC domain, we show that a catalytically active HNH domain contributes to an efficient process. Analysis of structural models provides tentative mechanistic insights. Together, these findings illustrate that fine modulation of Cas9 function can be achieved. Prokaryotic Class 2 CRISPR-Cas nucleases like Cas9 exhibit collateral cleavage activity. Here, the authors show that this activity is supported by unflanked R-loops in the RNA 5′ side, spacers of canonical length of 20 nt, and through its HNH and RuvC domains.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>BiG-SCAPE 2.0 and BiG-SLiCE 2.0: scalable, accurate and interactive sequence clustering of metabolic gene clusters</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68733-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68733-5</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 10:46:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Arjan Draisma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Catarina Loureiro</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nico L. L. Louwen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Satria A. Kautsar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jorge C. Navarro-Muñoz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Drew T. Doering</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nigel J. Mouncey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marnix H. Medema</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68733-5</prism:doi><description>Abstract Microbial metabolic gene clusters encode the biosynthesis or catabolism of metabolites that facilitate ecological specialization, mediate microbiome interactions and constitute a major source of medicines and crop protection agents. Here, we present BiG-SCAPE and BiG-SLiCE 2.0, next-generation methods that facilitate scalable, accurate and interactive gene cluster analyses. BiG-SCAPE 2.0 updates its classification, alignment methods, and visualizations, enabling more accurate analysis, up to 8x faster runtimes and halved memory requirements. BiG-SLiCE 2.0 updates its distance metric, pHMM database, and classification logic, resulting in increased sensitivity nearing that of BiG-SCAPE. Analysis of 260,630 biosynthetic gene clusters from publicly available genomes reveals that both tools generate concurring estimates of gene cluster diversity, thus providing significantly extended methodological support for recent evidence indicating that the vast majority of natural product diversity remains unexplored. Together, these updates will facilitate global genome mining efforts for natural product discovery and microbiome analyses scalable with current data sizes.
Published: 2026-01-24T10:46:19+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.424 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Arjan Draisma; Catarina Loureiro; Nico L. L. Louwen; Satria A. Kautsar; Jorge C. Navarro-Muñoz; Drew T. Doering; Nigel J. Mouncey; Marnix H. Medema&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68733-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68733-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.424 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Microbial metabolic gene clusters encode the biosynthesis or catabolism of metabolites that facilitate ecological specialization, mediate microbiome interactions and constitute a major source of medicines and crop protection agents. Here, we present BiG-SCAPE and BiG-SLiCE 2.0, next-generation methods that facilitate scalable, accurate and interactive gene cluster analyses. BiG-SCAPE 2.0 updates its classification, alignment methods, and visualizations, enabling more accurate analysis, up to 8x faster runtimes and halved memory requirements. BiG-SLiCE 2.0 updates its distance metric, pHMM database, and classification logic, resulting in increased sensitivity nearing that of BiG-SCAPE. Analysis of 260,630 biosynthetic gene clusters from publicly available genomes reveals that both tools generate concurring estimates of gene cluster diversity, thus providing significantly extended methodological support for recent evidence indicating that the vast majority of natural product diversity remains unexplored. Together, these updates will facilitate global genome mining efforts for natural product discovery and microbiome analyses scalable with current data sizes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Oceanic Heat Transport Along the Norwegian Atlantic Slope Current and the Role of Eddies</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022960</link><guid>10.1029/2025jc022960</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 07:32:53 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Dong Jian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoming Zhai</dc:creator><dc:creator>David P. Stevens</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ian A. Renfrew</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jc022960</prism:doi><description>Abstract The poleward warm Atlantic Water and returning cold water in the Nordic Seas play a crucial role in regulating the Northern Hemisphere climate. While previous studies have recognized the importance of mesoscale dynamics, a quantitative assessment of the role of mesoscale eddies in poleward heat transport is lacking. Our study investigates the role of eddies in poleward oceanic heat transport in the Nordic Seas using an ocean model where eddies are well represented. Using a novel configuration of the MITgcm ocean‐ice model, we analyze 21 years of simulation. We show that eddy heat flux divergence offsets more than 70% of heat flux convergence induced by the mean flow along the Norwegian Atlantic Slope Current. Eddy heat flux divergence peaks at a depth of about 400 m near the thermocline and reaches a maximum near the steep Lofoten Escarpment. A temporal decomposition reveals that eddy heat flux divergence is stable on interannual timescales, although there is strong seasonality. Our study emphasizes the significant role of eddies in reducing poleward heat transport by diverting heat out of the Norwegian Atlantic Current into the Nordic Seas.
Published: 2026-01-24T07:32:53+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans
Score: 0.424 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Dong Jian; Xiaoming Zhai; David P. Stevens; Ian A. Renfrew&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jc022960"&gt;10.1029/2025jc022960&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.424 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The poleward warm Atlantic Water and returning cold water in the Nordic Seas play a crucial role in regulating the Northern Hemisphere climate. While previous studies have recognized the importance of mesoscale dynamics, a quantitative assessment of the role of mesoscale eddies in poleward heat transport is lacking. Our study investigates the role of eddies in poleward oceanic heat transport in the Nordic Seas using an ocean model where eddies are well represented. Using a novel configuration of the MITgcm ocean‐ice model, we analyze 21 years of simulation. We show that eddy heat flux divergence offsets more than 70% of heat flux convergence induced by the mean flow along the Norwegian Atlantic Slope Current. Eddy heat flux divergence peaks at a depth of about 400 m near the thermocline and reaches a maximum near the steep Lofoten Escarpment. A temporal decomposition reveals that eddy heat flux divergence is stable on interannual timescales, although there is strong seasonality. Our study emphasizes the significant role of eddies in reducing poleward heat transport by diverting heat out of the Norwegian Atlantic Current into the Nordic Seas.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Potential and challenges for sustainable progress in human longevity</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68828-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-026-68828-z</guid><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2026 14:55:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Florian Bonnet</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ina Alliger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Carlo-Giovanni Camarda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sebastian Klüsener</dc:creator><dc:creator>France Meslé</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael Mühlichen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Josselin Thuilliez</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pavel Grigoriev</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-026-68828-z</prism:doi><description>Abstract Decelerating gains in life expectancy ( e 0 ) in high-income countries have raised concerns about the future of human longevity. To enhance our understanding of these developments, we examine subnational ( N = 450) mortality trends in Western Europe in the period 1992-2019. Between 1992 and 2005, gains in life expectancy were both substantial and widespread. Laggard regions experienced the fastest improvements, yielding rapid regional convergence. Between 2005 and 2019, however, gains in these regions decelerated, while remaining remarkably stable in vanguard regions, suggesting that it remains possible to continue extending longevity. The observed slowing of e 0 gains is strongly associated with mortality at ages 55-74, which increased in this period across large areas of Western Europe, particularly in Germany and France. In this work, we show that monitoring mortality trends at a fine geographical level is crucial for revealing both the potential for, and challenges to, sustainable progress in human longevity.
Published: 2026-01-24T14:55:15+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.423 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Florian Bonnet; Ina Alliger; Carlo-Giovanni Camarda; Sebastian Klüsener; France Meslé; Michael Mühlichen; Josselin Thuilliez; Pavel Grigoriev&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-026-68828-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-026-68828-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.423 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Decelerating gains in life expectancy ( e 0 ) in high-income countries have raised concerns about the future of human longevity. To enhance our understanding of these developments, we examine subnational ( N = 450) mortality trends in Western Europe in the period 1992-2019. Between 1992 and 2005, gains in life expectancy were both substantial and widespread. Laggard regions experienced the fastest improvements, yielding rapid regional convergence. Between 2005 and 2019, however, gains in these regions decelerated, while remaining remarkably stable in vanguard regions, suggesting that it remains possible to continue extending longevity. The observed slowing of e 0 gains is strongly associated with mortality at ages 55-74, which increased in this period across large areas of Western Europe, particularly in Germany and France. In this work, we show that monitoring mortality trends at a fine geographical level is crucial for revealing both the potential for, and challenges to, sustainable progress in human longevity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The Zonal Wave‐3 Mode Impacts Antarctic Dense Water Formation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119079</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl119079</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jan 2026 07:11:11 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>M. Auger</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. Spence</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. K. Morrison</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl119079</prism:doi><description>Abstract At the Antarctic margins, dense water masses form as sea ice develops, driving the Antarctic branch of the global meridional overturning circulation. Previous studies found that large‐scale climate modes such as the Southern Annular Mode and El Niño Southern do not fully account for the interannual variability of dense water formation. Here, we investigate the influence of the overlooked Zonal Wave‐3 (ZW3) mode, characterized by three alternating cyclone–anticyclone pairs in the Southern Hemisphere mid‐latitudes. Simulations with ZW3 perturbations of different phases show multi‐year impacts on dense water formation and export. The PC1 phase exerts the strongest influence in the Ross Sea, while the PC2 phase can nearly shut down or double dense water formation in the Weddell Sea. A simulation with interannually varying atmospheric forcing confirms ZW3 correlates with dense water formation in both regions. Our results highlight that ZW3 is a key driver of Antarctic dense water dynamics.
Published: 2026-01-25T07:11:11+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.422 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; M. Auger; P. Spence; A. K. Morrison&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl119079"&gt;10.1029/2025gl119079&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.422 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract At the Antarctic margins, dense water masses form as sea ice develops, driving the Antarctic branch of the global meridional overturning circulation. Previous studies found that large‐scale climate modes such as the Southern Annular Mode and El Niño Southern do not fully account for the interannual variability of dense water formation. Here, we investigate the influence of the overlooked Zonal Wave‐3 (ZW3) mode, characterized by three alternating cyclone–anticyclone pairs in the Southern Hemisphere mid‐latitudes. Simulations with ZW3 perturbations of different phases show multi‐year impacts on dense water formation and export. The PC1 phase exerts the strongest influence in the Ross Sea, while the PC2 phase can nearly shut down or double dense water formation in the Weddell Sea. A simulation with interannually varying atmospheric forcing confirms ZW3 correlates with dense water formation in both regions. Our results highlight that ZW3 is a key driver of Antarctic dense water dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>