<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jan 2026 23:27:44 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Distinct contributions of suspended and sinking prokaryotes to mesopelagic carbon budget</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01888-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41561-025-01888-w</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 10:02:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pauline Le Coq</dc:creator><dc:creator>Urania Christaki</dc:creator><dc:creator>France Van Wambeke</dc:creator><dc:creator>Elisabeth Chevillon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bruno Zakardjian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marc Garel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sophie Guasco</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chloé M. J. Baumas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anne E. Dekas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Patricia Bonin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Badr Al Ali</dc:creator><dc:creator>Maéva Gesson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Frédéric Le Moigne</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mireille Pujo-Pay</dc:creator><dc:creator>Olivier Crispi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Olivier Grosso</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thierry Moutin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nagib Bhairy</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emmanuel de Saint Léger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laurent Memery</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lionel Guidi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fabrice Armougom</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hans-Peter Grossart</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christian Tamburini</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Geoscience</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41561-025-01888-w</prism:doi><description>The mesopelagic zone, between 100 m and 1,000 m depth, is a crucial layer in which carbon preliminary coming down from the surface is transformed before a portion makes it into the deep ocean. While eddies and their fronts influence surface productivity and carbon export, their effects deeper in the water column remain poorly understood. Here we show the importance and contribution of dark carbon fixation—the conversion of inorganic into organic carbon by prokaryotes—across five contrasting hydrological features in the North Atlantic, using isotopic tracers and quantification of chemoautotrophy genes. The approach allows simultaneous assessment of dark carbon fixation and heterotrophic activity of prokaryotes living suspended in seawater and attached to gravitationally settling particles. Our results highlight that heterotrophic prokaryotes attached to sinking particles contribute up to 21% of the total organic carbon required to sustain prokaryotic metabolism under the influence of eddy fronts. By contrast, dark carbon fixation by suspended prokaryotes can contribute up to half of the total carbon input to the mesopelagic zone in the cyclonic eddy. Our findings challenge the idea that carbon cycling in the mid-depth ocean is uniform and highlight the need to integrate microbial fractions and physical heterogeneity into ocean carbon models. Genetic and isotopic analyses of samples from the northeast Atlantic reveal that suspended prokaryotic dark carbon fixation substantially fuels carbon inputs below the sunlit ocean, while particle-attached communities make an overlooked contribution to carbon demand.
Published: 2026-01-08T10:02:58+00:00
Venue: Nature Geoscience
Score: 0.606 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pauline Le Coq; Urania Christaki; France Van Wambeke; Elisabeth Chevillon; Bruno Zakardjian; Marc Garel; Sophie Guasco; Chloé M. J. Baumas; Anne E. Dekas; Patricia Bonin; Badr Al Ali; Maéva Gesson; Frédéric Le Moigne; Mireille Pujo-Pay; Olivier Crispi; Olivier Grosso; Thierry Moutin; Nagib Bhairy; Emmanuel de Saint Léger; Laurent Memery; Lionel Guidi; Fabrice Armougom; Hans-Peter Grossart; Christian Tamburini&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Geoscience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01888-w"&gt;10.1038/s41561-025-01888-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.606 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mesopelagic zone, between 100 m and 1,000 m depth, is a crucial layer in which carbon preliminary coming down from the surface is transformed before a portion makes it into the deep ocean. While eddies and their fronts influence surface productivity and carbon export, their effects deeper in the water column remain poorly understood. Here we show the importance and contribution of dark carbon fixation—the conversion of inorganic into organic carbon by prokaryotes—across five contrasting hydrological features in the North Atlantic, using isotopic tracers and quantification of chemoautotrophy genes. The approach allows simultaneous assessment of dark carbon fixation and heterotrophic activity of prokaryotes living suspended in seawater and attached to gravitationally settling particles. Our results highlight that heterotrophic prokaryotes attached to sinking particles contribute up to 21% of the total organic carbon required to sustain prokaryotic metabolism under the influence of eddy fronts. By contrast, dark carbon fixation by suspended prokaryotes can contribute up to half of the total carbon input to the mesopelagic zone in the cyclonic eddy. Our findings challenge the idea that carbon cycling in the mid-depth ocean is uniform and highlight the need to integrate microbial fractions and physical heterogeneity into ocean carbon models. Genetic and isotopic analyses of samples from the northeast Atlantic reveal that suspended prokaryotic dark carbon fixation substantially fuels carbon inputs below the sunlit ocean, while particle-attached communities make an overlooked contribution to carbon demand.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Protracted subduction and slab rollback of the Paleo-Asian Ocean during the late Paleozoic: Insight from polyphase metamorphism in the Baoyintu Group, central-western Inner Mongolia</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38668.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38668.1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 20:51:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shuang Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinrui Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chris Yakymchuk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunjing Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hang Chu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yidan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuan Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38668.1</prism:doi><description>Understanding the relationship between tectonic patterns and metamorphic processes generated by subduction is essential for reconstructing the evolutionary history of orogenic systems. However, these connections can be obscured by poly-metamorphism that overprints or erases evidence of earlier metamorphism. To evaluate the role of continuous subduction on overprinting previous metamorphic events, we examine the subduction dynamics of the Paleo-Asian Ocean during the late Paleozoic. This evaluation is based on evidence of multi-stage metamorphism, including high-, medium-, and low-pressure type metamorphism identified from the metasedimentary rocks in the Baoyintu Group terrane of central-western Inner Mongolia, China. We use petrographic observations, phase equilibrium modeling, and U-Pb and Rb-Sr geochronology. High-pressure metamorphic mineral assemblages from the Baoyintu Group include chlorite, garnet, phengite, rutile, and quartz. Medium-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, biotite, garnet, muscovite, staurolite, kyanite, plagioclase, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Low-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, garnet, biotite, muscovite, andalusite, sillimanite, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Phase equilibrium modeling suggests apparent pressure-temperature conditions of ∼14−19 kbar and 510−580 °C for the high-pressure metamorphism, ∼5−10 kbar and 575−770 °C for the medium-pressure metamorphism, and ∼3−7 kbar and 565−750 °C for the low-pressure metamorphism. In situ mica Rb-Sr geochronology yields a metamorphic age for the high-pressure phase of ca. 369 Ma; rutile U-Pb geochronology of medium-pressure metamorphism yields a metamorphic age of ca. 399 Ma. Monazite and rutile U-Pb geochronology of the low-pressure assemblage indicates a metamorphic age of ca. 267−252 Ma. Devonian high- and medium-pressure belts are distributed in a northeast-southwest direction, consistent with the timing of magmatic events in the Baoyintu Group during subduction. The Permian low-pressure belt is oriented east-west, partially overprinting the high- and medium-temperature belts, and is contemporaneous with magmatic events related to extension. These results suggest that the subduction boundary of the Paleo-Asian Ocean in this region was northeast-southwest during the Devonian and shifted to east-west during the late-stage subduction in the Permian. This study reveals that irregularities along subduction boundaries can lead to multiple orogenic events, prompting a re-evaluation of inferring complex tectonic processes from polymetamorphosed rocks.
Published: 2026-01-09T20:51:21+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.592 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shuang Tang; Jinrui Zhang; Chris Yakymchuk; Chunjing Wei; Hang Chu; Yidan Wang; Yuan Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38668.1"&gt;10.1130/b38668.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.592 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the relationship between tectonic patterns and metamorphic processes generated by subduction is essential for reconstructing the evolutionary history of orogenic systems. However, these connections can be obscured by poly-metamorphism that overprints or erases evidence of earlier metamorphism. To evaluate the role of continuous subduction on overprinting previous metamorphic events, we examine the subduction dynamics of the Paleo-Asian Ocean during the late Paleozoic. This evaluation is based on evidence of multi-stage metamorphism, including high-, medium-, and low-pressure type metamorphism identified from the metasedimentary rocks in the Baoyintu Group terrane of central-western Inner Mongolia, China. We use petrographic observations, phase equilibrium modeling, and U-Pb and Rb-Sr geochronology. High-pressure metamorphic mineral assemblages from the Baoyintu Group include chlorite, garnet, phengite, rutile, and quartz. Medium-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, biotite, garnet, muscovite, staurolite, kyanite, plagioclase, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Low-pressure metamorphism is characterized by chlorite, garnet, biotite, muscovite, andalusite, sillimanite, rutile, ilmenite, and quartz. Phase equilibrium modeling suggests apparent pressure-temperature conditions of ∼14−19 kbar and 510−580 °C for the high-pressure metamorphism, ∼5−10 kbar and 575−770 °C for the medium-pressure metamorphism, and ∼3−7 kbar and 565−750 °C for the low-pressure metamorphism. In situ mica Rb-Sr geochronology yields a metamorphic age for the high-pressure phase of ca. 369 Ma; rutile U-Pb geochronology of medium-pressure metamorphism yields a metamorphic age of ca. 399 Ma. Monazite and rutile U-Pb geochronology of the low-pressure assemblage indicates a metamorphic age of ca. 267−252 Ma. Devonian high- and medium-pressure belts are distributed in a northeast-southwest direction, consistent with the timing of magmatic events in the Baoyintu Group during subduction. The Permian low-pressure belt is oriented east-west, partially overprinting the high- and medium-temperature belts, and is contemporaneous with magmatic events related to extension. These results suggest that the subduction boundary of the Paleo-Asian Ocean in this region was northeast-southwest during the Devonian and shifted to east-west during the late-stage subduction in the Permian. This study reveals that irregularities along subduction boundaries can lead to multiple orogenic events, prompting a re-evaluation of inferring complex tectonic processes from polymetamorphosed rocks.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The major ion chemistry of seawater was closely coupled to the long-term carbon cycle during the Cenozoic</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2511781122</link><guid>10.1073/pnas.2511781122</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:46:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>David Evans</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yair Rosenthal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan Erez</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hagar Hauzer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laura J. Cotton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoli Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Romi Nambiar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter Stassen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul N. Pearson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Willem Renema</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pratul Kumar Saraswati</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan A. Todd</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wolfgang Müller</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hagit P. Affek</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1073/pnas.2511781122</prism:doi><description>A ~fivefold decrease in the atmospheric concentration of CO 2 took place during the Cenozoic. This has often been viewed within the context of silicate weathering changes, although the specific contributions of the potential drivers remain poorly understood. Indeed, it has been alternatively argued that changes in the sea floor spreading rate contributed to the Cenozoic p CO 2 decline, although the magnitude of the decrease means that this is unlikely to account for the entirety of the p CO 2 change. One previously overlooked factor is the concomitant change in the major element composition of seawater, especially the concentration of calcium ([Ca 2+ sw ]), which is typically viewed as responding to processes such as weathering, rather than representing a driver in and of itself. Here, we present the first detailed record of the Cenozoic major ion chemistry of seawater and show that [Ca 2+ sw ] has the potential to control key processes that impact the carbon cycle. Although our record cannot determine whether CO 2 is causally driven by [Ca 2+ sw ], carbon cycle box modeling identifies that this may have been the case. Whether or not [Ca 2+ sw ] indeed directly drove p CO 2 during the Cenozoic principally depends on the strength of the silicate weathering feedback and the magnitude of any possible changes in organic carbon burial, both of which could overwhelm a [Ca 2+ sw ]-driven impact on the carbon cycle. As such, determining the sensitivity of the weathering–climate relationship on million-year timescales is key to resolving whether factors such as seawater major ion composition are important carbon cycle drivers.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:46:07+00:00
Venue: Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences
Score: 0.584 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; David Evans; Yair Rosenthal; Jonathan Erez; Hagar Hauzer; Laura J. Cotton; Xiaoli Zhou; Romi Nambiar; Peter Stassen; Paul N. Pearson; Willem Renema; Pratul Kumar Saraswati; Jonathan A. Todd; Wolfgang Müller; Hagit P. Affek&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2511781122"&gt;10.1073/pnas.2511781122&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.584 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ~fivefold decrease in the atmospheric concentration of CO 2 took place during the Cenozoic. This has often been viewed within the context of silicate weathering changes, although the specific contributions of the potential drivers remain poorly understood. Indeed, it has been alternatively argued that changes in the sea floor spreading rate contributed to the Cenozoic p CO 2 decline, although the magnitude of the decrease means that this is unlikely to account for the entirety of the p CO 2 change. One previously overlooked factor is the concomitant change in the major element composition of seawater, especially the concentration of calcium ([Ca 2+ sw ]), which is typically viewed as responding to processes such as weathering, rather than representing a driver in and of itself. Here, we present the first detailed record of the Cenozoic major ion chemistry of seawater and show that [Ca 2+ sw ] has the potential to control key processes that impact the carbon cycle. Although our record cannot determine whether CO 2 is causally driven by [Ca 2+ sw ], carbon cycle box modeling identifies that this may have been the case. Whether or not [Ca 2+ sw ] indeed directly drove p CO 2 during the Cenozoic principally depends on the strength of the silicate weathering feedback and the magnitude of any possible changes in organic carbon burial, both of which could overwhelm a [Ca 2+ sw ]-driven impact on the carbon cycle. As such, determining the sensitivity of the weathering–climate relationship on million-year timescales is key to resolving whether factors such as seawater major ion composition are important carbon cycle drivers.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Well-connected basalt sequences as potential reservoirs for large-scale carbon sequestration revealed by strontium isotopes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 13:48:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Stéphane Polteau</dc:creator><dc:creator>P. Craig Smalley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Vani N. Devegowda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ingar Johansen</dc:creator><dc:creator>John M. Millett</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marija P. Rosenqvist</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mohamed Mansour Abdelmalak</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sverre Planke</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7</prism:doi><description>Abstract Permanent storage of gigatons of carbon in basalt requires thick, uncompartmentalized sequences that allow lateral dissipation of CO 2 away from injection sites. Here we assess the presence of flow barriers by evaluating the variations in 87 Sr/ 86 Sr patterns in pore water, a method used extensively in sedimentary successions. Present-day pore water 87 Sr/ 86 Sr was measured from residual salts in core samples, while past water compositions were reconstructed from carbonate cements of different ages. We reveal smooth and uninterrupted trends in strontium isotopes through a 100 m thick basalt section indicating a common fluid reservoir unaffected by low-permeability massive lava flow interiors. The data further indicate that unconsolidated overburden sediments act as a good seal preventing seawater to mix with in situ pore water, and buoyant supercritical CO 2 to leak. Finally, basaltic sequences form viable targets for CO 2 storage and suggests that fractures may bypass low-permeability units to create a well-connected reservoir system.
Published: 2026-01-09T13:48:16+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.571 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Stéphane Polteau; P. Craig Smalley; Vani N. Devegowda; Ingar Johansen; John M. Millett; Marija P. Rosenqvist; Mohamed Mansour Abdelmalak; Sverre Planke&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03020-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.571 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Permanent storage of gigatons of carbon in basalt requires thick, uncompartmentalized sequences that allow lateral dissipation of CO 2 away from injection sites. Here we assess the presence of flow barriers by evaluating the variations in 87 Sr/ 86 Sr patterns in pore water, a method used extensively in sedimentary successions. Present-day pore water 87 Sr/ 86 Sr was measured from residual salts in core samples, while past water compositions were reconstructed from carbonate cements of different ages. We reveal smooth and uninterrupted trends in strontium isotopes through a 100 m thick basalt section indicating a common fluid reservoir unaffected by low-permeability massive lava flow interiors. The data further indicate that unconsolidated overburden sediments act as a good seal preventing seawater to mix with in situ pore water, and buoyant supercritical CO 2 to leak. Finally, basaltic sequences form viable targets for CO 2 storage and suggests that fractures may bypass low-permeability units to create a well-connected reservoir system.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mantle heterogeneity and complicated melt migration revealed by chemical gradients across the dunite-harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite, South Tibet</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 01:14:46 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhen-Yu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuan-Zhou Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chang Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo-Da Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5</prism:doi><description>Dunite channels are critical pathways for melt extraction and migration within the asthenosphere. Although their formation within mantle peridotite sequences is often attributed to melt-rock interaction, the underlying physical processes remain poorly constrained. This study examines variations in both major and trace elements across a dunite-harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite to better understand these physical processes. Geochemical profiles across the dunite-harzburgite transect reveal concentration gradients near the dunite-harzburgite contact, particularly within the harzburgite. Such compositional variations were interpreted through two-dimensional numerical simulations, coupled with diffusion and advection in porous media. The results indicate that trace element gradients in olivine can be produced by a melt flow along the dunite–harzburgite boundary with lateral advection from dunite to harzburgite, which is consistent with those observed in the field. Trace element patterns of the interstitial clinopyroxene grains within the dunite suggest their crystallization from a final pulse of percolating melt through the channel during the waning stage of the melt transport system, which probably occurred shortly before the ophiolite obduction. Integrating these results with previous studies on mafic–ultramafic rocks in the Moho Transition Zone (MTZ), we propose that the dunite–harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite was initially generated in the asthenosphere beneath an ultra-slow spreading ridge, which subsequently experienced a multi-stage history of melt migration and melt–rock interaction during progressive mantle upwelling. Such a complex history significantly influenced the lithological and geochemical architecture of the MTZ of the ophiolite. Overall, results from this study demonstrate that both dunites and their surrounding harzburgites bear variable concentration gradients, resulting from both mantle heterogeneity and variations in melt compositions within individual dunite channel.
Published: 2026-01-09T01:14:46+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.563 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhen-Yu Zhang; Chuan-Zhou Liu; Yan Liang; Tong Liu; Chang Zhang; Bo-Da Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02287-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.563 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunite channels are critical pathways for melt extraction and migration within the asthenosphere. Although their formation within mantle peridotite sequences is often attributed to melt-rock interaction, the underlying physical processes remain poorly constrained. This study examines variations in both major and trace elements across a dunite-harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite to better understand these physical processes. Geochemical profiles across the dunite-harzburgite transect reveal concentration gradients near the dunite-harzburgite contact, particularly within the harzburgite. Such compositional variations were interpreted through two-dimensional numerical simulations, coupled with diffusion and advection in porous media. The results indicate that trace element gradients in olivine can be produced by a melt flow along the dunite–harzburgite boundary with lateral advection from dunite to harzburgite, which is consistent with those observed in the field. Trace element patterns of the interstitial clinopyroxene grains within the dunite suggest their crystallization from a final pulse of percolating melt through the channel during the waning stage of the melt transport system, which probably occurred shortly before the ophiolite obduction. Integrating these results with previous studies on mafic–ultramafic rocks in the Moho Transition Zone (MTZ), we propose that the dunite–harzburgite sequence in the Zedong ophiolite was initially generated in the asthenosphere beneath an ultra-slow spreading ridge, which subsequently experienced a multi-stage history of melt migration and melt–rock interaction during progressive mantle upwelling. Such a complex history significantly influenced the lithological and geochemical architecture of the MTZ of the ophiolite. Overall, results from this study demonstrate that both dunites and their surrounding harzburgites bear variable concentration gradients, resulting from both mantle heterogeneity and variations in melt compositions within individual dunite channel.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Deep crustal hot zones control shallow magma reservoirs in an active transcrustal magmatic system</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03160-w</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-03160-w</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 20:32:26 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bo Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Makoto Uyeshima</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wule Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianfeng Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xubo Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chen Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hui Fang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gengen Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiangyun Hu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-03160-w</prism:doi><description>Understanding volcanic dynamics and assessing eruptive risk require examining the entire transcrustal magmatic system. However, direct imaging of magma distribution and connectivity from the Moho to the surface remains rare. Changbaishan-Tianchi volcano, known for one of the Earth’s largest explosive eruptions, has recently undergone repeated magmatic unrest. To investigate the magmatic system beneath Tianchi volcano, we invert magnetotelluric data to image its three-dimensional resistivity structure, revealing a vertically extensive low-resistivity anomaly system spanning the entire crust. This system comprises three compositionally distinct, vertically connected melt reservoirs: a broad lower-crustal basaltic reservoir (20–35 km), an upper-crustal trachytic reservoir (5–10 km), and an uppermost comenditic reservoir (2–3.5 km). Estimated melt fractions are 2.1–3.7%, 7.0–16.3%, and 18.8–23.8%, respectively. Our results suggest progressive upward magma transfer among these reservoirs via well-resolved conductive pathways, consistent with recent episodes of unrest. Notably, melt volume in the lower crust is about one to two orders of magnitude greater than in the upper crust, a pattern also observed at Yellowstone and likely applicable to active volcanic systems at both divergent and convergent plate boundaries. These findings suggest that deep crustal hot zones may fundamentally control shallow melt volumes and thus the eruptive capacity of polygenetic volcanoes. Deep crustal melt accumulation controls the shallow melt volumes and hence the eruptive capacity of polygenetic volcanoes, according to geophysical and petrological analysis.
Published: 2026-01-08T20:32:26+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.562 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bo Yang; Fan Zhang; Makoto Uyeshima; Jian Lin; Wule Lin; Jianfeng Yang; Xubo Zhang; Wei Wang; Chen Liao; Hui Fang; Gengen Qiu; Xiangyun Hu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-03160-w"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-03160-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.562 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding volcanic dynamics and assessing eruptive risk require examining the entire transcrustal magmatic system. However, direct imaging of magma distribution and connectivity from the Moho to the surface remains rare. Changbaishan-Tianchi volcano, known for one of the Earth’s largest explosive eruptions, has recently undergone repeated magmatic unrest. To investigate the magmatic system beneath Tianchi volcano, we invert magnetotelluric data to image its three-dimensional resistivity structure, revealing a vertically extensive low-resistivity anomaly system spanning the entire crust. This system comprises three compositionally distinct, vertically connected melt reservoirs: a broad lower-crustal basaltic reservoir (20–35 km), an upper-crustal trachytic reservoir (5–10 km), and an uppermost comenditic reservoir (2–3.5 km). Estimated melt fractions are 2.1–3.7%, 7.0–16.3%, and 18.8–23.8%, respectively. Our results suggest progressive upward magma transfer among these reservoirs via well-resolved conductive pathways, consistent with recent episodes of unrest. Notably, melt volume in the lower crust is about one to two orders of magnitude greater than in the upper crust, a pattern also observed at Yellowstone and likely applicable to active volcanic systems at both divergent and convergent plate boundaries. These findings suggest that deep crustal hot zones may fundamentally control shallow melt volumes and thus the eruptive capacity of polygenetic volcanoes. Deep crustal melt accumulation controls the shallow melt volumes and hence the eruptive capacity of polygenetic volcanoes, according to geophysical and petrological analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The role of crustal magmatism in the formation and the evolution of orogenic plateaus</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38190.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38190.1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 20:40:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Mihai N. Ducea</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter G. DeCelles</dc:creator><dc:creator>James B. Chapman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jonathan R. Delph</dc:creator><dc:creator>Barbara Carrapa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lucian Petrescu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kevin M. Ward</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pablo Rossel</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38190.1</prism:doi><description>Here we review regional geological, petrological, geochemical, and geophysical data from the Central Andean plateau (comprising two distinct areas, the Altiplano and Puna) and its defunct North American sibling, the Nevadaplano, as well as to a lesser extent Tibet, to show that magmatism in the middle crust of orogenic plateaus plays an important role in the development of relief and high elevation and drives the mechanical behavior of these features. We show that in situ, mostly S-type melting is an intrinsic feature of plateaus and that these melts can reside in the crust for millions to tens of millions of years without freezing just below a critical melt fraction. Some of these in situ partial melt masses escape their source regions and erupt at the surface. The chemical evolution of volcanic masses produced by partial escape from these migmatites can be predicted by simple forward petrologic calculations. Extensive migmatite in sub-plateau middle crust also contributes to the mechanical weakness of plateaus and their buoyancy. In addition, magmatism from the underlying mantle wedge can further sustain the life of these extensive partial melting zones. Additional, much deeper melt accumulation zones exist close to the bottom of these thick-crusted domains, but we have much less information about their evolution and chemistry; they are probably similar to the deepest crustal root zones of the frontal arcs. We also suggest that there is a link between the ability of Li, B, Cs, and other elements to be concentrated in S-type leucogranites of the extensive migmatite blanket of the middle crust and the concentration of Li (and other metals) in brines and ultimately in the salars of the Central Andean plateau. Hydrothermal activity directly related to the present day Altiplano-Puna magma body or the recent equivalents on South America’s plateau may have leaked these incompatible elements into the former lakes that are now hosting the largest concentrations of Li on the planet.
Published: 2026-01-09T20:40:27+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.555 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mihai N. Ducea; Peter G. DeCelles; James B. Chapman; Jonathan R. Delph; Barbara Carrapa; Lucian Petrescu; Kevin M. Ward; Pablo Rossel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38190.1"&gt;10.1130/b38190.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.555 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we review regional geological, petrological, geochemical, and geophysical data from the Central Andean plateau (comprising two distinct areas, the Altiplano and Puna) and its defunct North American sibling, the Nevadaplano, as well as to a lesser extent Tibet, to show that magmatism in the middle crust of orogenic plateaus plays an important role in the development of relief and high elevation and drives the mechanical behavior of these features. We show that in situ, mostly S-type melting is an intrinsic feature of plateaus and that these melts can reside in the crust for millions to tens of millions of years without freezing just below a critical melt fraction. Some of these in situ partial melt masses escape their source regions and erupt at the surface. The chemical evolution of volcanic masses produced by partial escape from these migmatites can be predicted by simple forward petrologic calculations. Extensive migmatite in sub-plateau middle crust also contributes to the mechanical weakness of plateaus and their buoyancy. In addition, magmatism from the underlying mantle wedge can further sustain the life of these extensive partial melting zones. Additional, much deeper melt accumulation zones exist close to the bottom of these thick-crusted domains, but we have much less information about their evolution and chemistry; they are probably similar to the deepest crustal root zones of the frontal arcs. We also suggest that there is a link between the ability of Li, B, Cs, and other elements to be concentrated in S-type leucogranites of the extensive migmatite blanket of the middle crust and the concentration of Li (and other metals) in brines and ultimately in the salars of the Central Andean plateau. Hydrothermal activity directly related to the present day Altiplano-Puna magma body or the recent equivalents on South America’s plateau may have leaked these incompatible elements into the former lakes that are now hosting the largest concentrations of Li on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Programmable polariton canalization in reconfigurable metasurfaces</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea0072</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aea0072</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoqiang Su</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fusheng Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuqian Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yaping Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pablo Alonso-González</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hong Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiafang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiahua Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiwei Guo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aea0072</prism:doi><description>The topological transition of polariton dispersion in twisted van der Waals layers at the photonic magic angle results in the diffraction-less and collimated propagation state, termed canalization regime. This type of robust transport of polaritons (i.e., polariton canalization) holds promise for subwavelength control of energy flows. However, the lack of in situ dynamic tunability of canalized polaritons hinders such control because the canalization direction is fixed in the fabricated device. Here, we overcome this limitation by demonstrating programmable polariton canalization in a reconfigurable single-layer metasurface. By engineering the orientation of metasurface unit cells, the direction of canalized magnetic polaritons can be programmed along any in-plane direction (i.e., dynamic all-angle tunability). On-demand steering of canalized polaritons allows customized near-field patterns to be obtained at any desired location—a proof of concept for canalization-based information display applications. These findings offer opportunities to transcend conventional diffraction constraints for integrated photonic devices, thus opening the door for photonic applications where on-demand control is crucial.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.549 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yang Xu; Xiaoqiang Su; Fusheng Deng; Yuqian Wang; Yaping Yang; Pablo Alonso-González; Hong Chen; Jiafang Li; Jiahua Duan; Zhiwei Guo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea0072"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aea0072&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.549 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The topological transition of polariton dispersion in twisted van der Waals layers at the photonic magic angle results in the diffraction-less and collimated propagation state, termed canalization regime. This type of robust transport of polaritons (i.e., polariton canalization) holds promise for subwavelength control of energy flows. However, the lack of in situ dynamic tunability of canalized polaritons hinders such control because the canalization direction is fixed in the fabricated device. Here, we overcome this limitation by demonstrating programmable polariton canalization in a reconfigurable single-layer metasurface. By engineering the orientation of metasurface unit cells, the direction of canalized magnetic polaritons can be programmed along any in-plane direction (i.e., dynamic all-angle tunability). On-demand steering of canalized polaritons allows customized near-field patterns to be obtained at any desired location—a proof of concept for canalization-based information display applications. These findings offer opportunities to transcend conventional diffraction constraints for integrated photonic devices, thus opening the door for photonic applications where on-demand control is crucial.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Controlling the sign of optical forces using metaoptics</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 04:34:07 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Adeel Afridi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bruno Melo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nadine Meyer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Romain Quidant</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6</prism:doi><description>Abstract Precise manipulation of small objects using light holds transformative potential across diverse fields. While research in optical trapping and manipulation predominantly relies on the attraction of solid matter to light intensity maxima, here we demonstrate that meta-optics enables a departure from this accepted behavior. Specifically, we present deterministic control over the sign of optical forces exerted on a metasurface integrated on a suspended silicon nanomembrane. By tailoring the geometry of the constituent meta-atoms, we engineer the coherent superposition of their multipolar modes, and consequently, the net optical force experienced by the metasurface within a phase-controlled optical standing wave. In excellent agreement with 3D numerical simulations, we experimentally realize both attractive and repulsive forces on distinct metasurface designs, directly mirroring the behavior of two-level systems interacting with optical fields. This work establishes a versatile platform for the optical control of nanoscale mechanical systems, opening alternative avenues for both fundamental research and engineering.
Published: 2026-01-09T04:34:07+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.540 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Adeel Afridi; Bruno Melo; Nadine Meyer; Romain Quidant&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67928-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.540 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Precise manipulation of small objects using light holds transformative potential across diverse fields. While research in optical trapping and manipulation predominantly relies on the attraction of solid matter to light intensity maxima, here we demonstrate that meta-optics enables a departure from this accepted behavior. Specifically, we present deterministic control over the sign of optical forces exerted on a metasurface integrated on a suspended silicon nanomembrane. By tailoring the geometry of the constituent meta-atoms, we engineer the coherent superposition of their multipolar modes, and consequently, the net optical force experienced by the metasurface within a phase-controlled optical standing wave. In excellent agreement with 3D numerical simulations, we experimentally realize both attractive and repulsive forces on distinct metasurface designs, directly mirroring the behavior of two-level systems interacting with optical fields. This work establishes a versatile platform for the optical control of nanoscale mechanical systems, opening alternative avenues for both fundamental research and engineering.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Intraplate Volcanism Driven by Slab‐Plume Interaction: Numerical Modeling and Its Application to the Eifel, Massif Central and Hainan Volcanic Areas</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032799</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb032799</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 07:15:21 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yingying Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bernhard Steinberger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sascha Brune</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eline Le Breton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anne Glerum</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michaël Pons</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb032799</prism:doi><description>Abstract Intraplate volcanism has long been linked to deep mantle plumes. However, recent studies showed that intraplate magmatism can originate from transition zone dynamics, where lower‐mantle plumes might be ponding, creating a Thermal Boundary Layer (TBL). Inspired by intraplate volcanoes in Eifel, Massif Central and Hainan that are distributed near tips of stagnant slabs imaged at transition zone depth, we hypothesize that subducted slabs might destabilize the TBL and trigger upper mantle plumes (secondary plumes), leading to intraplate volcanism. So far, the generation of such secondary plumes and the influence of slabs on plumes remain poorly understood. In this study, we perform 2D upper‐mantle geodynamic models with a TBL imposed at 670 km depth interacting with a slab of an intra‐oceanic subduction zone. The effects of various slab geometries (rollback, rollover and intermediate), TBL temperature and heating time are tested. Our models show that slabs of all geometries can destabilize the TBL, initiating secondary plumes ahead of and behind the slab. All plumes are deflected by the slab‐induced mantle flow and a sinking slab may even suppress plumes beneath it. However, a higher TBL temperature and a longer pre‐subduction heating duration may increase buoyancy flux of secondary plumes, making them more resistant to slab‐driven flow. Under all conditions explored in this study, the strength of secondary plumes produced in our models is comparable to that of the Eifel plume. This paper elucidates slab‐plume interaction and their impact on intraplate volcanism with applications to the Eifel, Massif Central and Hainan volcanic areas.
Published: 2026-01-08T07:15:21+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.536 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yingying Li; Bernhard Steinberger; Sascha Brune; Eline Le Breton; Anne Glerum; Michaël Pons&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb032799"&gt;10.1029/2025jb032799&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.536 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Intraplate volcanism has long been linked to deep mantle plumes. However, recent studies showed that intraplate magmatism can originate from transition zone dynamics, where lower‐mantle plumes might be ponding, creating a Thermal Boundary Layer (TBL). Inspired by intraplate volcanoes in Eifel, Massif Central and Hainan that are distributed near tips of stagnant slabs imaged at transition zone depth, we hypothesize that subducted slabs might destabilize the TBL and trigger upper mantle plumes (secondary plumes), leading to intraplate volcanism. So far, the generation of such secondary plumes and the influence of slabs on plumes remain poorly understood. In this study, we perform 2D upper‐mantle geodynamic models with a TBL imposed at 670 km depth interacting with a slab of an intra‐oceanic subduction zone. The effects of various slab geometries (rollback, rollover and intermediate), TBL temperature and heating time are tested. Our models show that slabs of all geometries can destabilize the TBL, initiating secondary plumes ahead of and behind the slab. All plumes are deflected by the slab‐induced mantle flow and a sinking slab may even suppress plumes beneath it. However, a higher TBL temperature and a longer pre‐subduction heating duration may increase buoyancy flux of secondary plumes, making them more resistant to slab‐driven flow. Under all conditions explored in this study, the strength of secondary plumes produced in our models is comparable to that of the Eifel plume. This paper elucidates slab‐plume interaction and their impact on intraplate volcanism with applications to the Eifel, Massif Central and Hainan volcanic areas.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Improved air-sea CO
                    &lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;
                    flux estimates from sailboat measurements</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz1502</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.adz1502</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jacqueline Behncke</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tatiana Ilyina</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fatemeh Chegini</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter Landschützer</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.adz1502</prism:doi><description>Despite their importance in the climate system, remote ocean regions and their ability to absorb anthropogenic carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) remain highly uncertain. To address this issue, citizen science initiatives, including sailboats, expand the observational network. Using observing system simulations and novel sailboat tracks, we demonstrate how integrating sailboat data improves estimates of ocean carbon uptake. While we underestimate the ocean carbon sink when mimicking real-world sampling, adding available sailboat data does not substantially improve reconstructions. Nevertheless, increased sampling reveals a stronger carbon sink, particularly between 40°S and 60°S. The improvement persists with hypothetical measurement uncertainties, but substantial differences arise depending on whether positive or negative biases are applied to the race track data. While we show that two additional circumnavigations already improve the ocean mean sink estimate, we further highlight the finding that the additional data remain insufficient to correct the overestimated CO 2 sink trend, calling for continuation of the ongoing data collection.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.532 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jacqueline Behncke; Tatiana Ilyina; Fatemeh Chegini; Peter Landschützer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.adz1502"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.adz1502&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.532 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite their importance in the climate system, remote ocean regions and their ability to absorb anthropogenic carbon dioxide (CO 2 ) remain highly uncertain. To address this issue, citizen science initiatives, including sailboats, expand the observational network. Using observing system simulations and novel sailboat tracks, we demonstrate how integrating sailboat data improves estimates of ocean carbon uptake. While we underestimate the ocean carbon sink when mimicking real-world sampling, adding available sailboat data does not substantially improve reconstructions. Nevertheless, increased sampling reveals a stronger carbon sink, particularly between 40°S and 60°S. The improvement persists with hypothetical measurement uncertainties, but substantial differences arise depending on whether positive or negative biases are applied to the race track data. While we show that two additional circumnavigations already improve the ocean mean sink estimate, we further highlight the finding that the additional data remain insufficient to correct the overestimated CO 2 sink trend, calling for continuation of the ongoing data collection.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Seismicity diagnostic of permeability creation from centimeter to subkilometer scales in crystalline rock during shear stimulation</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5201</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.ady5201</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 18:58:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pengliang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Agathe Eijsink</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junpeng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chris Marone</dc:creator><dc:creator>Derek Elsworth</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.ady5201</prism:doi><description>Permeability evolves dynamically in the crust and mediates important natural and industrial processes in the subsurface. Episodic microearthquakes generate porosity and, thus, permeability by creating or reactivating fractures. We constrain the form of the scaling relationship linking seismic moment ( M 0 ) to incremental permeability generation ( Δ k ) through a series of laboratory fault reactivation experiments with absolute constraint on seismic moment. We demonstrate Δ k − M 0 proportionality at centimeter scale but confirm predictive power-law scaling using a first-order model as Δ k = λ M 0 2 / 3 from centimeter to subkilometer scale. Stress drop, fault roughness, and deformation modulus condition the prefactor λ , extending over 10 decades for reasonable natural parameter ranges. However, observed permeabilities are much more tightly constrained, with λ spanning only two orders of magnitude over length scales from centimeter to subkilometer, suggesting interdependencies in the controlling variables and rendering the relation as diagnostic in predicting fluid flow in crustal reservoirs.
Published: 2026-01-09T18:58:58+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.530 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pengliang Yu; Agathe Eijsink; Junpeng Wang; Chris Marone; Derek Elsworth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.ady5201"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.ady5201&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.530 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Permeability evolves dynamically in the crust and mediates important natural and industrial processes in the subsurface. Episodic microearthquakes generate porosity and, thus, permeability by creating or reactivating fractures. We constrain the form of the scaling relationship linking seismic moment ( M 0 ) to incremental permeability generation ( Δ k ) through a series of laboratory fault reactivation experiments with absolute constraint on seismic moment. We demonstrate Δ k − M 0 proportionality at centimeter scale but confirm predictive power-law scaling using a first-order model as Δ k = λ M 0 2 / 3 from centimeter to subkilometer scale. Stress drop, fault roughness, and deformation modulus condition the prefactor λ , extending over 10 decades for reasonable natural parameter ranges. However, observed permeabilities are much more tightly constrained, with λ spanning only two orders of magnitude over length scales from centimeter to subkilometer, suggesting interdependencies in the controlling variables and rendering the relation as diagnostic in predicting fluid flow in crustal reservoirs.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Experimental demonstration and transformation mechanism of quenchable two-dimensional diamond</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68005-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68005-8</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 06:34:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jiayin Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoshuai Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lili Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wuxiao Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaxin Ming</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pengcheng Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lu Bai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaohui Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yubing Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiajia Feng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongliang Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ke Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weigao Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bin Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianguo Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yabin Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68005-8</prism:doi><description>Two-dimensional (2D) diamond has aroused remarkable interest in nanoelectronics and optoelectronics, owing to its superior properties and flexible characteristics compared to bulk diamond. Despite significant efforts, great challenges lie in the experimental synthesis and transformation conditions of 2D diamond. Herein, we have demonstrated the experimental preparation of high quality 2D diamond with controlled thickness and distinguished properties, realized by laser-heating few-layer graphene in a diamond anvil cell. The quenched 2D diamond exhibited a narrow T2g Raman peak (linewidth ~3.6 cm−1) and intense photoluminescence of SiV- (linewidth ~6.1 nm) and NV0 centers. In terms of transformation mechanism, atomic structures of hybrid phase interfaces suggested that the intermediate rhombohedral phase subtly mediate hexagonal graphite to cubic diamond transition. Furthermore, the tunable optical bandgap and thermal stability of 2D diamond sensitively depend on its sp3 concentration. We believe our results can shed light on the structural design and preparation of many carbon allotropes and further uncover the underlying transition mechanism. 2D diamond is expected to show superior properties compared to bulk diamond, but its synthesis remains challenging. Here, the authors report a high-temperature high-pressure method to fabricate thermally stable 2D diamond via laser-heating of few-layer graphene in a diamond anvil cell, providing relevant insights into the 2D&amp;nbsp;graphene-diamond transformation mechanisms.
Published: 2026-01-08T06:34:58+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.528 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jiayin Li; Guoshuai Du; Lili Zhao; Wuxiao Han; Jiaxin Ming; Shang Chen; Pengcheng Zhao; Lu Bai; Jiaohui Yan; Yubing Du; Jiajia Feng; Hongliang Dong; Ke Jin; Weigao Xu; Bin Chen; Jianguo Zhang; Yabin Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68005-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68005-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.528 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-dimensional (2D) diamond has aroused remarkable interest in nanoelectronics and optoelectronics, owing to its superior properties and flexible characteristics compared to bulk diamond. Despite significant efforts, great challenges lie in the experimental synthesis and transformation conditions of 2D diamond. Herein, we have demonstrated the experimental preparation of high quality 2D diamond with controlled thickness and distinguished properties, realized by laser-heating few-layer graphene in a diamond anvil cell. The quenched 2D diamond exhibited a narrow T2g Raman peak (linewidth ~3.6 cm−1) and intense photoluminescence of SiV- (linewidth ~6.1 nm) and NV0 centers. In terms of transformation mechanism, atomic structures of hybrid phase interfaces suggested that the intermediate rhombohedral phase subtly mediate hexagonal graphite to cubic diamond transition. Furthermore, the tunable optical bandgap and thermal stability of 2D diamond sensitively depend on its sp3 concentration. We believe our results can shed light on the structural design and preparation of many carbon allotropes and further uncover the underlying transition mechanism. 2D diamond is expected to show superior properties compared to bulk diamond, but its synthesis remains challenging. Here, the authors report a high-temperature high-pressure method to fabricate thermally stable 2D diamond via laser-heating of few-layer graphene in a diamond anvil cell, providing relevant insights into the 2D&amp;amp;nbsp;graphene-diamond transformation mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Adaptive ionic liquid polymer microwave modulation surface with reprogrammable dielectric properties</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68170-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68170-w</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 10:28:42 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qichao Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhehui Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanyu Qiu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaofeng Gong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huying Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zengyong Chu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haipeng Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Longjiang Deng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68170-w</prism:doi><description>Abstract Adaptive microwave surfaces have the capability to dynamically adjust their electromagnetic transmission to meet specific needs, offering significant potential for efficient integration and flexible use in reconfigurable communication systems. In this work, we utilize temperature induced break and reconstruction of hydrogen bonds to drive the orientational motion and charge mobility of the ionic liquid [EtA⁺][NO₃⁻] in the poly-2-hydroxyethyl-acrylate, resulting controllable modulation of dielectric properties at microwave frequencies. Building on this mechanism, we applied machine learning algorithms to establish correlations between temperature, ionic liquid concentration, and dielectric constant, enabling the design of a reprogrammable dielectric microwave modulation surface. For example, the 2 mm-thick switchable microwave absorbing surfaces fabricated here can operate in two distinct modes during the temperature transition from low to high, namely, off-to-on and on-to-off. The corresponding tunable effective absorption bandwidths and reflection loss values reach 5.69 GHz, –6.04 dB to –46.21 dB, and 5.34 GHz, –50.48 dB to –6.47 dB, respectively. Using the developed active surface, we also demonstrate various device architectures fabricated by three-dimensional printing, including pixelated surfaces and self-sensing functionalities, which provide valuable guidance for the development of next-generation intelligent electromagnetic devices.
Published: 2026-01-08T10:28:42+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.528 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qichao Dong; Zhehui Wang; Hanyu Qiu; Xiaofeng Gong; Huying Yan; Zengyong Chu; Tao Luo; Haipeng Lu; Longjiang Deng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68170-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68170-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.528 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Adaptive microwave surfaces have the capability to dynamically adjust their electromagnetic transmission to meet specific needs, offering significant potential for efficient integration and flexible use in reconfigurable communication systems. In this work, we utilize temperature induced break and reconstruction of hydrogen bonds to drive the orientational motion and charge mobility of the ionic liquid [EtA⁺][NO₃⁻] in the poly-2-hydroxyethyl-acrylate, resulting controllable modulation of dielectric properties at microwave frequencies. Building on this mechanism, we applied machine learning algorithms to establish correlations between temperature, ionic liquid concentration, and dielectric constant, enabling the design of a reprogrammable dielectric microwave modulation surface. For example, the 2 mm-thick switchable microwave absorbing surfaces fabricated here can operate in two distinct modes during the temperature transition from low to high, namely, off-to-on and on-to-off. The corresponding tunable effective absorption bandwidths and reflection loss values reach 5.69 GHz, –6.04 dB to –46.21 dB, and 5.34 GHz, –50.48 dB to –6.47 dB, respectively. Using the developed active surface, we also demonstrate various device architectures fabricated by three-dimensional printing, including pixelated surfaces and self-sensing functionalities, which provide valuable guidance for the development of next-generation intelligent electromagnetic devices.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Geothermal effect on riverine molybdenum isotopes: Implications for its riverine input into the ocean</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38393.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38393.1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 20:39:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zhibing Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lian Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinlong Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gangjian Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ti Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yiwei Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Le Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38393.1</prism:doi><description>Molybdenum (Mo) isotopes preserved in marine sediments serve as a premier proxy for reconstructing Earth’s oxygenation history. However, their reliability depends on accurately deciphering the mechanisms driving spatiotemporal variations in Mo isotopes in river water—the ocean’s dominant Mo source. Chemical weathering of continental rocks is widely recognized as the primary control on δ98Mo values in the dissolved riverine flux. Nevertheless, continental geothermal inputs, which discharge into major river networks along tectonically active zones worldwide, may exert an additional, yet underexplored control on riverine Mo isotope signatures. This study presents the first systematic time-series investigation of geothermal impacts on riverine δ98Mo, utilizing the tectonically active Liuxihe River Basin (South China) as a natural laboratory. Our findings reveal that geothermal inputs along fault zones dramatically alter riverine Mo isotopes, depressing δ98Mo values from a weathering baseline of 0.99‰ to as low as −0.99‰, a 2‰ shift exceeding all previously documented riverine variations. Mixing models indicate that geothermal sources can contribute up to 56% of dissolved Mo in affected river segments. Given the ubiquity of continental geothermal systems along major plate boundaries and intracontinental fault zones, this previously unrecognized control may fundamentally transform our understanding of the global riverine Mo flux. These results carry significant implications for refining global Mo budgets to incorporate isotopically light continental geothermal inputs and for reinterpreting paleo-redox records by considering variable riverine end members rather than fixed crustal values.
Published: 2026-01-09T20:39:23+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.527 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zhibing Wang; Lian Peng; Jie Li; Jinlong Ma; Gangjian Wei; Ti Zeng; Feng Ye; Yiwei Chen; Le Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38393.1"&gt;10.1130/b38393.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.527 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molybdenum (Mo) isotopes preserved in marine sediments serve as a premier proxy for reconstructing Earth’s oxygenation history. However, their reliability depends on accurately deciphering the mechanisms driving spatiotemporal variations in Mo isotopes in river water—the ocean’s dominant Mo source. Chemical weathering of continental rocks is widely recognized as the primary control on δ98Mo values in the dissolved riverine flux. Nevertheless, continental geothermal inputs, which discharge into major river networks along tectonically active zones worldwide, may exert an additional, yet underexplored control on riverine Mo isotope signatures. This study presents the first systematic time-series investigation of geothermal impacts on riverine δ98Mo, utilizing the tectonically active Liuxihe River Basin (South China) as a natural laboratory. Our findings reveal that geothermal inputs along fault zones dramatically alter riverine Mo isotopes, depressing δ98Mo values from a weathering baseline of 0.99‰ to as low as −0.99‰, a 2‰ shift exceeding all previously documented riverine variations. Mixing models indicate that geothermal sources can contribute up to 56% of dissolved Mo in affected river segments. Given the ubiquity of continental geothermal systems along major plate boundaries and intracontinental fault zones, this previously unrecognized control may fundamentally transform our understanding of the global riverine Mo flux. These results carry significant implications for refining global Mo budgets to incorporate isotopically light continental geothermal inputs and for reinterpreting paleo-redox records by considering variable riverine end members rather than fixed crustal values.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Inherited Lithospheric Structure Controls Cenozoic Intraplate Basaltic Volcanism in Central Mongolia Due To Mantle Upwelling</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031727</link><guid>10.1029/2025jb031727</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 07:20:18 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Mengfan Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuewei Bao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingkai Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kecheng Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuejing Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025jb031727</prism:doi><description>Abstract The mechanisms responsible for intracontinental basaltic volcanism are not well understood. The Cenozoic long‐lived (∼30 Myr) and diffuse intraplate volcanism in central Mongolia is an ideal natural lab to address this issue. Here we present a high‐resolution lithospheric 3‐D shear‐wave velocity model using ambient noise tomography with data mainly from two dense seismic arrays. Our model shows strong lithospheric heterogeneities beneath central Mongolia, correlating well with the occurrence of Cenozoic basaltic volcanism. Specifically, relatively thick, high‐velocity lithospheric mantle is imaged beneath the central Hangai Dome and the Hövsgöl region where Precambrian basements have been suggested to exist, which likely represent relicts of old cratonic lithosphere. Step changes in lithospheric thickness formed at their peripheries due to heterogenous lithospheric thinning or modification likely caused by recent deep mantle upwelling. More interestingly, most basaltic volcanism in central Mongolia is located at or near these strong lateral gradients of lithospheric thickness, suggesting the important role of small‐scale convection in their formation due to lithospheric thickness undulations. Taken together, the Cenozoic intraplate volcanism in central Mongolia was likely controlled by inherited lithospheric heterogeneities and mantle upwelling.
Published: 2026-01-08T07:20:18+00:00
Venue: Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth
Score: 0.524 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Mengfan Jiang; Xuewei Bao; Tao Wang; Yingkai Wu; Kecheng Zhou; Xuejing Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Geophysical Research: Solid Earth&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025jb031727"&gt;10.1029/2025jb031727&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.524 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The mechanisms responsible for intracontinental basaltic volcanism are not well understood. The Cenozoic long‐lived (∼30 Myr) and diffuse intraplate volcanism in central Mongolia is an ideal natural lab to address this issue. Here we present a high‐resolution lithospheric 3‐D shear‐wave velocity model using ambient noise tomography with data mainly from two dense seismic arrays. Our model shows strong lithospheric heterogeneities beneath central Mongolia, correlating well with the occurrence of Cenozoic basaltic volcanism. Specifically, relatively thick, high‐velocity lithospheric mantle is imaged beneath the central Hangai Dome and the Hövsgöl region where Precambrian basements have been suggested to exist, which likely represent relicts of old cratonic lithosphere. Step changes in lithospheric thickness formed at their peripheries due to heterogenous lithospheric thinning or modification likely caused by recent deep mantle upwelling. More interestingly, most basaltic volcanism in central Mongolia is located at or near these strong lateral gradients of lithospheric thickness, suggesting the important role of small‐scale convection in their formation due to lithospheric thickness undulations. Taken together, the Cenozoic intraplate volcanism in central Mongolia was likely controlled by inherited lithospheric heterogeneities and mantle upwelling.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Understanding oxygen transfer on ceria with Pt single atoms for surface reaction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 10:43:13 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yunji Choi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Seokhyun Choung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jaebeom Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jae-eon Hwang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hyeon Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunkyung Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeongjin Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeong Young Park</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeong Woo Han</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hyunjoo Lee</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5</prism:doi><description>Reducible metal oxides are widely used in surface reactions, primarily due to their ability to activate and transfer oxygen. Ceria, known for its rapid Ce3+/Ce4+ redox property, is well-known to follow Mars van Krevelen mechanism. In this study, we prepare Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 catalysts with different ceria domain sizes of 3.7, 5.6, and 7.3 nm to understand oxygen transfer, mainly O2 activation and lattice oxygen transfer. The ceria domains are isolated on the alumina, preventing oxygen transfer between the ceria. Pt single atomic structures are meticulously prepared to exclude O2 activation on Pt nanoparticles and provide uniform active sites. Interestingly, the activity trend for CO oxidation is reversed in O2-rich and O2-deficient conditions. O2 activation occurs efficiently in small ceria domains of 3.7 nm. In contrast, larger ceria domains exhibit less O2 activation but significant lattice oxygen transfer. This behavior is also modeled using large-scale molecular dynamics simulations with a neural network potential trained on first-principles data. Based on these understanding, the catalyst for methane oxidation is proposed by accelerating O2 activation in O2-rich condition. This work provides an impactful platform for understanding metal oxide catalysts. Ceria enables oxygen transfer, but size effects complicate design. Here the authors build Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 with isolated CeO2 domains (3.7–7.3 nm) and Pt single atoms, showing small domains favor O2 activation, larger ones lattice-O transfer, guiding CO or methane oxidation.
Published: 2026-01-09T10:43:13+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.524 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yunji Choi; Seokhyun Choung; Jaebeom Han; Jae-eon Hwang; Hyeon Jin; Yunkyung Kim; Jeongjin Kim; Jeong Young Park; Jeong Woo Han; Hyunjoo Lee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66242-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.524 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reducible metal oxides are widely used in surface reactions, primarily due to their ability to activate and transfer oxygen. Ceria, known for its rapid Ce3+/Ce4+ redox property, is well-known to follow Mars van Krevelen mechanism. In this study, we prepare Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 catalysts with different ceria domain sizes of 3.7, 5.6, and 7.3 nm to understand oxygen transfer, mainly O2 activation and lattice oxygen transfer. The ceria domains are isolated on the alumina, preventing oxygen transfer between the ceria. Pt single atomic structures are meticulously prepared to exclude O2 activation on Pt nanoparticles and provide uniform active sites. Interestingly, the activity trend for CO oxidation is reversed in O2-rich and O2-deficient conditions. O2 activation occurs efficiently in small ceria domains of 3.7 nm. In contrast, larger ceria domains exhibit less O2 activation but significant lattice oxygen transfer. This behavior is also modeled using large-scale molecular dynamics simulations with a neural network potential trained on first-principles data. Based on these understanding, the catalyst for methane oxidation is proposed by accelerating O2 activation in O2-rich condition. This work provides an impactful platform for understanding metal oxide catalysts. Ceria enables oxygen transfer, but size effects complicate design. Here the authors build Pt/CeO2-Al2O3 with isolated CeO2 domains (3.7–7.3 nm) and Pt single atoms, showing small domains favor O2 activation, larger ones lattice-O transfer, guiding CO or methane oxidation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ultra-broadband near- to mid-infrared electro-optic modulator on thin-film lithium niobate</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67902-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67902-2</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 14:17:13 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qiyuan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiyuan Yi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aolong Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenglin Shang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yiqi Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sizhe Xing</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinlai Cui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yupeng Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiayi Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junwen Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nan Chi</dc:creator><dc:creator>An Pan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cheng Zeng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinsong Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuang Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Minming Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67902-2</prism:doi><description>The escalating capacity limitations of conventional near-infrared telecommunication bands have spurred urgent investigations into wide-band optical communication systems spanning from the near-infrared to mid-infrared regimes. This has motivated the development of optical components combining broadband bandwidth with high-speed operation. The state-of-the-art modulators face challenges in achieving broad operational bandwidth due to waveguide dispersion and velocity mismatch. Here we demonstrate a thin-film lithium niobate (TFLN) electro-optic (EO) modulator with an unprecedented 800-nm operational bandwidth, covering the full O-U telecom bands and extending into the 2-μm regime. The TFLN modulator exhibits &amp;gt;67 GHz EO bandwidth across O-U bands (~100 GHz at O-/S-/C-/L-bands) and &amp;gt;50 GHz at 2-μm band. It enables single-lane exceeding 240 Gbps PAM-4 transmission across O-U bands and a record 170 Gbps PAM-4 transmission at 2-μm band. This breakthrough establishes TFLN as a compelling platform for multispectral photonics, bridging conventional telecom infrastructure with emerging 2-μm technologies for next-generation optical communications. This work demonstrates a thin-film lithium niobate modulator with an 800-nm operational bandwidth covering from near- to mid-infrared region, enabling single-lane 240 Gbps and 170 Gbps PAM-4 transmission at all O-U bands and 2-μm band, respectively.
Published: 2026-01-08T14:17:13+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.522 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qiyuan Li; Qiyuan Yi; Aolong Sun; Chenglin Shang; Yiqi Dai; Sizhe Xing; Jinlai Cui; Yupeng Zhu; Jiayi Li; Jun Zheng; Junwen Zhang; Nan Chi; An Pan; Cheng Zeng; Jinsong Xia; Shuang Zheng; Li Shen; Minming Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67902-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67902-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.522 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The escalating capacity limitations of conventional near-infrared telecommunication bands have spurred urgent investigations into wide-band optical communication systems spanning from the near-infrared to mid-infrared regimes. This has motivated the development of optical components combining broadband bandwidth with high-speed operation. The state-of-the-art modulators face challenges in achieving broad operational bandwidth due to waveguide dispersion and velocity mismatch. Here we demonstrate a thin-film lithium niobate (TFLN) electro-optic (EO) modulator with an unprecedented 800-nm operational bandwidth, covering the full O-U telecom bands and extending into the 2-μm regime. The TFLN modulator exhibits &amp;amp;gt;67 GHz EO bandwidth across O-U bands (~100 GHz at O-/S-/C-/L-bands) and &amp;amp;gt;50 GHz at 2-μm band. It enables single-lane exceeding 240 Gbps PAM-4 transmission across O-U bands and a record 170 Gbps PAM-4 transmission at 2-μm band. This breakthrough establishes TFLN as a compelling platform for multispectral photonics, bridging conventional telecom infrastructure with emerging 2-μm technologies for next-generation optical communications. This work demonstrates a thin-film lithium niobate modulator with an 800-nm operational bandwidth covering from near- to mid-infrared region, enabling single-lane 240 Gbps and 170 Gbps PAM-4 transmission at all O-U bands and 2-μm band, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Multivalent ligands regulate dimensional engineering for inverted perovskite solar modules</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aea0656</link><guid>10.1126/science.aea0656</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 19:02:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiaoming Chang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanping Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yue Ping</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nan Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tinghuan Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenqing Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaoheng Ling</dc:creator><dc:creator>Badri Vishal</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anil Reddy Pininti</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jong Bin Park</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sang Young Jeong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Qin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wing Tung Hui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fion Sze Yan Yeung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu-Ying Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hailiang Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Adi Prasetio</dc:creator><dc:creator>Furkan H. Isikgor</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingjie He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Drajad Satrio Utomo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rongbo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kui Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mario Lanza</dc:creator><dc:creator>Han Young Woo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Martin Heeney</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stefaan De Wolf</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yen-Hung Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Leonidas Tsetseris</dc:creator><dc:creator>Randi Azmi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas D. Anthopoulos</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/science.aea0656</prism:doi><description>Multivalent, resonance-stabilized amidinium ligands enable stronger chemical coordination and reduced deprotonation compared with conventional monovalent ammonium ligands in low-dimensional perovskites. Here, we introduce a controllable one- to two-dimensional (1D-to-2D) structural transition strategy by systematically tuning ligand conformation, thereby modulating hydrogen bonding, π–π stacking, and basicity to elucidate the relationship between molecular structure, interfacial interactions, and resulting dimensionality. The 1D-amidinium perovskite structure, with its pronounced geometric anisotropy, impedes uniform surface coverage and defect passivation. In contrast, the 2D-amidinium perovskite forms a continuous, homogeneous interfacial layer, enabling more effective defect passivation and favorable energy-level alignment. With dimensionality control, inverted 3D/2D-amidinium perovskite solar cells deliver 25.4% power conversion efficiency (1.1 square centimeters, steady-state certified) and maintain &gt;95% of their initial efficiency after 1100 hours of continuous 1-sun operation at 85°C.
Published: 2026-01-08T19:02:31+00:00
Venue: Science
Score: 0.521 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiaoming Chang; Yanping Liu; Yue Ping; Nan Wu; Tinghuan Yang; Chenqing Tian; Zhaoheng Ling; Badri Vishal; Anil Reddy Pininti; Jong Bin Park; Sang Young Jeong; Yan Qin; Wing Tung Hui; Fion Sze Yan Yeung; Yu-Ying Yang; Hailiang Liao; Adi Prasetio; Furkan H. Isikgor; Mingjie He; Drajad Satrio Utomo; Rongbo Wang; Kui Zhao; Mario Lanza; Han Young Woo; Martin Heeney; Stefaan De Wolf; Yen-Hung Lin; Leonidas Tsetseris; Randi Azmi; Thomas D. Anthopoulos&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aea0656"&gt;10.1126/science.aea0656&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.521 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multivalent, resonance-stabilized amidinium ligands enable stronger chemical coordination and reduced deprotonation compared with conventional monovalent ammonium ligands in low-dimensional perovskites. Here, we introduce a controllable one- to two-dimensional (1D-to-2D) structural transition strategy by systematically tuning ligand conformation, thereby modulating hydrogen bonding, π–π stacking, and basicity to elucidate the relationship between molecular structure, interfacial interactions, and resulting dimensionality. The 1D-amidinium perovskite structure, with its pronounced geometric anisotropy, impedes uniform surface coverage and defect passivation. In contrast, the 2D-amidinium perovskite forms a continuous, homogeneous interfacial layer, enabling more effective defect passivation and favorable energy-level alignment. With dimensionality control, inverted 3D/2D-amidinium perovskite solar cells deliver 25.4% power conversion efficiency (1.1 square centimeters, steady-state certified) and maintain &amp;gt;95% of their initial efficiency after 1100 hours of continuous 1-sun operation at 85°C.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Can ecosystems recover after the deep sea is mined?</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aef2598</link><guid>10.1126/science.aef2598</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 19:02:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Christian Elliott</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/science.aef2598</prism:doi><description>Race to scoop metals from the sea floor spurs efforts to understand impacts on rare abyssal species
Published: 2026-01-08T19:02:31+00:00
Venue: Science
Score: 0.520 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Christian Elliott&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.aef2598"&gt;10.1126/science.aef2598&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.520 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Race to scoop metals from the sea floor spurs efforts to understand impacts on rare abyssal species&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Self-organized thermoelectric conversion systems on the deep seafloor</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/g53463.1</link><guid>10.1130/g53463.1</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 16:55:08 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Atsushi Okamoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Misaki Takahashi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshinori Sato</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ryoichi Yamada</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kentaro Toda</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tomonori Ihara</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tatsuo Nozaki</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/g53463.1</prism:doi><description>Deep-sea hydrothermal vents are sites where thermal energy from Earth’s interior is emitted into the ocean, and sulfide- or sulfate-rich chimneys form by mixing of hydrothermal fluids and ambient cold seawater. Sulfide minerals are semiconductors and can convert thermal to electrical energy. However, regardless of the high-temperature difference (up to 400 °C) between vent fluids and seawater, the significance of thermoelectric power generation by chimneys is poorly understood. We measured the electrical conductivity and thermoelectromotive force (TEMF) of typical sulfide minerals and each part of zoned chimney walls from seafloor hydrothermal vents to evaluate their thermoelectric conversion. Young and porous chimneys consist mainly of fine-grained sulfate and Zn sulfide, with extremely low electrical conductivity, resulting in no thermoelectric conversion. In contrast, mature chimneys with inner walls rich in Cu, Fe, and Pb sulfides are n-type semiconductors with a high thermoelectric conversion performance. Given a temperature difference of 200−300 °C between the vent fluids and ambient seawater, the TEMF of the mature chimneys approaches 10−210 mV, which is comparable to the redox potential between vent fluids and seawater (∼500 mV). This TEMF could play an essential role as a power source to overcome the overpotential required for the redox reactions at both sides of the chimney walls. Our findings suggest that seafloor chimneys are a unique self-organized thermoelectric conversion system that supplies substantial electrical energy to deep-sea ecosystems.
Published: 2026-01-08T16:55:08+00:00
Venue: Geology
Score: 0.519 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Atsushi Okamoto; Misaki Takahashi; Yoshinori Sato; Ryoichi Yamada; Kentaro Toda; Tomonori Ihara; Tatsuo Nozaki&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/g53463.1"&gt;10.1130/g53463.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.519 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep-sea hydrothermal vents are sites where thermal energy from Earth’s interior is emitted into the ocean, and sulfide- or sulfate-rich chimneys form by mixing of hydrothermal fluids and ambient cold seawater. Sulfide minerals are semiconductors and can convert thermal to electrical energy. However, regardless of the high-temperature difference (up to 400 °C) between vent fluids and seawater, the significance of thermoelectric power generation by chimneys is poorly understood. We measured the electrical conductivity and thermoelectromotive force (TEMF) of typical sulfide minerals and each part of zoned chimney walls from seafloor hydrothermal vents to evaluate their thermoelectric conversion. Young and porous chimneys consist mainly of fine-grained sulfate and Zn sulfide, with extremely low electrical conductivity, resulting in no thermoelectric conversion. In contrast, mature chimneys with inner walls rich in Cu, Fe, and Pb sulfides are n-type semiconductors with a high thermoelectric conversion performance. Given a temperature difference of 200−300 °C between the vent fluids and ambient seawater, the TEMF of the mature chimneys approaches 10−210 mV, which is comparable to the redox potential between vent fluids and seawater (∼500 mV). This TEMF could play an essential role as a power source to overcome the overpotential required for the redox reactions at both sides of the chimney walls. Our findings suggest that seafloor chimneys are a unique self-organized thermoelectric conversion system that supplies substantial electrical energy to deep-sea ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Electronegativity and entropy design of layered oxides for sodium-ion batteries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68016-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68016-5</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 00:15:04 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lu Gan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hu-Rong Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingwen Dai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zefeng Lai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin-Guang Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei-Huan He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qi-lin Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Wen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei-Wei Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Min Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian-Mao Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ze Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu-Jie Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinling Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fanghua Ning</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fei Zhan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Denglong Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lituo Zheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhigao Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chuying OuYang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu-Guo Guo</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68016-5</prism:doi><description>Exploring sodium-ion layered oxides with broad compositional diversity is an important approach for the development of high-performance positive electrodes. Structural chemistry determined by composition plays a decisive role in performance improvement, but the relationship between composition and structure becomes more elusive in complex multi-component systems. Here we propose an electronegativity entropy weight concept to understand entropy-dominated phases formation. Electronegativity and configurational entropy are used to quantify key interactions in layered materials. Guided by this understanding, we design a sodium-deficient layered oxide with an O3 stacking sequence. This material demonstrates good structural and thermal stability, along with air stability (negligible performance degradation after air exposure), cycling stability (93.02% capacity retention after 200 cycles), and rate capability (retaining 69.1% capacity retention from 86.5 mA g⁻¹ to 1.73 A g⁻¹). Even in potassium-ion batteries with larger inserted ions, the material still exhibits cycling stability. This strategy provides valuable compositional guidance for the rational design of high-performance layered oxide materials. The structure of layered oxides dictates their properties as positive electrodes in sodium-ion batteries, but its rational design remains challenging. Here, authors employ electronegativity and configurational entropy as a design descriptor to guide the synthesis of a sodium-deficient layered oxide with an O3 stacking sequence, rendering good thermal and air stability.
Published: 2026-01-08T00:15:04+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.518 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lu Gan; Hu-Rong Yao; Jingwen Dai; Zefeng Lai; Xin-Guang Yuan; Wei-Huan He; Qi-lin Zheng; Min Wen; Wei-Wei Yuan; Min Lin; Jian-Mao Xiao; Ze Yu; Yu-Jie Guo; Jinling Liu; Fanghua Ning; Fei Zhan; Denglong Chen; Lituo Zheng; Zhigao Huang; Chuying OuYang; Yu-Guo Guo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68016-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68016-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.518 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exploring sodium-ion layered oxides with broad compositional diversity is an important approach for the development of high-performance positive electrodes. Structural chemistry determined by composition plays a decisive role in performance improvement, but the relationship between composition and structure becomes more elusive in complex multi-component systems. Here we propose an electronegativity entropy weight concept to understand entropy-dominated phases formation. Electronegativity and configurational entropy are used to quantify key interactions in layered materials. Guided by this understanding, we design a sodium-deficient layered oxide with an O3 stacking sequence. This material demonstrates good structural and thermal stability, along with air stability (negligible performance degradation after air exposure), cycling stability (93.02% capacity retention after 200 cycles), and rate capability (retaining 69.1% capacity retention from 86.5 mA g⁻¹ to 1.73 A g⁻¹). Even in potassium-ion batteries with larger inserted ions, the material still exhibits cycling stability. This strategy provides valuable compositional guidance for the rational design of high-performance layered oxide materials. The structure of layered oxides dictates their properties as positive electrodes in sodium-ion batteries, but its rational design remains challenging. Here, authors employ electronegativity and configurational entropy as a design descriptor to guide the synthesis of a sodium-deficient layered oxide with an O3 stacking sequence, rendering good thermal and air stability.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Crystallographic microstructure engineering for artificial solid electrolyte interphases toward stable zinc electrode</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68212-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68212-3</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 06:34:57 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hongyu Cao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fengnian Zhuang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanfei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tang Sheng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenyuan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiwen Bai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengdie Lan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaoqi Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenshan Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shengping Shen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68212-3</prism:doi><description>The challenge of dendrite growth limiting metal battery lifespan, despite extensive chemical composition optimizations for artificial solid electrolyte interphases (ASEIs), necessitates the development of ASEI design routes. Regulating the ASEI crystallographic microstructure offers a promising yet underexplored solution with efficacy uncertainty. Critical issue lies in what is the optimal crystallographic microstructure state. Using the ZnS ASEI in aqueous Zn batteries as a case study, here we report the effects of grain orientation and grain boundary density on the performance of Zn negative electrode. The results reveal the existence of an optimal microstructure state—predominant in-plane (111) orientation coupled with a critical grain boundary density of ~55 μm/μm2—which delivers an 18-fold lifespan extension, and over 3400 cycles with a Coulombic efficiency of 99.92% at 5 mA cm-2, surpassing the efficacy of most chemical composition manipulations. Mechanistically, the (111) orientation integrates higher electrochemical kinetics and mechanical strength. As grain boundary density increases to tens of μm/μm2, the enhancement in electrochemical kinetics coincides with compromised mechanical strength, with their trade-off delineating the critical density that maximizes electrode cycling stability. Our findings exemplify an efficient ASEI design route—crystallographic microstructure engineering. Dendrite growth compromises the cycling life of metal batteries. Here, authors propose a crystallographic microstructure engineering approach to the artificial solid electrolyte interphase, demonstrating a high efficacy in stabilizing the zinc metal electrode during plating/stripping.
Published: 2026-01-08T06:34:57+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.516 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hongyu Cao; Fengnian Zhuang; Yanfei Wang; Tang Sheng; Wenyuan Liu; Zhiwen Bai; Mengdie Lan; Zhaoqi Li; Wenshan Yu; Shengping Shen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68212-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68212-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.516 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenge of dendrite growth limiting metal battery lifespan, despite extensive chemical composition optimizations for artificial solid electrolyte interphases (ASEIs), necessitates the development of ASEI design routes. Regulating the ASEI crystallographic microstructure offers a promising yet underexplored solution with efficacy uncertainty. Critical issue lies in what is the optimal crystallographic microstructure state. Using the ZnS ASEI in aqueous Zn batteries as a case study, here we report the effects of grain orientation and grain boundary density on the performance of Zn negative electrode. The results reveal the existence of an optimal microstructure state—predominant in-plane (111) orientation coupled with a critical grain boundary density of ~55 μm/μm2—which delivers an 18-fold lifespan extension, and over 3400 cycles with a Coulombic efficiency of 99.92% at 5 mA cm-2, surpassing the efficacy of most chemical composition manipulations. Mechanistically, the (111) orientation integrates higher electrochemical kinetics and mechanical strength. As grain boundary density increases to tens of μm/μm2, the enhancement in electrochemical kinetics coincides with compromised mechanical strength, with their trade-off delineating the critical density that maximizes electrode cycling stability. Our findings exemplify an efficient ASEI design route—crystallographic microstructure engineering. Dendrite growth compromises the cycling life of metal batteries. Here, authors propose a crystallographic microstructure engineering approach to the artificial solid electrolyte interphase, demonstrating a high efficacy in stabilizing the zinc metal electrode during plating/stripping.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>A sample dredged from the Alpha Ridge records evidence of an emergent volcanic setting at 90 Ma</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 13:51:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Marie-Claude Williamson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Grace E. Shephard</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Boggild</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rebecca Carey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul B. Hamilton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dawn Kellett</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel Miggins</dc:creator><dc:creator>Anthony A. P. Koppers</dc:creator><dc:creator>Derek H. C. Wilton</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daniel J. MacDonald</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dominique Weis</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuangquan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Brian L. Cousens</dc:creator><dc:creator>Simon E. Jackson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Duane C. Petts</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher M. Lawley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Erica Massey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lotte M. Larsen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wilfried Jokat</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeff Harris</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z</prism:doi><description>Abstract Recovering geological samples from the deep basins and ridges of the central Arctic Ocean presents significant challenges because of remote access and thick ice cover. During the 2016 Canada-Sweden Polar Expedition to the Arctic Ocean, volcaniclastic breccia was dredged from the Alpha Ridge, part of an underwater mountain chain extending from the Canadian polar margin to the Siberian shelf. Argon geochronology of plagioclase crystals within glassy lava fragments dates the sample to 90.4 ± 0.26 Ma. The geochemical composition of basalt clasts in the volcaniclastic breccia closely resembles that of igneous rocks from the High Arctic Large Igneous Province suggesting that the Alpha Ridge was an active volcanic feature within the circum-Arctic in the Late Cretaceous. Our results support lava–water interactions in a littoral environment, driven by the growth and emergence of a central igneous platform and accompanied by eruptive activity at constructional volcanic edifices along its margins.
Published: 2026-01-09T13:51:41+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.516 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Marie-Claude Williamson; Grace E. Shephard; Kai Boggild; Rebecca Carey; Paul B. Hamilton; Dawn Kellett; Daniel Miggins; Anthony A. P. Koppers; Derek H. C. Wilton; Daniel J. MacDonald; Dominique Weis; Shuangquan Zhang; Brian L. Cousens; Simon E. Jackson; Duane C. Petts; Christopher M. Lawley; Erica Massey; Lotte M. Larsen; Wilfried Jokat; Jeff Harris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-02981-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.516 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Recovering geological samples from the deep basins and ridges of the central Arctic Ocean presents significant challenges because of remote access and thick ice cover. During the 2016 Canada-Sweden Polar Expedition to the Arctic Ocean, volcaniclastic breccia was dredged from the Alpha Ridge, part of an underwater mountain chain extending from the Canadian polar margin to the Siberian shelf. Argon geochronology of plagioclase crystals within glassy lava fragments dates the sample to 90.4 ± 0.26 Ma. The geochemical composition of basalt clasts in the volcaniclastic breccia closely resembles that of igneous rocks from the High Arctic Large Igneous Province suggesting that the Alpha Ridge was an active volcanic feature within the circum-Arctic in the Late Cretaceous. Our results support lava–water interactions in a littoral environment, driven by the growth and emergence of a central igneous platform and accompanied by eruptive activity at constructional volcanic edifices along its margins.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Bark microbiota modulate climate-active gas fluxes in Australian forests</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.adu2182</link><guid>10.1126/science.adu2182</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 19:02:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pok Man Leung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Luke C. Jeffrey</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sean K. Bay</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paula Gomez-Alvarez</dc:creator><dc:creator>Montgomery Hall</dc:creator><dc:creator>Scott G. Johnston</dc:creator><dc:creator>Johannes Dittmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Elisabeth Deschaseaux</dc:creator><dc:creator>Billie Hopkins</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jasmine Haskell</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thanavit Jirapanjawat</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tess F. Hutchinson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicholas V. Coleman</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiyang Dong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Damien T. Maher</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chris Greening</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/science.adu2182</prism:doi><description>Recent studies suggest that microbes inhabit tree bark, yet little is known about their identities, functions, and environmental roles. Here we reveal, through gene-centric and genome-resolved metagenomics, that the bark of eight common Australian tree species hosts abundant and specialized microbial communities. The predominant bacteria are hydrogen-cycling facultative anaerobes adapted to dynamic redox and substrate conditions. Furthermore, bark-associated methanotrophs are abundant and can coexist with hydrogenotrophic methanogens. Microcosm experiments showed that bark microorganisms aerobically consume methane, hydrogen, and carbon monoxide at in planta concentrations and produce these gases under anoxia. Combined with in situ field measurements, we show that tree-dwelling microbiota metabolize multiple climate-active gases at marked rates within tree stems, highlighting a potentially substantial role in global atmospheric cycles.
Published: 2026-01-08T19:02:31+00:00
Venue: Science
Score: 0.508 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pok Man Leung; Luke C. Jeffrey; Sean K. Bay; Paula Gomez-Alvarez; Montgomery Hall; Scott G. Johnston; Johannes Dittmann; Elisabeth Deschaseaux; Billie Hopkins; Jasmine Haskell; Thanavit Jirapanjawat; Tess F. Hutchinson; Nicholas V. Coleman; Xiyang Dong; Damien T. Maher; Chris Greening&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.adu2182"&gt;10.1126/science.adu2182&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.508 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent studies suggest that microbes inhabit tree bark, yet little is known about their identities, functions, and environmental roles. Here we reveal, through gene-centric and genome-resolved metagenomics, that the bark of eight common Australian tree species hosts abundant and specialized microbial communities. The predominant bacteria are hydrogen-cycling facultative anaerobes adapted to dynamic redox and substrate conditions. Furthermore, bark-associated methanotrophs are abundant and can coexist with hydrogenotrophic methanogens. Microcosm experiments showed that bark microorganisms aerobically consume methane, hydrogen, and carbon monoxide at in planta concentrations and produce these gases under anoxia. Combined with in situ field measurements, we show that tree-dwelling microbiota metabolize multiple climate-active gases at marked rates within tree stems, highlighting a potentially substantial role in global atmospheric cycles.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Self-induced Floquet magnons in magnetic vortices</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.adq9891</link><guid>10.1126/science.adq9891</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 19:02:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Christopher Heins</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lukas Körber</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joo-Von Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thibaut Devolder</dc:creator><dc:creator>Johan H. Mentink</dc:creator><dc:creator>Attila Kákay</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jürgen Fassbender</dc:creator><dc:creator>Katrin Schultheiss</dc:creator><dc:creator>Helmut Schultheiss</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/science.adq9891</prism:doi><description>Driving condensed matter systems with periodic electromagnetic fields can result in exotic states not found in equilibrium. Termed Floquet engineering, such periodic driving applied to electronic systems can induce topological band structures and control spin interactions. In this study, we present a class of Floquet states in a magnetic vortex that arise from nonlinear interactions between the vortex core and microwave magnons. Floquet bands emerge through the periodic oscillation of the core, which can be initiated by either driving the core directly or pumping azimuthal magnon modes. For the latter, the azimuthal modes induce core gyration through nonlinear interactions, which in turn renormalizes the magnon band structure. This represents a self-induced mechanism for Floquet band engineering and opens avenues to study and control nonlinear magnon dynamics.
Published: 2026-01-08T19:02:31+00:00
Venue: Science
Score: 0.506 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Christopher Heins; Lukas Körber; Joo-Von Kim; Thibaut Devolder; Johan H. Mentink; Attila Kákay; Jürgen Fassbender; Katrin Schultheiss; Helmut Schultheiss&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.adq9891"&gt;10.1126/science.adq9891&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.506 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Driving condensed matter systems with periodic electromagnetic fields can result in exotic states not found in equilibrium. Termed Floquet engineering, such periodic driving applied to electronic systems can induce topological band structures and control spin interactions. In this study, we present a class of Floquet states in a magnetic vortex that arise from nonlinear interactions between the vortex core and microwave magnons. Floquet bands emerge through the periodic oscillation of the core, which can be initiated by either driving the core directly or pumping azimuthal magnon modes. For the latter, the azimuthal modes induce core gyration through nonlinear interactions, which in turn renormalizes the magnon band structure. This represents a self-induced mechanism for Floquet band engineering and opens avenues to study and control nonlinear magnon dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Magnetization generation and giant nonlinear transport at symmetry-engineered interfaces</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 04:24:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hang-Bo Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen-Yu Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi-Ning Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng-Hao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eoin Moynihan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ana M. Sanchez</dc:creator><dc:creator>WenGuang Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoshihiro Iwasa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Marin Alexe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming-Min Yang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1</prism:doi><description>Abstract Interfaces in heterostructures possess inherent inversion asymmetry and display diverse physical effects, however, the pristine in-plane mirror symmetries of the constituent layers are usually preserved at the interface. On-demand manipulation of these symmetries remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate a strategy to control the in-plane mirror symmetries of interfaces by engineering the crystallographic orientation of heterostructures. We design a workhorse system with a new orientation, i.e., the LaAlO 3 /SrTiO 3 heterostructure with metallic interfaces in the (112)-plane. Such a high index orientation leads to the breaking of all the pristine mirror symmetries except the mirror plane perpendicular to the $$[1\bar{1}0]$$ [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] direction ( $${M}_{[1\bar{1}0]}$$ M [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] ), resulting in the C s point symmetry with a metallic conduction. Consequently, this interface exhibits a giant nonlinear Hall effect characterized by a large Berry curvature dipole, a circular photogalvanic effect, and current-induced out-of-plane magnetization, all functional at room temperature. The magnitude of the nonlinear Hall effect rivals the Weyl and Dirac systems. Our work establishes a new strategy in exploring emerging electronic properties with nontrivial quantum geometry by designing the interface symmetry.
Published: 2026-01-09T04:24:36+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.503 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hang-Bo Zhang; Zhen-Yu Ding; Yi-Ning Xie; Zheng-Hao Li; Eoin Moynihan; Ana M. Sanchez; WenGuang Zhu; Yang Gao; Yoshihiro Iwasa; Marin Alexe; Ming-Min Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66149-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.503 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Interfaces in heterostructures possess inherent inversion asymmetry and display diverse physical effects, however, the pristine in-plane mirror symmetries of the constituent layers are usually preserved at the interface. On-demand manipulation of these symmetries remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate a strategy to control the in-plane mirror symmetries of interfaces by engineering the crystallographic orientation of heterostructures. We design a workhorse system with a new orientation, i.e., the LaAlO 3 /SrTiO 3 heterostructure with metallic interfaces in the (112)-plane. Such a high index orientation leads to the breaking of all the pristine mirror symmetries except the mirror plane perpendicular to the $$[1\bar{1}0]$$ [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] direction ( $${M}_{[1\bar{1}0]}$$ M [ 1 1 ¯ 0 ] ), resulting in the C s point symmetry with a metallic conduction. Consequently, this interface exhibits a giant nonlinear Hall effect characterized by a large Berry curvature dipole, a circular photogalvanic effect, and current-induced out-of-plane magnetization, all functional at room temperature. The magnitude of the nonlinear Hall effect rivals the Weyl and Dirac systems. Our work establishes a new strategy in exploring emerging electronic properties with nontrivial quantum geometry by designing the interface symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Unlocking limited electric double-layer capacity via electrochemically-driven continuous partial desolvations in carbon nanopores</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 09:47:30 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Sicheng Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zerui Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Binhao Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuting Song</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dafu Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yimei Ouyang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kun Lan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhangquan Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guiming Zhong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dong-Liang Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiulong Wei</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0</prism:doi><description>Electrochemical capacitors are primarily limited by the low electric double-layer storage capacity and narrow operating window that avoids the formation of solid electrolyte interface layers. Herein, we demonstrate that electric double-layer adsorption of solvated Na+ in carbon nanopores is achievable under a large offset potential of −2.95 V vs. potential of zero charge in diethylene-glycol-dimethyl-ether electrolyte, even accompanying with the as-formed solid electrolyte interface layers. The largely enlarged offset potential in situ drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, which largely reduces the average solvation numbers from 2.1 to 0.6, leading to a high electric double-layer capacitance of 172 F g−1, a high capacity of 508 C g−1 and high initial coulombic efficiency of 92.2% at 0.1 A g−1 (0.5 mA cm−2), together with high-rate capability and long-term cycling stability. Thereby, such increased electric double-layer charge storage enables the redesign and assembly of sodium-ion capacitor pouch cells that display a high specific density of 40 Wh kg−1 (on cell level) and 30,000 cycles at a fast (dis)charging rate of 51 C (20 mA cm−2). Such sodium-ion capacitors are assembled without any pretreatments that are beneficial for scale-up fabrications in industry. Electrochemical capacitors are limited by low capacity. Here, authors report that the increased offset potential from potential of zero charge electrochemically drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, leading to largely increased electric double-layer capacitance and capacity.
Published: 2026-01-09T09:47:30+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.503 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Sicheng Fan; Zerui Yan; Binhao Wang; Yuting Song; Dafu Tang; Huan Liu; Yimei Ouyang; Kun Lan; Zhangquan Peng; Guiming Zhong; Dong-Liang Peng; Qiulong Wei&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66433-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.503 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrochemical capacitors are primarily limited by the low electric double-layer storage capacity and narrow operating window that avoids the formation of solid electrolyte interface layers. Herein, we demonstrate that electric double-layer adsorption of solvated Na+ in carbon nanopores is achievable under a large offset potential of −2.95 V vs. potential of zero charge in diethylene-glycol-dimethyl-ether electrolyte, even accompanying with the as-formed solid electrolyte interface layers. The largely enlarged offset potential in situ drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, which largely reduces the average solvation numbers from 2.1 to 0.6, leading to a high electric double-layer capacitance of 172 F g−1, a high capacity of 508 C g−1 and high initial coulombic efficiency of 92.2% at 0.1 A g−1 (0.5 mA cm−2), together with high-rate capability and long-term cycling stability. Thereby, such increased electric double-layer charge storage enables the redesign and assembly of sodium-ion capacitor pouch cells that display a high specific density of 40 Wh kg−1 (on cell level) and 30,000 cycles at a fast (dis)charging rate of 51 C (20 mA cm−2). Such sodium-ion capacitors are assembled without any pretreatments that are beneficial for scale-up fabrications in industry. Electrochemical capacitors are limited by low capacity. Here, authors report that the increased offset potential from potential of zero charge electrochemically drives the continued partial desolvations in carbon nanopores, leading to largely increased electric double-layer capacitance and capacity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Enhancing hydrovoltaic power generation through coupled heat and light-driven surface charge dynamics</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jan 2026 19:16:34 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Tarique Anwar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Giulia Tagliabue</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8</prism:doi><description>Abstract Harnessing natural evaporation offers a sustainable pathway for next-generation energy technologies. We present a unified physical and experimental framework for evaporation-driven hydrovoltaic (EDHV) systems that decouples and controls the key interfacial processes underlying electricity generation from heat and sunlight. An intermediate ion-conducting layer separates the evaporative top interface from the silicon–dielectric nanopillar array, enabling independent modulation of evaporation, ion transport, and interfacial chemical equilibrium. This strategy enhances performance and clarifies mechanisms governing thermal and photo-induced charge generation, improving ion migration and electricity output. We develop a predictive equivalent-circuit model that captures process coupling through an analytically derived transfer capacitance. Our results show that capacitive photocharging and thermally modulated surface equilibria—rather than faradaic or photothermal effects—dominate energy conversion. The device achieves 1 V open-circuit voltage and 0.25 W/m² power density, with silicon doping and dielectric choice further boosting performance. These findings inform EDHV optimization across environmental and material conditions.
Published: 2026-01-09T19:16:34+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.501 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Tarique Anwar; Giulia Tagliabue&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68261-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.501 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Harnessing natural evaporation offers a sustainable pathway for next-generation energy technologies. We present a unified physical and experimental framework for evaporation-driven hydrovoltaic (EDHV) systems that decouples and controls the key interfacial processes underlying electricity generation from heat and sunlight. An intermediate ion-conducting layer separates the evaporative top interface from the silicon–dielectric nanopillar array, enabling independent modulation of evaporation, ion transport, and interfacial chemical equilibrium. This strategy enhances performance and clarifies mechanisms governing thermal and photo-induced charge generation, improving ion migration and electricity output. We develop a predictive equivalent-circuit model that captures process coupling through an analytically derived transfer capacitance. Our results show that capacitive photocharging and thermally modulated surface equilibria—rather than faradaic or photothermal effects—dominate energy conversion. The device achieves 1 V open-circuit voltage and 0.25 W/m² power density, with silicon doping and dielectric choice further boosting performance. These findings inform EDHV optimization across environmental and material conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Single symmetric nanopores in ultrathin crystalline ferroelectric BiFeO3 as polarization-switchable ionic diodes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68262-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68262-7</guid><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 05:23:30 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chun-Hao Chiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chia-Chun Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pai-Chia Kuo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei-Lun Hung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yin-Cheng Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Shu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chia-An Lung</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ting-Ran Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zih-Wei Cyue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jessie Shiue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yen-Lin Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jan-Chi Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Hsien Yeh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chun-Wei Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68262-7</prism:doi><description>Artificial ionic diodes, inspired by biological ion channels, are typically realized by creating asymmetries in pore geometry or surface charge. Ferroelectric polarization, arising from the spontaneous alignment of electric dipoles within materials, provides an alternative strategy to achieve directional ion transport without additional geometry modification or surface functionalization. This work demonstrates that ultrathin freestanding ferroelectric crystalline bismuth ferrite symmetric-type single-nanopore membranes, with a thickness down to 30 nm, exhibit rectified ion currents driven by naturally spontaneous polarization. These nanopores exhibit reversible polarization switching with hysteretic ion current rectification in response to external pH stimuli, offering additional tunability in emulating the functions of biological ion channels. Furthermore, significant osmotic power generation is observed, enabled by current amplification through directional ion transport. These findings highlight the potential of utilizing ultrathin ferroelectric oxide membrane materials as ionic diodes with directional preferences and switchable polarizations for developing ionic circuits, mimicking biological membranes, and facilitating osmotic power conversion. Achieving directional ion transport in thin membranes is desirable yet challenging. Here, authors demonstrate an ultrathin ferroelectric single-pore membrane that enables polarization-driven ion rectification and hysteretic responses under pH stimuli.
Published: 2026-01-08T05:23:30+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.499 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chun-Hao Chiang; Chia-Chun Wei; Pai-Chia Kuo; Wei-Lun Hung; Yin-Cheng Lin; Li-Shu Wang; Chia-An Lung; Ting-Ran Liu; Zih-Wei Cyue; Jessie Shiue; Yen-Lin Huang; Jan-Chi Yang; Li-Hsien Yeh; Chun-Wei Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68262-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68262-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.499 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Artificial ionic diodes, inspired by biological ion channels, are typically realized by creating asymmetries in pore geometry or surface charge. Ferroelectric polarization, arising from the spontaneous alignment of electric dipoles within materials, provides an alternative strategy to achieve directional ion transport without additional geometry modification or surface functionalization. This work demonstrates that ultrathin freestanding ferroelectric crystalline bismuth ferrite symmetric-type single-nanopore membranes, with a thickness down to 30 nm, exhibit rectified ion currents driven by naturally spontaneous polarization. These nanopores exhibit reversible polarization switching with hysteretic ion current rectification in response to external pH stimuli, offering additional tunability in emulating the functions of biological ion channels. Furthermore, significant osmotic power generation is observed, enabled by current amplification through directional ion transport. These findings highlight the potential of utilizing ultrathin ferroelectric oxide membrane materials as ionic diodes with directional preferences and switchable polarizations for developing ionic circuits, mimicking biological membranes, and facilitating osmotic power conversion. Achieving directional ion transport in thin membranes is desirable yet challenging. Here, authors demonstrate an ultrathin ferroelectric single-pore membrane that enables polarization-driven ion rectification and hysteretic responses under pH stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>