<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 23:47:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Pb isotope and sequential extraction constraints on metal sources of Mississippi Valley−type Zn-Pb deposits in the Lanping fold-thrust belt, Eastern Himalayan-Tibetan orogen (Southwest China)</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38395.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38395.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 21:28:02 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Longlong Yue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yingchao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jianxiong Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aihua Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yueyue Kang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wang Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingjuan Liang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38395.1</prism:doi><description>Metals for Mississippi Valley−type Zn-Pb mineralization were previously considered to be leached from regional shallow sedimentary strata and basement rocks. However, determining the specific metal source is challenging because of the complex fluid interaction histories in Mississippi Valley−type ore fields. To better constrain their metal sources, we conducted a comprehensive study of the Lanping ore field of Southwest China. This ore field hosts the world-class Jinding Mississippi Valley−type deposit and Baiyangping Mississippi Valley−type ore district. The latter comprises numerous smaller deposits. All these deposits formed during the Cenozoic Era and are situated within the Cenozoic fold-thrust belt of the Eastern Himalayan-Tibetan orogenic belt. Sequential extraction of regional sedimentary strata (Permian to Eocene) targeted four fractions (carbonate, Fe-Mn oxide, organic and reductive, and residual silicate). This study, combined with leaching experiments on Triassic magmatic basement rocks and Cenozoic high-K plutons, demonstrates that magmatic rocks constitute the key metal sources, particularly through feldspar dissolution. Pb isotope data indicate that most fractions extracted from sedimentary rocks deviate from the linear Pb isotope trend observed in the Jinding sulfides. The lower intercept of this trend aligns with lower Cretaceous Jingxing Formation muddy siltstone, while the upper intercept extends to middle Triassic dacite K-feldspar. Model ages and linear mixing models indicate that Triassic felsic−mafic magmatic rocks were significant radiogenic Pb-bearing metal sources for Jinding, while lower Cretaceous siltstone or an end member 213 Ma or younger provided common Pb-bearing metals. The Pb isotopes of Baiyangping sulfides partially overlap with the gabbro, biotite monzogranite, and granite porphyry of Cenozoic high-K plutons and the Eocene Baoxiangsi Formation’s argillaceous fine sandstone fractions. These results indicate that the voluminous Triassic felsic−mafic rocks, which served as the basement for the entire Mesozoic Lanping Basin and rolled into the Cenozoic fold-thrust belt, have undergone large-scale fluid-rock reactions with the regional basin brines, providing a plentiful supply of Zn-Pb metals for regional Mississippi Valley−type deposits. In contrast, Cenozoic high-K plutons may intrude into more restricted spatial domains and might have undergone smaller-scale fluid-rock interactions, providing less Zn-Pb metals. This explains why a world-class Zn-Pb deposit formed at Jinding, while only small-scale Zn-Pb deposits developed at the Baiyangping ore district. This study illustrates that metal sources for Mississippi Valley−type Zn-Pb mineralization commonly display composite provenance characteristics, integrating contributions from sedimentary successions and basement rocks. In addition, it underscores the importance of metal release through interactions between fluids and magmatic rocks for the formation of large-scale Zn-Pb mineralization and demonstrates the utility of Pb isotope model ages in evaluating metal sources.
Published: 2026-01-06T21:28:02+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.602 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Longlong Yue; Yingchao Liu; Jianxiong Ma; Aihua Wang; Yueyue Kang; Wang Ma; Mingjuan Liang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38395.1"&gt;10.1130/b38395.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.602 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metals for Mississippi Valley−type Zn-Pb mineralization were previously considered to be leached from regional shallow sedimentary strata and basement rocks. However, determining the specific metal source is challenging because of the complex fluid interaction histories in Mississippi Valley−type ore fields. To better constrain their metal sources, we conducted a comprehensive study of the Lanping ore field of Southwest China. This ore field hosts the world-class Jinding Mississippi Valley−type deposit and Baiyangping Mississippi Valley−type ore district. The latter comprises numerous smaller deposits. All these deposits formed during the Cenozoic Era and are situated within the Cenozoic fold-thrust belt of the Eastern Himalayan-Tibetan orogenic belt. Sequential extraction of regional sedimentary strata (Permian to Eocene) targeted four fractions (carbonate, Fe-Mn oxide, organic and reductive, and residual silicate). This study, combined with leaching experiments on Triassic magmatic basement rocks and Cenozoic high-K plutons, demonstrates that magmatic rocks constitute the key metal sources, particularly through feldspar dissolution. Pb isotope data indicate that most fractions extracted from sedimentary rocks deviate from the linear Pb isotope trend observed in the Jinding sulfides. The lower intercept of this trend aligns with lower Cretaceous Jingxing Formation muddy siltstone, while the upper intercept extends to middle Triassic dacite K-feldspar. Model ages and linear mixing models indicate that Triassic felsic−mafic magmatic rocks were significant radiogenic Pb-bearing metal sources for Jinding, while lower Cretaceous siltstone or an end member 213 Ma or younger provided common Pb-bearing metals. The Pb isotopes of Baiyangping sulfides partially overlap with the gabbro, biotite monzogranite, and granite porphyry of Cenozoic high-K plutons and the Eocene Baoxiangsi Formation’s argillaceous fine sandstone fractions. These results indicate that the voluminous Triassic felsic−mafic rocks, which served as the basement for the entire Mesozoic Lanping Basin and rolled into the Cenozoic fold-thrust belt, have undergone large-scale fluid-rock reactions with the regional basin brines, providing a plentiful supply of Zn-Pb metals for regional Mississippi Valley−type deposits. In contrast, Cenozoic high-K plutons may intrude into more restricted spatial domains and might have undergone smaller-scale fluid-rock interactions, providing less Zn-Pb metals. This explains why a world-class Zn-Pb deposit formed at Jinding, while only small-scale Zn-Pb deposits developed at the Baiyangping ore district. This study illustrates that metal sources for Mississippi Valley−type Zn-Pb mineralization commonly display composite provenance characteristics, integrating contributions from sedimentary successions and basement rocks. In addition, it underscores the importance of metal release through interactions between fluids and magmatic rocks for the formation of large-scale Zn-Pb mineralization and demonstrates the utility of Pb isotope model ages in evaluating metal sources.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Fingerprinting fluctuations in auriferous fluid chemistry in pyrite zonation: Implications for ore-forming processes</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38578.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38578.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 21:28:02 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jia-Nan Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao-Cheng Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zi-Yue Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christof Kusebauch</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael Wiedenbeck</dc:creator><dc:creator>Richard Wirth</dc:creator><dc:creator>Franco Pirajno</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lingli Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia-Yi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peng-Cong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kun-Feng Qiu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38578.1</prism:doi><description>Gold can be hosted by pyrite in a multiplicity of hydrothermal ore systems, but the processes controlling the precipitation of Au and its incorporation into pyrite remain unclear. Here, we present a detailed petrographic, geochemical, and theoretical study of pyrite from the Liba gold deposit, China, using both trace element chemistry and sulfur isotopes. Gold-bearing pyrite grains from Liba record a compositional zonation including a Co-Ni−rich, an As-Au−poor core (Py-1), an As-rich mantle (Py-2), and finally an outmost rim (Py-3) enriched only in Co and Ni. An As-Au-Cu−rich thin zone (Py-2a) with numerous fine pores and arsenopyrite inclusions exists between Py-2 and Py-3. The range of sulfur isotopes is narrow, showing a gradually decreasing trend from Py-1 (mean = +9.57‰) to Py-1a (mean = +8.45‰), Py-2 (mean = +7.82‰), and Py-2a (mean = +6.82‰) and an increase in Py-3 (mean = +9.38‰), which is similar to Py-1. We interpret the periodic cycling of trace elements and sulfur isotopes as indicative of multiple, consecutive fluid-release events that tapped one single reservoir, which led to the formation of zoned pyrite. The elevated As and depleted S contents in Py-2 potentially indicate a change in sulfur fugacity, which would have led to a decreased solubility of Au in the hydrothermal fluid. Elemental variations from Py-2 to Py-2a (i.e., Au/Cu ratios ranging from 0.01 to 1) and the presence of pyrrhotite in Py-2a suggest that mineralization occurred under reducing conditions. Lower fO2 and fS2 would lead to gold supersaturation in the fluid, triggering Au precipitation in Py-2a. Additionally, coupled dissolution and reprecipitation reactions are found to play a role during the formation of key features observed in Liba pyrites (e.g., formation of porosity and inclusions), which promote fluid evolution. In addition, theoretical evaluation reveals that Cu incorporation may create conditions favorable for Au uptake into the pyrite structure, triggering As-Au-Cu enrichment in the rims. Our use of multiple scales of observation provides significant insights into the complex formation processes of mineralized hydrothermal systems.
Published: 2026-01-06T21:28:02+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.601 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jia-Nan Fu; Hao-Cheng Yu; Zi-Yue Gao; Christof Kusebauch; Xin Liu; Michael Wiedenbeck; Richard Wirth; Franco Pirajno; Lingli Zhou; Jia-Yi Wang; Peng-Cong Zhang; Kun-Feng Qiu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38578.1"&gt;10.1130/b38578.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.601 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gold can be hosted by pyrite in a multiplicity of hydrothermal ore systems, but the processes controlling the precipitation of Au and its incorporation into pyrite remain unclear. Here, we present a detailed petrographic, geochemical, and theoretical study of pyrite from the Liba gold deposit, China, using both trace element chemistry and sulfur isotopes. Gold-bearing pyrite grains from Liba record a compositional zonation including a Co-Ni−rich, an As-Au−poor core (Py-1), an As-rich mantle (Py-2), and finally an outmost rim (Py-3) enriched only in Co and Ni. An As-Au-Cu−rich thin zone (Py-2a) with numerous fine pores and arsenopyrite inclusions exists between Py-2 and Py-3. The range of sulfur isotopes is narrow, showing a gradually decreasing trend from Py-1 (mean = +9.57‰) to Py-1a (mean = +8.45‰), Py-2 (mean = +7.82‰), and Py-2a (mean = +6.82‰) and an increase in Py-3 (mean = +9.38‰), which is similar to Py-1. We interpret the periodic cycling of trace elements and sulfur isotopes as indicative of multiple, consecutive fluid-release events that tapped one single reservoir, which led to the formation of zoned pyrite. The elevated As and depleted S contents in Py-2 potentially indicate a change in sulfur fugacity, which would have led to a decreased solubility of Au in the hydrothermal fluid. Elemental variations from Py-2 to Py-2a (i.e., Au/Cu ratios ranging from 0.01 to 1) and the presence of pyrrhotite in Py-2a suggest that mineralization occurred under reducing conditions. Lower fO2 and fS2 would lead to gold supersaturation in the fluid, triggering Au precipitation in Py-2a. Additionally, coupled dissolution and reprecipitation reactions are found to play a role during the formation of key features observed in Liba pyrites (e.g., formation of porosity and inclusions), which promote fluid evolution. In addition, theoretical evaluation reveals that Cu incorporation may create conditions favorable for Au uptake into the pyrite structure, triggering As-Au-Cu enrichment in the rims. Our use of multiple scales of observation provides significant insights into the complex formation processes of mineralized hydrothermal systems.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Growth and deformation of apatite across metamorphic facies during collisional orogenesis</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02293-7</link><guid>10.1007/s00410-025-02293-7</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 13:36:58 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yanyan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhongbao Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wentao Cao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinxue Du</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zuolin Tian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul D. Bons</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuxuan Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaohong Mao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fenghua Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiyong Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haibing Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guocan Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s00410-025-02293-7</prism:doi><description>Apatite is a key accessory phase in metamorphic rocks, capable of recording mineral growth, deformation, and fluid-rock interaction across a wide range of metamorphic conditions. To evaluate the mechanisms of apatite growth and deformation, we present an integrated microstructural and geochemical study of apatite in high-pressure granulite- to lower amphibolite-facies rocks from the Eastern Himalayan Syntaxis, Tibetan Plateau. Cathodoluminescence imaging, electron backscatter diffraction, electron probe microanalysis, and in situ laser ablation inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry trace element data were combined to assess apatite growth histories and post-crystallization modifications. In high-pressure granulite-facies samples, apatite grains display strong shape-preferred orientation (SPO) and significant intragranular deformation but lack a crystallographic preferred orientation (CPO), consistent with pre-peak metamorphism growth and experienced peak metamorphic conditions. Medium-pressure granulite-facies apatite shows oscillatory zoning, weak SPO and CPO, and limited deformation, indicating post-tectonic growth from compositionally homogeneous fluids. Apatite from upper amphibolite-facies samples preserves both strong SPO and CPO, with only minor deformation features, suggesting syn-tectonic crystallization during foliation development. In lower amphibolite-facies rocks, apatite is characterized by core-mantle structures, weak SPO, but CPO subparallel to stretching lineation, and variable trace element patterns, consistent with episodic growth during fluid-mediated dissolution–precipitation under retrograde conditions. Systematic variations in apatite chemistry—including decreasing Sr/Y, ΣLREE, and (La/Yb)N, and increasing Th/U and F/Cl with decreasing metamorphic grade—reflect the influence of metamorphic fluid composition, mineral reaction pathways, and elemental partition among mineral phases at corresponding metamorphic conditions. Despite differences in deformation and growth history, consistent correlations between texture and composition suggest localized, short-range fluid-mediated element redistribution. Our results demonstrate that multiple generations of apatite can be distinguished through integrated microstructural and geochemical datasets, providing a robust archive of pressure–temperature (P–T) conditions and fluid evolution in metamorphic terranes.
Published: 2026-01-06T13:36:58+00:00
Venue: Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology
Score: 0.596 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yanyan Zhang; Zhongbao Zhao; Wentao Cao; Jinxue Du; Zuolin Tian; Paul D. Bons; Xuxuan Ma; Xiaohong Mao; Fenghua Liang; Zhiyong Zhu; Haibing Li; Guocan Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Contributions to Mineralogy and Petrology&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00410-025-02293-7"&gt;10.1007/s00410-025-02293-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.596 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apatite is a key accessory phase in metamorphic rocks, capable of recording mineral growth, deformation, and fluid-rock interaction across a wide range of metamorphic conditions. To evaluate the mechanisms of apatite growth and deformation, we present an integrated microstructural and geochemical study of apatite in high-pressure granulite- to lower amphibolite-facies rocks from the Eastern Himalayan Syntaxis, Tibetan Plateau. Cathodoluminescence imaging, electron backscatter diffraction, electron probe microanalysis, and in situ laser ablation inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry trace element data were combined to assess apatite growth histories and post-crystallization modifications. In high-pressure granulite-facies samples, apatite grains display strong shape-preferred orientation (SPO) and significant intragranular deformation but lack a crystallographic preferred orientation (CPO), consistent with pre-peak metamorphism growth and experienced peak metamorphic conditions. Medium-pressure granulite-facies apatite shows oscillatory zoning, weak SPO and CPO, and limited deformation, indicating post-tectonic growth from compositionally homogeneous fluids. Apatite from upper amphibolite-facies samples preserves both strong SPO and CPO, with only minor deformation features, suggesting syn-tectonic crystallization during foliation development. In lower amphibolite-facies rocks, apatite is characterized by core-mantle structures, weak SPO, but CPO subparallel to stretching lineation, and variable trace element patterns, consistent with episodic growth during fluid-mediated dissolution–precipitation under retrograde conditions. Systematic variations in apatite chemistry—including decreasing Sr/Y, ΣLREE, and (La/Yb)N, and increasing Th/U and F/Cl with decreasing metamorphic grade—reflect the influence of metamorphic fluid composition, mineral reaction pathways, and elemental partition among mineral phases at corresponding metamorphic conditions. Despite differences in deformation and growth history, consistent correlations between texture and composition suggest localized, short-range fluid-mediated element redistribution. Our results demonstrate that multiple generations of apatite can be distinguished through integrated microstructural and geochemical datasets, providing a robust archive of pressure–temperature (P–T) conditions and fluid evolution in metamorphic terranes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Periodic ocean oxygenation events during the mid-Ediacaran</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01883-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41561-025-01883-1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 09:02:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zi-Heng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhong-Qiang Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stuart J. Daines</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feifei Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Timothy M. Lenton</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Geoscience</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41561-025-01883-1</prism:doi><description>The Ediacaran Gaskiers Glaciation (579.78–579.44 million years ago) is the last major climatic event of the Neoproterozoic, but the contemporaneous ocean redox conditions remain unclear. Here we conducted carbon–uranium–sulfur isotopic (δ13Ccarb–δ238Ucarb–δ34SCAS) and elemental analyses on marine carbonate samples from the glacial-to-deglacial succession (equivalent to the Gaskiers Glaciation successions) of the Egan Formation in northwestern Australia. Negative δ13Ccarb and positive δ238Ucarb excursions paired with δ34SCAS and cerium anomaly profiles reveal an extensive ocean oxygenation event. The Gaskiers ocean oxygenation event is the middle of three such transient mid-Ediacaran events, occurring roughly 5 million years apart. Using a model for the coupled biogeochemical cycles of phosphorus, oxygen and carbon, we show that these periodic ocean oxygenation events, associated δ238Ucarb variations and part of the δ13Ccarb variation can be explained by a self-sustaining oscillation in the Earth system. An increase in the organic carbon burial flux plausibly linked to eukaryote evolution at the time could have tipped the Earth system from a stable anoxic ocean regime to an unstable oscillatory regime. A later further increase in organic carbon burial flux could have tipped the system into a stable, modern-like oxic ocean regime. Periodic marine oxygen oscillations occurred throughout the middle Ediacaran Gaskiers Glaciation, probably stemming from increased organic carbon burial destabilizing ocean redox systems, according to geochemical constraints and modelling.
Published: 2026-01-06T09:02:23+00:00
Venue: Nature Geoscience
Score: 0.591 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zi-Heng Li; Zhong-Qiang Chen; Stuart J. Daines; Feifei Zhang; Timothy M. Lenton&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Geoscience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01883-1"&gt;10.1038/s41561-025-01883-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.591 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ediacaran Gaskiers Glaciation (579.78–579.44 million years ago) is the last major climatic event of the Neoproterozoic, but the contemporaneous ocean redox conditions remain unclear. Here we conducted carbon–uranium–sulfur isotopic (δ13Ccarb–δ238Ucarb–δ34SCAS) and elemental analyses on marine carbonate samples from the glacial-to-deglacial succession (equivalent to the Gaskiers Glaciation successions) of the Egan Formation in northwestern Australia. Negative δ13Ccarb and positive δ238Ucarb excursions paired with δ34SCAS and cerium anomaly profiles reveal an extensive ocean oxygenation event. The Gaskiers ocean oxygenation event is the middle of three such transient mid-Ediacaran events, occurring roughly 5 million years apart. Using a model for the coupled biogeochemical cycles of phosphorus, oxygen and carbon, we show that these periodic ocean oxygenation events, associated δ238Ucarb variations and part of the δ13Ccarb variation can be explained by a self-sustaining oscillation in the Earth system. An increase in the organic carbon burial flux plausibly linked to eukaryote evolution at the time could have tipped the Earth system from a stable anoxic ocean regime to an unstable oscillatory regime. A later further increase in organic carbon burial flux could have tipped the system into a stable, modern-like oxic ocean regime. Periodic marine oxygen oscillations occurred throughout the middle Ediacaran Gaskiers Glaciation, probably stemming from increased organic carbon burial destabilizing ocean redox systems, according to geochemical constraints and modelling.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Towards fibre-like loss for photonic integration from violet to near-infrared</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09889-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09889-w</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:01:44 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hao-Jing Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kellan Colburn</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peng Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongrui Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanfei Hou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinhao Ge</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jin-Yu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Phineas Lehan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qing-Xin Ji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiquan Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dirk Bouwmeester</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher Holmes</dc:creator><dc:creator>James Gates</dc:creator><dc:creator>Henry Blauvelt</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kerry Vahala</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09889-w</prism:doi><description>Over the past decades, remarkable progress has been made in reducing the loss of photonic integrated circuits (PICs) within the telecom band1–4, facilitating on-chip applications spanning low-noise optical5 and microwave synthesis6, to lidar7 and photonic artificial intelligence engines8. However, several obstacles arise from the marked increase in material absorption and scattering losses at shorter wavelengths9,10, which prominently elevate power requirements and limit performance in the visible and near-visible spectrum. Here we present an ultralow-loss PIC platform based on germano-silicate—the material underlying the extraordinary performance of optical fibre—but realized by a fully CMOS-foundry-compatible process. These PICs achieve resonator Q factors surpassing 180 million from violet to telecom wavelengths. They also attain a 10-dB higher quality factor without thermal treatment in the telecom band, expanding opportunities for heterogeneous integration with active components11. Other features of this platform include readily engineered waveguide dispersion, acoustic mode confinement and large-mode-area-induced thermal stability—each demonstrated by soliton microcomb generation, stimulated Brillouin lasing and low-frequency-noise self-injection locking, respectively. The success of these germano-silicate PICs can ultimately enable fibre-like loss onto a chip, leading to an additional 20-dB improvement in waveguide loss over the current highest performance photonic platforms. Moreover, the performance abilities demonstrated here bridge ultralow-loss PIC technology to optical clocks12, precision navigation systems13 and quantum sensors14. Germano-silicate used as a building material for integrated photonics circuits substantially reduces optical losses, approaching levels comparable to those in optical fibres.
Published: 2026-01-07T16:01:44+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.585 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hao-Jing Chen; Kellan Colburn; Peng Liu; Hongrui Yan; Hanfei Hou; Jinhao Ge; Jin-Yu Liu; Phineas Lehan; Qing-Xin Ji; Zhiquan Yuan; Dirk Bouwmeester; Christopher Holmes; James Gates; Henry Blauvelt; Kerry Vahala&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09889-w"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09889-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.585 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the past decades, remarkable progress has been made in reducing the loss of photonic integrated circuits (PICs) within the telecom band1–4, facilitating on-chip applications spanning low-noise optical5 and microwave synthesis6, to lidar7 and photonic artificial intelligence engines8. However, several obstacles arise from the marked increase in material absorption and scattering losses at shorter wavelengths9,10, which prominently elevate power requirements and limit performance in the visible and near-visible spectrum. Here we present an ultralow-loss PIC platform based on germano-silicate—the material underlying the extraordinary performance of optical fibre—but realized by a fully CMOS-foundry-compatible process. These PICs achieve resonator Q factors surpassing 180 million from violet to telecom wavelengths. They also attain a 10-dB higher quality factor without thermal treatment in the telecom band, expanding opportunities for heterogeneous integration with active components11. Other features of this platform include readily engineered waveguide dispersion, acoustic mode confinement and large-mode-area-induced thermal stability—each demonstrated by soliton microcomb generation, stimulated Brillouin lasing and low-frequency-noise self-injection locking, respectively. The success of these germano-silicate PICs can ultimately enable fibre-like loss onto a chip, leading to an additional 20-dB improvement in waveguide loss over the current highest performance photonic platforms. Moreover, the performance abilities demonstrated here bridge ultralow-loss PIC technology to optical clocks12, precision navigation systems13 and quantum sensors14. Germano-silicate used as a building material for integrated photonics circuits substantially reduces optical losses, approaching levels comparable to those in optical fibres.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Petrogenesis and tectonic implications of Paleoproterozoic mafic dikes in the southeastern North China Craton</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38622.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38622.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 21:27:50 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yayun Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christoph Beier</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tong Qu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haiyi Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Linyi Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Deng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38622.1</prism:doi><description>Mafic dikes in cratonic regions record extensional tectonic processes within the continental lithosphere and thus provide key insights into mantle−crust interaction and deep-mantle geodynamics at regional to global scales. The tectonic setting of the Jiao-Liao-Ji belt in the eastern North China Craton remains debated due to multistage Precambrian overprinting, but resolving this issue is critical for reconstructing the North China Craton’s Precambrian evolution and its role in the Columbia supercontinent. Here, we report new laser ablation−inductively coupled plasma−mass spectrometry (LA-ICP-MS) U-Pb ages of 1.86−1.82 Ga (zircon) and 1.89−1.86 Ga (titanite), together with geochemical data, for mafic dikes intruding Neoarchean−Paleoproterozoic strata of the Jiaodong Terrane in the southern Jiao-Liao-Ji belt. The dikes display moderate light rare earth element enrichment, low Nb/La ratios, and variable εNd(t) values (−8.99 to +5.89). Based on trace-element systematics and intrusion ages, the dikes can be divided into two groups. Group I dikes (ca. 1.86 Ga) show higher Mg# and Nb/La ratios, lower Th/Nb and (La/Yb)N values, and more positive εNd(t) values (up to +5.89) than Group II dikes (ca. 1.82 Ga). Both groups were derived from a metasomatized subcontinental lithospheric mantle (SCLM), but their contrasting geochemical signatures reflect preexisting mantle heterogeneity, involving both depleted and enriched SCLM domains and variable melting degrees. Together with coeval A-type granites, alkaline rocks, and associated carbonate-clastic assemblages, the mafic dikes point to an intracontinental rift setting. These results suggest that the Jiao-Liao-Ji belt underwent intracontinental extension during the Paleoproterozoic, likely linked to the collapse of the Trans−North China orogen and the initial breakup of the Columbia supercontinent.
Published: 2026-01-06T21:27:50+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.582 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yayun Liang; Christoph Beier; Tong Qu; Haiyi Wang; Linyi Li; Hao Yan; Jun Deng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38622.1"&gt;10.1130/b38622.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.582 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mafic dikes in cratonic regions record extensional tectonic processes within the continental lithosphere and thus provide key insights into mantle−crust interaction and deep-mantle geodynamics at regional to global scales. The tectonic setting of the Jiao-Liao-Ji belt in the eastern North China Craton remains debated due to multistage Precambrian overprinting, but resolving this issue is critical for reconstructing the North China Craton’s Precambrian evolution and its role in the Columbia supercontinent. Here, we report new laser ablation−inductively coupled plasma−mass spectrometry (LA-ICP-MS) U-Pb ages of 1.86−1.82 Ga (zircon) and 1.89−1.86 Ga (titanite), together with geochemical data, for mafic dikes intruding Neoarchean−Paleoproterozoic strata of the Jiaodong Terrane in the southern Jiao-Liao-Ji belt. The dikes display moderate light rare earth element enrichment, low Nb/La ratios, and variable εNd(t) values (−8.99 to +5.89). Based on trace-element systematics and intrusion ages, the dikes can be divided into two groups. Group I dikes (ca. 1.86 Ga) show higher Mg# and Nb/La ratios, lower Th/Nb and (La/Yb)N values, and more positive εNd(t) values (up to +5.89) than Group II dikes (ca. 1.82 Ga). Both groups were derived from a metasomatized subcontinental lithospheric mantle (SCLM), but their contrasting geochemical signatures reflect preexisting mantle heterogeneity, involving both depleted and enriched SCLM domains and variable melting degrees. Together with coeval A-type granites, alkaline rocks, and associated carbonate-clastic assemblages, the mafic dikes point to an intracontinental rift setting. These results suggest that the Jiao-Liao-Ji belt underwent intracontinental extension during the Paleoproterozoic, likely linked to the collapse of the Trans−North China orogen and the initial breakup of the Columbia supercontinent.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>High H2 production in sediment-hosted hydrothermal fluids at an ultraslow spreading mid-ocean ridge</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02962-2</link><guid>10.1038/s43247-025-02962-2</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 12:29:48 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Alexander Diehl</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eirini Anagnostou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Patrick Monien</dc:creator><dc:creator>Thomas Pape</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eva-Maria Meckel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Miriam Römer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Leila Mezri</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wolfgang Bach</dc:creator><dc:creator>Donata Monien</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christian Hansen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Aaron Röhler</dc:creator><dc:creator>Katharina Streuff</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sabina Strmic Palinkas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yann Marcon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ines Barrenechea Angeles</dc:creator><dc:creator>Charlotte Kleint</dc:creator><dc:creator>Stig‑Morten Knutsen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gerhard Bohrmann</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s43247-025-02962-2</prism:doi><description>Abstract Hydrothermal systems at ultraslow-spreading mid-ocean ridges remain poorly characterized, particularly where sedimentary and ultramafic influences intersect. Here we present geochemical analyses of vent fluids collected in 2024 from the Jøtul hydrothermal field on the northern Knipovich Ridge. Major element concentrations, dissolved gases, and thermodynamic modeling are used to investigate fluid-rock interactions. The fluids exhibit exceptionally high CH 4 concentrations, that exceed those at the Guaymas Basin, and display characteristics typical of sediment-hosted hydrothermal systems, indicating thermal decomposition of organic matter in clastic sediments. In contrast, high H 2 (&gt;15 mM) and low H 2 S concentrations are more typical of ultramafic-hosted fluids, while geological evidence indicates that the vent field lies atop a detachment fault. Thermodynamic modeling suggests that these high H 2 /H 2 S ratios may result solely from degradation of organic matter followed by abiotic CH 4 oxidation at ~400 °C, rather than from reactions with ultramafic rocks. These results expand the known diversity of sediment-hosted vent fluid compositions and highlight fluid-sediment interaction as an underestimated source of carbon and hydrogen.
Published: 2026-01-06T12:29:48+00:00
Venue: Communications Earth &amp;amp; Environment
Score: 0.576 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Alexander Diehl; Eirini Anagnostou; Patrick Monien; Thomas Pape; Eva-Maria Meckel; Miriam Römer; Leila Mezri; Wolfgang Bach; Donata Monien; Christian Hansen; Aaron Röhler; Katharina Streuff; Sabina Strmic Palinkas; Yann Marcon; Ines Barrenechea Angeles; Charlotte Kleint; Stig‑Morten Knutsen; Gerhard Bohrmann&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Communications Earth &amp;amp;amp; Environment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s43247-025-02962-2"&gt;10.1038/s43247-025-02962-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.576 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Hydrothermal systems at ultraslow-spreading mid-ocean ridges remain poorly characterized, particularly where sedimentary and ultramafic influences intersect. Here we present geochemical analyses of vent fluids collected in 2024 from the Jøtul hydrothermal field on the northern Knipovich Ridge. Major element concentrations, dissolved gases, and thermodynamic modeling are used to investigate fluid-rock interactions. The fluids exhibit exceptionally high CH 4 concentrations, that exceed those at the Guaymas Basin, and display characteristics typical of sediment-hosted hydrothermal systems, indicating thermal decomposition of organic matter in clastic sediments. In contrast, high H 2 (&amp;gt;15 mM) and low H 2 S concentrations are more typical of ultramafic-hosted fluids, while geological evidence indicates that the vent field lies atop a detachment fault. Thermodynamic modeling suggests that these high H 2 /H 2 S ratios may result solely from degradation of organic matter followed by abiotic CH 4 oxidation at ~400 °C, rather than from reactions with ultramafic rocks. These results expand the known diversity of sediment-hosted vent fluid compositions and highlight fluid-sediment interaction as an underestimated source of carbon and hydrogen.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Oligocene deep ocean oxygen isotope variations primarily driven by temperature</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01878-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41561-025-01878-y</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 10:03:16 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Flavia Boscolo-Galazzo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Victoria E. Taylor</dc:creator><dc:creator>Eirik V. Galaasen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Diederik Liebrand</dc:creator><dc:creator>Edward Gasson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Edoardo Dallanave</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alvaro Fernandez-Bremer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jakub Witkowski</dc:creator><dc:creator>Steve M. Bohaty</dc:creator><dc:creator>A. Nele Meckler</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Geoscience</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41561-025-01878-y</prism:doi><description>Abstract Our understanding of the long-term behaviour of global climate and the Antarctic ice sheet relies heavily on the oxygen isotopic composition of marine calcite (δ 18 O calcite ), which reflects a combination of ocean temperature and the amount of water stored in ice sheets. On the basis of δ 18 O calcite , the Antarctic ice sheet has been interpreted as extremely dynamic in the Oligocene, 34–23 million years ago. Yet, the proposed continental-scale ice volume changes are challenging to reproduce with models and may be overestimated owing to a larger influence of temperature on the deep-sea δ 18 O calcite than previously assumed. Here we present the first Oligocene record of orbital variability in deep ocean temperature based on benthic foraminiferal clumped isotope thermometry, a method affected only by temperature and independent of seawater chemistry. We find large, eccentricity-paced temperature variations of up to 4 °C, sufficient to explain the δ 18 O calcite cycles without requiring continental-scale ice volume changes. This finding is consistent with the simulated stability of the Antarctic ice sheet, highlighting the importance of robust independent temperature reconstructions. Our results show that the temperature in the deep Southern Ocean, and possibly globally, is highly sensitive to the seasonal distribution of insolation in an Oligocene-like climate state warmer than today.
Published: 2026-01-07T10:03:16+00:00
Venue: Nature Geoscience
Score: 0.559 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Flavia Boscolo-Galazzo; Victoria E. Taylor; Eirik V. Galaasen; Diederik Liebrand; Edward Gasson; Edoardo Dallanave; Alvaro Fernandez-Bremer; Jakub Witkowski; Steve M. Bohaty; A. Nele Meckler&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Geoscience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01878-y"&gt;10.1038/s41561-025-01878-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.559 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Our understanding of the long-term behaviour of global climate and the Antarctic ice sheet relies heavily on the oxygen isotopic composition of marine calcite (δ 18 O calcite ), which reflects a combination of ocean temperature and the amount of water stored in ice sheets. On the basis of δ 18 O calcite , the Antarctic ice sheet has been interpreted as extremely dynamic in the Oligocene, 34–23 million years ago. Yet, the proposed continental-scale ice volume changes are challenging to reproduce with models and may be overestimated owing to a larger influence of temperature on the deep-sea δ 18 O calcite than previously assumed. Here we present the first Oligocene record of orbital variability in deep ocean temperature based on benthic foraminiferal clumped isotope thermometry, a method affected only by temperature and independent of seawater chemistry. We find large, eccentricity-paced temperature variations of up to 4 °C, sufficient to explain the δ 18 O calcite cycles without requiring continental-scale ice volume changes. This finding is consistent with the simulated stability of the Antarctic ice sheet, highlighting the importance of robust independent temperature reconstructions. Our results show that the temperature in the deep Southern Ocean, and possibly globally, is highly sensitive to the seasonal distribution of insolation in an Oligocene-like climate state warmer than today.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Integrated millimeter-wave cavity electro-optic transduction</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67932-w</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67932-w</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 22:36:14 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Kevin K. S. Multani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jason F. Herrmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emilio A. Nanni</dc:creator><dc:creator>Amir H. Safavi-Naeini</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67932-w</prism:doi><description>Abstract Emerging communications and computing technologies will rely ever-more on expanding the useful radio frequency spectrum into the millimeter-wave and terahertz frequency range. Both classical and quantum applications would benefit from advancing integration and incorporation of millimeter-wave and electro-optic technologies into common devices, such as modulators. Here we demonstrate an integrated triply-resonant, superconducting electro-optic transducer. Our design incorporates an on-chip 107 GHz niobium titanium nitride superconducting resonator, modulating a thin-film lithium niobate optical racetrack resonator operating at telecom wavelengths. We observe a maximum photon transduction efficiency of η OE ≈ 0.82 × 10 −6 and an average single-photon electro-optic interaction rate of g 0 /2 π ≈ 0.7 kHz. We also present a study and analysis of the challenges associated with the design of integrated millimeter-wave resonators and propose possible solutions to these challenges. Our work paves the way for further advancements in resonant electro-optic technologies operating at millimeter-wave frequencies.
Published: 2026-01-06T22:36:14+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.555 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Kevin K. S. Multani; Jason F. Herrmann; Emilio A. Nanni; Amir H. Safavi-Naeini&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67932-w"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67932-w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.555 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Emerging communications and computing technologies will rely ever-more on expanding the useful radio frequency spectrum into the millimeter-wave and terahertz frequency range. Both classical and quantum applications would benefit from advancing integration and incorporation of millimeter-wave and electro-optic technologies into common devices, such as modulators. Here we demonstrate an integrated triply-resonant, superconducting electro-optic transducer. Our design incorporates an on-chip 107 GHz niobium titanium nitride superconducting resonator, modulating a thin-film lithium niobate optical racetrack resonator operating at telecom wavelengths. We observe a maximum photon transduction efficiency of η OE ≈ 0.82 × 10 −6 and an average single-photon electro-optic interaction rate of g 0 /2 π ≈ 0.7 kHz. We also present a study and analysis of the challenges associated with the design of integrated millimeter-wave resonators and propose possible solutions to these challenges. Our work paves the way for further advancements in resonant electro-optic technologies operating at millimeter-wave frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Reconfigurable all-solid-state topological lasing at arbitrary sites</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68173-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68173-7</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 23:04:32 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Bo Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinting Ding</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenchao Yan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuechen Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Haohai Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiang Ni</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Chen</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68173-7</prism:doi><description>Topological lasers have emerged as a promising platform for robust photonic systems, yet current implementations relying on semiconductor microcavities and resonators suffer from fundamental constraints including low optical gain, limited output power and fixed lasing sites. To address these challenges, we present an all-solid-state, reconfigurable topological laser based on a Su-Schrieffer-Heeger waveguide array platform, fabricated in disordered laser crystal (Nd:BaLaGa3O7). Harnessing the high gain provided by solid-state lasers, we experimentally and theoretically demonstrate single-mode, continuous-wave topological lasing with output power surpassing 100 mW. In addition to conventional topological edge lasing, we observe topological lasing at trivial lattice terminations and reconfigurable interface sites at arbitrary lattice positions. This unconventional behavior arises from the non-Hermitian parity-time symmetry transition in subsystem at elevated pump power. Our work demonstrates on-demand, site-selectable topological lasing, offering both fundamental insights into topological phase transitions in non-Hermitian systems and practical opportunities to develop robust, reconfigurable topological photonic devices for advanced lasing and optical information processing. Topological lasers usually emit light from a fixed spot. Here, authors report on an all-solid-state platform where topological lasing is demonstrated at trivial lattice terminations as well as at reconfigurable arbitrary sites. The device consists of a Su-Schrieffer-Heeger waveguide array, printed in a disordered Nd:BaLaGa₃O₇ crystal.
Published: 2026-01-06T23:04:32+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.552 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Bo Wu; Jinting Ding; Wenchao Yan; Yuechen Jia; Haohai Yu; Xiang Ni; Feng Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68173-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68173-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.552 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topological lasers have emerged as a promising platform for robust photonic systems, yet current implementations relying on semiconductor microcavities and resonators suffer from fundamental constraints including low optical gain, limited output power and fixed lasing sites. To address these challenges, we present an all-solid-state, reconfigurable topological laser based on a Su-Schrieffer-Heeger waveguide array platform, fabricated in disordered laser crystal (Nd:BaLaGa3O7). Harnessing the high gain provided by solid-state lasers, we experimentally and theoretically demonstrate single-mode, continuous-wave topological lasing with output power surpassing 100 mW. In addition to conventional topological edge lasing, we observe topological lasing at trivial lattice terminations and reconfigurable interface sites at arbitrary lattice positions. This unconventional behavior arises from the non-Hermitian parity-time symmetry transition in subsystem at elevated pump power. Our work demonstrates on-demand, site-selectable topological lasing, offering both fundamental insights into topological phase transitions in non-Hermitian systems and practical opportunities to develop robust, reconfigurable topological photonic devices for advanced lasing and optical information processing. Topological lasers usually emit light from a fixed spot. Here, authors report on an all-solid-state platform where topological lasing is demonstrated at trivial lattice terminations as well as at reconfigurable arbitrary sites. The device consists of a Su-Schrieffer-Heeger waveguide array, printed in a disordered Nd:BaLaGa₃O₇ crystal.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Dynamic oxygen vacancy engineering on CuO via refreshable catalytic surface for high-efficient water decontamination</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68180-8</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68180-8</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:24:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xinyi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liangjie Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jian Wei</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhuang Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinyao Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lijie Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huazhang Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yonghui Song</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68180-8</prism:doi><description>Oxygen vacancies (Ov) on metal oxide surfaces exhibit high catalytic activity for activating peroxymonosulfate (PMS) in wastewater decontamination, yet their in-situ regeneration remains a significant challenge. This study successfully achieves in-situ real-time regeneration of Ov on CuO surfaces through simple alkali etching without interrupting the contaminant removal process. The surface hydroxyl groups introduced by alkali treatment significantly reduce the formation energy of Ov on CuO surfaces from 1.60 eV to 0.38 eV. Both experimental results and density functional theory calculations reveal that the high activity of CuO relies on the synergy of surface hydroxyl groups and Ov. This synergy increases the antibonding states below the Fermi level and the electron spin density of Cu near Ov, thereby promoting electron transfer from CuO to PMS. As a result, by just adding an equimolar amount of alkali relative to PMS in CuO/PMS system, the degradation rate constant of sulfamethoxazole (SMX) greatly increases by 42 times. The primary reactive oxygen species in this system are sulfate radicals and hydroxyl radicals. Furthermore, OH-/CuO/PMS system exhibits a long-term stability (&amp;gt; 300 h) for SMX removal in a real water matrix. This work provides a highly executable method to in-situ real-time regenerate Ov on CuO surfaces, representing significant progress in the critical yet underappreciated field of catalyst regeneration. This study demonstrates that simple alkali etching enables in-situ regeneration of oxygen vacancies on CuO, enhancing peroxymonosulfate activation for efficient pollutant degradation with a 42-fold increase and long-term stability.
Published: 2026-01-07T18:24:55+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.548 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xinyi Zhang; Liangjie Wang; Jian Wei; Zhuang Guo; Xinyao Liu; Lijie Duan; Huazhang Zhao; Yonghui Song&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68180-8"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68180-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.548 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oxygen vacancies (Ov) on metal oxide surfaces exhibit high catalytic activity for activating peroxymonosulfate (PMS) in wastewater decontamination, yet their in-situ regeneration remains a significant challenge. This study successfully achieves in-situ real-time regeneration of Ov on CuO surfaces through simple alkali etching without interrupting the contaminant removal process. The surface hydroxyl groups introduced by alkali treatment significantly reduce the formation energy of Ov on CuO surfaces from 1.60 eV to 0.38 eV. Both experimental results and density functional theory calculations reveal that the high activity of CuO relies on the synergy of surface hydroxyl groups and Ov. This synergy increases the antibonding states below the Fermi level and the electron spin density of Cu near Ov, thereby promoting electron transfer from CuO to PMS. As a result, by just adding an equimolar amount of alkali relative to PMS in CuO/PMS system, the degradation rate constant of sulfamethoxazole (SMX) greatly increases by 42 times. The primary reactive oxygen species in this system are sulfate radicals and hydroxyl radicals. Furthermore, OH-/CuO/PMS system exhibits a long-term stability (&amp;amp;gt; 300 h) for SMX removal in a real water matrix. This work provides a highly executable method to in-situ real-time regenerate Ov on CuO surfaces, representing significant progress in the critical yet underappreciated field of catalyst regeneration. This study demonstrates that simple alkali etching enables in-situ regeneration of oxygen vacancies on CuO, enhancing peroxymonosulfate activation for efficient pollutant degradation with a 42-fold increase and long-term stability.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Little to no active faulting likely at Europa’s seafloor today</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67151-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67151-3</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 16:01:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Paul K. Byrne</dc:creator><dc:creator>Henry G. Dawson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christian Klimczak</dc:creator><dc:creator>Paul V. Regensburger</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kelsey T. Crane</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jeffrey G. Catalano</dc:creator><dc:creator>Catherine M. Elder</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bradford J. Foley</dc:creator><dc:creator>Christopher R. German</dc:creator><dc:creator>Austin P. Green</dc:creator><dc:creator>Douglas J. Hemingway</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mohit Melwani Daswani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mark P. Panning</dc:creator><dc:creator>Noah Randolph-Flagg</dc:creator><dc:creator>Barbara Sherwood Lollar</dc:creator><dc:creator>Philip Skemer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Steven D. Vance</dc:creator><dc:creator>Douglas A. Wiens</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67151-3</prism:doi><description>Many of the outer Solar System’s icy satellites feature known or suspected subsurface oceans, at least some of which are likely situated atop rocky interiors. Water–rock interactions at and beneath these seafloors might support active chemoautotrophic habitats, with subseafloor fluid flow facilitated by active faulting and hydrothermal systems. Absent such phenomena, however, any attainment of chemical equilibrium between the seafloor and ocean might limit the availability of chemical energy for life. Here, we characterise the stress state of the seafloor of Jupiter’s moon Europa, and thus the prospect for fracturing and associated sub-seafloor fluid flow there. We consider stresses from tidal forcing, global contraction, mantle convection, and serpentinisation. We find that none of these mechanisms is likely able to drive slip along even weak, pre-existing fractures in the present. Ocean water–rock reactions taking place today are therefore probably restricted to fluid flow through only the upper few hundred metres of the seafloor. Any processes able to sustain habitable conditions at the Europan seafloor today must therefore be independent of ongoing tectonic activity. In this study, the authors model the current mechanical properties of the seafloor of Jupiter’s icy moon Europa, and find those rocks to be too strong to allow the kind of fracturing that, on Earth, enables rock–water chemical reactions on which chemosynthetic life relies.
Published: 2026-01-06T16:01:31+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.546 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Paul K. Byrne; Henry G. Dawson; Christian Klimczak; Paul V. Regensburger; Kelsey T. Crane; Jeffrey G. Catalano; Catherine M. Elder; Bradford J. Foley; Christopher R. German; Austin P. Green; Douglas J. Hemingway; Mohit Melwani Daswani; Mark P. Panning; Noah Randolph-Flagg; Barbara Sherwood Lollar; Philip Skemer; Steven D. Vance; Douglas A. Wiens&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67151-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67151-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.546 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the outer Solar System’s icy satellites feature known or suspected subsurface oceans, at least some of which are likely situated atop rocky interiors. Water–rock interactions at and beneath these seafloors might support active chemoautotrophic habitats, with subseafloor fluid flow facilitated by active faulting and hydrothermal systems. Absent such phenomena, however, any attainment of chemical equilibrium between the seafloor and ocean might limit the availability of chemical energy for life. Here, we characterise the stress state of the seafloor of Jupiter’s moon Europa, and thus the prospect for fracturing and associated sub-seafloor fluid flow there. We consider stresses from tidal forcing, global contraction, mantle convection, and serpentinisation. We find that none of these mechanisms is likely able to drive slip along even weak, pre-existing fractures in the present. Ocean water–rock reactions taking place today are therefore probably restricted to fluid flow through only the upper few hundred metres of the seafloor. Any processes able to sustain habitable conditions at the Europan seafloor today must therefore be independent of ongoing tectonic activity. In this study, the authors model the current mechanical properties of the seafloor of Jupiter’s icy moon Europa, and find those rocks to be too strong to allow the kind of fracturing that, on Earth, enables rock–water chemical reactions on which chemosynthetic life relies.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>High normal stress promoted supershear rupture during the 2023 Mw 7.8 Kahramanmaraş earthquake</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01893-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41561-025-01893-z</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 10:02:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jing Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mijian Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yiming Bai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shucheng Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao Xiao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shijie Hao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Masaru Nagaso</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hongfeng Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ping Tong</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Geoscience</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41561-025-01893-z</prism:doi><description>On 6 February 2023, two major earthquakes with moment magnitude (Mw) of 7.8 and 7.6 ruptured multiple segments of the Eastern Anatolian Fault system, resulting in many casualties and extensive property damage in Turkey and Syria. The Mw 7.8 earthquake involved bilateral rupture along the Eastern Anatolian Fault, with at least partially supershear rupture towards the northeast and subshear rupture towards the southwest. The cause of this difference in rupture speed remains debated. Here we present evidence from seismic tomographic imaging linking this difference to structural and stress variations along the fault. Specifically, a low-velocity anomaly and a fault-parallel fast velocity direction of anisotropy in the southwest Amanos–Pazarcık segment suggest fluid infiltration, which could facilitate fault creep and reduce the stress loading rate. By contrast, the Erkenek segment to the northeast is associated with a high-velocity anomaly and fault-normal fast velocity direction, suggesting limited fluid infiltration and increased stress accumulation. Hence, we propose that the contrast in stress accumulation explains the discrepancy in rupture speeds in this earthquake and that fault structure in addition to stress loading may influence stress accumulation and thus whether a fault ruptures at supershear speeds. The difference in rupture speed between fault segments in the 2023 Mw 7.8 Kahramanmaraş earthquake may be explained by the contrasting structure of and stress on these segments, according to seismic tomographic imaging of beneath the fault zone.
Published: 2026-01-06T10:02:33+00:00
Venue: Nature Geoscience
Score: 0.545 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jing Chen; Mijian Xu; Yiming Bai; Shucheng Wu; Xiao Xiao; Shijie Hao; Masaru Nagaso; Hongfeng Yang; Ping Tong&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Geoscience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41561-025-01893-z"&gt;10.1038/s41561-025-01893-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.545 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 6 February 2023, two major earthquakes with moment magnitude (Mw) of 7.8 and 7.6 ruptured multiple segments of the Eastern Anatolian Fault system, resulting in many casualties and extensive property damage in Turkey and Syria. The Mw 7.8 earthquake involved bilateral rupture along the Eastern Anatolian Fault, with at least partially supershear rupture towards the northeast and subshear rupture towards the southwest. The cause of this difference in rupture speed remains debated. Here we present evidence from seismic tomographic imaging linking this difference to structural and stress variations along the fault. Specifically, a low-velocity anomaly and a fault-parallel fast velocity direction of anisotropy in the southwest Amanos–Pazarcık segment suggest fluid infiltration, which could facilitate fault creep and reduce the stress loading rate. By contrast, the Erkenek segment to the northeast is associated with a high-velocity anomaly and fault-normal fast velocity direction, suggesting limited fluid infiltration and increased stress accumulation. Hence, we propose that the contrast in stress accumulation explains the discrepancy in rupture speeds in this earthquake and that fault structure in addition to stress loading may influence stress accumulation and thus whether a fault ruptures at supershear speeds. The difference in rupture speed between fault segments in the 2023 Mw 7.8 Kahramanmaraş earthquake may be explained by the contrasting structure of and stress on these segments, according to seismic tomographic imaging of beneath the fault zone.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>On demand laser-induced frequency tuning of coherent magnons in a nanometer-thick magnet at room temperature</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66707-7</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66707-7</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 15:49:04 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Volker Wiechert</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hanchen Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>William Legrand</dc:creator><dc:creator>Pietro Gambardella</dc:creator><dc:creator>David Breitbach</dc:creator><dc:creator>Philipp Pirro</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michaela Lammel</dc:creator><dc:creator>Andrea Meo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Giovanni Finocchio</dc:creator><dc:creator>Davide Bossini</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66707-7</prism:doi><description>Abstract The collective vibrational and magnetic response of a solid to external stimuli is encoded in the dispersion relations of phonons and magnons, respectively. Recently, the coherent drive and nonlinear manipulation of collective lattice and magnetic excitations via laser pulses has been explored, as a route to control the non-equilibrium properties of quantum materials. Device concepts that leverage coupled multiphysical dynamics must exhibit laser-induced frequency tunability controllable through external parameters. Although previous works have shown that optically driven excitations in the midinfrared can manipulate magnon frequencies, inducing deterministic red- or blue-shifts of the magnon frequency in the same material is still elusive. Here we demonstrate this concept in a nanometer-thick magnet at room temperature. Visible light pulses in combination with an external magnetic field (
Published: 2026-01-06T15:49:04+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.544 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Volker Wiechert; Hanchen Wang; William Legrand; Pietro Gambardella; David Breitbach; Philipp Pirro; Michaela Lammel; Andrea Meo; Giovanni Finocchio; Davide Bossini&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66707-7"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66707-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.544 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The collective vibrational and magnetic response of a solid to external stimuli is encoded in the dispersion relations of phonons and magnons, respectively. Recently, the coherent drive and nonlinear manipulation of collective lattice and magnetic excitations via laser pulses has been explored, as a route to control the non-equilibrium properties of quantum materials. Device concepts that leverage coupled multiphysical dynamics must exhibit laser-induced frequency tunability controllable through external parameters. Although previous works have shown that optically driven excitations in the midinfrared can manipulate magnon frequencies, inducing deterministic red- or blue-shifts of the magnon frequency in the same material is still elusive. Here we demonstrate this concept in a nanometer-thick magnet at room temperature. Visible light pulses in combination with an external magnetic field (&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>First submillimeter lights from Dome A: Tracing the carbon cycle in the feedback of massive stars</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea9433</link><guid>10.1126/sciadv.aea9433</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:58:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yan Gong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiaqiang Zhong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuan Ren</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yilong Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Daizhong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yiping Ao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qijun Yao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wen Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wei Miao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenhui Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenying Duan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kangmin Zhou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zheng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junda Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kun Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jinpeng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Boliang Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhengheng Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiameng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huiqian Hao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xingming Lu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shaoming Xie</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia Quan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yanjie Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jingtao Liang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xianjin Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Liang Guo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tuo Ji</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peng Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chenggang Shu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sudeep Neupane</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruiqing Mao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shengcai Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Li</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science Advances</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1126/sciadv.aea9433</prism:doi><description>The cycling of carbon between its ionized, atomic, and molecular phases shapes the chemical compositions and physical conditions of the interstellar medium (ISM). However, ground-based studies of the full carbon cycle have been limited by atmospheric absorption. Dome A, the most promising site for submillimeter astronomy, has long resisted successful submillimeter astronomical observations. Using the 60-centimeter Antarctic Terahertz Explorer, we present the first successful CO (4-3) and [CI] ( P 1 3 − P 0 3 ) mapping observations of two archetypal triggered massive star-formation regions at Dome A. These data, together with archival [CII], provide the first complete characterization of all three carbon phases in these environments. We find elevated C 0 /CO abundance ratios in high-extinction regions, plausibly driven by deep penetration of intense radiation fields from massive stars into a clumpy ISM. These findings mark a major milestone for submillimeter astronomy at Dome A and offer valuable insights into the impact of massive star feedback on the surrounding ISM.
Published: 2026-01-07T18:58:36+00:00
Venue: Science Advances
Score: 0.544 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yan Gong; Jiaqiang Zhong; Yuan Ren; Yilong Zhang; Daizhong Liu; Yiping Ao; Qijun Yao; Wen Zhang; Wei Miao; Zhenhui Lin; Wenying Duan; Dong Liu; Kangmin Zhou; Jie Liu; Zheng Wang; Junda Jin; Kun Zhang; Feng Wu; Jinpeng Li; Boliang Liu; Xuan Zhang; Zhengheng Luo; Jiameng Wang; Huiqian Hao; Xingming Lu; Shaoming Xie; Jia Quan; Yanjie Liu; Jingtao Liang; Xianjin Deng; Jun Jiang; Li Li; Liang Guo; Tuo Ji; Peng Jiang; Yi Zhang; Chenggang Shu; Sudeep Neupane; Ruiqing Mao; Shengcai Shi; Jing Li&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science Advances&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aea9433"&gt;10.1126/sciadv.aea9433&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.544 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cycling of carbon between its ionized, atomic, and molecular phases shapes the chemical compositions and physical conditions of the interstellar medium (ISM). However, ground-based studies of the full carbon cycle have been limited by atmospheric absorption. Dome A, the most promising site for submillimeter astronomy, has long resisted successful submillimeter astronomical observations. Using the 60-centimeter Antarctic Terahertz Explorer, we present the first successful CO (4-3) and [CI] ( P 1 3 − P 0 3 ) mapping observations of two archetypal triggered massive star-formation regions at Dome A. These data, together with archival [CII], provide the first complete characterization of all three carbon phases in these environments. We find elevated C 0 /CO abundance ratios in high-extinction regions, plausibly driven by deep penetration of intense radiation fields from massive stars into a clumpy ISM. These findings mark a major milestone for submillimeter astronomy at Dome A and offer valuable insights into the impact of massive star feedback on the surrounding ISM.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Boosted catalytic activity by metal-oxide interface in porous single-crystalline niobium oxide monoliths</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68117-1</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68117-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 09:49:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Xiangqi Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guoliang Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cong Luo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Lingting Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kui Xie</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68117-1</prism:doi><description>Introducing and stabilizing oxygen vacancies in the lattice of oxide support materials has been a huge challenge to boost the catalytic activity in redox reaction. Herein, we fabricate porous single-crystalline Nb2O5 monoliths at the centimeter scale, then we introduce the oxygen vacancies in lattice by reduction treatment and stabilize the oxygen vacancy defects by the ordered lattice. We then deposit Pt clusters at surface in the porous microstructures to construct an interfacial system and we show the significantly enhanced surface oxygen exchange coefficient. As a case study, we demonstrate the complete CO oxidation with air at 110 °C and 30,000 mL g-1 h-1 conditions, following the Mars-van Krevelen mechanism, with no visible performance attenuation after a continuous operation of ~500 h. At 60,000 mL g-1 h-1 and 110 °C, the CO conversion rate decreases to 83.8% and ultimately remains 76.3% after 185 h of long-term operation. Introducing and stabilizing oxygen vacancies within oxide supports remains a significant challenge for enhancing catalytic activity in redox reactions. Here, the authors fabricate centimeter-scale porous single-crystalline Nb₂O₅ monoliths and deposit Pt clusters on their surfaces, creating an interfacial system that markedly improves catalytic CO oxidation.
Published: 2026-01-07T09:49:33+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.542 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiangqi Gao; Guoliang Ma; Cong Luo; Lingting Ye; Kui Xie&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68117-1"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68117-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.542 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Introducing and stabilizing oxygen vacancies in the lattice of oxide support materials has been a huge challenge to boost the catalytic activity in redox reaction. Herein, we fabricate porous single-crystalline Nb2O5 monoliths at the centimeter scale, then we introduce the oxygen vacancies in lattice by reduction treatment and stabilize the oxygen vacancy defects by the ordered lattice. We then deposit Pt clusters at surface in the porous microstructures to construct an interfacial system and we show the significantly enhanced surface oxygen exchange coefficient. As a case study, we demonstrate the complete CO oxidation with air at 110 °C and 30,000 mL g-1 h-1 conditions, following the Mars-van Krevelen mechanism, with no visible performance attenuation after a continuous operation of ~500 h. At 60,000 mL g-1 h-1 and 110 °C, the CO conversion rate decreases to 83.8% and ultimately remains 76.3% after 185 h of long-term operation. Introducing and stabilizing oxygen vacancies within oxide supports remains a significant challenge for enhancing catalytic activity in redox reactions. Here, the authors fabricate centimeter-scale porous single-crystalline Nb₂O₅ monoliths and deposit Pt clusters on their surfaces, creating an interfacial system that markedly improves catalytic CO oxidation.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Lithospheric models supported by the Caribbean and Levant examples help rethink transpression at plate boundaries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68051-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68051-2</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 02:25:23 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Anthony Jourdon</dc:creator><dc:creator>Laetitia Le Pourhiet</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dave A. May</dc:creator><dc:creator>Manuel Pubellier</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alice-Agnes Gabriel</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68051-2</prism:doi><description>Strike-slip restraining bends, such as the Levant Fault, belonging to push-up systems and the Jamaican fault network, belonging to duplex systems, display a diversity of fault geometries and deformation patterns that reflect distinct modes of lithospheric-scale strain localization. To investigate the origin of this variability, we develop 3D numerical models of transpressional strike-slip systems using heterogeneous simple shear boundary conditions and thermally-dependent, non-linear rheology. Unlike classical analog or numerical models that impose velocity discontinuities, our approach allows spontaneous fault localization that naturally generates transpression. We systematically explore how the position and geometry of inherited weak zones influence fault development. We show that three distinct strike-slip systems emerge: (1) push-up systems with a single strike-slip fault and outward-propagating thrusts; (2) duplex systems with interacting parallel faults connected by P-shears; and (3) systems of non-interacting parallel faults. These results highlight spontaneous strike-slip localization and how initial heterogeneities control formation and evolution of long-term lithospheric deformation. The study shows how inherited weak zones determine whether transpression produces pushups, duplexes, or parallel faults. 3D models offer insights into the deep processes that drive deformation and seismic patterns in the Caribbean and Levant.
Published: 2026-01-06T02:25:23+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.541 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Anthony Jourdon; Laetitia Le Pourhiet; Dave A. May; Manuel Pubellier; Alice-Agnes Gabriel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68051-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68051-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.541 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strike-slip restraining bends, such as the Levant Fault, belonging to push-up systems and the Jamaican fault network, belonging to duplex systems, display a diversity of fault geometries and deformation patterns that reflect distinct modes of lithospheric-scale strain localization. To investigate the origin of this variability, we develop 3D numerical models of transpressional strike-slip systems using heterogeneous simple shear boundary conditions and thermally-dependent, non-linear rheology. Unlike classical analog or numerical models that impose velocity discontinuities, our approach allows spontaneous fault localization that naturally generates transpression. We systematically explore how the position and geometry of inherited weak zones influence fault development. We show that three distinct strike-slip systems emerge: (1) push-up systems with a single strike-slip fault and outward-propagating thrusts; (2) duplex systems with interacting parallel faults connected by P-shears; and (3) systems of non-interacting parallel faults. These results highlight spontaneous strike-slip localization and how initial heterogeneities control formation and evolution of long-term lithospheric deformation. The study shows how inherited weak zones determine whether transpression produces pushups, duplexes, or parallel faults. 3D models offer insights into the deep processes that drive deformation and seismic patterns in the Caribbean and Levant.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Breaking immiscibility barriers: ultrafast sintering of interlocked Cu-Fe-based composites</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68107-3</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68107-3</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 15:49:37 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shiji Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhenduo Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoye Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Si Lan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengwei Wang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68107-3</prism:doi><description>With increasingly stringent application environments, there is a growing demand for designing and fabricating of promising structural materials. Conventional metallurgical methods typically struggle to produce positive mixing enthalpy alloys with uniform microstructures and consistent properties due to mutual immiscibility and uncontrollable segregation during solidification. To this end, we employ a bottom-up approach to fabricate Cu-50 vol% Fe55Cr25Mo16B2C2 positive mixing enthalpy composites, utilizing ultrafast high-temperature sintering and instantaneous quenching. The method effectively prevents liquid segregation during the molten state and allows precise control over the size and distribution of the two phases. In addition, incorporated metallic glass particles as the hard phase additives, which can quickly form the localized multi-phase nanocrystals and establish a robust interlocking structure with pure copper during rapid sintering. Upon rapid quenching, the two phases solidify with a tight and conformal interface, while the elemental cross-diffusion and phase separation are mitigated. The mechanical tensile strength of the resulting composite is approximately 8 times greater than that of pure Cu. The wear resistance improves by 40-50 times, and the Vickers hardness increases by a factor of 10. The innovative sintering method provides a feasible pathway for developing and manufacturing of positive mixing enthalpy composite materials. Immiscibility limits the performance of positive mixing enthalpy alloys. Here, the authors apply ultrafast sintering and quenching to fabricate mechanically interlocked Cu-Fe composites with good strength and conductivity.
Published: 2026-01-06T15:49:37+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.540 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shiji Shen; Zhenduo Wu; Xiaoye Liu; Si Lan; Chengwei Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68107-3"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68107-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.540 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With increasingly stringent application environments, there is a growing demand for designing and fabricating of promising structural materials. Conventional metallurgical methods typically struggle to produce positive mixing enthalpy alloys with uniform microstructures and consistent properties due to mutual immiscibility and uncontrollable segregation during solidification. To this end, we employ a bottom-up approach to fabricate Cu-50 vol% Fe55Cr25Mo16B2C2 positive mixing enthalpy composites, utilizing ultrafast high-temperature sintering and instantaneous quenching. The method effectively prevents liquid segregation during the molten state and allows precise control over the size and distribution of the two phases. In addition, incorporated metallic glass particles as the hard phase additives, which can quickly form the localized multi-phase nanocrystals and establish a robust interlocking structure with pure copper during rapid sintering. Upon rapid quenching, the two phases solidify with a tight and conformal interface, while the elemental cross-diffusion and phase separation are mitigated. The mechanical tensile strength of the resulting composite is approximately 8 times greater than that of pure Cu. The wear resistance improves by 40-50 times, and the Vickers hardness increases by a factor of 10. The innovative sintering method provides a feasible pathway for developing and manufacturing of positive mixing enthalpy composite materials. Immiscibility limits the performance of positive mixing enthalpy alloys. Here, the authors apply ultrafast sintering and quenching to fabricate mechanically interlocked Cu-Fe composites with good strength and conductivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Soft photonic skins with dynamic texture and colour control</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09948-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09948-2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:01:56 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Siddharth Doshi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicholas A. Güsken</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gerwin Dijk</dc:creator><dc:creator>Johan Carlström</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jennifer E. Ortiz-Cárdenas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peter Suzuki</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bohan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Polly M. Fordyce</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alberto Salleo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nicholas A. Melosh</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mark L. Brongersma</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09948-2</prism:doi><description>The visual appearances of surfaces are influenced by their colour and texture. Although the creation and tuning of structural colours has been realized with nanostructures1,2, achieving dynamic control over visual texture3,4 remains challenging. Inspired by dynamic modulation of cephalopod skin5,6, we develop polymer films with programmable surface textures. We bring these textures to life through immersion in different liquids that cause reversible local swelling/contraction to a degree that is determined by electron-beam irradiation. We show how standard electron-beam patterning tools can spatially encode arbitrary textures that can be hidden and shown on demand. Similarly, by modulating the topography of optical Fabry–Pérot cavities, we create colour patterns that can be continuously tuned with microfluidic control to achieve several distinct appearance states, allowing them to camouflage with different backgrounds. Finally, by creating multilayer devices, we demonstrate independent control of texture and colour in a single device, enabling a higher level of dynamic control over visual appearance. Inspired by dynamic textural modulation in cephalopod skin, polymer films whose colour and surface texture can be dynamically and independently controlled are developed and demonstrated using standard electron-beam patterning tools.
Published: 2026-01-07T16:01:56+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.536 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Siddharth Doshi; Nicholas A. Güsken; Gerwin Dijk; Johan Carlström; Jennifer E. Ortiz-Cárdenas; Peter Suzuki; Bohan Li; Polly M. Fordyce; Alberto Salleo; Nicholas A. Melosh; Mark L. Brongersma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09948-2"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09948-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.536 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The visual appearances of surfaces are influenced by their colour and texture. Although the creation and tuning of structural colours has been realized with nanostructures1,2, achieving dynamic control over visual texture3,4 remains challenging. Inspired by dynamic modulation of cephalopod skin5,6, we develop polymer films with programmable surface textures. We bring these textures to life through immersion in different liquids that cause reversible local swelling/contraction to a degree that is determined by electron-beam irradiation. We show how standard electron-beam patterning tools can spatially encode arbitrary textures that can be hidden and shown on demand. Similarly, by modulating the topography of optical Fabry–Pérot cavities, we create colour patterns that can be continuously tuned with microfluidic control to achieve several distinct appearance states, allowing them to camouflage with different backgrounds. Finally, by creating multilayer devices, we demonstrate independent control of texture and colour in a single device, enabling a higher level of dynamic control over visual appearance. Inspired by dynamic textural modulation in cephalopod skin, polymer films whose colour and surface texture can be dynamically and independently controlled are developed and demonstrated using standard electron-beam patterning tools.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>[Hg3Se2]2- cluster drives giant optical anisotropy and broad infrared transparency</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66148-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-66148-2</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 10:02:20 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Qixian Ren</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chen Cui</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xinchen Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yabo Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ran An</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhihua Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shilie Pan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-66148-2</prism:doi><description>Optical anisotropy, a fundamental physical property for polarization control, has long presented a critical consideration in the development of optical materials, particularly in terms of its modulation mechanisms and performance optimization. In the mid-&amp;nbsp;to&amp;nbsp;far-infrared region, simultaneously achieving large birefringence and broad transparency within a single material remains a major challenge. Herein, we report the synthesis of Hg18Ga8Se8Cl32 (HGSC), a crystalline material featuring linear [Hg3Se2] structural units. HGSC demonstrates a large birefringence of 0.871 at 546 nm, accompanied by the broadest transparency window among Hg-based chalcogenide single crystals (0.4 to 25 µm). Theoretical calculations reveal that the significant birefringence of HGSC originates from the well-aligned linear [Hg3Se2]2- clusters, which exhibit the highest polarizability anisotropy (δ = 430) among all reported birefringence-active functional units. The demonstration of [Hg3Se2]2- clusters as an effective bifunctional unit offers new opportunities for designing infrared photonic materials. Here authors show that linear [Hg3Se2]2- cluster enables large birefringence and broad infrared transparency in Hg18Ga8Se8Cl32, enabling advanced infrared photonics.
Published: 2026-01-06T10:02:20+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.536 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Qixian Ren; Chen Cui; Xinchen Chen; Yabo Wu; Ran An; Zhihua Yang; Shilie Pan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-66148-2"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-66148-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.536 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optical anisotropy, a fundamental physical property for polarization control, has long presented a critical consideration in the development of optical materials, particularly in terms of its modulation mechanisms and performance optimization. In the mid-&amp;amp;nbsp;to&amp;amp;nbsp;far-infrared region, simultaneously achieving large birefringence and broad transparency within a single material remains a major challenge. Herein, we report the synthesis of Hg18Ga8Se8Cl32 (HGSC), a crystalline material featuring linear [Hg3Se2] structural units. HGSC demonstrates a large birefringence of 0.871 at 546 nm, accompanied by the broadest transparency window among Hg-based chalcogenide single crystals (0.4 to 25 µm). Theoretical calculations reveal that the significant birefringence of HGSC originates from the well-aligned linear [Hg3Se2]2- clusters, which exhibit the highest polarizability anisotropy (δ = 430) among all reported birefringence-active functional units. The demonstration of [Hg3Se2]2- clusters as an effective bifunctional unit offers new opportunities for designing infrared photonic materials. Here authors show that linear [Hg3Se2]2- cluster enables large birefringence and broad infrared transparency in Hg18Ga8Se8Cl32, enabling advanced infrared photonics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Field-effect passivation for minimized voltage loss in highly efficient antimony selenosulfide solar cells</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67334-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67334-y</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 10:02:19 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Anwen Gong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Cong Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiexi Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Binghuan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shilin Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Rongshan Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yousheng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kai Shen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qifan Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhiqiang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jing Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bingsuo Zou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yaohua Mai</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67334-y</prism:doi><description>The inferior heterojunction quality and misaligned energy levels at the buffer/absorber interface cause severe interface recombination and large open-circuit voltage (VOC) loss, limiting the power conversion efficiency (PCE) of antimony selenosulfide (Sb2(S,Se)3) solar cells. Here, we develop a field-effect passivation strategy by introducing a low-work-function Ta2O5 dielectric layer between the CdS and Sb2(S,Se)3 layers. This Ta2O5 layer serves as an optimal substrate for growing highly crystalline Sb2(S,Se)3 films while also enhancing interfacial charge transport. The positive fixed charges in Ta2O5 strengthen the built-in electric field and promotes electrons extraction while suppressing holes accumulation at the interface, thereby substantially suppressing non-radiative recombination probabilities. Implementing this passivation strategy yields a record PCE of 10.95% (10.65% certified) an VOC of 695 mV, corresponding to a remarkably low voltage deficit. This work establishes a universal physical passivation paradigm for interface quality optimization and VOC loss mitigation in high-performance Sb2(S,Se)3 photovoltaics. The inferior heterojunction quality and misaligned energy levels at the buffer/absorber layer hinders development of antimony selenosulfide solar cells. Here, authors introduce low-work-function tantalum pentoxide dielectric layer for field-effect passivation, achieving device efficiency of 10.95%.
Published: 2026-01-06T10:02:19+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.529 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Anwen Gong; Cong Liu; Jiexi Yang; Binghuan Li; Shilin Yang; Rongshan Yang; Yousheng Wang; Kai Shen; Qifan Xue; Zhiqiang Li; Jing Wang; Bingsuo Zou; Yaohua Mai&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67334-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67334-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.529 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inferior heterojunction quality and misaligned energy levels at the buffer/absorber interface cause severe interface recombination and large open-circuit voltage (VOC) loss, limiting the power conversion efficiency (PCE) of antimony selenosulfide (Sb2(S,Se)3) solar cells. Here, we develop a field-effect passivation strategy by introducing a low-work-function Ta2O5 dielectric layer between the CdS and Sb2(S,Se)3 layers. This Ta2O5 layer serves as an optimal substrate for growing highly crystalline Sb2(S,Se)3 films while also enhancing interfacial charge transport. The positive fixed charges in Ta2O5 strengthen the built-in electric field and promotes electrons extraction while suppressing holes accumulation at the interface, thereby substantially suppressing non-radiative recombination probabilities. Implementing this passivation strategy yields a record PCE of 10.95% (10.65% certified) an VOC of 695 mV, corresponding to a remarkably low voltage deficit. This work establishes a universal physical passivation paradigm for interface quality optimization and VOC loss mitigation in high-performance Sb2(S,Se)3 photovoltaics. The inferior heterojunction quality and misaligned energy levels at the buffer/absorber layer hinders development of antimony selenosulfide solar cells. Here, authors introduce low-work-function tantalum pentoxide dielectric layer for field-effect passivation, achieving device efficiency of 10.95%.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Surface-energy-compensated fabrication of single-crystal alloy films with atomic-scale flatness</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68196-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68196-0</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 02:34:31 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jiaxin Shao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sheng Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhuofeng Shi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yue Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengyuan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiumei Ma</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guangcun Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shiwei Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yunsong Ge</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dapeng Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weichuan Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junhao Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ali Cai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bo Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jincan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiucai Sun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mengxi Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li Lin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kaicheng Jia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhongfan Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68196-0</prism:doi><description>Single-crystal alloy thin films (SATFs), featuring highly ordered atomic lattices and superior composition-dependent properties, hold great potential for applications including crystal epitaxy, surface catalysis, and energy conversion. However, their scalable synthesis and practical applications have been hindered by the difficulty of achieving wafer-scale single crystallinity, atomic-scale surface flatness, as well as flexible and uniform control of alloy composition. Here, we developed a surface-energy-compensated technique for synthesizing a series of wafer-scale binary and ternary SATFs with sub-nanometer roughness (minimum roughness lower than 0.2 nm) and uniform, controllable elemental composition with a wide range (5 ~ 50 at%). Furthermore, using CuPtNi(111) ternary SATFs as epitaxial substrates, we achieve wafer-scale synthesis of wrinkle-free graphene single crystals exhibiting fine electronic quality, including a uniform sheet resistance of 552&amp;nbsp;Ω&amp;nbsp;sq−1 with 4.5% deviation, an ultrahigh carrier mobility up to over half a million cm2 V−1 s−1 at 1.7 K, and well-developed quantum plateaus. Single-crystal alloy thin films (SATFs) are appealing for applications in crystal epitaxy, surface catalysis, and energy conversion. Here, the authors report a method to synthesize wafer-scale binary and ternary SATFs with sub-nanometer roughness, which can be used as substrates for the growth of high-quality graphene single crystals.
Published: 2026-01-07T02:34:31+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.526 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jiaxin Shao; Sheng Li; Zhuofeng Shi; Yue Sun; Mengyuan Liu; Xiumei Ma; Guangcun Gao; Shiwei Wang; Yunsong Ge; Bo Jin; Dapeng Zhang; Weichuan Chen; Junhao Liao; Ali Cai; Bo Yang; Hao Li; Jincan Zhang; Xiucai Sun; Mengxi Liu; Li Lin; Kaicheng Jia; Zhongfan Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68196-0"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68196-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.526 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single-crystal alloy thin films (SATFs), featuring highly ordered atomic lattices and superior composition-dependent properties, hold great potential for applications including crystal epitaxy, surface catalysis, and energy conversion. However, their scalable synthesis and practical applications have been hindered by the difficulty of achieving wafer-scale single crystallinity, atomic-scale surface flatness, as well as flexible and uniform control of alloy composition. Here, we developed a surface-energy-compensated technique for synthesizing a series of wafer-scale binary and ternary SATFs with sub-nanometer roughness (minimum roughness lower than 0.2 nm) and uniform, controllable elemental composition with a wide range (5 ~ 50 at%). Furthermore, using CuPtNi(111) ternary SATFs as epitaxial substrates, we achieve wafer-scale synthesis of wrinkle-free graphene single crystals exhibiting fine electronic quality, including a uniform sheet resistance of 552&amp;amp;nbsp;Ω&amp;amp;nbsp;sq−1 with 4.5% deviation, an ultrahigh carrier mobility up to over half a million cm2 V−1 s−1 at 1.7 K, and well-developed quantum plateaus. Single-crystal alloy thin films (SATFs) are appealing for applications in crystal epitaxy, surface catalysis, and energy conversion. Here, the authors report a method to synthesize wafer-scale binary and ternary SATFs with sub-nanometer roughness, which can be used as substrates for the growth of high-quality graphene single crystals.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pulse heating and slip enhance charging of phase-change thermal batteries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09877-0</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09877-0</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:01:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Zi-Rui Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Nan Hu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhen-Bo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guo-Tao Fu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yang-Yan Lai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yue-Fei Wu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jia-Jie Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao-Rong Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuang-Shuang Ni</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu-Min Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zi-Tao Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiang Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Howard A. Stone</dc:creator><dc:creator>Li-Wu Fan</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09877-0</prism:doi><description>Phase-change thermal batteries for renewable energy storage and waste heat recovery demand high energy density and fast charging1–5, which are mutually exclusive because phase-change materials (PCMs) with high melting enthalpy are usually poor heat conductors6–8. The charging rate can be improved by making composite phase-change materials (CPCMs) with increased thermal conductivity9 and/or by exerting an external force to realize close-contact melting (CCM)10–12. However, these methods inevitably result in energy density losses and/or extra energy consumption. Here we report a strategy to boost the charging rates without sacrificing energy density, based on a rational design of a composite coating that enables slip-enhanced close-contact melting (sCCM) inside sealed thermal batteries. Using organic PCMs, we demonstrate a record-high power density of 1,100 ± 2% kW m−3 in a prototype. Our coating design integrates a pulse-heated (PH) layer that premelts the PCM to initiate CCM, together with a liquid-like slip surface that ensures unimpeded sinking of the remaining solid and sustains the sCCM mode throughout charging. We develop a model to explain how the slip surface enhances the charging rate. With high cycling life, adaptability and scalability, this strategy is generalizable to diverse PCMs, enabling high-performance thermal energy storage over a wide range of temperatures. A strategy based on the design of a composite coating that enables slip-enhanced close-contact melting inside sealed phase-change thermal batteries to improve charging rates enables high-performance thermal energy storage over a wide range of temperatures.
Published: 2026-01-07T16:01:33+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.525 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Zi-Rui Li; Nan Hu; Zhen-Bo Wang; Guo-Tao Fu; Yang-Yan Lai; Yue-Fei Wu; Jia-Jie Jiang; Xiao-Rong Wang; Shuang-Shuang Ni; Yu-Min Ye; Zi-Tao Yu; Xiang Gao; Howard A. Stone; Li-Wu Fan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09877-0"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09877-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.525 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phase-change thermal batteries for renewable energy storage and waste heat recovery demand high energy density and fast charging1–5, which are mutually exclusive because phase-change materials (PCMs) with high melting enthalpy are usually poor heat conductors6–8. The charging rate can be improved by making composite phase-change materials (CPCMs) with increased thermal conductivity9 and/or by exerting an external force to realize close-contact melting (CCM)10–12. However, these methods inevitably result in energy density losses and/or extra energy consumption. Here we report a strategy to boost the charging rates without sacrificing energy density, based on a rational design of a composite coating that enables slip-enhanced close-contact melting (sCCM) inside sealed thermal batteries. Using organic PCMs, we demonstrate a record-high power density of 1,100 ± 2% kW m−3 in a prototype. Our coating design integrates a pulse-heated (PH) layer that premelts the PCM to initiate CCM, together with a liquid-like slip surface that ensures unimpeded sinking of the remaining solid and sustains the sCCM mode throughout charging. We develop a model to explain how the slip surface enhances the charging rate. With high cycling life, adaptability and scalability, this strategy is generalizable to diverse PCMs, enabling high-performance thermal energy storage over a wide range of temperatures. A strategy based on the design of a composite coating that enables slip-enhanced close-contact melting inside sealed phase-change thermal batteries to improve charging rates enables high-performance thermal energy storage over a wide range of temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ferroelectric switching of interfacial dipoles in α-RuCl3/graphene heterostructure</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68072-x</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68072-x</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 14:42:51 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Soyun Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jo Hyun Yun</dc:creator><dc:creator>Junsik Choe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Dohun Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Takashi Taniguchi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kenji Watanabe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Joseph Falson</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jun Sung Kim</dc:creator><dc:creator>Kyung-Hwan Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gil Young Cho</dc:creator><dc:creator>Youngwook Kim</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68072-x</prism:doi><description>We demonstrate electrically switchable, non-volatile dipoles in graphene/thin hBN/α-RuCl3alpha-RuCl3 heterostructures, stabilized purely by interfacial charge transfer across an atomically thin dielectric barrier. This mechanism requires no sliding or twisting to explicitly break inversion symmetry and produces robust ferroelectric-like hysteresis loops that emerge prominently near 30 K. Systematic measurements under strong in-plane and out-of-plane magnetic fields reveal negligible effects on the hysteresis characteristics, confirming that the primary mechanism driving the dipole switching is electrostatic. Our findings establish a distinct and robust route to electrically tunable ferroelectric phenomena in van der Waals heterostructures, opening opportunities to explore the interplay between interfacial charge transfer and temperature-tuned barrier crossing of dipole states at the atomic scale. This study shows that electrically switchable and non-volatile dipoles can form at the interface of graphene and α-RuCl3 when separated by an ultrathin hBN layer. The dipole switching is driven by interfacial charge transfer, is stable without continuous power, and emerges in a narrow temperature window around 30 K.
Published: 2026-01-06T14:42:51+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.523 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Soyun Kim; Jo Hyun Yun; Junsik Choe; Dohun Kim; Takashi Taniguchi; Kenji Watanabe; Joseph Falson; Jun Sung Kim; Kyung-Hwan Jin; Gil Young Cho; Youngwook Kim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68072-x"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68072-x&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.523 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrate electrically switchable, non-volatile dipoles in graphene/thin hBN/α-RuCl3alpha-RuCl3 heterostructures, stabilized purely by interfacial charge transfer across an atomically thin dielectric barrier. This mechanism requires no sliding or twisting to explicitly break inversion symmetry and produces robust ferroelectric-like hysteresis loops that emerge prominently near 30 K. Systematic measurements under strong in-plane and out-of-plane magnetic fields reveal negligible effects on the hysteresis characteristics, confirming that the primary mechanism driving the dipole switching is electrostatic. Our findings establish a distinct and robust route to electrically tunable ferroelectric phenomena in van der Waals heterostructures, opening opportunities to explore the interplay between interfacial charge transfer and temperature-tuned barrier crossing of dipole states at the atomic scale. This study shows that electrically switchable and non-volatile dipoles can form at the interface of graphene and α-RuCl3 when separated by an ultrathin hBN layer. The dipole switching is driven by interfacial charge transfer, is stable without continuous power, and emerges in a narrow temperature window around 30 K.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Dredging and dumping impact coastal fluxes of sediment and organic carbon</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68105-5</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68105-5</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:36:36 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Lucas Porz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jiayue Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ruemeysa Yilmaz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jannis Kuhlmann</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenyan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Corinna Schrum</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68105-5</prism:doi><description>Abstract The disturbance and relocation of coastal sediments by human activities constitutes a potentially large disruption to natural sediment and organic carbon fluxes, but large-scale estimates of these impacts are lacking. Here, we estimate the amounts of sediment and organic carbon disturbed and relocated in the North Sea resulting from (1) dredging in the form of mineral aggregate extraction and (2) material dumping during waterway maintenance. We show that despite disturbing less sediment than aggregate extraction, dumping causes greater carbon disturbance. We estimate carbon disturbance by both activities to be higher than by marine construction, but lower than by bottom-contacting fisheries. Simulations indicate that most dumped material re-deposits near the coast. Globally, dumping of organic carbon is estimated to 0.09–0.46 GtC yr −1 , and disturbance by material extraction to 0.04−0.08 GtC yr −1 . Comparison to natural processes suggests that these activities should be considered in regional to global sediment and carbon budgets.
Published: 2026-01-07T08:36:36+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.522 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Lucas Porz; Jiayue Chen; Ruemeysa Yilmaz; Jannis Kuhlmann; Wenyan Zhang; Corinna Schrum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68105-5"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68105-5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.522 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract The disturbance and relocation of coastal sediments by human activities constitutes a potentially large disruption to natural sediment and organic carbon fluxes, but large-scale estimates of these impacts are lacking. Here, we estimate the amounts of sediment and organic carbon disturbed and relocated in the North Sea resulting from (1) dredging in the form of mineral aggregate extraction and (2) material dumping during waterway maintenance. We show that despite disturbing less sediment than aggregate extraction, dumping causes greater carbon disturbance. We estimate carbon disturbance by both activities to be higher than by marine construction, but lower than by bottom-contacting fisheries. Simulations indicate that most dumped material re-deposits near the coast. Globally, dumping of organic carbon is estimated to 0.09–0.46 GtC yr −1 , and disturbance by material extraction to 0.04−0.08 GtC yr −1 . Comparison to natural processes suggests that these activities should be considered in regional to global sediment and carbon budgets.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>High-voltage anode-free sodium–sulfur batteries</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09867-2</link><guid>10.1038/s41586-025-09867-2</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:01:33 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Shitao Geng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bin Yuan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiaoju Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qiuchen Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yan Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zhaofeng Ouyang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shanshan Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuo Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chengxiao Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qianyun Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Meng Liao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bingjie Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chen Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Weihua Jin</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zichuang Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tian-Nan Ye</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xueqing Gong</dc:creator><dc:creator>Huisheng Peng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hao Sun</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41586-025-09867-2</prism:doi><description>Room-temperature sodium–sulfur (Na–S) batteries offer a sustainable energy storage solution to conventional lithium (Li)-based systems1–3, owing to the high element abundances and theoretical electrochemical performance4,5. However, their practical applications have been severely hindered by the low discharge voltages and the need for largely excessive Na metal anode6–8. Here we report a 3.6&amp;nbsp;V&amp;nbsp;class Na–S battery featuring a high-valence sulfur/sulfur tetrachloride (S/SCl4) cathode chemistry and anode-free configuration. We show that sodium dicyanamide (NaDCA) can simultaneously unlock reversible S/SCl4 conversion and Na plating/stripping in a non-flammable chloroaluminate electrolyte. This design enables the maximum energy and power densities of 1,198 Wh kg−1 and 23,773 W kg−1, respectively, calculated on the basis of the total electrode mass including both the cathode and the anode. Also, we demonstrate facilitated S/SCl4 conversion by incorporating a bismuth-coordinated covalent organic framework (Bi-COF) catalyst (8 wt% loading) into the S cathode, which realizes an impressive discharge capacity of 1,206 mAh g(sulfur+catalyst)−1, contributing to a maximum energy density of 2,021 Wh kg−1 calculated on the basis of the total electrode mass. With an estimated cost of US$5.03 per kWh and excellent scalability, our anode-free Na–S battery shows promise in grid energy storage and wearable electronics. A new architecture based on high-valence sulfur/sulfur tetrachloride cathode chemistry is described for manufacturing high-voltage anode-free sodium–sulfur batteries, demonstrating promise for applications in grid energy storage and wearable electronics.
Published: 2026-01-07T16:01:33+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.522 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Shitao Geng; Bin Yuan; Xiaoju Zhao; Qiuchen Xu; Yan Wang; Zhaofeng Ouyang; Shanshan Tang; Shuo Wang; Chengxiao Zhang; Qianyun Chen; Meng Liao; Bingjie Wang; Chen Zhao; Weihua Jin; Zichuang Li; Tian-Nan Ye; Xueqing Gong; Huisheng Peng; Hao Sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-025-09867-2"&gt;10.1038/s41586-025-09867-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.522 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Room-temperature sodium–sulfur (Na–S) batteries offer a sustainable energy storage solution to conventional lithium (Li)-based systems1–3, owing to the high element abundances and theoretical electrochemical performance4,5. However, their practical applications have been severely hindered by the low discharge voltages and the need for largely excessive Na metal anode6–8. Here we report a 3.6&amp;amp;nbsp;V&amp;amp;nbsp;class Na–S battery featuring a high-valence sulfur/sulfur tetrachloride (S/SCl4) cathode chemistry and anode-free configuration. We show that sodium dicyanamide (NaDCA) can simultaneously unlock reversible S/SCl4 conversion and Na plating/stripping in a non-flammable chloroaluminate electrolyte. This design enables the maximum energy and power densities of 1,198 Wh kg−1 and 23,773 W kg−1, respectively, calculated on the basis of the total electrode mass including both the cathode and the anode. Also, we demonstrate facilitated S/SCl4 conversion by incorporating a bismuth-coordinated covalent organic framework (Bi-COF) catalyst (8 wt% loading) into the S cathode, which realizes an impressive discharge capacity of 1,206 mAh g(sulfur+catalyst)−1, contributing to a maximum energy density of 2,021 Wh kg−1 calculated on the basis of the total electrode mass. With an estimated cost of US$5.03 per kWh and excellent scalability, our anode-free Na–S battery shows promise in grid energy storage and wearable electronics. A new architecture based on high-valence sulfur/sulfur tetrachloride cathode chemistry is described for manufacturing high-voltage anode-free sodium–sulfur batteries, demonstrating promise for applications in grid energy storage and wearable electronics.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Artificial skin mimics the octopus’s art of disguise</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-03984-8</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-025-03984-8</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 15:01:52 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Benjamin Renz</dc:creator><dc:creator>Na Liu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-025-03984-8</prism:doi><description>A ‘photonic skin’ with controllable colour and texture brings materials science a step closer to the adaptive camouflage found in nature. A ‘photonic skin’ with controllable colour and texture brings materials science a step closer to the adaptive camouflage found in nature.
Published: 2026-01-06T15:01:52+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.518 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Benjamin Renz; Na Liu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-03984-8"&gt;10.1038/d41586-025-03984-8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.518 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ‘photonic skin’ with controllable colour and texture brings materials science a step closer to the adaptive camouflage found in nature. A ‘photonic skin’ with controllable colour and texture brings materials science a step closer to the adaptive camouflage found in nature.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Transport evidence of current-induced nematic Dirac valleys in a parity-time-symmetric antiferromagnet</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67229-y</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-67229-y</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 10:02:27 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Hideaki Sakai</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yuya Miyamoto</dc:creator><dc:creator>Motoi Kimata</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hikaru Watanabe</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yoichi Yanase</dc:creator><dc:creator>Masayuki Ochi</dc:creator><dc:creator>Masaki Kondo</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hiroshi Murakawa</dc:creator><dc:creator>Noriaki Hanasaki</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-67229-y</prism:doi><description>Itinerant antiferromagnets with broken time-reversal symmetry have recently attracted attention, since their spin-split bands enable large magnetotransport responses comparable to ferromagnets despite the negligible spontaneous magnetisation. When the inversion symmetry is further broken by the antiferromagnetic order, the emerging odd-parity multipole order renders the bands spin-degenerate but asymmetric in the momentum space. For such parity-time-symmetric antiferromagnets, it has been predicted that electronic nematicity is induced by current, allowing unconventional nonlinear transport phenomena. However, their experimental evidence has been lacking. Here, we report two-fold nonreciprocal angular magnetoresistance in the tetragonal layered Dirac material SrMnBi2 with parity-time-symmetric antiferromagnetic order in its Mn-Bi layers. By quantitatively modelling the angular and field dependencies using a phenomenological framework, we reveal that the observed nonreciprocal interlayer resistivity arises from the current-induced breaking of four-fold rotoinversion symmetry of the Dirac valleys in the Bi square net adjacent to the Mn-Bi layer. Furthermore, we demonstrate the alignment of parity-time-symmetric antiferromagnetic domains via current-field cooling, achieving electric-magnetic control of the f-wave polarity in momentum space. The observed switchable nonreciprocal transport associated with current-tuneable valley nematicity paves the way for novel antiferromagnetic spintronic and valleytronic applications. It has been predicted that in PT-symmetric antiferromagnets, electric currents can induce electronic nematicity that breaks the original rotational symmetry of the crystal, however, experimental confirmation of this has proven challenging. Here, Sakai et al find a twofold non-reciprocal anisotropic magnetoresistance in tetragonal SrMnBi2 and show that this arises due to current-induced breaking of four-fold roto-inversion symmetry of the electronic valleys.
Published: 2026-01-07T10:02:27+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.514 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Hideaki Sakai; Yuya Miyamoto; Motoi Kimata; Hikaru Watanabe; Yoichi Yanase; Masayuki Ochi; Masaki Kondo; Hiroshi Murakawa; Noriaki Hanasaki&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-67229-y"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-67229-y&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.514 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Itinerant antiferromagnets with broken time-reversal symmetry have recently attracted attention, since their spin-split bands enable large magnetotransport responses comparable to ferromagnets despite the negligible spontaneous magnetisation. When the inversion symmetry is further broken by the antiferromagnetic order, the emerging odd-parity multipole order renders the bands spin-degenerate but asymmetric in the momentum space. For such parity-time-symmetric antiferromagnets, it has been predicted that electronic nematicity is induced by current, allowing unconventional nonlinear transport phenomena. However, their experimental evidence has been lacking. Here, we report two-fold nonreciprocal angular magnetoresistance in the tetragonal layered Dirac material SrMnBi2 with parity-time-symmetric antiferromagnetic order in its Mn-Bi layers. By quantitatively modelling the angular and field dependencies using a phenomenological framework, we reveal that the observed nonreciprocal interlayer resistivity arises from the current-induced breaking of four-fold rotoinversion symmetry of the Dirac valleys in the Bi square net adjacent to the Mn-Bi layer. Furthermore, we demonstrate the alignment of parity-time-symmetric antiferromagnetic domains via current-field cooling, achieving electric-magnetic control of the f-wave polarity in momentum space. The observed switchable nonreciprocal transport associated with current-tuneable valley nematicity paves the way for novel antiferromagnetic spintronic and valleytronic applications. It has been predicted that in PT-symmetric antiferromagnets, electric currents can induce electronic nematicity that breaks the original rotational symmetry of the crystal, however, experimental confirmation of this has proven challenging. Here, Sakai et al find a twofold non-reciprocal anisotropic magnetoresistance in tetragonal SrMnBi2 and show that this arises due to current-induced breaking of four-fold roto-inversion symmetry of the electronic valleys.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Exotic quasiparticles glimpsed in graphene</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-04016-1</link><guid>10.1038/d41586-025-04016-1</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 15:01:41 +0000</pubDate><prism:publicationName>Nature</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/d41586-025-04016-1</prism:doi><description>Bilayer graphene has been used to observe robust interference patterns consistent with the presence of fractionally charged quasiparticles known as non-Abelian anyons. Demonstrating and controlling this interference is a crucial step towards harnessing these elusive quasiparticles as building blocks for fault-tolerant quantum computers. Observation is a step towards fault-tolerant quantum computers.
Published: 2026-01-07T15:01:41+00:00
Venue: Nature
Score: 0.510 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-025-04016-1"&gt;10.1038/d41586-025-04016-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.510 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilayer graphene has been used to observe robust interference patterns consistent with the presence of fractionally charged quasiparticles known as non-Abelian anyons. Demonstrating and controlling this interference is a crucial step towards harnessing these elusive quasiparticles as building blocks for fault-tolerant quantum computers. Observation is a step towards fault-tolerant quantum computers.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Continuous MXene fibers with near-gigapascal tensile strength via radial confinement and axial stretching</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68038-z</link><guid>10.1038/s41467-025-68038-z</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 22:33:03 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Chaojie Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying Chen</dc:creator><dc:creator>Tengyuan Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Enlai Gao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yongheng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Guo Xia</dc:creator><dc:creator>Mingshan Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wangwei Lian</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xuliang Deng</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sijie Wan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Qunfeng Cheng</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Nature Communications</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1038/s41467-025-68038-z</prism:doi><description>Assembling titanium carbide MXene nanosheets into macroscopic high-performance fibers is very challenging because of the voids caused by transverse wrinkles, hindering their practical applications in wearable smart textiles. Here we continuously fabricate ultrastrong MXene fibers by coaxial-wet-spinning-assisted radial confining integrated with roll-to-roll-assisted axial stretching under near room temperature. Wet-spun MXene fibers are bridged with calcium ions and radially confined to reduce the voids resulting from transverse wrinkles by an in-situ bridged sodium alginate encapsulation layer, followed by stretching to axially align nanosheets. The resultant MXene fibers provide record tensile strength (958 MPa) and electrical conductivity (13,692 S cm-1). Large-area textiles made from the MXene fibers present extraordinary electromagnetic interference shielding capacity (6,509 dB cm-1). The proposed strategy opens an avenue for scalable assembling other two-dimensional nanosheets into high-performance fibers. Compact MXene fibers with near-gigapascal strength are continuously fabricated by radial confinement and axial stretching under room temperature. Large-area textiles made from the fibers show superior electromagnetic interference shielding capacity.
Published: 2026-01-07T22:33:03+00:00
Venue: Nature Communications
Score: 0.508 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Chaojie Huang; Ying Chen; Tengyuan Zhang; Enlai Gao; Yongheng Wang; Guo Xia; Mingshan Li; Wangwei Lian; Xuliang Deng; Sijie Wan; Qunfeng Cheng&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-025-68038-z"&gt;10.1038/s41467-025-68038-z&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.508 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assembling titanium carbide MXene nanosheets into macroscopic high-performance fibers is very challenging because of the voids caused by transverse wrinkles, hindering their practical applications in wearable smart textiles. Here we continuously fabricate ultrastrong MXene fibers by coaxial-wet-spinning-assisted radial confining integrated with roll-to-roll-assisted axial stretching under near room temperature. Wet-spun MXene fibers are bridged with calcium ions and radially confined to reduce the voids resulting from transverse wrinkles by an in-situ bridged sodium alginate encapsulation layer, followed by stretching to axially align nanosheets. The resultant MXene fibers provide record tensile strength (958 MPa) and electrical conductivity (13,692 S cm-1). Large-area textiles made from the MXene fibers present extraordinary electromagnetic interference shielding capacity (6,509 dB cm-1). The proposed strategy opens an avenue for scalable assembling other two-dimensional nanosheets into high-performance fibers. Compact MXene fibers with near-gigapascal strength are continuously fabricated by radial confinement and axial stretching under room temperature. Large-area textiles made from the fibers show superior electromagnetic interference shielding capacity.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>