<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/3.0/" version="2.0"><channel><title>ZotWatch Feed</title><link>https://ehehe.cn/zotwatch/</link><description>AI-assisted literature watch</description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2026 04:26:43 +0000</lastBuildDate><item><title>Transformation of silica-rich to carbonated silicate melts in a big mantle wedge revealed by geochemistry of mantle xenoliths</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7</link><guid>10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 05:59:09 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Pengtao Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jie Tang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Feng Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Chunguang Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Wenliang Xu</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science China Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7</prism:doi><description>Carbonated silicate melts transport oxidized carbon from the deep to shallow mantle, and thus play an important role in the deep carbon cycle. However, it is unclear how carbonated silicate melts are formed. Here, we report whole-rock major and trace element, and Mg-Zn-Fe isotope, and in situ olivine and clinopyroxene Mg isotope data for peridotites and pyroxenites in Cenozoic alkaline basalts from Shulan and Yitong, Northeast China, to reveal the formation mechanisms of carbonated silicate melts. As residues of the primitive mantle, most of the Shulan and Yitong (spinel) harzburgite and lherzolite have relatively lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn than the mantle values, and show LREE-enriched patterns. These features indicate that these peridotites have been modified by carbonated silicate melt, transforming them into carbonated peridotites. The Shulan websterites exhibit metasomatic textures, and most of their whole-rock and in situ δ26Mg values are lower than the mantle values, which also supports the presence of a carbonated lithospheric mantle. The Yitong cumulate orthopyroxenites, representing silica-rich melts, have lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn values than mantle peridotites, implying that recycled carbonate has been involved in these silica-rich melts. The Yitong cumulate wehrlites and (olivine) websterites display major element compositions similar to those of carbonated peridotite melts, coupled with low whole-rock and clinopyroxene δ26Mg values, high δ66Zn and δ57Fe values, indicating the occurrence of carbonated silicate melts. The transition from orthopyroxenites to (olivine) websterites is marked by the decreasing of their whole-rock δ26Mg, δ57Fe values and Zn/Fe ratios and increasing of their δ66Zn values, along with decreasing of their crystallization temperatures, suggesting that silica-rich melts were gradually transformed into carbonated silicate melts via continuous interaction with carbonated peridotite. Our findings demonstrate that silica-rich melts from the stagnant slab can extract carbon from pre-existing carbonated mantle within the big mantle wedge.
Published: 2026-01-28T05:59:09+00:00
Venue: Science China Earth Sciences
Score: 0.671 (must_read)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Pengtao Xu; Jie Tang; Feng Wang; Chunguang Wang; Wenliang Xu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science China Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7"&gt;10.1007/s11430-025-1774-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.671 (must_read)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbonated silicate melts transport oxidized carbon from the deep to shallow mantle, and thus play an important role in the deep carbon cycle. However, it is unclear how carbonated silicate melts are formed. Here, we report whole-rock major and trace element, and Mg-Zn-Fe isotope, and in situ olivine and clinopyroxene Mg isotope data for peridotites and pyroxenites in Cenozoic alkaline basalts from Shulan and Yitong, Northeast China, to reveal the formation mechanisms of carbonated silicate melts. As residues of the primitive mantle, most of the Shulan and Yitong (spinel) harzburgite and lherzolite have relatively lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn than the mantle values, and show LREE-enriched patterns. These features indicate that these peridotites have been modified by carbonated silicate melt, transforming them into carbonated peridotites. The Shulan websterites exhibit metasomatic textures, and most of their whole-rock and in situ δ26Mg values are lower than the mantle values, which also supports the presence of a carbonated lithospheric mantle. The Yitong cumulate orthopyroxenites, representing silica-rich melts, have lower δ26Mg and higher δ66Zn values than mantle peridotites, implying that recycled carbonate has been involved in these silica-rich melts. The Yitong cumulate wehrlites and (olivine) websterites display major element compositions similar to those of carbonated peridotite melts, coupled with low whole-rock and clinopyroxene δ26Mg values, high δ66Zn and δ57Fe values, indicating the occurrence of carbonated silicate melts. The transition from orthopyroxenites to (olivine) websterites is marked by the decreasing of their whole-rock δ26Mg, δ57Fe values and Zn/Fe ratios and increasing of their δ66Zn values, along with decreasing of their crystallization temperatures, suggesting that silica-rich melts were gradually transformed into carbonated silicate melts via continuous interaction with carbonated peridotite. Our findings demonstrate that silica-rich melts from the stagnant slab can extract carbon from pre-existing carbonated mantle within the big mantle wedge.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Ba isotope unmasks recycling processes of fluid mobile elements in subduction zones</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.038</link><guid>10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.038</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:58:25 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yang Yu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao-Long Huang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Betchaida D. Payot</dc:creator><dc:creator>Hai-Quan Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ying-De Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yu Wang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Carla B. Dimalanta</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xin-Feng Ou</dc:creator><dc:creator>Gabriel Theophilus V. Valera</dc:creator><dc:creator>Fan Yang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Graciano P. Yumul</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yi-Gang Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xiao-Han Tang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.038</prism:doi><description>Geochemical recycling processes in subduction zones exhibit significant variability due to the incorporation of complex subduction components into the mantle wedge. Here, we present whole-rock geochemical and Ba–Sr–Nd–Hf–Pb isotopic data for basalts from the sediment-rich Luzon Arc and the sediment-poor Bicol Arc to constrain the recycling processes of fluid mobile elements (FME) in different subduction settings. Our results suggest that the mantle wedge beneath the Luzon and Bicol arcs was primarily metasomatized by melts from subducted sediments and fluids from subducted oceanic crust, respectively. The basalts from both arcs show variable δ 138/134 Ba values despite their limited variations in Sr–Nd–Hf–Pb isotopes, reflecting the heterogeneous dehydration of phengite in subducted sediments and oceanic crust, which have undergone different extents of Ba isotopic fractionation at shallow depths. Luzon back-arc basalts (BAB) exhibit Sr–Nd–Hf–Pb isotopic compositions similar to those of island arc basalts (IAB), yet possess more variable and lighter Ba isotopic compositions. This defines a distinct Ba isotopic lightening trend across the arc, reflecting progressive Ba isotopic fractionation associated with enhanced phengite dehydration at increasing subduction depths. The Bicol basalts show lower 87 Sr/ 86 Sr and much higher Sr/Zr ratios compared to the Luzon basalts, indicating pervasive fluid infiltration from the subducted oceanic crust into their mantle sources, which promotes the preferential breakdown of lawsonite and results in significant Sr enrichment in the mantle wedge. This observation explains why global arc basalts tend to have higher Sr/Zr ratios with decreasing 87 Sr/ 86 Sr ratios. Notably, Luzon basalts display Ba/Zr, K/Zr, and Rb/Zr ratios that largely overlap with those of Bicol arc basalts. We propose that subducted oceanic crust plays a role similar to that of subducted sediments in recycling FME, such as K, Rb, and Ba, owing to the buffering effect of phengite. Nevertheless, it potentially contributes more significantly to Sr enrichment within the mantle wedge of subduction zones.
Published: 2026-01-27T16:58:25+00:00
Venue: Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta
Score: 0.633 (consider)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yang Yu; Xiao-Long Huang; Betchaida D. Payot; Hai-Quan Liu; Ying-De Jiang; Yu Wang; Carla B. Dimalanta; Xin-Feng Ou; Gabriel Theophilus V. Valera; Fan Yang; Graciano P. Yumul; Yi-Gang Xu; Xiao-Han Tang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.038"&gt;10.1016/j.gca.2026.01.038&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.633 (consider)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geochemical recycling processes in subduction zones exhibit significant variability due to the incorporation of complex subduction components into the mantle wedge. Here, we present whole-rock geochemical and Ba–Sr–Nd–Hf–Pb isotopic data for basalts from the sediment-rich Luzon Arc and the sediment-poor Bicol Arc to constrain the recycling processes of fluid mobile elements (FME) in different subduction settings. Our results suggest that the mantle wedge beneath the Luzon and Bicol arcs was primarily metasomatized by melts from subducted sediments and fluids from subducted oceanic crust, respectively. The basalts from both arcs show variable δ 138/134 Ba values despite their limited variations in Sr–Nd–Hf–Pb isotopes, reflecting the heterogeneous dehydration of phengite in subducted sediments and oceanic crust, which have undergone different extents of Ba isotopic fractionation at shallow depths. Luzon back-arc basalts (BAB) exhibit Sr–Nd–Hf–Pb isotopic compositions similar to those of island arc basalts (IAB), yet possess more variable and lighter Ba isotopic compositions. This defines a distinct Ba isotopic lightening trend across the arc, reflecting progressive Ba isotopic fractionation associated with enhanced phengite dehydration at increasing subduction depths. The Bicol basalts show lower 87 Sr/ 86 Sr and much higher Sr/Zr ratios compared to the Luzon basalts, indicating pervasive fluid infiltration from the subducted oceanic crust into their mantle sources, which promotes the preferential breakdown of lawsonite and results in significant Sr enrichment in the mantle wedge. This observation explains why global arc basalts tend to have higher Sr/Zr ratios with decreasing 87 Sr/ 86 Sr ratios. Notably, Luzon basalts display Ba/Zr, K/Zr, and Rb/Zr ratios that largely overlap with those of Bicol arc basalts. We propose that subducted oceanic crust plays a role similar to that of subducted sediments in recycling FME, such as K, Rb, and Ba, owing to the buffering effect of phengite. Nevertheless, it potentially contributes more significantly to Sr enrichment within the mantle wedge of subduction zones.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>The effect of fluorine in the genesis of carbonatite-hosted rare earth element and niobium deposits</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1735-0</link><guid>10.1007/s11430-025-1735-0</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 02:27:15 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Wanzhu Zhang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Shuo Xue</dc:creator><dc:creator>Ming-Xing Ling</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xing Ding</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Science China Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1007/s11430-025-1735-0</prism:doi><description>Carbonatite is a rare but highly prospective rock that plays a significant role as a source of critical metals, notably rare earth elements (REE) and niobium (Nb). The widespread occurrence of fluorine-bearing minerals (e.g., fluorite, fluorapatite, and bastnäsite) in carbonatites indicates that their parent magmas are rich in fluorine. Nevertheless, the mechanisms by which fluorine controls REE and Nb mineralization remain unclear. Building on previous work, we systematically synthesize the regulatory role of fluorine in REE and Nb mineralization throughout the entire magmatic evolution of carbonatites. Our key findings are: (1) during partial melting, fluorine decreases the solidus of carbonated peridotite, thereby enhancing the generation and stability of carbonatitic melt. (2) In the mantle melting stage, it lowers the partition coefficients of REE and Nb between mantle minerals and melt, effectively promoting their extraction. (3) Throughout magmatic crystallization, fluorine significantly enriches REE and Nb in the residual melt. (4) During liquid immiscibility, fluorine exerts limited influence, as the partition behaviors of REE and Nb are primarily governed by structural differences between the conjugate melts. (5) In the hydrothermal stage, fluorine facilitates the mobilization, transport, and ultimate precipitation of REE- and Nb-bearing minerals, directly driving mineralization. The presented evidence implies that carbonatitic melts and fluoride-bearing minerals exert primary control over the spatial distribution and mineralization potential of REE and Nb. Future studies should focus on (1) clarifying how fluorine promotes REE and Nb enrichment in late-stage brine melts and (2) investigating its effect on the solubility and precipitation mechanisms of REE- and Nb-bearing minerals during the late stages of magma evolution.
Published: 2026-01-27T02:27:15+00:00
Venue: Science China Earth Sciences
Score: 0.607 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Wanzhu Zhang; Shuo Xue; Ming-Xing Ling; Xing Ding&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Science China Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11430-025-1735-0"&gt;10.1007/s11430-025-1735-0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.607 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carbonatite is a rare but highly prospective rock that plays a significant role as a source of critical metals, notably rare earth elements (REE) and niobium (Nb). The widespread occurrence of fluorine-bearing minerals (e.g., fluorite, fluorapatite, and bastnäsite) in carbonatites indicates that their parent magmas are rich in fluorine. Nevertheless, the mechanisms by which fluorine controls REE and Nb mineralization remain unclear. Building on previous work, we systematically synthesize the regulatory role of fluorine in REE and Nb mineralization throughout the entire magmatic evolution of carbonatites. Our key findings are: (1) during partial melting, fluorine decreases the solidus of carbonated peridotite, thereby enhancing the generation and stability of carbonatitic melt. (2) In the mantle melting stage, it lowers the partition coefficients of REE and Nb between mantle minerals and melt, effectively promoting their extraction. (3) Throughout magmatic crystallization, fluorine significantly enriches REE and Nb in the residual melt. (4) During liquid immiscibility, fluorine exerts limited influence, as the partition behaviors of REE and Nb are primarily governed by structural differences between the conjugate melts. (5) In the hydrothermal stage, fluorine facilitates the mobilization, transport, and ultimate precipitation of REE- and Nb-bearing minerals, directly driving mineralization. The presented evidence implies that carbonatitic melts and fluoride-bearing minerals exert primary control over the spatial distribution and mineralization potential of REE and Nb. Future studies should focus on (1) clarifying how fluorine promotes REE and Nb enrichment in late-stage brine melts and (2) investigating its effect on the solubility and precipitation mechanisms of REE- and Nb-bearing minerals during the late stages of magma evolution.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Generation of ferroan (“A-type”) granite in a subduction zone setting: Petrology of the Golden Horn batholith, North Cascades, Washington, USA</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1130/b38681.1</link><guid>10.1130/b38681.1</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 19:47:41 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Jeffrey H. Tepper</dc:creator><dc:creator>Michael P. Eddy</dc:creator><dc:creator>Samuel E. Berkelhammer</dc:creator><dc:creator>Bruce K. Nelson</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geological Society of America Bulletin</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1130/b38681.1</prism:doi><description>The Eocene Golden Horn batholith (North Cascades, northwestern United States) is an unusual example of coeval ferroan (A-type) and I-type granitoids that formed in a subduction zone setting. Associated mafic to intermediate dikes and stocks (adakites and calc-alkaline basalts to andesites) attest to the presence of mafic magmas in the shallow crust during batholith assembly and imply anomalously hot conditions in the mantle that are attributed to rupture or rollback of the subducting slab. Field, geochemical, and Sr-Nd-Pb isotopic data support generation of the ferroan magmas at midcrustal depth by melting of calc-alkaline plutonic rocks or by protracted differentiation of a parental basalt, and production of the I-type magmas by partial melting of gabbroic rocks at greater depth. Metasomatism by fluids bearing Na, F, and high field strength elements enriched some ferroan rocks to produce peralkaline granite. Mixing between the I-type and ferroan magmas also produced a hornblende-biotite granite with rapakivi feldspars, which is the most voluminous phase of the batholith. Results of this study suggest that ferroan granitoids rarely form in continental arcs because that tectonic regime limits voluminous basalt intrusion into the upper crust, and not because of a lack of suitable source rocks. Their presence in an arc setting likely indicates rollback or tearing of the slab or the presence of a slab window.
Published: 2026-01-27T19:47:41+00:00
Venue: Geological Society of America Bulletin
Score: 0.572 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Jeffrey H. Tepper; Michael P. Eddy; Samuel E. Berkelhammer; Bruce K. Nelson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geological Society of America Bulletin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1130/b38681.1"&gt;10.1130/b38681.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.572 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eocene Golden Horn batholith (North Cascades, northwestern United States) is an unusual example of coeval ferroan (A-type) and I-type granitoids that formed in a subduction zone setting. Associated mafic to intermediate dikes and stocks (adakites and calc-alkaline basalts to andesites) attest to the presence of mafic magmas in the shallow crust during batholith assembly and imply anomalously hot conditions in the mantle that are attributed to rupture or rollback of the subducting slab. Field, geochemical, and Sr-Nd-Pb isotopic data support generation of the ferroan magmas at midcrustal depth by melting of calc-alkaline plutonic rocks or by protracted differentiation of a parental basalt, and production of the I-type magmas by partial melting of gabbroic rocks at greater depth. Metasomatism by fluids bearing Na, F, and high field strength elements enriched some ferroan rocks to produce peralkaline granite. Mixing between the I-type and ferroan magmas also produced a hornblende-biotite granite with rapakivi feldspars, which is the most voluminous phase of the batholith. Results of this study suggest that ferroan granitoids rarely form in continental arcs because that tectonic regime limits voluminous basalt intrusion into the upper crust, and not because of a lack of suitable source rocks. Their presence in an arc setting likely indicates rollback or tearing of the slab or the presence of a slab window.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Mineralization processes for sphalerite in MVT deposits: Insights from the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang ore field, Guizhou, Southwest China</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-125</link><guid>10.1144/jgs2025-125</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 11:01:17 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Weijun He</dc:creator><dc:creator>Youguo Li</dc:creator><dc:creator>Sigen Ma</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of the Geological Society</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1144/jgs2025-125</prism:doi><description>Although Mississippi Valley-type (MVT) deposit mineralization processes are well characterized, the associated ore-forming fluids, which are crucial to understanding Pb and Zn mineralization, should be investigated further. With more than 0.7 million tonnes (Mt) of Zn reserves at average grades ranging from 4–8%, the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field comprises representative deposits such as those of Caiyuanhe, Heli, and Qingshuitang. The ore bodies, which exhibit stratiform, vein-like, and lenticular forms, are hosted within the Cambrian Qingxudong Formation dolomite and are spatially associated with the NE-trending Mandong fault. This Zn ore field in Southwest China is a classic example of Zn-rich mineralization. However, the genetic mechanisms and processes responsible for the Zn-rich nature of these MVT Pb‒Zn deposits remain poorly understood. This study aims to characterize Zn mineralization in the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field, Southwest China. The rare earth elements (REE) concentrations in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol2) from the syn-ore stage vary between 5.63 and 32.50 ppm (with an average of 14.07 ppm), whereas in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol3) from post-ore stage, the values range from 45.63 to 95.69 ppm (with an average of 72.03 ppm). The fluid inclusions of Dol2 and Dol3 exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 98–204°C (with an average of 143°C) and 98–195°C (with an average of 132°C), with corresponding salinity ranges of 13.0–29.5 wt% (with an average of 20.9 wt%) and 16.0–25.7 wt% (with an average of 18.9 wt%) NaCl equivalent, respectively. Sphalerite inclusions exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 95–230°C (with a mean of 143°C) and salinities ranging from 13.8–28.9 wt% (with a mean of 23.7 wt%) NaCl. The δ 13 C fluid , δ D fluid , and δ 18 O fluid values of the ore-forming fluids range from -4.4‰ to -3.8‰ (with a mean of -4.1‰), -36.4‰ to -27.8‰ (with a mean of -31.9‰), and 4.9‰ to 5.7‰ (with a mean of 5.3‰), respectively. In this study, an Fe- and Zn-enriched NaCl-H₂O basement brine is identified as the ore-forming fluid responsible for the Zn-rich MVT deposits. During its low- to medium-temperature migration, the fluid was channelled by the Mandong fault and Wangsi anticline structural framework, which provided ideal pathways and traps. During migration, the fluid leached sulfur (reduced from evaporites to H 2 S) from wall rocks and ultimately precipitated within dolomite faults and fractures. The distinct Zn-rich character of the deposits stems from the following two key factors: a primary derivation from the Zn-rich basement of the Yangtze Block and a chemical preference for Zn enrichment, which is driven by the differing fractionation coefficients of Zn- and Pb-chloride complexes in the NaCl–H 2 O system. This study advances the understanding of the genesis of MVT deposits worldwide.
Published: 2026-01-28T11:01:17+00:00
Venue: Journal of the Geological Society
Score: 0.570 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Weijun He; Youguo Li; Sigen Ma&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of the Geological Society&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1144/jgs2025-125"&gt;10.1144/jgs2025-125&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.570 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Mississippi Valley-type (MVT) deposit mineralization processes are well characterized, the associated ore-forming fluids, which are crucial to understanding Pb and Zn mineralization, should be investigated further. With more than 0.7 million tonnes (Mt) of Zn reserves at average grades ranging from 4–8%, the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field comprises representative deposits such as those of Caiyuanhe, Heli, and Qingshuitang. The ore bodies, which exhibit stratiform, vein-like, and lenticular forms, are hosted within the Cambrian Qingxudong Formation dolomite and are spatially associated with the NE-trending Mandong fault. This Zn ore field in Southwest China is a classic example of Zn-rich mineralization. However, the genetic mechanisms and processes responsible for the Zn-rich nature of these MVT Pb‒Zn deposits remain poorly understood. This study aims to characterize Zn mineralization in the Niujiaotang–Qingshuitang Zn ore field, Southwest China. The rare earth elements (REE) concentrations in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol2) from the syn-ore stage vary between 5.63 and 32.50 ppm (with an average of 14.07 ppm), whereas in hydrothermal dolomite (Dol3) from post-ore stage, the values range from 45.63 to 95.69 ppm (with an average of 72.03 ppm). The fluid inclusions of Dol2 and Dol3 exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 98–204°C (with an average of 143°C) and 98–195°C (with an average of 132°C), with corresponding salinity ranges of 13.0–29.5 wt% (with an average of 20.9 wt%) and 16.0–25.7 wt% (with an average of 18.9 wt%) NaCl equivalent, respectively. Sphalerite inclusions exhibit homogenization temperatures ranging from 95–230°C (with a mean of 143°C) and salinities ranging from 13.8–28.9 wt% (with a mean of 23.7 wt%) NaCl. The δ 13 C fluid , δ D fluid , and δ 18 O fluid values of the ore-forming fluids range from -4.4‰ to -3.8‰ (with a mean of -4.1‰), -36.4‰ to -27.8‰ (with a mean of -31.9‰), and 4.9‰ to 5.7‰ (with a mean of 5.3‰), respectively. In this study, an Fe- and Zn-enriched NaCl-H₂O basement brine is identified as the ore-forming fluid responsible for the Zn-rich MVT deposits. During its low- to medium-temperature migration, the fluid was channelled by the Mandong fault and Wangsi anticline structural framework, which provided ideal pathways and traps. During migration, the fluid leached sulfur (reduced from evaporites to H 2 S) from wall rocks and ultimately precipitated within dolomite faults and fractures. The distinct Zn-rich character of the deposits stems from the following two key factors: a primary derivation from the Zn-rich basement of the Yangtze Block and a chemical preference for Zn enrichment, which is driven by the differing fractionation coefficients of Zn- and Pb-chloride complexes in the NaCl–H 2 O system. This study advances the understanding of the genesis of MVT deposits worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Genesis and mineral exploration of the Daqishan Lead-Zinc Deposit, Beishan orogenic Belt, NW China: Constraints from In-Situ trace element compositions of Sphalerite, Pyrite, and chalcopyrite</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106981</link><guid>10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106981</guid><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 00:37:59 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Yu Liu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Biao Jiang</dc:creator><dc:creator>Jichang Zhao</dc:creator><dc:creator>Zongfu Fan</dc:creator><dc:creator>Peibin Xu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Xudong Zhu</dc:creator><dc:creator>Yinding Zhang</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Journal of Asian Earth Sciences</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106981</prism:doi><description>The Daqishan deposit is located in the Beishan orogenic belt, with a Pb + Zn metal reserve of 108 kilotons, qualifying it as a medium-sized deposit. Through the field investigations and microscopic observations, this study divides the Daqishan deposit’s ore-forming process into three stages: (I) Quartz-pyrite stage; (II) Quartz + calcite + sphalerite + galena + pyrite stage; (III) Quartz + chalcopyrite + cassiterite + silver minerals stage. To explore the distribution and substitution mechanisms of trace elements in key minerals and clarify the deposit’s genesis, LA-ICP-MS was employed for in situ analysis of trace element compositions in sphalerite, pyrite, and chalcopyrite from different stages. In sphalerite, trace elements including Fe, Mn, Cd, Co, In, and Ag are mainly integrated into the mineral lattice through isomorphism. In pyrite, Co and Ni are primarily incorporated via coupled substitution, while in chalcopyrite, In, Ag, and Sn are predominantly integrated through coupled substitution. The Co/Ni ratio and As content in pyrite suggest the mineral formed in a medium- to low-temperature environment, with temperatures decreasing as mineralization advanced. The Ga/In and Zn/Cd ratios in sphalerite indicate its formation under medium- to low-temperature conditions, with higher temperatures during the main mineralization stage. Collectively, the mineralization of the Daqishan Pb-Zn deposit is inferred to result from multiple episodes of pulsed mineralization by ore-forming fluids, there remains potential for discovering copper-tin mineralization at depth and in peripheral areas of the deposit. Based on trace element characteristics of sphalerite and pyrite, the Daqishan deposit is classified as an epithermal deposit.
Published: 2026-01-28T00:37:59+00:00
Venue: Journal of Asian Earth Sciences
Score: 0.526 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Yu Liu; Biao Jiang; Jichang Zhao; Zongfu Fan; Peibin Xu; Xudong Zhu; Yinding Zhang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Journal of Asian Earth Sciences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106981"&gt;10.1016/j.jseaes.2026.106981&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.526 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Daqishan deposit is located in the Beishan orogenic belt, with a Pb + Zn metal reserve of 108 kilotons, qualifying it as a medium-sized deposit. Through the field investigations and microscopic observations, this study divides the Daqishan deposit’s ore-forming process into three stages: (I) Quartz-pyrite stage; (II) Quartz + calcite + sphalerite + galena + pyrite stage; (III) Quartz + chalcopyrite + cassiterite + silver minerals stage. To explore the distribution and substitution mechanisms of trace elements in key minerals and clarify the deposit’s genesis, LA-ICP-MS was employed for in situ analysis of trace element compositions in sphalerite, pyrite, and chalcopyrite from different stages. In sphalerite, trace elements including Fe, Mn, Cd, Co, In, and Ag are mainly integrated into the mineral lattice through isomorphism. In pyrite, Co and Ni are primarily incorporated via coupled substitution, while in chalcopyrite, In, Ag, and Sn are predominantly integrated through coupled substitution. The Co/Ni ratio and As content in pyrite suggest the mineral formed in a medium- to low-temperature environment, with temperatures decreasing as mineralization advanced. The Ga/In and Zn/Cd ratios in sphalerite indicate its formation under medium- to low-temperature conditions, with higher temperatures during the main mineralization stage. Collectively, the mineralization of the Daqishan Pb-Zn deposit is inferred to result from multiple episodes of pulsed mineralization by ore-forming fluids, there remains potential for discovering copper-tin mineralization at depth and in peripheral areas of the deposit. Based on trace element characteristics of sphalerite and pyrite, the Daqishan deposit is classified as an epithermal deposit.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Characterizing Martian Primary Crustal Compositions With Gamma Ray Spectroscopy</title><link>https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118214</link><guid>10.1029/2025gl118214</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 12:55:55 +0000</pubDate><dc:creator>Carlos E. Gary‐Bicas</dc:creator><dc:creator>Suniti Karunatillake</dc:creator><dc:creator>James J. Wray</dc:creator><dc:creator>Scott M. Perl</dc:creator><dc:creator>Alka Rani</dc:creator><dc:creator>Emmy B. Hughes</dc:creator><prism:publicationName>Geophysical Research Letters</prism:publicationName><prism:doi>10.1029/2025gl118214</prism:doi><description>Abstract Mars's global‐scale chemical maps of the midlatitudes, derived from Mars Odyssey gamma and neutron spectroscopy, have constrained martian geology across a multitude of processes. However, the chemical maps are often used to analyze pre‐defined regions based on mapped geology and/or mineralogy. Previous mapping works have relied on first‐principles methods like principal component analyses and k‐means clustering. In response, we adapt dimensionality reduction and multivariate clustering methods to analyze the spatial variability of nine key elements in martian geochemical maps. We identify seven individually contiguous chemical provinces, nearly exclusively in the highlands. We then conduct geochemical analysis coupled with first order petrological modeling to assess the histories for individually delineated provinces. We identified two new regions where one is consistent with minimal chemical weathering and represents a ∼3.7 Ga old crustal block preserving compositional evidence of fractional crystallization, suggestive of Mars's primary crust sequestering early as a magma ocean solidified.
Published: 2026-01-27T12:55:55+00:00
Venue: Geophysical Research Letters
Score: 0.476 (ignore)</description><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors:&lt;/strong&gt; Carlos E. Gary‐Bicas; Suniti Karunatillake; James J. Wray; Scott M. Perl; Alka Rani; Emmy B. Hughes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal:&lt;/strong&gt; Geophysical Research Letters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DOI:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2025gl118214"&gt;10.1029/2025gl118214&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance:&lt;/strong&gt; 0.476 (ignore)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract Mars&amp;#x27;s global‐scale chemical maps of the midlatitudes, derived from Mars Odyssey gamma and neutron spectroscopy, have constrained martian geology across a multitude of processes. However, the chemical maps are often used to analyze pre‐defined regions based on mapped geology and/or mineralogy. Previous mapping works have relied on first‐principles methods like principal component analyses and k‐means clustering. In response, we adapt dimensionality reduction and multivariate clustering methods to analyze the spatial variability of nine key elements in martian geochemical maps. We identify seven individually contiguous chemical provinces, nearly exclusively in the highlands. We then conduct geochemical analysis coupled with first order petrological modeling to assess the histories for individually delineated provinces. We identified two new regions where one is consistent with minimal chemical weathering and represents a ∼3.7 Ga old crustal block preserving compositional evidence of fractional crystallization, suggestive of Mars&amp;#x27;s primary crust sequestering early as a magma ocean solidified.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>